Twilight of the Idols

or How to Philosophize with a Hammer

Maxims and Arrows

1. Idleness is the beginning of psychology. What? could psychology be - a vice?

2. Even the bravest of us rarely has the courage for what he really knows...

3. To live alone one must be an animal or a god - says Aristotle. There is yet a third case: one must be both - a philosopher.

4. 'All truth is simple' - Is that not a compound lie? -

5. Once and for all, there is a great deal I do not want to know. - Wisdom sets bounds even to knowledge.

6. It is by being 'natural' that one best recovers from one's unnaturalness, from one's spirituality...

7. Which is it? Is man only God's mistake or God only man's mistake? -

8. From the military school of life - What does not kill me makes me stronger.

9. Help thyself: then everyone will help thee too. Principle of Christian charity.

10. Let us not be cowardly in face of our actions! Let us not afterwards leave them in the lurch! - Remorse of conscience is indecent.

11. Can an ass be tragic? - To be crushed by a burden one can neither bear nor throw off?... The case of the philosopher.

12. If we possess our why of life we can put up with almost any how. - Man does not strive after happiness; only the Englishman does that.

13. Man created woman - but what out of? Out of a rib of his God, of his 'ideal'...

14. What? you are seeking? you want to multiply yourself by ten, by a hundred? you are seeking followers? - Seek noughts!

15. Posthumous men - like me, for instance - are not so well understood as timely men, but they are listened to better. More precisely: we are never understood - and hence our authority...

16. Among women. - 'Truth? Oh, you don't know the truth, do you! Is it not an outrage on all our pudeurs?' -

17. This is an artist as an artist should be, modest in his requirements: there are only two things he really wants, his bread and his art - panem et Circen...

18. He who does not know how to put his will into things at least puts a meaning into them: that is, he believes there is a will in them already (principle of 'belief').

19. What? you have chosen virtue and the heaving bosom, yet at the same time look with envy on the advantages enjoyed by those who live for the day? - But with virtue one renounces 'advantage'... (laid at the door of an anti-Semite).

20. The complete woman perpetrates literature in the same way as she perpetrates a little sin: as an experiment, in passing, looking around to see if someone notices and so that someone may notice...

21. To get into only those situations in which illusory virtues are of no use, but in which, like the tightrope-walker on his rope, one either falls or stands - or gets off...

22. 'Bad men have no songs' - How is it the Russians have songs?

23. 'German spirit': for eighteen years a contradictio in adjecta.

24. In order to look for beginners one becomes a crab. The historian looks backwards; at last he also believes backwards.

25. Contentment protects one even from catching a cold. Has a woman who knew she was well dressed ever caught a cold? - I am assuming she was hardly dressed at all.

26. I mistrust all systematizers and avoid them. The will to a system is a lack of integrity.

27. Women are considered deep - why? because one can never discover any bottom to them. Women are not even shallow.

28. If a woman possesses manly virtues one should run away from her; and if she does not possess them she runs away herself.

29. 'How much the conscience formerly had to bite on! what good teeth it had! - And today? what's the trouble?' - A dentist's question.

30. One seldom commits only one rash act. In the first rash act one always does too much. For just that reason one usually commits a second - and then one does too little...

31. When it is trodden on a worm will curl up. That is prudent. It thereby reduces the chance of being trodden on again. In the language of morals: humility. -

32. Hatred of lies and dissembling may arise out of a sensitive notion of honour; the same hatred may arise out of cowardice, in as much as lying is forbidden by divine command. Too cowardly to tell lies...

33. How little is needed for happiness! The note of a bagpipe. - Without music life would be a mistake. The German even thinks of God as singing songs.

34. On ne peut penser et écrire qu'assis (G. Flaubert). - Now I have you, nihilist! Assiduity is the sin against the holy spirit. Only ideas won by walking have any value.

35. There are times when we are like horses, we psychologists, and grow restive: we see our own shadow moving up and down before us. The psychologist has to look away from himself in order to see at all.

36. Whether we immoralists do virtue any harm? - As little as anarchists do princes. Only since they have been shot at do they again sit firmly on their thrones. Moral: one must shoot at morals.

37. You run on ahead? - Do you do so as a herdsman? or as an exception? A third possibility would be as a deserter... First question of conscience.

38. Are you genuine? or only an actor? A representative? or that itself which is represented? - Finally you are no more than an imitation of an actor... Second question of conscience.

39. The disappointed man speaks. - I sought great human beings, I never found anything but the apes of their ideal.

40. Are you one who looks on? or who sets to work? - or who looks away, turns aside... Third question of conscience.

41. Do you want to accompany? or go on ahead? or go off alone?... One must know what one wants and that one wants. - Fourth question of conscience.

42. For me they were steps, I have climbed up upon them - therefore I had to pass over them. But they thought I wanted to settle down on them...

43. What does it matter that I am proved right! I am too much in the right. - And he who laughs best today will also laugh last.

44. Formula of my happiness; a Yes, a No, a straight line, a goal...

The Four Great Errors

1

The error of confusing cause and consequence. - There is no more dangerous error than that of mistaking the consequence for the cause: I call it reason's intrinsic form of corruption. None the less, this error is among the most ancient and most recent habits of mankind: it is even sanctified among us, it bears the names 'religion' and 'morality'. Every proposition formulated by religion and morality contains it, priests and moral legislators are the authors of this corruption of reason. - I adduce an example. Everyone knows the book of the celebrated Cornaro in which he recommends his meagre diet as a recipe for a long and happy life - a virtuous one, too. Few books have been so widely read; even now many thousands of copies are printed in England every year. I do not doubt that hardly any book (the Bible rightly excepted) has done so much harm, has shortened so many lives, as this curiosity, which was so well meant. The reason: mistaking the consequence for the cause. The worthy Italian saw in his diet the cause of his long life: while the prerequisite of long life, an extraordinarily slow metabolism, a small consumption, was the cause of his meagre diet. He was not free to eat much or little as he chose, his frugality was not an act of 'free will': he became ill when he ate more. But if one is not a bony fellow of this sort one does not merely do well, one positively needs to eat properly. A scholar of our day, with his rapid consumption of nervous energy, would kill himself with Cornaro's regimen. Credo experto. -

2

The most general formula at the basis of every religion and morality is: 'Do this and this, refrain from this and this - and you will be happy! Otherwise...' Every morality, every religion is this imperative - I call it the great original sin of reason, immortal unreason. In my mouth this formula is converted into its reverse - first example of my 'revaluation of all values': a well-constituted human being, a 'happy one', must perform certain actions and instinctively shrinks from other actions, he transports the order of which he is the physiological representative into his relations with other human beings and with things. In a formula: his virtue is the consequence of his happiness... Long life, a plentiful posterity is not the reward of virtue, virtue itself is rather just that slowing down of the metabolism which also has, among other things, a long life, a plentiful posterity, in short Cornarism, as its outcome. - The Church and morality say: 'A race, a people perishes through vice and luxury'. My restored reason says: when a people is perishing, degenerating physiologically, vice and luxury (that is to say the necessity for stronger and stronger and more and more frequent stimulants, such as every exhausted nature is acquainted with) follow therefrom. A young man grows prematurely pale and faded. His friends say: this and that illness is to blame. I say: that he became ill, that he failed to resist the illness, was already the consequence of an impoverished life, an hereditary exhaustion. The newspaper reader says: this party will ruin itself if it makes errors like this. My higher politics says: a party which makes errors like this is already finished - it is no longer secure in its instincts. Every error, of whatever kind, is a consequence of degeneration of instinct, disgregation of will: one has thereby virtually defined the bad. Everything good is instinct - and consequently easy, necessary, free. Effort is an objection, the god is typically distinguished from the hero (in my language: light feet are the first attribute of divinity).

3

The error of a false causality. - We have always believed we know what a cause is: but whence did we derive our knowledge, more precisely our belief we possessed this knowledge? From the realm of the celebrated 'inner facts', none of which has up till now been shown to be factual. We believed ourselves to be causal agents in the act of willing; we at least thought we were there catching causality in the act. It was likewise never doubted that all the antecedentia of an action, its causes, were to be sought in the consciousness and could be discovered there if one sought them - as 'motives': for otherwise one would not have been free to perform it, responsible for it. Finally, who would have disputed that a thought is caused? that the ego causes the thought?... Of these three 'inner facts' through which causality seemed to be guaranteed the first and most convincing was that of will as cause; the conception of a consciousness ('mind') as cause and later still that of the ego (the 'subject') as cause are merely after-products after causality had, on the basis of will, been firmly established as a given fact, as empiricism... Meanwhile, we have thought better. Today we do not believe a word of it. The 'inner world' is full of phantoms and false lights: the will is one of them. The will no longer moves anything, consequently no longer explains anything - it merely accompanies events, it can also be absent. The so-called 'motive': another error. Merely a surface phenomenon of consciousness, an accompaniment to an act, which conceals rather than exposes the antecedentia of the act. And as for the ego! It has become a fable, a fiction, a play on words: it has totally ceased to think, to feel and to will!... What follows from this? There are no spiritual causes at all! The whole of the alleged empiricism which affirmed them has gone to the devil! That is what follows! - And we had made a nice misuse of that 'empiricism', we had created the world on the basis of it as a world of causes, as a world of will, as a world of spirit. The oldest and longest-lived psychology was at work here - indeed it has done nothing else: every event was to it an action, every action the effect of a will, the world became for it a multiplicity of agents, an agent ('subject') foisted itself upon every event. Man projected his three 'inner facts', that in which he believed more firmly than in anything else, will, spirit, ego, outside himself - he derived the concept 'being' only from the concept 'ego', he posited 'things' as possessing being according to his own image, according to his concept of the ego as cause. No wonder cause-creating drive; we want to have a reason for feeling as we do - for feeling well or for feeling ill. It never suffices us simply to establish the mere fact that we feel as we do: we acknowledge this fact - become conscious of it - only when we have furnished it with a motivation of some kind. - The memory, which in such a case becomes active without our being aware of it, calls up earlier states of a similar kind and the causal interpretations which have grown out of them - not their causality. To be sure, the belief that these ideas, the accompanying occurrences in the consciousness, were causes is also brought up by the memory. Thus there arises an habituation to a certain causal interpretation which in truth obstructs and even prohibits an investigation of the cause.

5

Psychological explanation. - To trace something unknown back to something known is alleviating, soothing, gratifying and gives moreover a feeling of power. Danger, disquiet, anxiety attend the unknown - the first instinct is to eliminate these distressing states. First principle: any explanation is better than none. Because it is at bottom only a question of wanting to get rid of oppressive ideas, one is not exactly particular about what means one uses to get rid of them: the first idea which explains that the unknown is in fact the known does so much good that one 'holds it for true'. Proof by pleasure ('by potency') as criterion of truth. - The cause-creating drive is thus conditioned and excited by the feeling of fear. The question 'why?' should furnish, if at all possible, not so much the cause for its own sake as a certain kind of cause - a soothing, liberating, alleviating cause. That something already known, experienced, inscribed in the memory is posited as cause is the first consequence of this need. The new, the unexperienced, the strange is excluded from being cause. - Thus there is sought not only some kind of explanation as cause, but a selected and preferred kind of explanation, the kind by means of which the feeling of the strange, new, unexperienced is most speedily and most frequently abolished - the most common explanations. - Consequence: a particular kind of causeascription comes to preponderate more and more, becomes concentrated into a system and finally comes to dominate over the rest, that is to say simply to exclude other causes and explanations. - The banker thinks at once of 'business', the Christian of 'sin', the girl of her love.

6

The entire realm of morality and religion falls under this concept of imaginary causes. - 'Explanation' of unpleasant general feelings. They arise from beings hostile to us (evil spirits: most celebrated case - hysterics misunderstood as witches). They arise from actions we cannot approve of (the feeling of 'sin', of 'culpability' foisted upon a physiological discomfort - one always finds reasons for being discontented with oneself). They arise as punishments, as payment for something we should not have done, should not have been (generalized in an impudent form by Schopenhauer into a proposition in which morality appears for what it is, the actual poisoner and calumniator of life: 'Every great pain, whether physical or mental, declares what it is we deserve; for it could not have come upon us if we had not deserved it.' World as Will and Idea Ⅱ 666). They arise as the consequences of rash actions which have turned out badly (- the emotions, the senses assigned as 'cause', as 'to blame'; physiological states of distress construed, with the aid of other states of distress, as 'deserved'). - 'Explanation' of pleasant general feelings. They arise from trust in God. They arise from the consciousness of good actions (the so-called 'good conscience', a physiological condition sometimes so like a sound digestion as to be mistaken for it). They arise from the successful outcome of undertakings (- naïve fallacy: the successful outcome of an undertaking certainly does not produce any pleasant general feelings in a hypochondriac or a Pascal). They arise from faith, hope and charity - the Christian virtues. - In reality all these supposed explanations are consequential states and as it were translations of pleasurable and unpleasurable feelings into a false dialect: one is in a state in which one can experience hope because the physiological basic feeling is once more strong and ample; one trusts in God because the feeling of plenitude and strength makes one calm. - Morality and religion fall entirely under the psychology of error: in every single case cause is mistaken for effect; or the effect of what is believed true is mistaken for the truth; or a state of consciousness is mistaken for the causation of this state.

7

The error of free will. - We no longer have any sympathy today with the concept of 'free will': we know only too well what it is - the most infamous of all the arts of the theologian for making mankind 'accountable' in his sense of the word, that is to say for making mankind dependent on him... I give here only the psychology of making men accountable. - Everywhere accountability is sought, it is usually the instinct for punishing and judging which seeks it. One has deprived becoming of its innocence if being in this or that state is traced back to will, to intentions, to accountable acts: the doctrine of will has been invented essentially for the purpose of punishment, that is of finding guilty. The whole of the old-style psychology, the psychology of will, has as its precondition the desire of its authors, the priests at the head of the ancient communities, to create for themselves a right to ordain punishments - or their desire to create for God a right to do so... Men were thought of as 'free' so that they could become guilty: consequently, every action had to be thought of as willed, the origin of every action as lying in the consciousness (- whereby the most fundamental falsification in psychologicis was made into the very principle of psychology)... Today, when we have started to move in the reverse direction, when we immoralists especially are trying with all our might to remove the concept of guilt and the concept of punishment from the world and to purge psychology, history, nature, the social institutions and sanctions of them, there is in our eyes no more radical opposition than that of the theologians, who continue to infect the innocence of becoming with 'punishment' and 'guilt' by means of the concept of the 'moral world-order'. Christianity is a hangman's metaphysics...

8

What alone can our teaching be? - That no one gives a human being his qualities: not God, not society, not his parents or ancestors, not he himself (- the nonsensical idea here last rejected was propounded, as 'intelligible freedom', by Kant, and perhaps also by Plato before him). No one is accountable for existing at all, or for being constituted as he is, or for living in the circumstances and surroundings in which he lives. The fatality of his nature cannot be disentangled from the fatality of all that which has been and will be. He is not the result of a special design, a will, a purpose; he is not the subject of an attempt to attain to an 'ideal of man' or an 'ideal of happiness' or an 'ideal of morality' - it is absurd to want to hand over his nature to some purpose or other. We invented the concept 'purpose': in reality purpose is lacking... One is necessary, one is a piece of fate, one belongs to the whole, one is in the whole - there exists nothing which could judge, measure, compare, condemn our being, for that would be to judge, measure, compare, condemn the whole... But nothing exists apart from the whole! - That no one is any longer made accountable, that the kind of being manifested cannot be traced back to a causa prima, that the world is a unity neither as sensorium nor as 'spirit', this alone is the great liberation - thus alone is the innocence of becoming restored... The concept 'God' has hitherto been the greatest objection to existence... We deny God; in denying God, we deny accountability: only by doing that do we redeem the world. -

The Hammer Speaks

'Why so hard?' the charcoal once said to the diamond; 'for are we not close relations?'

Why so soft? O my brothers, thus I ask you: for are you not - my brothers?

Why so soft, unresisting and yielding? Why is there so much denial and abnegation in your hearts? So little fate in your glances?

And if you will not be fates, if you will not be inexorable: how can you - conquer with me?

And if your hardness will not flash and cut and cut to pieces: how can you one day - create with me?

For all creators are hard. And it must seem bliss to you to press your hand upon millennia as upon wax,

bliss to write upon the will of millennia as upon metal - harder than metal, nobler than metal. Only the noblest is perfectly hard.

This new law-table do I put over you, O my brothers: Become hard!

译者导读

柏拉图（Plato，公元前427—前347），古希腊伟大的哲学家，也是全部西方哲学乃至整个西方文化最伟大的哲学家和思想家之一。柏拉图和他的老师苏格拉底以及他的学生亚里士多德被并称为古希腊三大哲学家。柏拉图是西方客观唯心主义的创始人，他的哲学体系博大精深，一生作品很多，写下了许多哲学对话录，并且后来在雅典创办了著名的书院。

《会饮篇》（或译作《飨宴篇》《宴话篇》）是柏拉图早期的一篇对话式作品，它描述了在一次宴会上，一群雅典男性对爱的本质的讨论。该作品以演讲和对话的形式写成，既有讽刺式的，也有认真的谈话。他们对话的大前提是（而且有些讲者更清楚说明），最高贵的爱是男人之间的爱。爱是对美的企盼，美貌、智慧和美德都被讨论。他们反对古希腊风俗中男人对少年的爱，说男人不应该在这些尚未了解基本美德，也未定型的少年身上下功夫，而更应该去爱一个男子并长相厮守，并强调两人间若只有美德与知识的交流最为崇高。柏拉图提出肉体的爱不如精神上对智慧和美德的爱，这就是著名的“柏拉图式的爱情”，这样的爱就是至善。在《会饮篇》里，柏拉图还描述了认识“美”的过程：从认识美的形体到美的道理、美的制度，等等，逐级上升，经过飞跃最后认识到美本身，即“美的相”。柏拉图又进一步描述了这种“相”的基本特征：它是永恒的，不生不灭的，绝对的，单一的，等等。

此书还收录了柏拉图著名的“洞穴寓言”，选自《理想国》。在《理想国》中，苏格拉底一开始提到了哲学家必须具备的各种素质，然后着重强调这些素质必须建立在学问的基础之上，最终则是建立在为善的学问基础之上。对苏格拉底来说它是善的本质。一些人认为善即快乐，或者认为善即学问。柏拉图简明扼要地驳斥了此类观点，却拒绝直接给出自己的看法，而是借用“洞穴寓言”来阐述他的观点，这是他首次详细解释唯心主义。

柏拉图还提到了太阳的比喻和分割线的比喻，柏拉图解释说，分割线比喻是太阳比喻的续篇，旨在进一步说明太阳比喻所涉及的现实中两种层次之间的关系。但它是从一个特定的角度来讲述的，即我们用来理解这两种层次或领域的心智状态。因此，这个线的目的主要也不是用来给事物分类。与可知领域相关的两种心智状态，都是与同种类型的东西（本质）打交道，尽管每种心智状态的处理方式各不相同；虽然在物质世界里，物质的东西与其自身的影子有区别，但这种差异主要用于阐明需要了解的东西当中存在的“真实”或真实性的程度——如果我们的学问仅局限于它的影子或影像，那么，我们对自身学问的东西了解就太有限了。就这个问题而言，就是仅仅局限于肤浅的外表了。

会饮篇

阿波罗多洛斯：实际上，我已经准备好回答你的问题了。前几天我碰巧要从我位于法勒鲁姆的家去城里，一个我认识的人从后面看见了我，大老远地叫我。他喊道（扯着嗓门用开玩笑的口吻）：

“嘿，从法勒鲁姆来的人！你！阿波罗多洛斯，能等我一下吗？”

我停了下来，等着他。

他说：“阿波罗多洛斯，我刚才一直在找你，想让你告诉我在阿伽松家举行的聚会上发生的故事。苏格拉底、亚西比德等人都参加了那次晚宴。他们在关于爱的发言中都说了什么？有个人从菲利普的儿子菲尼克斯那里了解了一些，我听他说了；但他说你也知道那次晚宴。他讲述的内容不够确切。请告诉我你知道的东西吧。苏格拉底是你的朋友，要复述他说的话，没有人比你更有权利了。不过，开始讲之前，”他补充说，“先告诉我：你当时在场吗？”

“你得到的肯定不是精准的复述，”我回答道，“你以为这次聚会是最近发生的，连我也参加了。”

“是的，我确实这样认为。”他说。

“你怎会这样认为呢，格老孔？阿伽松已经有很多年不在雅典住了，而我开始和苏格拉底交往，把追随他的一言一行当作我的职业，还不到三年时间，你难道不知道这些吗？那之前我经常漫无目的地闲逛。我自认为在做一些重要的事，但其实我当时处于最可悲的境地——就像你现在这样！——认为哲学是我最不应该做的事。”

“别取笑我，”他说，“告诉我这次聚会是什么时候举办的吧。”

“那时你和我都还是小孩子，”我说，“阿伽松的第一部悲剧得了奖。他和他的伙伴们举行了祭祀盛宴，庆祝他们的成功，聚会就发生在次日。”

“所以确实是很久以前的事了，”他说，“是谁告诉你这件事的，是苏格拉底自己吗？”

“当然不是了！”我说，“和告诉菲尼克斯的是同一个人，是居达塞奈乌姆一个叫阿里斯托得摩斯的矮个子，他总是光着脚走来走去。他当时参加了那次聚会，我想他是苏格拉底当时最狂热的崇拜者之一，不过，我后来就他告诉我的一些要点问了苏格拉底，他证实了阿里斯托得摩斯的说法。”

“来吧，”他说，“你把这些再给我讲一遍吧。在去城邦的路上，我们正好可以边走边说。”

于是我们一起走的时候就谈了这些，所以正如我一开始说的，我已经准备好了。如果需要给你讲一遍，我也会那样做的。实际上，每当我讨论哲学或听他人讨论哲学时，我都会得到极大的愉悦，更不用说从中受益了。但至于其他类的讨论，尤其是像你们这样的富商的谈话，我感到索然无味，为你和你的朋友感到可惜，因为你们自认为在做一些重要的事，其实不然。可能你觉得我是个失败者，不中用，我却认为你是自以为是。我不仅认为你是个失败者，而且我知道你就是。

朋友：你总是这样，阿波罗多洛斯。你总是贬低自己，贬低其他人。你似乎相信除了苏格拉底，其余所有的人都处于悲惨境地，首当其冲的就是你自己。我不知道你是怎么得到“软蛋”这个绰号的。你在说话时，总是现在这个样子，残酷地攻击你自己和所有人——只有苏格拉底除外。

阿波罗多洛斯：我亲爱的朋友，很明显，如果我对自己和你持有这种看法，我是不是在胡说八道？

朋友：阿波罗多洛斯，我们现在实在不值得为此争论。请按照我的请求，告诉我谈话的进展如何。

阿波罗多洛斯：好吧，差不多是这样的——但如果我从头开始讲的话会更好点儿，就像阿里斯托得摩斯做的那样。

他说他在路上遇到了苏格拉底，苏格拉底刚洗过澡，还穿上了鞋——他几乎从不这样做。他问苏格拉底穿戴这么整齐是要去哪里。

苏格拉底答道：“去和阿伽松一起参加晚宴。昨天我没去他的得奖庆典，避开了人群；但我答应今天参加他的晚宴。因此我才打扮一番，这样我去美貌的人的家时也能看起来精神点儿。你呢？”他问道，“虽然你没受邀请，但是愿意和我参加晚宴吗？”

“你怎么说我就怎么做。”阿里斯托得摩斯答道。

“那么你就和我一起走吧，”苏格拉底说，“这样我们就可以证实谚语是错的，将它倒过来说：‘每逢好人开宴，好人不请自来。’其实，荷马也借用过这条谚语，但他把它曲解了，并且几乎是用蔑视的态度对待它的。他笔下的阿伽门农是位异常优秀的战将，而墨涅拉俄斯是个‘软弱无能的枪兵’。但当阿伽门农祭祀并举办盛宴时，墨涅拉俄斯这个卑微的人不请自来地参加了优等人的盛宴，这样看来，就是让不太好的人赴好人的宴会了。”

阿里斯托得摩斯回答道：“但是恐怕我也符合荷马描述的情况，而不像你说的那个意思，苏格拉底，我是个卑微的人，不请自来地参加聪明者的盛宴。如果你要带我一起去，想想你该用什么借口；我不会承认我是不请自来的，我只能说是你邀请了我。”

“‘我们两个路上搭伴儿来的’，”他说，“这样说就行了。那么快走吧。”

阿里斯托得摩斯说，这段交谈之后，他们就出发了。但苏格拉底陷入了自己的沉思，他们一起走的时候总是落在后面。阿里斯托得摩斯也停下来时，苏格拉底就让他继续走。到达阿伽松家时，阿里斯托得摩斯发现门是开着的，并且遇到了一件很荒谬可笑的事情。家中的一位仆人看到了他，把他带进屋里，其他人都已落座，正准备用餐。阿伽松一看到他，就说：“阿里斯托得摩斯，你来得正好，和我们一起用餐吧！你要是为了别的事情而来，就先放一边。我昨天找你，要邀请你，但没找到你。苏格拉底呢——你为什么没带他一块儿来？”

他转身的时候（阿里斯托得摩斯说的），发现苏格拉底根本没跟在后面。他解释说是苏格拉底带他来的，他是受苏格拉底的邀请来参加晚宴的。

“很高兴你来了，”阿伽松说，“但是苏格拉底去哪儿了呢？”

“刚才他还在我后面。我不知道现在他在哪儿。”

“仆人，去看看，”阿伽松说，“把苏格拉底带到这儿来。阿里斯托得摩斯，请你挨着厄律克西马库坐。”

一个仆人帮阿里斯托得摩斯洗了手和脚，这样他就可以坐下了。另一个仆人过来说：“苏格拉底已经到这儿了；他退回到了邻居家的走廊里，一直站在那里，不肯进来，我请他进来也不行。”

“真奇怪，”阿伽松说，“你再去请他进来，别让他独自一人待着。”

“别，”阿里斯托得摩斯说，“随他去吧。这是他的习惯。有时他离开人群，走到哪儿，就站在那里不动了。我敢肯定他一会儿就过来。别打扰他，让他一个人待着吧。”

“好吧，如果你这样认为，那我们就这样做，”阿伽松说，“现在，仆人，给我们上菜吧。你们想上什么食物就上什么食物，没人监督你们——我从未这样做过。这一次，你们就把我及其他人当作你们晚宴的客人，要好好伺候，争取赢得我们的赞扬。”

接着他们就开始用餐了，但苏格拉底还没进来。阿伽松不停地说应该派人去叫苏格拉底，但阿里斯托得摩斯不让他这么做。实际上，苏格拉底不一会儿就来了（他没有像往常那样迟到很长时间），其他人用餐才刚用到了一半。阿伽松正好独自一人坐在末席，就说：“苏格拉底，过来坐在我旁边吧，这样靠近你，我就可以分享你在走廊中获得的智慧了。显然你已经找到了你要寻找的东西并且拥有它了；不然你不会来的。”

苏格拉底坐了下来，说：“阿伽松，如果智慧这种东西能像水一样，在双方彼此接触的时候从丰盈者流到匮乏者那里，通过一根毛线从满杯子流到空杯子中，该有多好啊。如果智慧真像这样，我把与你共坐当作莫大的荣耀。我希望用你丰富的美好智慧把自己填满。我的智慧无疑是肤浅的——更确切地说，是真是假说不清，就像梦一样——但你的智慧光辉灿烂，有巨大的发展潜力。在你还年轻的时候，你的智慧就大放异彩；前几天三万多在场的希腊同胞都见证了你的智慧。”

“你在嘲笑我，”阿伽松说，“稍后我们再争论智慧问题，让狄奥尼索斯做我们的评判员。不过现在你先把注意力放在用餐上吧。”

之后，阿里斯托得摩斯说，苏格拉底坐了下来，与其他人一起用餐。然后他们向神祭酒、唱颂神歌，进行了其他例行的礼仪，然后开始饮酒。鲍桑尼亚带了头，说了类似下面的话：“先生们，最愉快的饮酒方式是什么？我可以告诉你们，我由于昨天饮酒，今天的身体状况非常糟糕，需要多休息。我觉得你们中许多人也是这样，因为你们昨天也在场——所以想想我们应该怎样饮酒才最合适吧。”

阿里斯托芬说：“鲍桑尼亚，你说得对，我们得想办法喝得从容一些。我昨天也属于酩酊大醉之列。”

此后，阿库门努的儿子厄律克西马库说：“我赞同你的说法。但还有个人的意见我需要问问，看看他还能喝吗，那个人就是阿伽松。”

“我也绝对没有耐力再喝了。”他说。

“那我们就交了好运了——我是说，对于阿里斯托得摩斯、费德鲁斯及其他人来说——你们这些酒量最大的已经放弃了。我们永远抵不过你们。当然，我没有算苏格拉底：他可以喝也可以不喝，所以我们不管怎么做对他来说都行。既然大家没人热衷于大量饮酒，所以如果我说说醉酒是怎么回事，大概没人会觉得厌烦吧。从我的医疗经验来看，醉酒显然对人体有害。所以如果我可以随心所欲的话，我不愿意喝过头，我也不建议任何人喝过头，尤其是你还没从昨晚的宿醉中醒过来，头还昏昏沉沉时。”

这时费德鲁斯说话了：“我通常都听从你的建议，尤其是涉及医药方面的。如果其余的人都还理智的话，也该相信。”

听到这话，他们都同意不要把当前的场合弄成豪饮的局面，而是愿意喝多少就喝多少。

“好，”厄律克西马库说，“既然大家都同意愿意喝多少就喝多少，没有任何强迫与勉强，那我下一个提议是把刚进来的吹笛女打发走，让她们自吹自乐吧，或者如果她们愿意的话，吹给屋子里的女人听，我们今晚就以交谈来度过。要是你们同意的话，我想提议一个讨论的话题。”

大家都同意，让他提议。厄律克西马库说：“我以引用欧里庇得斯的《墨拉尼佩》开头：我将要讲的‘不是我自己的故事’，而是费德鲁斯的。他总是这样抱怨：‘厄律克西马库，诗人为其他的神谱写赞美诗和颂歌，但没人谱写过一首爱神的颂词，尽管他是位非常古老又非常重要的神，这岂不是很糟糕？你看看最优秀的智者（例如，杰出的普罗迪库斯），他们为赫拉克勒斯还有其他的神写颂词。可能这也不足为奇；但有一次我发现一位聪明的作者写的书，由于盐的效用，他在其中对其大力赞美——你也能发现诸多类似的颂词。人们如此重视这类东西，但至今却无人有勇气歌颂爱神应得的赞歌，这岂不是很荒唐。他是位如此伟大的神，却被忽略到如此地步！’我认为费德鲁斯在这一点上说得很对。我想让他高兴，为这件事作出自己的贡献；同时现在似乎是在座各位赞美爱神的好时机。如果你们同意，我们不需要做其他事了，就进行讨论。我提议每人尽其所能作最出色的发言，赞美爱神，然后坐在他右边的人继续。费德鲁斯应该起头，因为他不仅坐在首席，而且是这个话题的发起人。”

“没人会反对你，厄律克西马库，”苏格拉底说，“我当然也不能拒绝，因为爱这个主题是我唯一可以声称懂得的。阿伽松和鲍桑尼亚不会；阿里斯托芬也不会，他的整个事业都集中在狄奥尼索斯和阿佛洛狄特上；在座的其他任何人也不会。当然，这种安排对于我们坐在末席的人不公平。但如果先说的人说了所要求说的，并且说得很好，那我们也就满足了。费德鲁斯起头，作他对爱神的颂词，祝你好运！”

其余人都同意，让费德鲁斯按苏格拉底说的做。当然，阿里斯托得摩斯没有记住所有发言者说的话，我也没记住他说的所有的话。不过我会告诉你那些他记得最清楚、我认为最重要的人的发言。

如我所说的，阿里斯托得摩斯告诉我是费德鲁斯先说，他是这样说的：爱神被人类及诸神认为是一位伟大且了不起的神，这表现在很多方面，尤其是他的出身方面。

“爱神受人们尊敬，”费德鲁斯说，“是因为他是最古老的一位神，古老就是一种荣誉，可以由这个事实来论证：爱神没有父母，散文或诗歌里也从未提到过他的父母。但与此相反，赫西奥德说首先存在的是一片混沌，‘然后是宽阔的大地，为一切事物提供了永久、安全的根基，然后就是爱。’阿里斯托得摩斯同意赫西奥德的说法，说混沌之后两样东西出现了，即大地和爱。关于他的出身，巴门尼德说‘她创造的第一位神即是爱神’。所以爱神的古老历史已广为人们接受。

“由于其古老历史，他是我们最大福祉的源泉。我会宣称，对于青年来说，没有什么比拥有一位钟爱自己的爱人更幸福了；对爱人来说，没有什么比一位好情郎更幸福了。不管是亲情、社会地位、财富，还是其他任何东西，在向那些想要过上好生活的人灌输毕生指导方面的东西时，没有一个比爱更有效。这原则是什么呢？这是一种厌恶丑陋、爱慕美好的意识在起作用。没有这些，没有任何人或任何城邦能获得伟大或高尚的事物。

“以一个处于热恋中的人为例，他被发现做了不光彩的事，或经历了某些可耻的事情，因为他受人凌辱而懦弱不敢反抗。我认为这种情况下，被他的情郎看见会比被他的父亲、朋友或其他任何人看见给他带来更多的痛苦。若是情郎的话，我们也会看到同样的情景：若他被发现处于某种可耻的情形中，他会在他的爱人面前感觉最无地自容。如果有机制能创建由爱人和情郎组成的城邦或军队，那就没有比这更好的社会组织形式了：他们会阻止一切不光彩的事，为彼此眼中的荣誉而竞争。即使一小部分这样的人并肩作战，也几乎可以打败整个人类。爱人在从战线退缩或丢弃自己的武器时，最不能容忍被他的情郎看到；相反，他宁愿死千百回。至于抛弃自己的情郎或没能在危险中帮助他——没人会如此懦弱，不能从爱中激发出勇气，与天生就很勇敢的人相匹敌。当荷马说一位神‘把力量吹进’一些英雄体内时，这是爱情对爱人才会产生的效果。

“而且，只有爱人才会愿意为对方而死；这对女人和男人都适用。希腊人能从珀利阿斯的女儿阿尔刻提斯身上找到这一事实的充分证据，她是唯一一个愿意替她丈夫去死的人，尽管他的父亲和母亲都还活着。她将爱付诸行动，展示出了超出父母的深切关爱，使他们看起来像自己儿子的陌生人一样，只是名义上的亲属罢了。诸神以及人类都把这看作是高尚的行为。尽管许多人表现出许多高尚的行为，尽管神只授予少数人将生命从冥界再还阳一次的特权，但他们将她从冥界放了出来，因为钦佩她的行为。这显示了即使神也多么珍视爱情激发出的承诺和勇气。

“但是他们把奥阿格罗斯之子奥尔甫斯两手空空地从冥界打发了出来；他们只给他看了他想要拥有的妻子的幻影，而没有给他这个女人本身。他们认为他很软弱（他只是个音乐家），因为他没有勇气像阿尔刻提斯那样为自己的爱人去死，而是在还活着的时候找到了进入冥界的方法。他们为此惩罚他，让他死在女人的手中。

“相反，他们钦佩忒提斯的儿子阿喀琉斯，把他送到极乐岛。他从母亲那里知道，如果他杀死赫克托耳，他自己也会死，但是如果他不杀死他，他就可以回家并长命百岁。他有勇气代表他的爱人作出选择并行动，替他报仇：他不仅为他而死，并且要和他一起死去，因为帕特洛克罗斯已经死了。这种行为赢得了诸神的特别敬佩和特殊赞誉，因为这显示了他多么珍视自己的爱人。当埃斯库罗斯在说阿喀琉斯是帕特洛克罗斯的爱人时，是在胡说八道：如荷马告诉我们的，他比帕特洛克罗斯更英俊（实际上，他是所有英雄中最英俊的），他还没有胡须，而且比帕特洛克罗斯年轻得多。尽管神给予爱情激发出的勇气特殊赞誉，但当一位情郎向自己的爱人展示出深切关爱时，与爱人对情郎这样做时相比，他们展示出更大的惊异和赞赏，也给予更慷慨的回应。爱人比情郎更像神，因为他受到了神灵的激发。这就是为什么他们给阿喀琉斯比阿尔刻提斯更高的荣誉，并把他送到极乐岛。

“这就是我为什么说爱神是最古老的神，最受人尊敬，在激发人们获得勇气和幸福方面最有效，不管是对生还是死来说都一样。”

按照阿里斯托得摩斯说的，费德鲁斯的发言大致是这样。费德鲁斯之后，有一些其他人的发言，阿里斯托得摩斯记不清了，所以他就略过了他们，接着说鲍桑尼亚的发言。鲍桑尼亚说：“费德鲁斯，我们仅仅被告知去赞美爱神，我认为我们没有作出明确规定。如果爱是单一的，那就没问题，但实际上它不是；由于它不是，那最好提前规定我们应该赞美哪种爱。我尽力把情况摆正，先说说我们应该赞美哪种爱，然后再给予诸神他应得的赞美。

“我们都知道阿佛洛狄特与爱神不可分开。如果只有一个阿佛洛狄特，那就只有一种爱；但由于有两类阿佛洛狄特，也就必须有两种爱。肯定有两类阿佛洛狄特吗？其中一个较年长，是乌拉诺斯的女儿，尽管她没有母亲：我们称她为乌拉诺斯或神圣的阿佛洛狄特。较年轻的一个是宙斯和狄俄涅的女儿：我们称她为凡间的阿佛洛狄特。因此结果就是，每一种爱，根据他是谁的伴侣，应该有与女神一样的名字，也称之为神圣的爱或凡间的爱。当然，所有的神都应该受到赞美，但我们必须尽力区分开这两个神的职能。

“每一种活动本身没有对错之分。就拿我们现在的活动为例：我们可以饮酒、唱歌或讨论。这些就其本身而言没有一种是对的；活动的性质取决于完成它的方式。如果做得适当，它就是对的；如果做得不当，它就是错的。所以并不是每一种爱和爱神都是对的，都值得赞美，只有那种激励我们以正确的方式去爱的才如此。

“凡间的爱是名副其实的‘凡俗’，效果方面没什么区别；这是下等人感受到的那种爱。这类人既受女人的吸引，也受少男的吸引，吸引他们的是肉体而不是灵魂。他们受到智力最低下的伴侣的吸引，因为他们的唯一目的是得到他们所想要的，而不关心这样做是否恰当。所以爱对他们的影响就是他们不加区别地行动：不管他们的行为是好是坏，对他们来说都一样。其原因就是，他们的爱源自更年轻的女神，由于她的出身，她本性上一部分是女的，一部分是男的。

“另一种爱源自神圣的女神，她体内没有一点儿女性的特质，完全是男性的；所以这种爱的对象是少男。这位女神也较年长，所以会避免滥用暴力。这就是为什么受这种爱激发的人倾向于男性，对本性更精力充沛和智慧的事物心怀喜爱。在受少男吸引的那一类人中，你们也可以区别那些纯粹受神圣的爱激励的人。他们只有在开始完成智力发育的时候才会受少男吸引，这通常会发生在他们开始长胡须的时候。我认为那些在这个时候开始恋爱的人做好了共度一生、终生相守的准备。他们不会利用少男的年幼无知哄骗他，引诱他，然后碰到另外合适的对象便喜新厌旧。

“甚至应该有针对与宠爱少男相关的法律，阻止他们将巨大的精力花费在结果不明的事情上。就少男而言，他们无论在心灵或身体上最终是好还是坏谁也无法预知。善良的人们为自己制定这条规则，并愿意这样做。应该强迫凡俗的爱的追随者采用同样的规则，就像我们尽自己最大努力强行阻止他们爱恋自由民妇女一样。这种凡俗的爱情使人们对爱情有了不好的印象，也给爱带来了不良声誉，以至于一些人竟然说满足爱人的要求是错的。人们这样说，是因为他们考虑的是这类人的卑鄙放荡的行为；当然，如果行为是以有条理的方式进行且符合通常的规范，就不会招致批评指责。

“其他城邦管理恋爱的规范都用了明确的语言进行规定，很容易被人领会。但在斯巴达这里却很复杂。在厄利斯和比奥夏，以及人们不擅长演讲的地方，有明确的规定，认为满足爱人的需求是对的，不管老少，没人会说那是错的。毫无疑问，这是因为他们不愿费尽心思通过劝说赢得少男，别忘了他们本来都是不够格的演说家。但在爱奥尼亚的许多地方以及波斯帝国的其他地方，规定恋爱是错的。在波斯，由于其残暴的政府，人们谴责他们，还谴责智力和体育活动。毫无疑问，在他们的政府中，人们不适合有伟大的思想或建立深厚的友谊和私人关系，这些都是通过这些活动，尤其是爱情促成的。在雅典，暴君通过自己的经验发现了这一点：亚里斯托杰顿的爱及哈尔摩狄奥斯互相爱慕的力量使他们的统治走向了终点。所以在有这样的基本规则（即满足爱人的需求是错误的）的地方，就可以将其归结为制定这条规则的人自身的缺陷：政府对权力的贪求和人民的懦弱。而在一些地方，认为这是完全正确的，那是因为规则的制定者头脑迟钝。

“在雅典，我们的规范比那些地方强得多；但正如我刚才说的，这些规范不太容易理解。据说公开地去爱比秘密地爱更好，尤其是你爱的是具有社会地位和良好品行的少男时，即使他们不是特别英俊。而且爱人从众人那里得到巨大的鼓舞，暗示他做的不是可耻的事；获取你想要的少男的心被认为是高尚的行为，而未能获取则被认为是可耻的。当爱人尽力抓获少男的心时，规范允许他因做非凡的事而赢得赞美。如果他胆敢在做这些事时有任何其他目的和意图，他将会受到强烈的谴责。

“比如说，一个人想从别人那里得到钱，或政治职务或其他某种势力，他就去做像爱人对待自己喜爱的少男那样的事情。想象一下，他会像个哀求者一样双膝跪地，乞求他想要的东西，发誓，整夜都待在人家的门阶上，准备好遭受任何仆人都不会做的奴性行为。他的朋友和仇敌都会阻止他这样做；他的敌人会批评他为了得到想要的东西而使自己蒙受耻辱，而他的朋友会责备他，并为他感到羞耻。但当爱人这样做时，规范就会纵容他并允许他逃避批评，意味着他的意图反而会得到赞扬。最值得注意的是，人们普遍认为神会宽恕的未能遵从誓言的唯一的人即是爱人。他们说，爱人的誓言根本不是誓言。所以，根据我们的规范，神以及人给予了爱人各种纵容。从这个观点来看，你会认为在这个城邦，成为爱人并热切地回应爱人是非常值得赞扬的事。

“另一方面，当少男吸引爱人时，他们的父亲会让仆人管束他们，明确规定不让少男与爱人交谈。少男的朋友和同龄人如果看到这样的事发生时就会谩骂他们，长辈也不去阻止这种谩骂，或责备他们这样说话。你们看到这种情况时，就会想，相比之下，在我们这个城邦里，恋爱会被认为是很丢人的事。

“我认为情况是这样的。这种事并不十分单纯；如我之前说的，恋爱本身没有对错之分，行为恰当时它即是对，行为不当时它即是错。以不当的方式满足坏人的需求即是错的，以恰当的方式满足好人的需求即是对的。在这一点上，卑鄙的对象即是上面提到的凡俗的爱人，他们爱肉体而不是灵魂。他所爱的东西不是恒定不变的，所以他的爱也不会始终如一：一旦肉体的花蕊（这正是吸引他的东西）凋谢，‘他就远走高飞，消失不见了’，毁掉他以前所有的誓言。但那些热爱良好品行的人终其一生都是恒定不变的，因为他们所爱的东西也是始终如一的。

“我们考验的目的是要充分地、以恰当的方式检验爱人，确保少男满足一种，而远离另一种。这就是为什么我们同时鼓励爱人去追逐少男，又鼓励少男躲避爱人。这是一种比赛，来检验爱人属于哪一类，少男属于哪一类。这就解释了为什么快速俘获内心被认为是错误的：就是为了确保时间起到干预作用，这被认为是检验多数事物的好方法。这也解释了为什么被爱人的金钱或政治权力俘获被认为是错误的。这种情况下，少男要么由于受虐待而害怕地屈从，要么可耻地享受金钱或政治成就的利益。这些东西没有一样被认为是稳定或永恒的，除了这样一个事实，即没有真正的感情能建立在这样的基础之上。

“根据我们的规则，只剩下一种方法，少男以这种方法满足他的爱人是正确的。我之前说过，爱人愿意忍受各种奴役且不算献媚也不受谴责。同样，根据我们的规则，只有一种自愿的奴役不受谴责：那种目的是要产生美德的奴役。我们的观点是，如果某个人愿意屈身为他人效劳，相信那个人会帮助他提升智慧或其他方面的美德，那么这种自愿的奴役并无不对，也不丢脸。

“这两条规则必须合二为一（一条规定对少男的爱，一条规定对智慧及其他美德的爱），才能创造出少男满足他的爱人无过错的条件。当爱人和情郎集合起来，每一方都遵守相应的规则时，这些条件就实现了：爱人完全可以为满足了自己需求的情郎做任何事，情郎也完全可以为使自己变得智慧和高尚的人做任何事。而且一般来说爱人必须能够增进情郎的理解力和品德，情郎必须想要获得教育和智慧。当所有这些条件都满足时，而且只有这时，情郎满足爱人的需求才是对的，而不是相反的情况。

“这种情况下，被欺骗也没什么错；但是，除此之外，爱就是错的，不管你是否被欺骗。假设一个少男认为他的爱人很富有，由于贪恋钱财就满足了他；如若结果证明这位爱人很贫穷，少男没得到任何钱，那他做的仍是错的。这类少男显示了他品性中的一些东西：他愿意为了挣钱为任何人效劳，而那是不对的。在同样的基础上，假设一位少男认为他的爱人是个好人，就满足了他，希望通过和他的爱人的交往使自己变得更好。如果结果证明这位爱人是个坏人，缺乏美德，这样被欺骗也没有耻辱。这类少男也显示了他品性中的一些东西：他为了获得美德、使自己变得更好，愿意为他人做任何事，没有什么动机比这更值得赞扬了。所以为了获得美德而满足爱人是完全正确的。这是属于神圣女神的神圣之爱，对城邦和个人来说都是巨大价值的来源，因为它迫使爱人和情郎重视自己的品德。其他形式的爱都来源于另一位一般的爱神。

“费德鲁斯，这就是我对爱的理解，”他说，“这是我在没准备的情况下能说的最好的了。”

当鲍桑尼亚停下来时（我是从专家那里学的这种拐弯抹角的说话技巧），阿里斯托得摩斯说，轮到阿里斯托芬发言了。但是，巧合的是，他由于吃得过多或其他原因正在打嗝，无法说话。他对厄律克西马库（这位医生正坐在他下一位）说：“正巧，你要么帮助我止住嗝，要么替我说，直到我不打嗝为止。”厄律克西马库回答道：“两件事我都做。我来取代你的位置，等轮到我的时候你再讲。我发言时，你屏住呼吸，可能就可以止住嗝；如果没止住，你就用水漱漱口。如果还是打嗝，你就用个东西戳一下鼻孔，让自己打个喷嚏。这样一两次，不管多么顽固的嗝儿，都可以止得住了。”

“尽快开始你的发言吧，”阿里斯托芬说，“我照你说的办。”

厄律克西马库说：“我是这样认为的：鲍桑尼亚的发言，开头很好，但没有贯彻下去，结尾处不是很相称，所以我尽力完成他的论证。我认为他对爱情有两重性，作了很妥当的区分。但是爱不仅可以通过人们对英俊的人的情绪反应来表达，而且还有许多种其他类型的反应：既可以追溯到动物的生殖，也可以追溯到植物的生长。我可以说，存在于神圣的或世俗的各种活动中的爱的威力适用于一切类型的存在物。我确信，我是从医学、从我自己的专业领域认识到爱神的威力有多么伟大、多么美妙，他的力量延伸到人类和神圣生命的各个方面。

“我将从医学开始，为了对我自己从事的行业表示尊敬。身体的性质中天生就显示出了这两种爱。人们通常认为身体的健康和疾病是不同的状态，彼此互不相同。当事物不同时，它们渴望和爱的对象也不同。因此，在身体健康和患有疾病的情况下爱是不同的。鲍桑尼亚刚才说，满足好人是对的，而满足放纵的人是错的。身体也一样。对于每个身体，满足好的部分是对的，且你应该这样做（行医就是这个意思）；但满足不好的、有病的部分就是错的，若你打算成为医术高明的人，就应该剥夺那部分的满足。

“实质上，医学就是关于填满和排空身体之爱的各种形式的知识。医生最重要的是能区分出这些过程中正确的和错误的爱。好的医生能引起改变，这样身体就能获得一种爱而不是另一种；当一种爱不在那里而应该在那里时，他知道如何来灌输这种爱，并排除在那里的另一种爱。他应该能够取出身体中最具对抗性的元素，在它们之间建立友谊和爱。最具对抗性的元素是对立的，如冷与热，苦与甜，干与湿，等等。找到在这些元素之间灌输爱与和谐的方法的人是我们的祖先阿斯克勒庇俄斯（这是一些诗人告诉我们的，有些就在这里，我相信他们），他就是这样创建医学的。

“如我所说的，医学完全由这位神掌管，他也掌管体育和农业；任何人思考片刻都会清楚，这一点也适用于音乐。这可能是赫拉克利特心里所想的，虽然他没有很好地表达出来。关于团结，他说：‘通过背离，它与自身达成一致。……就像弓或琴的和谐。’若说和谐与自身背离，或它的构成要素仍然分离的时候它就存在，是很荒谬的。但可能他心里想的是，音乐的技艺是通过用一致性替换高音和低音之间的分歧，从而创造和谐。高音和低音仍分离的时候，它们之间当然不会存在和谐。和谐就是协调，协调是一种一致性；但是当分离的东西仍分离时就不能从中创建一致性，只有当分离的东西一致时才能创造和谐。同样，韵律是通过用一致性替换快拍和慢拍之间的分离创造出来的。正如医学在一个区域内创造一致性，音乐通过向涉及的元素中灌输爱和协调，在另一个区域内创造它；反过来，音乐就是与和谐和韵律有关的爱的各种形式的知识。

“在和谐和韵律的结构中，考虑其自身，不难发现爱的作用；所以爱的双重性在这里没有呈现出来。但是当用韵律与和谐对人产生影响时，不管是创作音乐（他们称之为‘作曲’），还是恰当运用曲调和诗歌（称为‘教育’），困难就出现了，需要好的音乐大师了。这里同样的原则仍然有效：你应该满足并促进秩序井然的人们的爱，或者那些尚未秩序井然但能用这种方式获得改善的人的爱。这种爱是美好的、神圣的，是神圣的缪斯之爱。但一般的爱是缪斯圣歌女神之爱；当是这种爱时，我们必须慎重，确保爱的接受者享受它提供的欢愉，而不会变得放纵。同样，在我的专业领域，工作的一个关键部分是正确处理通过烹饪艺术满足的欲望，确保人们享受这种欢愉，而不生病。所以在音乐、医学及其他所有领域中，既有人类的也有神的，我们必须尽其所能地留意这两种爱，因为这两种爱都存在。

“季节的特性也是由这两种爱决定的。当我之前提到的那些元素（热与冷、干与湿）受到秩序井然的爱的影响时，它们就会彼此协调一致，风调雨顺。它们的到来就会为人类及其他动植物带来丰收和健康，不会造成危害。但是当无节制的、暴力的爱主导季节时，它们就会造成巨大的破坏。这些情况常常会造成牲畜和植物得瘟疫及其他反常疾病。霜冻、冰雹和疫病是受这种爱的影响，互相激烈竞争和陷入混乱而产生的结果。所以我们所说的天文学是关于爱的作用的知识，因为这些影响星辰的运动和四季的推移。

“而且，各种祭祀和占卜的所有活动（这些是神与人类互相交流的方式）都在于维持一种爱，而消除另一种。当人们未满足、尊重或把活动中的首要位置让给秩序井然的爱时，而且对另一种爱做了这些，那么就常常会出现对自己父母（活着的或去世的）或神的不尊敬。预言有一个职责，就是留意那些错误的爱，并将其消除。它还有一个职责，就是通过理解人类生命中爱的运作如何影响正确的行为和虔诚之心，在神和人类之间产生友谊。

“所以当把这一切集合在一起时，爱作为整体拥有巨大（更确切地说是所有的）力量。但是拥有最大力量的爱是那种本性表现在良好的行为中、以自制和正义为标志、在人类和神的层级上的爱，它是我们所有幸福的源泉。它使我们能够与彼此及神交往并成为朋友。

“可能我对爱神的颂词遗漏了许多东西，如果是这样，我并不是故意的。如果我遗漏了任何东西，阿里斯托芬，该你来填补缺口了。或者，如果你想到了其他对神的颂词，就继续说吧，你已经不打嗝了。”

现在轮到阿里斯托芬了（阿里斯托得摩斯说的），他说：“是的，已经不打嗝了，但是直到我用打喷嚏的方法后才停下来。这让我怀疑是否是我身体中‘秩序井然’的部分想要那种噪音和让我打喷嚏的挠痒。无论如何，我一打喷嚏嗝立刻就止住了。”

“亲爱的阿里斯托芬，”厄律克西马库说，“当心你正在做的事。你一开口就开玩笑，这让我不得不提防着你的玩笑，不然你的发言就可以不被打扰了。”

“你说得对，厄律克西马库，”阿里斯托芬说，“我收回刚才说的话。但如果你留意我的发言的话，别以为我不敢说一些有趣的事（那是我的缪斯女神的特权和典型特征），我是害怕说了荒唐的话。”

厄律克西马库说：“你认为你可以射我一箭然后就逃跑啊！好吧，当心了；你必须对你说的话负责。不过即使如此，如果我下了决心，我也会放你一马的。”

“事实上，厄律克西马库，”阿里斯托芬说，“我确实打算采用一种与你和鲍桑尼亚发言中不同的方式。我认为人们完全没有认识到爱神的力量；如果他们领会了这一点，他们会为他建造最大的寺庙和祭坛，做最大规模的祭祀。事实上，人们没有为他做其中任何一项，虽然他是最值得这样做的。他比其他任何神都更爱人类；他是他们的助手，是疾病的医治者，那些疾病的治愈构成了人类最大的幸福。我会试着把他的力量解释给你们听，你们再把这些传授给其他人。

“首先，你们必须要了解人类的本性以及它发生了什么变化。很久以前，我们的本性与现在的不同，而且有很大的差异。首先，人类有三种性别，而不是现在的男性和女性两种。还有第三种，它结合了这两种；现在它的名字保存了下来，不过这种性别已经消失了。‘阴阳人’是一种独特的性别，也是一个名字，它结合了男性和女性的特征；现在除了名字什么也没留下，现在它的名字是对人的侮辱。

“其次，最初的人外形是个圆形的整体，背部和两侧形成了一个圆。每个人有四只手、四条腿，圆形的脖子上有两张一样的脸。一个头上有两张脸，朝向相反，有四只耳朵，两个生殖器，其余的你们可以从我刚才说的话中想象出来。他们可以笔直地来回走动，像我们现在一样，可以随心所欲地朝任何一个方向走。当他们要动身快跑时，就用八肢支撑着自己的身体，快速地旋转着移动，就像翻筋斗一样，他们在旋转时，腿伸直着翻筋斗。

“之所以有这三种性别以及他们如描述的那样，是因为男性最初是由太阳生的，女性是由大地生的，而阴阳人是由月亮生的，因为月亮是太阳和大地的结合体。他们是圆的，所以他们也以圆形的方式移动，因为他们与自己的父母相像。他们在力量和活力方面很糟糕；他们有雄心壮志，向神发起进攻。荷马讲的关于厄菲阿尔忒斯和俄图斯的故事，说他们如何尝试着爬上天国攻击诸神，实际上指的就是他们。宙斯和其他神讨论如何对付他们，但没有得出结论。诸神不知道如何能杀死他们，不能像以前对待巨人那样用雷电把人类全部消灭；如果他们那样做的话，诸神从他们那里得到的荣誉和祭品将会消失。但也不能让他们再这样蛮横无理下去。在经过深思之后，宙斯有了一个主意：‘我有个计划，通过这个计划人类还可以继续存在，但非常虚弱，不能再有这样的野蛮行径了。我现在把他们每个人一分为二；他们将变得虚弱，也对我们更有用，因为他们人数增多了。他们将用两条腿直立行走。如果我们觉得他们仍然蛮横，不肯安静下来，我就再把他们分成两半，这样他们就只能用一条腿跳着走路了。’

“说完之后，宙斯把人劈成了两半，就像人们把苹果切成两半或把煮熟的蛋切开一样。他在切每个人的时候，告诉阿波罗把他们的脸和与之相连的半面脖颈扭向伤口那面，这样人类就能看到自己的伤口，变得懂规矩点儿；宙斯也让他治愈其他伤口。阿波罗扭转了脸；他把周身的皮肤拉向现在称为腹部的方向（就像用拉链把手提袋拉紧一样），然后在腹部的中央留了一个口，我们称之为肚脐。他也磨平了许多其他褶皱，把胸部弄成鞋匠磨平皮革的褶皱时使用的工具的形状。但他留了一些肚脐附近的褶皱，提醒人类很久以前发生在他们身上的事。

“由于他们被分成两半了，每个人都想念自己的另一半，希望能与另一半在一起。他们用胳膊搂着彼此，交织在一起，想要形成一个单独的个体。所以他们死于饥饿和凝滞不动，因为他们不想离开彼此。当其中一半死去，另一半被剩下时，剩下的那一半就寻找另一个，与另一个交织在一起。有时他遇到的那一个是女人的一半（这一半我们现在称为‘女人’），有时是剖开的男人的一半。不管怎样，他们继续以这种方式死去。

“宙斯怜悯他们，想出了另一个办法：他把他们的生殖器移到前面来；那之前，他们的生殖器在身体的后面，不是与彼此交配进行有性繁殖，而是在地上繁殖，就像蝉一样。所以宙斯把生殖器移到前面，这样通过男女交配进行繁殖。这样做的目的在于，如果男人遇到女人，进行交配，就会繁殖后代，人类就可以延续。并且，如果两个男人在一起，他们至少能得到性交的满足感，然后平息情欲、放松、继续工作，考虑生活中的其他事情。

“从远古时代人类对彼此内在的渴望就是这样开始的。它吸引我们本性的两部分恢复到一起，尽力合二为一，治愈人类从前剖开的伤口。我们每个人都是人类要匹配的一半，因为我们像比目鱼一样被分成两半，被一分为二，我们每个人都在寻找匹配自己的另一半。从阴阳人（那时称为雌雄同体）被切开的男人为女人所吸引，许多奸夫属于这一群体。同样，为男人所吸引、成为淫妇的女人也属于这一群体。那些被从女性切开的女人对男人一点儿也不感兴趣，而更多地受到女人的吸引，女同性恋属于这个群体。

“那些被从男性切开的人喜爱男性。当他们还是少男时，由于他们是男性的一部分，他们受到男人的吸引，喜欢与男人一起睡、被他们拥抱。这些是他们那一代中最好的人，不管是少男还是青年，因为他们天生是最勇敢的。有些人说他们无耻，但并不是这样。他们这样做并不是由于无耻，而是因为他们大胆、勇敢、有阳刚之气，并赞赏其他人的这种品质。下面就是明显证据：这样的男人长大后，是唯一能成为政治家的人。当他们成人后，会受到少男的性吸引；他们没有要结婚娶妻生子的本能愿望，尽管按照规范他们会被迫做这些。他们自己对不结婚而和爱人相守共度人生很满足。总之，这样的人成为少男的爱人，少男热爱自己的男性爱人，总是喜欢他们共同的本性。

“当少男的爱人或其他类人遇到自己的另一半时，他就会欣喜若狂，显示出喜爱、关怀和爱慕。两人一刻也不想离开彼此。这些人终生都在一起度过，但仍说不出想从彼此那里得到什么。我的意思是，没有人会认为他们想要的仅是性交，这正是他们在彼此的陪伴中找到如此多的乐趣并对它如此重视的原因。显然他们每个人心中都有一些无法表达的愿望；他像圣人一样，部分领会了自己所想要的，并隐晦地对别人进行暗示。想象一下，当他们躺在一起时，赫菲斯托斯拿着工具在旁边看着他们，并问：‘人类，你想从对方身上得到什么？’如果他们不知道，想象他会接着问：‘这是你们想要的吗，完完整整地在一起，无论白天黑夜都不分离？如果这是你们想要的，我就把你们融合在一起，这样你们两个就变成一个人了。然后你们两人只要活着，就可以共享生命，因为你们是一个人；当你们死亡时，你们作为一个人而不是两个人，共享冥界中的死亡。但是先想想这是不是你们渴望的，实现这种状态是否能满足你们。’我们都知道，听到这种提议的人没一个会拒绝，显然没人会想要其他东西了。每个人都会想，他现在听到的正是他一直以来渴望的东西：与所爱的人在一起，融为一体，合二为一而不是两个人。其原因就是这是我们最初的自然状态，我们过去是完整的个体：‘爱’是渴望并追求完整之名。

“在这之前，如我说的，我们是一体的；但是现在，由于自己的罪恶，我们被宙斯分开了，就像阿卡迪亚人被斯巴达人分开了一样。还有这种危险，即如果我们对神灵不守规矩，我们会被进一步分开，像墓碑上浮雕中的人一样走动，被从鼻子锯成两半，像半个骰子一样。所以每个人都应该鼓励他人对神灵显出全部应有的尊敬，这样我们就可以避免一种惩罚，实现另一种结果，把爱神作为我们的领袖和将领。没人应该违背爱神，站在错误的神的一边即是违背爱神。如果我们是神的朋友并把他拉到我们这一边，我们应该做现在几乎无人做的事——找到真正属于我们的爱人并与之亲近。

“我不想让厄律克西马库认为我的发言仅是个喜剧，针对的是鲍桑尼亚和阿伽松。很可能他们属于这种类型，都是男性本质的另一半。但我所说的也适用于所有的男人和女人：只有当爱得出结论，每个人找到自己的爱人并恢复最初的本性，我们人类才能获得幸福。如果这是理想状态，当前环境下最接近它的必定是最好的：即找一个与你自己的品性最适合的爱人。如果我们想赞美对这件事负责的神，我们当然应该赞美爱神。在当前情况下，他为我们做了能做的最好的，指引我们走向天生与我们接近的事物。他也为我们提供了未来最大的希望：即如果我们尊敬神，他将把我们恢复为最初的本性，使我们愈合，从而给我们最好的幸福。

“好了，厄律克西马库，这就是我关于爱的发言，和你的迥然不同。就像我刚才说的，别把我的发言当作玩笑。咱们继续，看看剩下的发言者有什么要说的——更确切地说是两个，因为只剩下阿伽松和苏格拉底了。”

“我会按你说的做的，”厄律克西马库说，“不管怎样，我非常欣赏你的颂词。如果我事先不知道苏格拉底和阿伽松是爱情这个题目的专家的话，我会担心他们可能没什么可说的了，因为我们已经有这么多种发言了。不过，照目前的情况，对于他们两位，我还是很有信心的。”

苏格拉底说：“那是因为你们成功参与了我们的竞争。如果你处在我的位置上，更确切地说是处在阿伽松也做了精彩发言之后我所在的位置，你将会诚惶诚恐，处在和我一样的窘境之中。”

“你在设法给我施咒语，苏格拉底，”阿伽松说，“让我觉得观众对我的发言有很高期望，从而让我紧张。”

“阿伽松，如果我那样做的话，那就未免太健忘了吧，”苏格拉底说，“你站在舞台上，领着演员们高视阔步地登台，面对众多的观众展示自己的作品时没有一点儿慌张，我看到了你那时展示出来的勇气和自信。所以我认为你不会在我们这个小团体面前紧张。”

“但是，苏格拉底，”阿伽松说，“我希望你不要认为我对剧场如此着迷，以至于没有意识到少数几个有智慧的人比一群无知的人更使人担心。”

“阿伽松，”苏格拉底说，“如果我认为你在任何方面都天真无邪，那我就是大错特错了。我很清楚，如果你发现了一些你认为聪明的人，你给予他们的注意力会比给予一般群众的多。但恐怕我们不属于那一类；毕竟我们也在那里，是那群人的一部分。但如果你找到了其他一些聪明的人，若你觉得在他们面前做了一些错事，你可能会感到羞愧——你是不是这个意思？”

“是的。”阿伽松答道。

“但如果你在一般群众面前做了错事就不会感到羞愧吗？”

这时候费德鲁斯插话了：“亲爱的阿伽松，如果你回答苏格拉底的问题，只要他有讨论的伙伴，尤其是有魅力的人，他不会在乎我们当前的活动是否会有进展。我喜欢听苏格拉底的讨论，但我必须负责对爱神的颂词，从你们每个人的发言中提取一些内容作为你们的贡献。因此你们两人作完对神的颂词后，再继续进行辩论吧。”

“你说得对，费德鲁斯，”阿伽松说，“我没有理由不发言。至于和苏格拉底的辩论，以后会有足够多的机会。

“我打算先说一下我认为应该怎么说，然后再开始讲。我认为之前的所有发言者都不是赞美神灵，而是称颂人类从神那里得到幸福。没人谈论给予我们这些东西的神灵自身的本性。不管话题是什么，作颂词只有一种正确的方式，就是定义颂扬的主题的性质及这个主题产生的效果。所以，就爱神来说，正确的做法是先赞美他的性质，然后赞美他的天赋。

“我敢说，虽然所有的神灵都是幸福的，但爱神（如果这样说合适且不冒犯任何人的话）是最幸福的，因为他是最英俊、最优秀的。他最英俊，是因为：首先，费德鲁斯，他是最年轻的神。他自己匆忙地从老年（它比应该的更快地发生在我们身上）逃离，也为这一点提供了证据。爱天生讨厌老年，并与之保持距离。他总是与年轻人结交，是他们中的一分子；古语说得对，物以类聚。虽然我赞同费德鲁斯说的许多话，但我不赞同爱神比克罗诺斯和伊阿珀托斯年长。我敢说，他是诸神中最年轻的，且会永葆青春。根据赫西奥德和巴门尼德说的，古代诸神对彼此做的事（他们说的是真的）是由于必要性而非爱。如果爱神在他们当中，诸神就不会阉割或囚禁彼此，或进行许多其他暴行；就像现在及爱神开始管理诸神时一样，他们之间会有友谊与和平。

“他既年轻，又娇嫩；但需要有荷马那样素养的诗人才能说出他有多娇嫩。荷马把妄想神说成是一位女神，她也很娇嫩；至少她的脚很娇嫩，如他说的：

但对大地来说，她的脚很娇嫩；

她从不靠近人类，而是行走在他们的头上。

荷马说她不在坚硬的东西上行走，而是走在柔软的东西上，我认为这是她的娇嫩性的明显证据。爱神的娇嫩也可运用同样的证据。他不在大地或头骨（它一点儿也不软）上行走，而是行走并居住在最柔软的东西之中。他在神和人类的品性和头脑中安家；但并不是所有的头脑，而是当发现具有坚韧性格的人时，他就会继续前进，当发现具有柔和性格的人时，他就定居下来。由于他不断地与最柔软的事物中最柔和的成员接触，不只用他的脚，而是全身心地接触，他必定极其娇嫩。

“所以他很年轻、很娇嫩，形体上也是流动的。否则，如果他很粗暴的话，他就不能完全遮盖人们的心灵，或穿梭于其中时不被发觉。他形体良好、流畅的充分证据在于他的优雅，人们普遍认为这是爱的独特特征（粗俗与爱总是互为仇敌）。他总在花丛中打发时间，这个事实可以体现他面容之姣好。爱神不栖身在没有花朵或花朵凋谢的身体、心灵或事物上；但当他发现有花朵盛开和芳香的地方，他就停留下来。

“关于爱神的美貌已经说够多了（虽然还有许多可说）；我接下来必须说的话题是爱神的美德。最重要的一点是，爱神在与神或人交往时，不做不公正的事，他自己也没遭受不公正的事。当爱神身上发生神秘事时，从来不是靠武力进行的（因为爱从来不是被迫的）。当爱神做事时，他也从不使用武力，因为每个人都赞成爱的所有命令；任何双方同意的事，就是‘城邦的主宰即法律’规定为正义的事。

“和正义一样，爱神也是非常节制的。人们普遍认为，节制掌管着欢愉和欲望，没有什么欢愉能比得上爱。如果欢愉较弱的话，必定是受爱掌控，他必是它们的主人；如果爱掌控着欢愉和欲望，他必定异常节制。

“至于勇敢，‘即使阿瑞斯也敌不过’爱神。不是阿瑞斯俘获了爱，而是爱俘获了阿瑞斯（据说是阿佛洛狄特的爱），俘获者掌控着被俘获者。掌控着其他人中最勇敢者的人必定是所有人中最勇敢的。

“我已经说了爱神的公正、节制和勇气；还需要说的是他的智慧。我必须尽可能充分地阐述这一点。首先——像厄律克西马库敬重自己的专业领域一样，我也对自己的领域表示敬重——爱神是如此熟练的诗人，他使其他人也成为了诗人。任何人受到爱的触动时，都会变成诗人，‘即使以前与缪斯是陌生人的人也这样’。我们可以把这作为证据，认为爱神是各种艺术作品的优秀创作者，因为你不可能给予他人你没有的东西，或教导他人你自己不知道的东西。当然，关于生物的创造，谁会否认是由于爱，一切生物才存在并被创造出来呢？关于在艺术或工艺方面的专门技术，我们不是都知道那些受爱神教导的人最后都声名显赫，而那些没被他触动的人都默默无闻吗？阿波罗跟随着自己的欲望和爱为他指引的路，才发现了箭术、医药和预言，这使得阿波罗成为爱神的学生。同样，他使缪斯成为他在音乐方面的学生，赫菲斯托斯成为他在冶炼方面的学生，雅典娜成为他在编织方面的学生，宙斯成为他在掌管神和人类方面的学生。所以只有当爱神出生后，诸神的活动才变得有条理——爱美，当然，因为爱不可能指向丑陋。在那之前，如我开始说的，神在必要的统治之下做了许多坏事。但一旦爱神降生，所有的好事都由于爱美而发生在神和人身上。

“所以，费德鲁斯，在我看来，爱神自身是极美、极优秀的，并且创立了各种美好善良的东西。我心情很激动，想用韵文来表述，我认为爱促成了：

人类的和平，大海的风平浪静，

狂风的平息，痛苦的寂然长眠。

爱排除了我们的隔阂，用亲密填满我们，使我们聚在一起像现在这样分享感受，节日、合唱和祭祀时他来担当我们的领导者。他迎来温和，逐出野蛮。他对友好慷慨大方，对敌意心胸狭窄。他亲切、和善；受到智者的关注、神的钦佩；拒绝他的人渴望他，欣赏他的人珍惜他；他是豪华、典雅、精美、优雅、欲望、渴望的父亲；他关心好人，无视坏人；在困难、恐惧、渴望和演说中，他是最好的舵手、水兵、伙伴和拯救者。对所有的神和人类来说，他是最优美、最好的领导者；每个人都应该跟着他唱优美的赞美诗，分享他唱的歌，吸引每一位神灵和人类的心灵。

“费德鲁斯，这就是我的发言，”他说，“是我对爱神的献辞；在我能掌控的范围内，诙谐并有一定的严肃性。”

阿里斯托得摩斯说，阿伽松发完言后，在场的每个人都发出了钦佩的呐喊声，因为这个年轻人的发言某种程度上很好地映射在了他自己及爱神身上。苏格拉底看着阿里斯托得摩斯说：“阿库门努的儿子，你还认为我之前的忧虑是庸人自扰吗？我刚才说阿伽松会作精彩发言，我将难以为继，不是很有预见性吗？”

“有一点，”厄律克西马库说，“你很有预见性，就是你说阿伽松将做精彩发言；但我认为你不会无言以对的。”

“我的好朋友，”苏格拉底说，“跟在如此优美华丽的发言后面，我或其他任何人怎么不会无言以对呢？其余部分还不让人吃惊；但到最后时，谁会不被他优美的语言和措辞打动呢？我知道，我的发言远远达不到这种精妙，我非常惭愧，差点儿从这儿逃跑（我若是有其他地方可去，就逃跑了）。他的发言让我想起了高尔吉斯，所以我的体验和荷马描述的一模一样。我还担心阿伽松在发言结束时，会拿出雄辩的演说家高尔吉斯的头颅给我看，使我哑口无言。然后我意识到，我若同意加入你们一起颂扬爱神、宣称拥有爱情方面的专长，我就是在愚弄自己；实际上我对颂扬某物都包含什么内容一无所知。我非常天真，竟以为你们会讲讲颂扬这个主题的真相；我认为这应该是基础，然后从中选择最出色的特点，以能呈现主题的最佳方式对其进行阐述。我自豪的是我认为能做精彩发言，因为我知道如何就一个主题进行颂扬的真相。

“但事实上，似乎这不是赞美事物的正确方式。相反，你应该宣称你的主题有最伟大、最出色的品质，不管它是否真的有；如果你说的不是真的，也没什么关系。现在提议做的似乎是我们每个人应该装出赞美爱神的样子，并不是说我们真的应该这样做。你们其余人找到任何可说的事物，把它归因于爱，说他像这样，对那件事负责，使他看起来尽可能地出色、优秀，必定就是这个原因。你们显然是对无知者这样做（当然不是对理解这个主题的人这样做）；你们的颂扬当然很优美，令人印象很深刻。

“但是我并不知道进行颂扬的正确方式，我是由于无知才同意在轮到我时进行发言的。但那是‘舌头’承诺的，而不是‘心’；所以忘了我的承诺吧。我不会进行那种颂扬的——我不能那样做。然而，若你们愿意的话，我准备告诉你们真相，不过是以我自己的方式，不与你们的发言进行竞争，这可能会让我自己看起来有点儿荒谬。所以，费德鲁斯，告诉我是否有进行那种发言的必要，那样的发言会讲出爱的真相，但使用的是发言时正好出现在我头脑中的词和句子。”

费德鲁斯及其他人让他以自己认为最好的方式进行发言。

“费德鲁斯，”苏格拉底说，“你能也允许我问阿伽松几个小问题，这样我可以根据与他达成的共识进行发言吗？”

“我同意，”费德鲁斯说，“随便问吧。”

然后，阿里斯托得摩斯说，苏格拉底开始了他的发言。

“亲爱的阿伽松，我认为你的发言有个很好的开头，你说我们应该先说出爱的品性，然后说他产生的效果。我认为以那样的方式开头值得赞扬。那么，既然你在其他方面出色地阐述了爱的性质，也请告诉我这一点。爱的性质是对某物的爱，还是没有对象的爱？我并不是问爱是否是某个特定父母的孩子；如果在这个意义上我问爱是对母亲的爱还是对父亲的爱，会很荒谬。但是假设我问的问题是，一位父亲是否是某人的父亲。如果你想给出正确答案，你当然会说父亲是儿子或女儿的父亲，是吗？”

“当然。”阿伽松说。

“母亲也是一样的吗？”

他也同意这一点。

“那么”，苏格拉底说，“再回答一些，你就会更好地理解我头脑中所想的。假设我问：兄弟，在他是兄弟的情况下，是否是某人的兄弟？”

他说是的。

“也就是说，是兄弟或姐妹的兄弟？”

他同意。

“现在告诉我关于爱的情形，”他说，“爱是对某物的爱，还是没有对象的爱？”

“毫无疑问是对某物的爱！”

“现在，”苏格拉底说，“记住爱是什么。但是告诉我：爱是否渴望他所爱的对象？”

“渴望。”他说。

“当他渴望并爱时，他是否拥有他渴望和爱的对象？”

“没有——至少可能没有。”他说。

“考虑一下，”苏格拉底说，“渴望针对的是你需要的东西，当然不只是可能的，而是必须是这样的，如果你不需要某物，你不会渴望它。我觉得它肯定是必须的；你觉得呢？”

“我也这样认为。”阿伽松说。

“好的。现在，高个子的人想要高个子，或强壮的人想要强壮吗？”

“根据我们已经同意的说法，那是不可能的。”

“是的，因为没人需要他已经拥有的品质。”

“是的。”

“假设某个强壮的人想要强壮，”苏格拉底说，“行动迅速的人想要迅速，健康的人想要健康。你可能会想，在这样及所有像这样类似的情况下，那些拥有这些品质的人也渴望他们已经拥有的东西。我这样说是想阻止我们产生错误的想法。如果你考虑一下，阿伽松，这些人必定任何时候都拥有这些品质，不管他们是否想要，因此这不可能是他们渴望的。所以如果某个人说，‘我很健康，我想要健康’，或‘我很富有，我想要富有’，或‘我渴望我已经拥有的东西’，我们应该跟他说：‘朋友，你已经拥有财富或健康或力量了，你想要的是在未来拥有它们，因为目前不管你是否想要它们，你已经拥有它们了。当你说你渴望已经拥有的东西时，问问自己你的意思是否是你想要现在拥有的东西在将来仍然拥有。’他必须同意这一点，是不是？”

阿伽松说是的。

苏格拉底说：“这些情况下某人做的事是爱他缺少的、不拥有的东西，也就是将来继续拥有他现在拥有的东西。”

“当然。”他说。

“所以渴望的这个及所有其他情况是对缺少的、实际上不拥有的东西的渴望。渴望和爱针对的是你不拥有的、缺少的、需要的东西。”

“当然。”他说。

“那么好吧，”苏格拉底说，“咱们总结一下刚才达成一致的事。首先，爱是对某物的爱；其次，某物是他当前需要的东西。”

“是的。”他说。

“现在，记住这一点，回想一下你刚才在发言中说的爱是什么。如果你愿意的话，我来提醒你。我认为你是这样说的，神的事是通过对美好事物的爱组织的，因为不可能爱丑陋的事物。这是不是你说的？”

“是的，我是这样说的。”阿伽松说。

“朋友，你说的话似乎有理，”苏格拉底说，“如果你说得对，那么爱岂不是必须爱美、而不爱丑陋吗？”

他同意。

“我们不是同意他爱他需要和不拥有的事物吗？”

“是的。”他说。

“由此断定爱需要美且不拥有美吧？”

“肯定是这样。”他说。

“好吧，你会说需要美且完全没有美的事物是美的吗？”

“不会。”

“如果是这样，你仍然假定爱是美的吗？”

阿伽松说：“苏格拉底，我似乎不知道刚才自己在说些什么。”

“哎呀，你刚才做的仍是很精彩的发言，阿伽松，”他说，“不过请再回答一个小问题：你认为好的事物也是美的吗？”

“我这样认为。”

“那么如果爱需要美的东西，好的东西是美的，则他需要好的东西吧？”

“我无法反驳你，苏格拉底，”他说，“咱们接受事物就像你说的那样吧。”

“你无法反驳的是真理，亲爱的朋友阿伽松，”苏格拉底说，“反驳苏格拉底一点儿也不难。”

“现在我让你喘口气。我尝试向你复述我曾听到的关于爱的故事，那是曼提尼亚一个叫狄奥提玛的女人告诉我的。她对这及许多其他事物都很了解。有一次，她告诉雅典人供奉哪些祭祀，从而把瘟疫推迟了十年。她也是教导我爱的方式的人。我将汇报她所说的话，把它作为我和阿伽松得出的结论的基础，不过是尽我一己之力罢了。

“阿伽松，如你所说的，人们应该首先说明爱是谁及他有什么样的品性，然后再说明他的效力。我认为最简单的是汇报我曾经和狄奥提玛进行的一次讨论的内容，在讨论时她对我提出了一些问题。我对她说的几乎和阿伽松刚才跟我说的完全一样：爱神是位伟大的神，他自身也是美的。她反驳我的论据跟我用于反驳阿伽松的也一样，根据我的推理，证明爱既不美也不好。

“我说，‘你是什么意思，狄奥提玛？那么爱是丑陋的、坏的了？’

“她说，‘这话多么亵渎神明啊！你认为任何不美的事物必然是丑陋的吗？’

“‘我当然这样认为。’

“‘不智慧的事物必是无知的吗？你难道没有意识到某种介于智慧和无知之间的事物吗？’

“‘那是什么？’

“‘就是有正确的见解，但不能说明有这些见解的理由。难道你没意识到这不是认知吗？因为只有能给出理由才具有知识；但它也不是无知，因为无知不会知道真理。当然，正确的观点具有这种情形，介于理解和无知之间。’

“‘你说得对。’我说。

“‘那么不要以为不美的事物必是丑的，不好的事物必是坏的。同样，你自己也同意爱既不好也不美时，不要认为他因而必是丑陋且坏的，而应该是介于这两者之间。’

“‘但是，’我说，‘每个人都赞成爱是位伟大的神。’

“‘你的意思是不知道的每个人，’她说，‘还是包括那些知道的？’

“‘当然是每个人。’

“她笑着说，‘但是苏格拉底，如果人们否认爱是神的话，怎么赞同他是位伟大的神呢？’

“‘这些人是谁？’我说。

“‘你是一个，’她说，‘我是另一个。’

“听到此后，我询问，‘你怎能这样说呢？’

“‘很简单，’她说，‘告诉我，你认为所有的神都是幸福、美丽的吗？或者你敢提议任何神不美、不幸福吗？’

“‘以宙斯的名义，我不会。’我说。

“‘你认为那些拥有好和美的事物的人是幸福的吗？’

“‘当然。’

“‘但是你刚才赞同爱是因为需要好和美的事物，他才渴求那些他需要的东西。’

“‘是的，我同意那一点。’

“‘因此如果他需要美和好的事物他怎能是神呢？’

“‘似乎不可能。’

“‘那么，你是否看出你认为爱不是神？’

“‘但爱会是什么呢？’我说，‘凡人？’

“‘远非如此。’

“‘那是什么呢？’

“‘就像之前讨论的那些例子一样，’她说，‘他介于凡人和神仙之间。’

“‘狄奥提玛，那使他成为什么？’

“‘他是伟大的精灵，苏格拉底。归为精灵的一切事物都介于神和人之间。’

“‘他们有什么职能啊？’我问道。

“‘他们解释并传递人至神及神至人的消息。他们传达人类的祈祷和献祭，并传达神的命令和礼品，作为对祭祀的回报。他们作为这两者的媒介，填补了他们之间的空缺，使宇宙形成了一个相互连接的整体。他们是所有占卜活动的媒介，在祭祀、仪式、符咒、预言和巫术方面具有祭司的专长。神不与人直接接触；他们完全通过精灵这个媒介与人交流和沟通（不管是清醒还是熟睡状态）。具有这些方面智慧的人是受精灵感召的人，而具有其他领域专长和技艺的人只是技工。有许多不同种类的精灵，其中一个便是爱。’

“‘谁是他的父母？’我问道。

“‘这说来话长，’她答道，‘不过无论如何我会告诉你的。阿佛洛狄特出生后，其他神来吃宴席，其中包括创造神的儿子资源神。当他们吃完晚宴后，贫乏神来乞讨，像其他人在宴席上做的那样，她也站在门口。资源神喝多了仙酒（这是在葡萄酒发现前神喝的酒），走到宙斯的花园，醉着睡着了。贫乏神想了一个计划，就是通过怀有资源神的孩子来减轻自己的资源匮乏；她与他睡在了一起，怀上了爱神。所以爱神之所以成为阿佛洛狄特的追随者和随从，是因为他是在她出生那天怀上的；他也天生热爱美，因为阿佛洛狄特很美。

“‘由于他是资源神和贫乏神的儿子，爱神的处境就像这样。首先，他总是贫乏；一点儿也不娇嫩和漂亮，如人们通常认为的那样，他很强硬，有坚硬的皮肤，没有鞋子，没有家。他总是露宿在地上，没有床，躺在露天的门廊下和路边；他和他母亲的本性一样，总是生活在贫乏的状态中。另一方面，他与他父亲相像，谋划得到美和好的东西。他很勇敢、冲动、热情；是位令人敬畏的猎人，总是耍花招；他渴望知识，并有足够的智谋得到它；毕生热爱智慧；擅长使用音乐、药物和诡辩。

“‘究其本性而言，他既不是神仙也不是凡人。他成功的时候，好几次在同一天内获得生命，然后死去，然后（像他父亲一样）复活。他获得的资源不断地枯竭，所以爱神既不是完全没有资源，但也不富有。他也处于智慧和无知之间。情况是这样的。没有一位神热爱智慧，或有变得智慧的欲望——因为他们已经很智慧了；任何已经智慧的人也不会热爱智慧。无知者也不热爱智慧，或有变得智慧的欲望。无知者的问题恰恰在于，虽然不好、不聪明，但他认为自己很令人满意。如果某人认为自己不需要某物，就不可能渴望自己认为不需要的东西。’

“‘狄奥提玛，如果智慧者和无知者都不热爱智慧，’我问，‘那么谁热爱智慧？’

“‘即使一个孩子，’她说，‘到现在也会意识到是那些介于这两者之间的，爱神是其中之一。智慧是最美的事物之一，而爱神爱美。所以爱神必定热爱智慧；作为智慧的热爱者，他介于智慧和无知之间。究其原因还是因为他的出身：他父亲智慧、资源丰富，而他母亲两者皆无。所以这就是爱这个精灵的本性，亲爱的苏格拉底。但你对爱持有原来的观点一点儿也不奇怪。从你所说的判断，我觉得你把爱看作爱的对象，而不是施爱者：那是你把爱想象得非常美的原因。但实际上，美丽、优雅、完美和幸福是值得被爱的对象的特征，而施爱者的本性与之迥异，我已经说过了。’

“‘好吧，狄奥提玛，’我说，‘我确信你的观点是对的。但爱若是这样，他对人类有什么用处呢？’

“‘那是接下来要讲的，苏格拉底，’她说，‘我会尽力告诉你。目前为止我们讲了爱的本性和出生；而且，根据你的想法，爱是对美的事物的爱。不过，假设某个人问我们，“为什么爱是对美的事物的爱？”或者，更清晰地说，“对美的事物的热爱者有一个渴望——他渴望的是什么？”’

“‘渴望它们成为自己的。’我说。

“‘但是这个回答引出了另一个问题，’她说，‘当美的事物成为他自己的之后他将得到什么？’

“‘我没有想好那个问题的答案。’

“‘但是，’她说，‘假设某人改变了问题，用“好”这个字代替“美”，并问：“那么，苏格拉底，好的事物的热爱者有一个渴望——他渴望的是什么？”’

“‘渴望它们成为自己的。’我说。

“‘当好的事物成为他自己的之后他将得到什么？’

“‘这我就容易回答了，’我说，‘他会幸福。’

“‘所以拥有好的事物使幸福的人感觉幸福；你不必问进一步的问题，“为什么某人想要幸福？”这个回答似乎标志着询问的终结。’

“‘是的。’我说。

“‘你认为这个愿望和这种形式的爱对所有人来说都是共同的，每个人都想要好的事物永远成为自己的吗，或者你有什么想法？’

“‘就像你说的那样，’我说，‘它是每个人共同的愿望。’

“‘那样的话，苏格拉底，’她说，‘如果每个人总是爱相同的事物，我们为什么不说每个人都是爱人呢；我们为什么称某些人为爱人，而某些不是呢？’

“‘这也是我感到疑惑的事。’我说。

“‘没什么可疑惑的，’她说，‘我们现在正在做的是挑选出一种爱，把属于整个种类的名字（“爱”）应用到它身上，而我们对其他种的爱使用的是不同的名字。’

“‘你能再给我举个例子吗？’我问道。

“‘好的，这就是一个。你知道创作形成了一个大体的种类。当任何以前不存在的事物形成时，其中的原因总是创作。所以所有技艺的产品都是创作品，制作它们的艺人都是创作者？’

“‘是的。’我说。

“‘但你知道他们没被称为创作者，而是有不同的名字。在创作的整个种类中，我们选出与音乐和韵文有关的一部分，用整个种类的名字称呼它。只有这才被称为创作，那些拥有这种技能的人才被称为创作者。’

“‘是的。’我说。

“‘爱也是这样。本质上，在所有情况下，对好的事物或幸福的各种类型的渴望就是构成“强大、热烈的爱”的事物。但这可以通过多种途径实现，那些通过其他途径这样做的人，如通过挣钱或竞技或哲学等，不被称为“钟情的人”或“爱人”。只有那些将热情指向术语规定属于整个种类的特定类型的人，才被称为爱、钟情的人和爱人。’

“‘我想是这样。’我说。

“‘已经提出了这样的观念，’她说，‘即爱人是那些寻找自己另一半的人。但，朋友，我的观点是，除非结果是好的，否则爱指向的既不是他们的另一半，也不是他们的整体。毕竟，如果人们认为自身的脚或手患病，他们甚至准备好将那些部分切断。我认为并不是我们每个人都眷恋自己的特性，除非你把好的说成是“他自己的”、“属于他的”，坏的说成是“不属于他的”。要点就是人们爱的唯一对象是好的事物——你难道不同意吗？’

“‘以宙斯之名，我同意！’我说。

“‘那么，’她说，‘我们能简单地说人们热爱好的事物吗？’

“‘能。’我说。

“‘但是，’她说，‘我们不应该补充说他们爱的对象即是他们应该拥有好的事物吗？’

“‘是的，我们应该补充那一点。’

“‘不只那一点，’她说，‘还有他们应该永远拥有好的事物。’

“‘我们也必须补充那一点。’

“‘那么总而言之，’她说，‘爱即是对永远拥有好的事物的渴望。’

“‘你说的绝对正确。’我说。

“‘考虑到爱总是有这个整体目标，’她说，‘我们也应该问问这个问题。如果人们在追求这个目标中显示出的热情和强烈程度被称为爱，那么他们必须用什么方式及什么类型的行动追求它呢？爱真正有什么职能：你能告诉我吗？’

“‘如果我能，狄奥提玛，’我说，‘我就不会对你的智慧感到吃惊了，不会不断以学生的身份来找你，向你学习这些东西了。’

“‘那么我会告诉你，’她说，‘爱的职能是既在身体也在灵魂中产生美。’

“‘需要先知才能阐明你说的话，’我说，‘我理解不了。’

“‘好吧，’她说，‘我会更清楚地解释这一点的。所有的人在身体和灵魂方面都会生育，当我们到了一定年龄，自然会渴望生育。我们不能生育丑的东西，只能生育美的东西。是的，男人和女人之间的性交是一种生育。这个过程中有种神圣的东西，这就是平凡的生物在怀孕和生育中获得永生的方式。在不和谐状况下这是不能发生的。丑陋与神圣不和谐，而美与它适合。所以美作为命运或爱勒提亚，是掌管生育的女神。怀孕的生物接近美的事物时，就变得温和、快乐、放松，并生育幼儿，就是这个原因。但当它接近丑的事物时，就皱眉、在痛苦中缩紧身体；它躲避、变得干瘪，不繁殖；它把婴儿隐藏在身体内部，感觉不适。这就是那些怀孕和肚子已经隆起的人对美如此兴奋的原因：美的承载者身份使他们能解除生育的痛苦。你瞧，苏格拉底，’她说，‘爱的对象不如你所想的那样是美。’

“‘那是什么呢？’

“‘是美之中的繁殖和诞生。’

“‘很可能是这样。’我说。

“‘当然是这样，’她说，‘为什么繁殖是爱的对象？因为繁殖是凡人能永远活着并不朽的最近途径。如果我们之前赞同的事正确的话，即爱的对象是一直拥有好的事物，则结果就是我们除了渴望好的事物，还渴望不朽。它是从爱的对象也必须不朽这个论点推断出的。’

“狄奥提玛在与我的交谈中告诉了我关于爱的方式的所有这些内容。一天她问道：‘苏格拉底，你认为这种爱和渴望的原因是什么？你难道没注意到各种动物（有翼的鸟以及有脚的动物）在感受到繁殖的欲望时陷入了多么可怕的状态。它们受到爱的刺激，首先想要彼此交配，然后哺育幼儿。即使最弱的动物也愿意为了自己的幼崽与最强的动物搏斗，不惜牺牲性命；它们准备好遭受饥饿的折磨，以便为幼崽提供食物，并为它们做其他任何事。你可能会想，人类这样做是因为他们理解其中的原因；但是，就动物而言，是什么引起了这种对爱的兴奋——你能告诉我吗？’

“我再一次说不知道。

“她说：‘如果你不理解这一点，你认为你会成为爱的方式方面的专家吗？’

“我说：‘但是，狄奥提玛，正如我之前说的，那正是我来向你学习的原因，因为我意识到我需要老师。所以请告诉我这及其他与爱的方式有关的一切的原因吧。’

“‘好吧，’她说，‘如果你相信爱的自然对象是我们经常赞同的东西，你就不应该对此感到意外。关于人类的论点也适用于动物；为了永生并不朽，平凡的生物会尽最大的努力。它只有通过繁殖才能实现这一点：它总是留下下一代，新的一代取代老的一代。这一点甚至也适用于每个生物存活且一直未变的时期——例如，人们说某个人从幼年到老年都是同一个人。虽然他被称为同一个人，但他身体的成分从来不是一样的，而是一些方面在不断地更新，其他方面，如毛发、皮肤、骨骼、血液和全身等，在不断地衰退。这不仅适用于身体，也适用于心灵：属性、人格特征、信念、欲望、欢愉、痛苦、恐惧——这些没有一个在我们之中是保持不变的，而是一些在浮现，一些在消失。更显著的是我们的知识也在改变这个事实，一些知识在形成，而其他的在消失，所以在知识方面我们不是同一个人；的确，每一条目的知识都经历了同样的过程。之所以学习，就是因为知识在不断地消失。遗忘是知识的消失，而学习将新的信息放回到我们的记忆中，取代消失的部分，所以知识一直存在，看起来似乎是一样的。

“‘这就是凡俗的事物保持存在的方式，不是像神圣的事物似的通过保持完全一样实现，而是因为变老、消逝的事物留下了同类的另外的新事物。苏格拉底，这就是凡俗的事物能在生理上及所有其他方面不朽的方式；但不朽的事物是通过与之不同的方式实现这些的。所以如果各种事物天生地珍视自己的后代，你也不应感到吃惊。各种事物展示出热情是为了实现不朽，而这正是爱的本质。’

“但实际上，我听到她的话后非常吃惊，就问她：‘嗯，狄奥提玛，你很有智慧，但事物真的如你所说的那样吗？’

“她像位十足的智者一样，说：‘你可以确信这一点。如果你看看人们热爱荣誉的方式，就会明白起作用的也是这同一个原则。在考虑人们因热爱出名及“永远保存不朽的名声”而受的巨大影响后，如果没能明白我所说的这点，你就应该对自己的愚笨感到惊讶。他们爱这胜过爱子孙，更愿意为这冒各种风险，倾家荡产，遭受任何折磨，并愿为荣誉而死。”她说，‘阿尔刻提斯愿为阿德墨托斯而死，或者阿喀琉斯愿意与帕特洛克罗斯一起死去，或者你们雅典的英雄科德洛斯愿意牺牲自己来保卫儿子们的王国，如果他们没有想到他们的英勇（我们至今仍然对其表示尊敬）将会永载史册的话，你认为他们会这样做吗？他们当然不会，’她说，‘我认为是这种永恒的美德和光荣的名声促使每个人这样做，而且他们越优秀越会这样；他们热爱的是不朽的名声。

“‘身体具有生育能力的男人，’她说，‘会更多地受到女人的吸引；他们通过生育后代来表达自己的爱，尽力获得不朽、怀念及永远的幸福。心灵具有生育能力的男人，’她说，‘有些人心灵的生育能力比身体的更旺盛，他们生育适合头脑记住并诞生的东西。所以什么适合呢？智慧及其他美德：这些是由所有的诗人及具有创新精神的手艺人孕育的。许多最重要、最出色的智慧，’她说，‘是与城市和家庭的组织相关联的，这被称为节制和公正。再拿年轻时心灵中就孕育这些美德的人为例。当他还没有伴侣且成年后，他就感受到生产和繁殖的欲望。我认为，他也四处走动，寻找美，以在其中繁殖；他永远不会在丑陋中繁殖。由于他怀孕了，他会受到美的身体而不是丑的身体的吸引；如果他也足够幸运，找到了美、高尚且有天赋的心灵，他会受到这种结合的强烈吸引。对于这样的人，他会立即发现自己有谈论美德、好的男人应该是什么样子及应该怎么做的素材，并尽力教导他。

“‘我认为，当某个人与这种美接触并形成关系后，他才生产、繁殖长久以来孕育的孩子。不管他们是否陪伴彼此，都会想着对方的美，并且与对方一起抚养繁殖的孩子。这样的人与彼此的伙伴关系更亲近，友谊更牢不可破，胜过父母的情分，因为他们这种伙伴关系诞生的孩子更美、更永久。每个人都更愿意拥有这样的孩子，而不是凡俗的孩子。人们羡慕荷马、赫西奥德及其他优秀的诗人，就是因为他们留下了这种孩子，这些孩子自身的不朽，也为他们带来了不朽的名声和怀念。或者，’她说，‘拿莱克格斯留下的孩子为例，他们为斯巴达（你可能会说整个希腊）带来了安全。梭伦也由于创立的法律而为你们雅典人所敬仰；还有其他人，他们在希腊和其他国家的其他地方，展示出了许多卓越的成就，形成了各种美德。已经有许多教派成立，来仰慕生出那种孩子的这些人，但这种情况从未发生在生出凡俗孩子的人身上。

“‘甚至你，苏格拉底，可能也接受过我目前为止描述的爱的仪式。但这些仪式如果进行得得体的话，其目的应是抵达未解之谜的最终愿景；我不确定你是否能领会这一点。但我会告诉你这些的，’她说，‘我会尽全力讲的；你尽可能地领会吧。

“‘某个人处理这件事的正确方式，’她说，‘应该是在年轻的时候开始接近美的身体。最初，如果他的向导正确指引他的话，他应该只爱一个身体，并在那种关系中产生美的交谈。接下来，他应该意识到任何一个身体的美都与另一个的密切相关，如果他要追求形式美，而不把所有身体的美看作是完全相同的，则非常愚蠢。一旦他明白这一点，就会热爱所有美的身体，并仅对一个身体释放自己的激情，轻视这种激情并把它视为微不足道的。之后，他应该把心灵的美看得比身体的美更有价值，这样，如果某人有美好的心灵，即使形貌不美，他也会对他感到满足，会爱他、关心他，与他进行那些能帮助年轻人变得更好的交谈。结果，他会被迫观察实践和法则中的美，明白每种美都与其他美密切相关，这样他就会把身体的美看作是微不足道的事物。实践之后，向导必须为他们指引知识的形式，这样他也会明白它们的美。现在他从总体上看待美，而不是仅看个别的例子，就不会像奴隶般的爱慕身体之美、任何特定的人的美，或具体的实践的美。取代这种卑贱、心胸狭窄的奴役的是，他将转向美的汪洋大海，凝视着它，通过对知识无尽的爱，产生许多华美、宏伟的对话和思想。最后，当他以这种方式变得成熟、强大后，他会突然看到一种特殊的知识，这种知识的对象是我接下来要讲的那种美。

“‘现在，’她说，‘尽你最大的努力集中精神。任何人在受到关于爱的方式这么多教导、以正确的次序和方式看待美的事物后，现在将会抵达爱的方式的终极目标。他会在美的性质中突然看到一些极其美的事物；而这，苏格拉底，正是以前所有努力的最终目标。首先，这种美一直存在，不生不灭；不增不减。其次，它不是一方面美而另一方面丑，或某个时间美而另个时间不美，或与这有关美而与那有关就丑；也不会因为它对一些人来说美而对其他人来说丑就这里美而那里丑。美也不会以脸或手或身体的任何部分的形式出现在他面前；或者以具体的某条知识的形式出现；或者在别的东西中出现在其他地方，例如，在生物、大地、天堂或其他东西中。它会以自身的形式单独出现，形式上总是单一的；所有其他美的事物也有这些特性，但方式不同，当其他事物出现或消失时，它不以任何形式增加或减少，也不会作出任何改变。

“‘当某个人通过这些阶段成长，以正确的方式热爱少男，并开始看到那种美的时候，他就接近目标了。这是接近爱的方式或由其他人指引的正确方法：总是从这些美的事物开始，本着抵达那种美的目的成长。像使用楼梯的人一样，他应该从一个身体到两个身体，从两个身体到所有美的身体，从美的身体到美的实践，从实践到美的学习形式。从各种学习形式中，他应该在那种除了美本身别无他物的学习形式处告终，这样他就能完成学习美的真正本质的过程。

“‘在那种生命形式中，亲爱的苏格拉底，’这位曼提尼亚的局外人说，‘如果人的生活值得过的话，就在于凝视美本身。如果你曾注意到，它似乎与金钱、衣服、美少男和青年处于完全不同的层次上。现在你看到这些的时候会如痴如醉，和其他许多人一样，愿意看着自己的情郎并与其永远在一起，如果可能的话，愿意不吃不喝，除了凝视着他们、与他们在一起之外其他什么也不做。因此，’她说，‘如果某个人能看到美本身，看到绝对、纯粹的美，而不是与人的血肉之躯、颜色和大量凡俗的废物杂乱在一起，如果他能看到以独立形式存在的神圣的美本身，我们应该想象它是什么样子呢？你是否会认为，’她说，‘如果某个人以自身正确的部位朝那个方向看，并凝视那个对象、与它做伴，他的生命会是无意义的？你难道没有意识到，’她说，‘只有在那种生命中，当某个人以能看到的部位查看美时，他才能不仅孕育出美德的影像（因为这不是他接触的影像），而且孕育出真正的美德（因为他接触的是真正的美）。那些孕育出真正的美德并对其进行培育的人才有机会受到神的热爱，并变得不朽——如果有人能不朽的话。’

“好吧，费德鲁斯及在座各位，这就是狄奥提玛所说的，我很信服她的话。因为我对其信服，所以我尽力说服他人，若要达到这样，你不可能轻易地为人性找到一位比爱神更好的伙伴。我宣称每个人都应该尊敬爱神，就是以此为基础的，我自己也尊敬爱的方式，并极其小心地实践着它们。这就是我劝说他人这样做的原因，在当前及其他每个场合，我尽自己所能赞美爱神的力量和勇气。这就是我的发言，费德鲁斯。如果你愿意，你可以把它看作是对爱神的颂词，或者你可以给它任何你想给它的名字。”

阿里斯托得摩斯说，苏格拉底的发言完毕后，其他人都在祝贺他，而阿里斯托芬尝试着表达自己的观点，因为苏格拉底在某个阶段提到了他的发言。突然，传来一阵敲击前门的响亮的噪音，听起来像是一些纵酒狂欢者，他们也听到了吹笛女的声音。

“仆人们，去看看是谁，”阿伽松说，“若是我的朋友，就请他们进来；若不是，就告诉他们宴会结束了，我们正要上床睡觉。”

不一会儿，他们听到了庭院中亚西比德的声音；他醉得一塌糊涂，大声嚷嚷着，问阿伽松在哪里，让仆人带自己去见他。他被带了进来，由吹笛女和其他人搀扶着。他站在门口，戴着常春藤和紫罗兰编织而成的厚重花环，头上缠着许多丝带，说：

“晚上好，先生们。你们愿意让喝醉的人（非常醉的人）加入你们的宴会吗？还是我们应该为阿伽松戴上花环（这正是我们来的原因），然后就走呢？我昨天没能来参加你们的庆典，”他说，“但现在我头上戴着丝带来了，这样我可以直接把丝带从我头上取下来，戴到（我想宣布）最智慧、最美的人头上。我想你们会因为我喝醉了嘲笑我的。但即使你们嘲笑我，我也非常清楚我讲的是实话。不过请立马告诉我，我是否可以进来。我能和你们一起喝酒吗？”

大家大声叫着，告诉他进来，坐在长椅上，阿伽松也邀请他进来。所以他由朋友搀着进来了。他解开丝带，打算系到阿伽松头上，丝带滑落到了他的眼睛上。所以他没有注意到苏格拉底，而是坐在阿伽松旁边，在他和苏格拉底之间，苏格拉底看到他后就挪开了。他坐下后，拥抱了阿伽松，并把花环系到他头上。

阿伽松说：“仆人，把他的鞋脱掉，这样他可以坐下来，我们三人坐得舒服一些。”

“好的，”亚西比德说，“但和我们一起喝酒的第三位是谁？”他说话的时候，转了一下身，看到了苏格拉底。他看到他后，跳了起来说，“哦，赫拉克勒斯大神啊，这是怎么回事？这是苏格拉底吗？你又坐在这儿等着我，这样你可以玩老把戏，在我最不希望看到你的地方突然冒出来。你为什么来这里？你为什么选择坐在这里？我看出来了，你没有选择坐在阿里斯托芬或其他愿意愚弄自己的人旁边，而是务必坐在屋子中最有魅力的人旁边。”

苏格拉底说：“阿伽松，请保护我。我对这个人的爱变得多么令人讨厌啊！自从我开始爱他，我就不能看或和有魅力的单身人士说话，否则他就变得非常妒忌、愤怒，变得发疯一样，对我大喊大叫，几乎要痛打我一顿。所以现在一定要保证他不对我做任何事，让我们和平相处；或者如果他开始变得暴力，请保护我。他对自己爱人的癫狂依恋让我很害怕。”

“我和你之间不可能有和平，”亚西比德说。“我下次再跟你算这次的账。但是现在，阿伽松，”他说，“还给我一些丝带，我把它们系到他这个神奇的头上。否则，他会批评我把丝带系到你头上而不是他头上，尽管他总是赶走口头抗辩的来者（两天前你还这样做过）。”

他说着的时候，取下了一些丝带，系到了苏格拉底头上，又坐了下来。他坐下后，说：“先生们，我看你们都很清醒。这可不行；你们得喝酒。这是我们事先同意过的。我们选个司仪，负责大家的饮酒，直到大家都喝醉，我推选——我自己！阿伽松，你若有大高脚杯，拿一个过来。哦，不必了；小子，把那个晾酒器给我，”他看到了那个能盛四品脱多酒的器具。他把它倒满，自己喝了下去，然后让仆人为苏格拉底满上。他边这样做边说，“先生们，并不是我的花招会对苏格拉底产生任何影响。不管你让他喝多少，他也不会醉。”

仆人为苏格拉底斟满，在他喝的时候，厄律克西马库说：“亚西比德，这是什么行为？我们在轮流喝酒的时候不打算聊聊天或唱唱歌，而是好像口渴似的只喝酒吗？”

亚西比德说：“你好啊，厄律克西马库，最杰出——且最温和——的父亲生出的最杰出的儿子。”

“你也好啊，”厄律克西马库说：“但我们应该怎么做呢？”

“你让我们怎么做我们就怎么做。我们应该听从你，因为‘一个医生抵得过许多人’；所以告诉我们你想做的事吧。”

“那么请听我说，”厄律克西马库说，“你来之前，我们决定尽自己所能从左到右轮流作最好的发言，赞美爱神。我们其余人都已经发过言了。虽然你酒喝得很好，但你还没发言，所以你应该发个言。你说过之后，就可以命令苏格拉底做任何你想要他做的事，他也可以对他右边的人这样做，以此类推。”

“好主意，厄律克西马库，”亚西比德说，“但我觉得让一个喝醉的人和清醒的人作的发言相竞争不公平。而且，亲爱的朋友，我希望你不要相信苏格拉底刚才说的任何话。你难道没意识到真理和他说的正好相反吗？如果他在附近的时候我赞美其他人，不管是神还是人，他都会痛打我一顿。”

“多么亵渎神明啊！”苏格拉底说。

“以海神波塞冬的名义起誓！”亚西比德说，“不要在这一点上反驳我。你在附近的时候我决不会赞美其他人的。”

“那好吧，如果你愿意的话，就那样做吧，”厄律克西马库说，“作一个对苏格拉底的颂词。”

“你是什么意思？”亚西比德说，“你认为我应该那样做吗，厄律克西马库？我应该在你们大家面前攻击他、惩罚他吗？”

“等一下，”苏格拉底说，“你计划的是什么——作一个嘲笑我的颂词，还是其他什么？”

“我会讲实话——你让我那样做吗？”

“不过我当然会让你讲实话；实际上，我命令你那样做。”

“那我就开始了，”亚西比德说，“不过我先说明一下。如果我说了任何不真实的事，要是你愿意的话就打断我，指出我说的是假的。我不想说任何假的事情。不过如果我记事情的顺序不对，不要感到惊讶。对于处于像我这样情形中的人来说，要流畅、有序地列举出你的特性的各个方面，可真不容易。

“先生们，我试着通过比喻来赞美苏格拉底。可能他会认为这是在嘲笑他；但比喻是用来说明真相的，而不是用来嘲笑的。我要说的是，他就像你们看到的坐在雕刻家作坊中的西勒诺斯的那些雕像。那些人物拿着牧羊人的管乐器或长笛；打开它们后，你们会发现里面有神的雕像。我还认为他像森林之神玛尔叙阿斯。苏格拉底，你自己也不能否认你外表上像他们；不过接下来你将听到你在其他方面与他们如何相像。

“你很无礼、口出恶言，不是吗？如果你不承认这一点，我来提供证据。你不是会吹长笛吗？实际上，你比玛尔叙阿斯吹得好多了。他凭借嘴的力量使用乐器蛊惑人们，今天吹奏他的长笛乐曲的人也都是如此（我把奥林匹斯的曲调真正看作是玛尔叙阿斯的，因为玛尔叙阿斯是奥林匹斯的老师）。不管这些曲调是由专业演奏者还是可怜的吹笛女演奏，由于其神圣的起源，它们是唯一能用符咒迷惑人们的曲调，显示出哪些人准备好了接受神的启示。你和玛尔叙阿斯的唯一区别在于你不用乐器、仅用语言就能产生同样的效果。当我们听到其他人演讲时，即使他是位优秀的演说家，也几乎对我们产生不了什么影响。但每当有人听到你说话或听到他人（即使他是个蹩脚的说话者）复述你的话，不管是谁（女人、男人或少男）都会如痴如醉、像施了符咒一样。

“若不是你们认为我喝醉了，先生们，我愿意发誓，他的话对我产生影响是真话——现在这些话仍对我产生影响。每当听他说话，我的狂热比科律班忒斯的还有过之而无不及。当他说话时，我的心脏扑通扑通地跳动，眼泪奔流而出，我看到许多其他人也受到同样的影响。我听过伯里克利及其他优秀演说家的演说，我认为他们说得很好。但他们从未对我产生过这种影响；他们没有扰乱我的整体人格，让我对自己生命的奴役性质感到不满。但坐在这里的这位玛尔叙阿斯经常对我产生这种影响，让我认为自己的生活不值得过。你不能说这不是真的，苏格拉底。即使现在我也清楚地知道，如果我放任自己听他说话，我会无法抵制，再次经历相同的体验。他让我承认，尽管由于种种巨大缺陷，我忽视自己，却反而卷入到雅典的政治活动中。所以我强迫自己捂着耳朵走开，就像人们逃离妖妇一样，防止自己在变老之前坐在他旁边。

“只有在他的陪伴下我才会有这种体验，你们可能会认为我不会有这种体验——与某人在一起感到羞耻；我只有在他的陪伴下才感到羞耻。我清楚地知道，我不能反对他，应该做他让我做的事；但离开他后，我就会因人们的赞赏而忘乎所以。所以我表现得像个逃亡的奴隶一样，从他那里逃脱；每当看到他，我都会因为他让我赞同的话而感到羞愧。我经常觉得看到他从人间消失我会高兴；但如果这真的发生，我知道我会更不安。我就是不知道怎样与这个人打交道。

“这就是这位森林之神吹笛时对我及其他许多人产生的影响。让我来告诉你们，这个比喻在某些方面也非常恰当，看看他有多么令人惊讶的力量。你们应该认识到你们中没有一个人真正懂他。但既然已经开了头，我会说明他是什么样子的。你们看到苏格拉底受美貌少男吸引，总是兴奋地与他们一起消磨时间。他也完全愚昧，一无所知。他给人这种印象，不是很像西勒诺斯吗？正是这样。这种行为仅是他的外壳，就像西勒诺斯的雕像的外壳一样。但如果你们能把他打开往里看，我亲爱的酒友，你们无法想象他有多么节制！你们应该知道，他根本不在乎某人是否漂亮（他对此怀有难以置信的蔑视）或富有，或拥有普通人视为的其他优势。他把所有这些看得毫无价值，也把我们看得一文不值。（请相信我！）他整个一生都在伪装，在玩弄人。

“当苏格拉底表情严肃、内心被打开的时候，我不知道你们中是否有人看到过他身体内部的雕像。不过我看到过一次，它们看起来如此神圣、珍贵，如此美丽、让人惊讶，以至于（简而言之）我不得不做苏格拉底让我做的任何事。我认为他对我的相貌感兴趣是认真的，这对我来说是天赐之物、是难得的好运，因为，如果我让他满足，我就能听到他所知道的一切。你们瞧，我为自己的美貌感到骄傲。这之前，我从未在没有随从的情况下和他单独相处；但一有了这个想法，我就把随从打发走，独自一人和他在一起。是的，我必须告诉你们整个真相；所以仔细听着，如果我说了任何不正确的话，苏格拉底，你必须反驳我。

“好吧，先生们，我们就在那里，只有我们两人。我认为他会立即与我进行爱人与情郎独处时进行的那种对话，心里很高兴。但根本没发生那种事。他与我进行与平常一样的交流，一天过完后就走了。我邀请他来到健身房，与他一起锻炼，我以为可以以那种方式取得些进展。所以我们进行锻炼，旁边没有一人，还摔了很多次跤——怎么跟你们说呢？我还是一无所获。

“由于通过这些方式一无所获，我决定对这个人展开直接攻击，既然已经开始了就不放弃。我觉得我应该了解实际情况如何。我邀请他一起就餐，就好像我是爱人他是情郎一样。他没有立即接受我的邀请，不过最后还是同意来了。第一次就完餐后他就想走，那一次我有点儿害羞，就让他走了。不过我又进行了一次这个计划，用餐后，我一直和他谈话到深夜。然后他想走的时候，我找了个借口，说太晚了，让他留了下来。所以他在我旁边的沙发上躺下睡觉，那是他就餐的地方，房间里除了我们两个就没其他人了。

“到目前为止，任何人听我说都无所谓了。不过从现在开始，有些事你们一般不会听到我说，正如俗语所说，‘仆人离开时酒后吐真言’，仆人不离开时也会吐真言！而且，我认为既然开始了对苏格拉底的颂扬，那么让他的自豪行为湮没无闻将是我的失误。此外，我的经历就像人被蛇咬了一样。有人说拥有这种经历的人只愿意向那些同样被咬过的人述说其中情形，因为只有他们才能懂，且如果那种痛苦驱使你做和说一些令人震惊的事，他们也会体谅。但我是被更痛苦的东西咬的，其中的每一口都极端痛苦（咬的是心或灵魂），或随便你们怎么称呼它。我受到的是哲学言论的撞击和撕咬，当它抓住一个年轻、天才的灵魂时，会比蛇更猛烈地攀附，使其做和说各种各样的事。而且我能看到在座的各位，像费德鲁斯、阿伽松、厄律克西马库、鲍桑尼亚、阿里斯托得摩斯和阿里斯托芬（我无须提及苏格拉底自己）以及其余各位。你们都有哲学的疯狂和醉酒般的狂热，所以你们都会听到我要说的话。你们得体谅我那时做的事和现在说的话。但是你们，仆人及所有其他下人，都堵上你们的耳朵！

“所以，先生们，灯灭之后，仆人离开了房间，我决定不应该再拐弯抹角，而是坦率地告诉他我心里所想的。我推了他一下，说：‘苏格拉底，你睡着了吗？’

“‘还没有。’他说。

“‘你知道我在想什么吗？’

“‘想什么啊？’他说。

“‘我认为，’我说，‘只有你才配得上做我的爱人，但你似乎很害羞，不愿跟我提及。我告诉你我的感受吧。我认为如果你对我或我的朋友有需求，我不满足你这方面或其他任何方面的需求会很愚蠢。对我来说，没有什么比成为优秀的人更重要了，我认为要实现这个目的，没有人能比你给予我更有力的帮助。如果我未能满足像你这样的人的需求，考虑到明理的人会怎样看待我，与普通、愚蠢的人怎样看待我相比，我会更羞愧。’

“他听了我说的，以他自己典型的极度讽刺语气对我说了这些：‘亲爱的亚西比德，如果你说的关于我的话是真的，且我确实有能力让你成为更好的人的话，你似乎绝不是傻瓜。你肯定从我身上看到了无与伦比的、与你自己的美貌相比优越许多的美。如果你看到了这一点，尝试着与我达成协议，我们用一种美交换另一种美，那么你是打算从我身上大赚一笔。你在试图以外表换取真正的美，所以实际上是在进行“以铜换金”的交易。但仔细看看，我的好朋友，你认为我对你有价值，请确保你没弄错。视力衰退的时候，灵魂才开始变得敏锐，你离那一点还远着呢。’

“听到这些之后，我说：‘依我看，情况就是这样，我的计划正如我所说的。现在由你来决定怎样对你我来说是最好的。’

“‘好吧，’他说，‘至少这一点你说得对。将来我们要考虑做对我们最好的事，既包括这方面的也包括其他事情的。’

“他对我作如此回复后，我认为由于我对他放了箭，他被射中了。我站起来，没给他再多说任何话的机会，把他包裹进我厚厚的户外斗篷里（当时是冬天），躺在他的短斗篷下。然后我用双臂搂着这个像上帝一样、令人惊讶的人，整夜都和他一起躺在那里。你不能说这是谎话，苏格拉底。在我做完这些之后，他彻底击败了我的美貌（并轻视、嘲笑、侮辱了我的美貌），尽管我很看重这些相貌，陪审团的诸位先生们。我这样称呼你们，是因为你们成为了苏格拉底的傲慢事件中的陪审团！我以上帝及女神的名义向你们发誓，第二天早上起来时，我跟苏格拉底睡觉，与跟我父亲或兄长睡觉相比，没有什么差别。

“那之后，你们认为我有什么样的心情？虽然我觉得自己受辱了，但我钦佩他的品行、自制能力和勇气。他是位明智且意志坚强的人，我从未期望能找到这样的人。所以，尽管我不能生他的气或不能没他的陪伴，但我不知道怎样赢取他的心。我很清楚，他完全不为金钱所动，就像埃阿斯不会为武器所伤一样；我视为唯一能赢取他的方法也被证实无效。我感到困惑；我来回踱步，完全沉湎于这个人，比其他人都更甚。

“这些事情发生之后，我们一起参与了雅典抵御波提狄亚的战役，一起领受了那里的混乱。首先要指出的是他比我更能忍受战争的严苛——实际上，他比其他所有人都更能忍受。我们被切断粮食供应之后，就像出征时有时会发生的那样，没有人比他更能忍受饥饿。但另一方面，我们能大吃一顿时，他又是最能享受盛宴的。例如，他虽然不愿意喝酒，但被迫喝时，他能把我们都打败。最令人吃惊的是没人曾看到苏格拉底喝醉过。我觉得你们很快就会看到这一点的证据了。

“而且当提到忍受冬天的严寒时（那里的冬天酷寒难耐），他的忍耐力也是非凡的。有一次，霜冻很厉害，没有人出去，或者就是出去，也会把自己裹得严严实实的，靴子上另外系上毡或羊皮。但苏格拉底在这种天气下还是穿着以前穿的户外斗篷出去，他光着脚走在冰上比别人穿着靴子走得还稳健。士兵们怀疑地看着他，认为他轻视他们。

“这件事就说到这里；但战场上‘这位刚毅的人接下来所做和忍受的事’值得一听。一天早上，他开始考虑一个问题，就站在那里思考，没取得进展就不放弃，而是一直站在那里思索。中午时，人们注意到了他，惊愕地对彼此说苏格拉底从破晓就开始站在那里思考事情了。最后，到傍晚时，吃过晚饭后，一些爱奥尼亚人把铺盖拿到外面（当时是夏天），部分是为了睡觉凉快点儿，部分是为了密切注视苏格拉底，看他夜晚是否也会一直站在那里。他一直站在那里，直到第二天黎明太阳出来时；然后他向太阳祈祷，就离开了。

“如果你们想知道他在战斗中是什么样子——现在正是我向他还债的机会。在将军授予我英勇奖章之后的战斗中，是苏格拉底（没有其他人）救了我。我受伤后，他没有离开我，所以他不仅救了我的盔甲和武器，还救了我的生命。实际上那个时候我让将军把英勇奖章授予你，苏格拉底。这一点上你不能批评我，或说我撒谎。但将军受到我社会地位的影响，想把奖章授予我时，你自己比将军更热心地认为我应该得到奖章。

“先生们，还有一件事。当军队从代里恩混乱地撤退时，苏格拉底是值得一看的景观。我当时在骑兵服役，而他是甲兵。人们那时已经四散了，他和拉凯斯一起撤退。巧合的是，我就在附近，我看到他们时，就立即鼓励他们，告诉他们我不会留下他们不管的。在那里，我比在波提狄亚能更好地观察苏格拉底（因为我在马背上，不那么担心自己的安全），首先让我心里一震的是他比拉凯斯镇静得多。接下来，我注意到他在那里散步，就像在雅典一样（阿里斯托芬，引用你的话就是）‘大摇大摆，环顾四周’。他冷静地环顾着朋友和敌人，即使在远处的人也知道，如果有人袭击这个人，他会顽强反抗的。就这样，他和他的同伴安全撤退了。通常，战斗中人们不会袭击显出这种神情的人；他们更愿意追赶仓皇逃离的人。

“除此之外，苏格拉底还有许多其他事情值得称赞。其中的一些显著特点也可能在其他人身上找到。但最令人吃惊的一点是他完全不像其他任何人，不管是过去的还是现在的。如果你想说阿喀琉斯是什么样子，你可以拿他与布拉西达斯或其他人相比，伯里克利的话，你可以拿他与涅斯托耳或安忒诺耳相比（还有其他的人），你可以以同样方式作其他比较。但这个人非常奇特，他谈话的方式也很奇特，无论你多么努力地找，永远也不会找到现在或过去与他相近的人。实际上，你们能做的最好的就是像我做的那样，当我比较他及他的谈话方式时，不是与人类相比，而是与西伦尼和森林之神对比。

“这是我开始时忘记说的：他的论述也非常像那些你们打开的西伦尼。一听苏格拉底的论述，起初似乎会觉得非常荒谬。这是他使用的词和语句的缘故，它们就像无礼的森林之神粗糙的皮肤一样。他谈论驮货的驴子、铁匠、鞋匠、皮匠，似乎总是用相同的话得出相同的论点；所以不习惯他的人或无知的人会觉得他的论述很荒谬。但如果你能打开它们，看看内部，就会发觉只有那些论述才有道理。你也会发觉它们是最神圣的，包含最多的美德影像。它们涉及大部分（更确切地说是所有）的主题，如果你想成为优秀的人，必须细阅所有这些主题。

“先生们，这就是我赞美苏格拉底的话。我也掺杂了一些对他的责备，告诉你们他是怎么侮辱我的。我并不是唯一一个受到他这样对待的人；还有格老孔的儿子查米德斯、狄奥克莱斯的儿子欧西德莫斯及许多其他人。他欺骗他们，让他们认为他是自己的爱人，结果他却是被爱的人，而不是施爱的人。我警告你，阿伽松，不要被他骗了，而要从我们的遭遇中吸取教训，要谨慎一些，如谚语所说，不要成为傻瓜，只从自己遭受的痛苦中学习。”

亚西比德的坦率发言带来了许多乐趣，因为他似乎还在爱着苏格拉底。苏格拉底说：“我认为你非常清醒，亚西比德。否则你不能够隐藏你整个发言的动机，巧妙地用这种方式掩盖着它。你在最后泄露了出来，好像是你的事后想法——好像你整个演讲的目的不是为了离间我和阿伽松一样。你这样做是因为你认为我应该只爱你一人，而不是其他人，阿伽松应该只被你爱，而不被其他人爱。但你没有侥幸成功；我们看出了你的这场森林之神和西勒诺斯把戏的目的。但是，亲爱的阿伽松，不要让他得逞；一定不要让任何人离间我和你。”

然后阿伽松说：“你知道，苏格拉底，我认为你一定是对的。他坐在我和你中间，把我们分开，是别有用心。但他不会得逞的。我过去，坐在你旁边。”

“请过来吧，”苏格拉底说，“坐在这一边。”

“哦，宙斯啊！”亚西比德说，“我真是受够了这个人！他认为他总得胜过我。但如果没有别的办法（你这个令人惊讶的人）就让阿伽松坐在我们俩之间吧。”

“那是不可能的事，”苏格拉底说，“你已经赞美过了我，现在该我赞美我右边的人了。如果阿伽松坐在我们之间，他不是也得赞美我，而不是受我赞美吗？看在上帝的份上，不要阻止这个年轻人受到我的赞美；我有赞颂他一番的强烈愿望。”

“好哇，”阿伽松说，“亚西比德，现在我决不会再待在这里了。我必须换位置，让苏格拉底赞美我。”

“又是这样，”亚西比德说，“总是老样子。苏格拉底在时，别人休想接近有魅力的人。现在，看他多么机智地找到一个貌似有理的借口，说明为什么这个人应该坐在他旁边。”

所以阿伽松站起来，去坐到苏格拉底旁边。突然，一大群饮酒狂欢者来到了前门。由于某个人刚出去了，他们发现门是开着的；所以他们直接闯了进来，加入了他们，坐在沙发上。到处都是嘈杂声，所有的顺序都被打破了；每个人都被迫喝了大量的酒。阿里斯托得摩斯说厄律克西马库、费德鲁斯及其他一些人离开了，而他睡了很长时间，因为那时候夜很长。将近黎明时他醒了过来，那时公鸡已经开始打鸣了。他一醒来，就看到其他人要么正睡着，要么已经离开了，只有阿伽松、阿里斯托芬和苏格拉底还醒着，正用一个大碗喝酒，碗从左到右传递着。苏格拉底正与他们说话。阿里斯托得摩斯说大部分争辩他已记不得了，因为他错过了开头，中间又睡着了。但他说，要点是苏格拉底迫使他们同意同一个人应该既能写喜剧又能写悲剧，擅长写悲剧的人一定也擅长写喜剧。虽然他们昏昏欲睡，没跟上他的思路，但他让他们同意这一点；阿里斯托芬先睡着了，天已经破晓时阿伽松也睡着了。

他们睡着之后，苏格拉底站起来，离开了。阿里斯托得摩斯像往常一样跟着他。苏格拉底去了学园（吕格恩），洗了脸，像平时一样在那里度过了一天，直到傍晚才回家休息。

洞穴寓言（选自《理想国》）

一、苏格拉底一开始提到了哲学家必须具备的各种素质，然后着重强调这些素质必须建立在学问的基础之上，最终则是建立在为善的学问基础之上。对苏格拉底来说它是善的本质，正如此段文字所阐明的那样。一些人认为善即快乐，或者认为善即学问。苏格拉底简明扼要地驳斥了此类观点，却拒绝直接给出自己的看法，而是借用一个比喻来描述他的观点。

“好了，我们总算完成了这部分任务——真是不容易啊；下面继续讨论下一个问题，研究如何通过学习和不懈的追求，造就出这个社会制度的捍卫者。他们要学习什么东西？从什么年龄起就要开始学习？”

“对，这就是我们下一个要讨论的问题。”

“我耍了一点小聪明，”我说，“我把娶妻、生子、确立统治者这些难题都放到了后面去讨论。不过，到头来我并没占到一点便宜，最终还是要论及的。我心中构想的那个真实社会必定会触怒一些人，而且也难以实现。这一点我十分清楚，不过我还是要把它描绘出来。妇女和儿童问题我已经谈过了，现在得重新讨论统治者的问题。你记得我们曾经说过：他们必须要热爱自己的国家，必须经历快乐和痛苦的双重考验，以确保他们在面对痛苦、恐惧和各种兴衰荣辱时，仍然能够矢志不渝；没能通过测试的人，必须予以淘汰；经受住了考验而且毫发无损的人，就好比真金一样不怕火炼，理应被拥立为统治者，生要享有荣光，死要加以褒奖。我们大概就是这么说的。不过，由于担心过早卷入我们今日的议题，当时我们神不知鬼不觉巧妙地回避了这个问题。”

“是的，我记得这件事。”他说。

“你知道，我在说出这番不太成熟的观点之前，也是犹豫再三的，”我回答道，“不过，现在我可以斗胆直言：从最完美的意义上讲，我们的守护者只能是哲学家。”

“好吧，就照你说的。”

“想一想这样的人总共能有几个。我们前面曾经说过，这些人必须具备某种品格，而这种品格又包含了多个方面的品质。通常一个人不会坐拥全部品质，多数情况下仅具有某些品质。”

“此话怎讲？”

“一方面具备好学、强记、头脑机灵、敏锐等各方面的素质，而且积极进取、视野广博，但另一方面却常常不愿意过按部就班、安静稳定的生活；敏锐的性格让其性情变得扑朔迷离、变幻莫测，毫无稳定可言。”

“说得对。”

“而且，你可以信赖的始终如一的稳重之人，尽管在战争面前毫不畏惧，但同样也不会为说教所动。他们这种难以撼动的性格最终确实会令他们变得麻木不仁。当需要他们奉献才智的时候，他们会打着哈欠，昏然入睡。”

“确实是这样的。”

“但是我们需要的是完全兼备两种品格的人，让他们接受最高等的教育，并赋予他们地位和权力。”

“没错。”

“这样的人才可谓凤毛麟角。”

“是很少见。”

“我们不仅应当在前面描述的苦与乐的环境中考验他们，还应当在以往曾经忽略的系列智力学习中考查他们，以检验其是否具有追求最高层次学问的毅力，是否会像其他人畏惧体能测试一样回避退缩。”

“很公道的测试。不过，”他问，“最高层次学问指的是什么？”

“你一定记得，”我回答道，“先前我们在区分过头脑三要素之后，又讨论了正义、自我控制、勇气和智慧问题。”

“如果连这我都不记得，”他说，“我就不配再听别的东西了。”

“那你还记得我们在谈论这些话题之前说过什么吗？”

“说过什么？”

“我们说过，只有绕过一个很大的弯路，才有可能获得真正清晰的认识，不过我们可以根据前面的讨论给出一些暗示。你说那已经够好的了。正因为你的那句话，后面的描述在我看来便不是十分精确了。对你来说是否足够精确，只有你自己知道。”

“我认为你提出的衡量标准不错。我想其他人也是这么认为的。”

“我亲爱的阿得曼托斯，在这类问题上，任何失真的东西都不能作为衡量标准，”我答道，“你不能用本身不完善的东西去衡量任何东西——尽管人们有时会满足于此，而不愿做进一步深究。”

“是的，通常是因为他们太懒惰了。”

“国家和法律的守护者最要不得这种品行。”

“说得不错。”

“那么，他就必须走那条较长的路，”我说，“他必须像锻炼身体一样刻苦地进行智力训练；否则，就像我们刚才说的那样，最终他永远都达不到那个本应属于他的做学问的最高境界。”

“最高境界？”他问道，“可是有比我们讨论的正义和其他品质更高层次的东西吗？”

“有。”我说，“我们不应该仅满足于拥有这些品质的一个草图，而不去充实每个细节。如果我们在小事情上都能全身心投入，力求尽可能高的精确度和清晰度，而在最重要的事情上反而不需要最高的精确度了，这不是十分荒谬吗？”

“是十分荒谬，”他表示同意，“但别指望蒙混过关，你还得回答最高层次的学问是什么这个问题。”

“我不指望蒙混过关，”我答道，“你问吧。其实你已经听过很多遍了。要么你是真的不明白，要么你就是一直存心给我难堪——我觉得是后一种情况，因为你肯定经常听过我说，学问的最高层次是关于善的本质的学问，正义一类事物的实用性和价值从中得以体现。你非常清楚这就是我要说的。另外，我还要补充一点，我们这方面的学问还很不够。如果我们对此一无所知，那么，其他方面的学问纵使再完美，对我们来说也是毫无裨益的。这就好比是说，如果你无法从你拥有的东西中得到任何好处，那么，即使拥有它也没什么用处。换句话说，如果东西不好的话，你认为拥有它还有任何意义吗？如果拥有所有其他形式的学问，但唯独没有善的学问，也就是说，缺乏有关什么是好的、什么是有价值的这方面的知识，这样的话，还有什么意义吗？”

“肯定没有任何意义。”

“当然，你也清楚，大多数普通人都认为快乐就是善，而阅历丰富的人则认为学问才是善。”

“是这样的。”

“但是，那些持后一种观点的人却无法向我们解释清楚他们所指的是哪种学问。如果他们被逼问急了，最后就会说他们指的是善的学问。”

“这是很荒谬的。”

“他们先是批评我们不懂善，但回头与我们交谈时，却又把我们当成懂善的；因为他们说这就是‘善的学问’，就好像他们在说‘善’字的时候，我们都能理解他们的意思。如果是这样的话，他们就无法回避自身的荒谬。”

“完全正确。”

“那些把善定义为快乐的人呢？他们面临的困惑会少一些吗？是不是他们也不得不承认存在恶的快乐？”

“他们当然得承认。”

“结果他们会发现自己承认同一事物是既有善的一面，又有恶的一面，对吗？”

“对。”

“所以说这个议题明显极具争议。”

“的确是这样。”

“再者，当涉及正义或价值观方面的问题时，不论是占有，还是行动，抑或是荣誉，很多人宁肯注重外在的东西，也不在意实实在在的东西；可是，没有人仅满足于拥有看起来好的东西，他们要的是实实在在好的东西。在这个问题上外在的东西没有任何用处。这些现象是不是也很明显呢？”

“绝对明显。”

“那么，善是全部劳动付出的结果，是每个人心中的目标，并且它预言了自身的存在，尽管人们发现很难把握它究竟是什么；由于没有像处理其他事物那样的把握，所以善缺少其他事物所具有的价值。我们将要把一切事物都托付给这些最优秀的公民。如果他们对如此重要的问题一窍不通，我们能答应吗？”

“绝对不答应。”

“不管怎样，如果一个人不知道何处有善的话，那么，让他来保卫正义和价值观，也就没有多大的用处。我猜只有在他搞明白何处有善之后，才能充分理解这些。”

“你猜得有道理。”

“所以说，只有将我们的社会置于拥有这门学问的守护者监管之下，社会才能得到妥善管理。”

“必须这样，”他说，“可是你呢，苏格拉底？你认为善是学问呢，还是快乐呢？还是其他的什么东西？”

“你这个人哪！”我惊叫了一声，“我很久之前就看出来了，你对别人的意见总是感到不满意！”

“可是，苏格拉底，给了你这么长时间谈论这个话题，”他抗议道，“你却只给我们讲别人的意见，而不是你自己的意见。我认为你不应该这样。”

“的确不应该。不过，如果一个人谈论自己不懂的事情时却给人一种好像他什么都懂的感觉。你认为这样就对吗？”

“他没有权利像个万事通似的高谈阔论。但他应该精心准备，把自己的想法说出来。”

“嗯，”我说，“难道你没注意，如果没有知识的支撑，观点总是很可悲的一件事吗？最理想的情况就是瞎蒙却蒙对了——虽然自己不甚理解，但却恰好持一种正确的意见，就好比一位盲人走对了路一样。不是有这样的人吗？”

“是有这样的人。”

“那么，如果你能够从其他人那里得到异常清晰的描述的话，那你还会想从我这里得到一幅简陋不堪、难以理解、支离破碎的画面吗？”

“现在你就行行好吧，都快到终点了，千万不要放弃啊，苏格拉底。”格老孔乞求说，“如果你能像解释正义、自我控制等概念一样来解释什么才是善，我们就会心满意足的。”

“那样的话，我也会心满意足的，我亲爱的伙计。”我回答道，“不过，我担心这超出了我的能力所限。我要是这样做的话，只会让我自己出丑，惹来他人耻笑。所以，请允许我们暂时把善的本质是什么的问题先放在一边，在今天所讨论的范围里恐怕是找不出一个令我满意的答案的。不过，如果你喜欢的话，我会谈一件事。它在我看来就好似是善的孩子，与善长得非常像——你愿不愿意听？”

“给我们讲讲这个孩子的事吧。孩子家长的那笔账就先记在你的账上，留着以后再讲。”他说。

“我希望欠你们的债能够连本带息地还给你们，而不仅仅是支付贷款利息。”我回答道，“不过，现在你们只能把善的孩子的故事当作利息收下。当心我不留神把到期利息金额写错了，那样的话你们就上当了。”

“我们会加倍小心的，”他说，“接着往下讲吧。”

二、太阳的比喻[……]

“我必须首先征得你们的同意，并提醒大家我们在前面的讨论中曾经说过的事情，实际上还有在许多其他场合讲过的事情。”

他问：“都是些什么？”

我回答说：“我们说过，有很多特定的东西都非常美，还有很多东西非常善，诸如此类，而且在描述过程中我们还对它们进行了区分。”

“是的，我们是说过。”

“接着我们针对我们认为数量很多的那些特定的东西，又谈到了美本身和善本身等问题。然后，我们通过对比，推断出每样事物都是独一无二的种类，并称之为每样事物‘真正是什么’。”

“是这样的。”

“我们说过这些特定的东西是视觉意义而不是智能意义上的东西，而其种类则是智能意义上而不是视觉意义上的东西。”

“当然。”

“我们看到的一切是用身体的哪个部分看到的呢？”

“视觉。”

“我们用听觉来听，用其他感官来感知与之相应的事物。”

“当然了。”

“不知道你注意到了没有，”我问，“我们的感官设计者在赋予我们视力，让我们能够看见东西的时候是多么慷慨？”

“没有注意到。”

“那么我们就再来看一遍。听觉和声音是否需要借助他们自身之外的另外一种形式的东西，才能让耳朵听得到，让声音听得见（即第三种要素），没有它的话，既没法听，也听不见？”

“不需要。”

“其他大部分感官，也可能是全部感官，也都是如此。你知道有什么感官需要这种东西吗？”

“不，我不知道。”

“但不知道你是否注意到了视觉及可见的东西的确需要这种东西？”

“怎么会呢？”

“假设眼睛具有视力，眼睛的主人也准备用视力去看东西，再假设物体具有颜色，可你知道，要是不专门地、自然地借助用于这个第三种要素的话，他什么东西也看不到，颜色也依然不可见。”

“那是什么东西？”他问。

“一种叫作光的东西。”我答道。

“对。”

“也就是说，如果光算是一种宝物的话，那么，视觉与物体的可见性就是用这样一条比任何东西都宝贵的纽带连接在一起。”

“光当然算是宝物。”

“那么，在众多天体当中你认为是哪个天体成就了这一切？又是哪个天体发出的光能够让我们的眼睛完美地看到东西，东西也能够为我们所见呢？”

“我的看法跟你和其他人是一样的，当然是太阳。”

“那么视力与这种神圣的光源有怎样的关联呢？”

“怎样的关联？”

“太阳不等同于视力，也不等同于视力所依赖的东西，也就是我们所说的眼睛。”

“它们是不同的东西。”

“但在所有的感觉器官当中，眼睛是最像太阳的。”

“是很像。”

“所以，眼睛的视觉能力，是太阳所赋予的一种能力。”

“是的。”

“而且，虽然太阳本身不是视力，但它却是视力产生的原因，并且能够为视力所见。”

“是这样的。”

“其实，那就是善的孩子。”我说，“善所生的孩子与善长得极为相像。在思想世界里，善与智能和可理解的事物之间存在的关联，同样也存在于有形世界里视力和可见物体之间。”

“你能再详细解释一下吗？”他问。

“你知道，当我们把目光转向阳光照射不到的物体时，借助于月光或星光，物体的颜色会看起来灰暗一片，眼睛好像失明了一样，仿佛视力原本就是模糊的。”

“是的。”

“但是，当我们把目光转向阳光照射的物体时，就会看得很清楚。这时眼睛明显是有视觉的。”

“肯定是这样的。”

“让我们借这个比喻来描绘一下心灵。当心灵之眼凝视着被真理和现实照亮的事物时，是完全能够认识和理解这些事物的。显然，心灵具有智能；但是，当心灵之眼盯住充满变数和衰败景色的黄昏世界时，心灵只能形成飘忽不定的意见，视野会变得模糊起来，明显缺少智能。”

“真的是这么回事。”

“那么说，赋予学问以真理，赋予认知者心灵以认知能力，这便是善的本质。它是学问和真理的动因，自身是为人所知的，但又不是学问和真理本身，而是一种更加辉煌的东西。你如果是这么想的，就对了。就好比说，把光和视觉看作与太阳类似的东西是正确的，但把它们看作太阳本身则是错误的。同样道理，把学问和真理看作与善类似的东西是可以的，但把它们看作是善本身则是大错特错，善是更高层次上的东西。”

“如果善是学问和真理的源泉，而且比之更加灿烂辉煌，你可真是把它奉若神明了。我想你不会指的是快乐吧？”他问。

“你这个想法真可怕。”我答道，“我们继续我们的比喻。”

“往下讲吧。”

“太阳不仅让我们看到世间万物，而且推动万物出生、成长和获取营养的进程，但其并非这个过程本身。这个观点我想你也同意。”

“同意。”

“因此，可以说善不仅促成学问知识为人所理解，而且促成对它们自身和现实的理解；不过，善本身不是指现实，而是超越了现实，并较之更加高贵、更加权威。”

“真是奇迹般的超然。”格老孔略带戏谑地说。

“这可不能怪我，”我抗议道，“是你让我心里怎么想的就怎么说的。”

“是我让的。请继续往下说。不管怎么说，如果你那个太阳的比喻还没讲完的话，还请你把它讲完。”

“离讲完还早着呢。”

“那就接着讲，不要遗漏任何东西。”

“恐怕必须略去很多内容。”我说，“不过，我会尽力把我目前所知道的一切都讲出来。”

“好的，请吧。”

分割线

柏拉图解释说，分割线比喻是太阳比喻的续篇，旨在进一步说明太阳比喻所涉及的现实中两种层次之间的关系。但它是从一个特定的角度来讲述的，即我们用来理解这两种层次或领域的心智状态。因此，这个线的目的主要也不是用来给事物分类。与可知领域相关的两种心智状态，都是与同种类型的东西（本质）打交道，尽管每种心智状态的处理方式各不相同；虽然在物质世界里，物质的东西与其自身的影子有区别，但这种差异主要用于阐明需要了解的东西当中存在的“真实”或真实性的程度——如果我们的学问仅局限于它的影子或影像，那么，我们对自身学问的东西了解就太有限了。就这个问题而言，就是仅仅局限于肤浅的外表了[……]

“那么，”我继续说道，“你必须假设存在我前面提到的这两种能力。一种能力比可知层次或领域内的所有东西都至高无上，另一种能力则凌驾于可见领域内一切东西之上——我不会说是在物质宇宙当中，否则你会认为我是在玩文字游戏。不管怎么说，你头脑面对的是两个层次上的东西，一个是可见的东西，一个是可知的东西。对吗？”

“对。”

“那好，假设有一条线，你把它分成了长短不等的两份。然后，你再按照相同的比例，把它们分成两部分，分别代表可见层次和可理解层次。你会在可见的层次上看到一个以模糊与清晰相对照的形式展现的、由影像构成的二次分段。如果你听得懂我说的话，我这里的‘影像’首先指的是阴影，然后指水面和其他光滑细致的表面反射的影子。”

“我听得懂。”

“其他二次分段代表着这些影像对应的原始实物本身——我们身边的各种动物、植物和人造物品。”

“说得很好。”

“你是不是准备说这些分段的区别在于：一个是真实的，一个是不真实的，而且，影像与原物之间的关系，就如同意见领域和学问领域之间的关系呢？”

“我肯定会这么说。”

“下面再考虑一下如何划分这条线上的可知部分。”

“如何划分呢？”

“在其中一个二次分段上，心智这次把可见领域中的原始实物作为影像，一切探究只能在假设的基础之上进行，从中得到的不是基本原理，而是结论性的东西；在另外一个二次分段上，它从假设上升到了不包含假设的基本原理，而且没有用到在另一个二次分段中用到的影像，而只是用类型自身或通过类型自身进行探究。”

“我听不大懂。”

“我再试着解释一下。不过，我刚刚谈到的东西会对你有点帮助。我想你也知道，那些学习几何、算术一类课程的学生，一开始会假设有奇数和偶数、几何图形、三种角以及与课程相应的其他东西；他们把这些东西都当成已知的，把它们作为最基本的假设。由于这些东西属于尽人皆知的东西，因此，完全没有必要对其自身进行任何的解释。他们以此为起点，通过一系列连贯的步骤，得出了他们想要得到的结论。”

“对，这个我肯定懂。”

“你还知道他们使用可见的图形进行研究。但是，他们心里想的实际上不是这些图形，而是这些图形所代表的原始事物；他们所研究的并不是他们所绘制出的正方形、对角线或是其他什么图形本身。他们所绘制或仿真的图形，在水中投下了自身的影子，并反射出去——他们只把这些当作影像而已，而他们研究的真实物体只有理性的眼睛方能看到。”

“非常正确。”

“我把此类东西称为可知的东西。我还说过，心智在研究它的过程中迫不得已使用了假设，但由于无法摆脱和超越假设，也就无法上升到基本原理的层面；不过，同样是这些东西，由于它们在较低的层面上留有影像和影子，用它们的示意图与其进行对比，会因其更加清晰而受到重视，也就更有价值。”

“我明白了，”他说，“你说的是几何学和相近学科发生的事。”

“那么，当我提到这条线上可知部分的另外一个二次分段时，你就会明白我的意思是指辩论过程本身通过辩证法的力量所理解的东西；它不是把假设当作原理，而是当作真正意义上的假设，也就是说，把它作为出发点和上升到更高层次的跳板，那里没有假设，只有万物的基本原理；而一旦掌握了基本原理，通过遵循其后面的推论，回过头来又可以得出结论。整个过程没有涉及可感知的世界里的任何东西，而只是从一种本质到另一种本质，最后归结为本质。”

“我明白你的意思了，但没有全懂，”他说，“你所描述的东西貌似说来话长。但是，你想区分辩证法所研究的真实与可知的部分，因为这部分比所谓的‘学科’所研究的东西清晰程度更高一些。尽管这些学科在研究他们自身的题材时也要使用推理，而不是感官知觉，但他们把假设当成了基本原理。由于他们在研究过程中从假设出发，无法到达基本原理的层次，所以，你认为他们在这个问题上面没有展现出理智。尽管借助于基本原理，它是可知的。我认为，你把几何学家一类人的思维习惯称为推理，而不是理智，意思是说，推理是介于意见和理智之间的一种东西。”

“你理解得非常好。”我说，“可以这么认为，与四段分隔线对应的是四种心智状态；位于最顶层的是理智，第二层的是推理，第三层的是信念，最下面的一层是幻觉。你可以按比例排一下，假设它们的清晰程度与题材所具有的真实程度相对应。”

“我懂了，”他答道，“我同意你的建议，把它们排列一下。”

洞穴的比喻

那个分割线比喻当中所蕴含的真理，可以用更形象化的方法展现，尤其是它可以告诉我们更多有关分隔线比喻当中称之为信仰和幻觉的两种心智状态方面的事。我们看到了心智从幻觉升华到了纯哲学，也看到了伴随其成长所经历的艰难困苦。哲学家在到达视野的最高点后，应返回到山洞中，为他的同伴服务。他极不情愿这样做，但这却成了他的主要资本[……]

“接下来，我想让你描述一下我们人类的启蒙状态或者愚昧状态。把一个地下密室想象成类似洞穴的东西，长长的密室入口面对阳光，入口的宽度与洞穴一样宽。住在这个地下密室里的人，从小就被囚禁于此。他们的腿和脖子被锁链绑得很紧，头也无法转动，只能直视前方。在他们的身后、上方，有一团火正在熊熊燃烧。在囚徒与火之间，有一条走道相通。通道的前面竖起了一面幕墙，就像在木偶表演（皮影戏）中操纵者与观众之间放置的那种幕布。”

“明白。”

“继续想象有一群人携带各式装备在幕墙后面行走，并在它的上方投射出了影子，包括用木头、石头和其他各种材料制作的人和动物。也可以想象得到，这些人中有的在谈话，还有的沉默不语。”

“真是怪异的画面，怪异的囚徒。”

“这都是依据真实生活描绘出来的啊，”我回答道，“你说说看，这些可怜的囚徒除了可以看见火光在他们对面的洞壁上投射的影子之外，你认为他们还可以看到自己或他们的同伴吗？”

“如果一辈子都不允许他们转头，他们又怎么可能看到其他东西呢？”

“他们能看到通道上被搬运的那些东西吗？”

“当然不能。”

“那么，假使他们能够互相交谈，难道他们不会断定他们所看到的影子都是真实的事物吗？”

“他们难免会这样认为。”

“假使囚室里他们正对着的那面墙能够反射回声，如果一个人路过时发出了声音，难道你不认为他们会断定这个声音就是他们面前的影子所发出的吗？”

“他们只能这样想。”

“所以，他们完全相信，这里提到的物体的影子就是全部的事实真相。”

“是的，他们难免这样认为。”

“那么，设想一下，如果有一天解除了他们的禁锢，治愈了他们的错觉，那将会是一番怎样的景象？假设将其中一个人松了绑，然后强迫他站立起来，转过头，目视火堆，并向火堆走去；这些动作会令他痛苦不堪，眼前的一切会让他眼花缭乱，难以看清原先他只能看见其影子的物体。如果有人告诉他，他以前看到的东西都是空洞的、虚假的，他现在看到的东西才更接近于真实，观看的方法也更正确，这是因为他面对的是更真实的东西。如果在此基础上，再指着从他面前经过的每样东西，强迫他说出这些东西都是什么。如果是这样的话，你觉得他会怎么回答呢？难道你不认为他会不知所措，并且认为他以前见过的东西比现在指给他看的东西更真实吗？”

“是的，他会认为以前的更真实。”

“如果强迫他对着火光看的话，会伤害到他的眼睛。他会转身回到他能够看得清的事物中去，他认为这些东西比指给他看的东西要清晰得多。”

“是的。”

“如果把他强行拉上那条陡峭崎岖的上坡道，直至把他拖出洞外，见到洞外的阳光，”我继续说着，“这个过程会令他非常痛苦，他也会非常抵触。当他来到阳光下，耀眼的阳光会刺得他的眼睛无法睁开，人们说的真实物体他一样东西也看不清。”

“一开始肯定看不清。”他表示同意。

“因为在他可以看清洞外世界里的东西之前，肯定需要时间慢慢地去适应外面的光线。首先，他会发现最容易做的事就是看影子，然后是看人和其他物体在水中的倒影，最后再去观看物体本身。此后，他会发现在夜晚时分观察天体和天空会容易一些，还会发现在夜里观看月光和星光，要比在白天看太阳和太阳光容易得多。”

“当然了。”

“他最终能够做到直视太阳本身，而不必通过太阳在水或其他介质中的倒影来观看，而是直接盯住太阳看。”

“必须最后做这事。”

“不久，他就会得出一个结论：正是太阳才带来了四季变化和昼夜更替。太阳主宰着可见世界里的一切，并且从某种意义上讲，太阳也是他和他的囚徒同伴过去看到的一切的起因。”

“很明显他会得出这个结论的。”

“当他想起他在洞穴里的那个最初的家，想起曾经被当作智慧的那些东西，想起他的那些囚徒同伴，难道你不认为他会为自己的幸运感到庆幸，并为他的同伴感到难过吗？”

“非常有可能。”

“囚徒当中有可能也存在某种荣誉感，那些把闪过的影子出现的先后顺序记得最牢的囚徒，还有那些预言影子未来出现次序最准确的囚徒，会因其敏锐的眼力而受到大家的赞扬。那个获释的囚徒还会热衷于这种表扬、羡慕这种能力或荣誉吗？他可能宁愿‘在失去主人的房子里当一名农奴’，实际上你让他在世界上做其他什么都行，他也不愿意再和囚徒们持相同的看法，过相同的生活。难道他不会如荷马所说的这样吗？”

“会的，”他回答说，“他宁愿做什么都行，但就是不愿意像他们一样生活。”

“那么，当他有朝一日回到洞穴，”我问，“坐回到他原来的位子上时，你觉得会发生什么事情？难道他的眼睛就不会因为阳光突然消失而完全被黑暗所笼罩，于是就什么都看不见了吗？”

“肯定会这样的。”

“假使在他视力没有恢复、眼睛也没有习惯黑暗之前（这个过程需要一段时间）让他和其他囚徒展开区分影子的比赛——他还有可能会自欺欺人，愚弄自己吗？囚徒们会说，他的外面世界之旅把他自己的视力都给毁了。上到上面去的想法根本一点都不值去试。假使有人试图释放他们，并带他们到上面去。如果他们抓住他，一定会杀了他。”

“他们肯定会杀了他。”

“我亲爱的格老孔，”我接着说，“现在，必须把这个比喻与前面所讲的东西贯穿在一起讲。视力所揭示的世界好比囚室，囚室里面的火光好比太阳的力量。如果你把去到上面的世界以及在那里看到的一切与心灵上升到可知领域联系在一起，你就不会理解错误。不管怎样，这就是我的解释，也是你急于想听的东西；不过，真相终究如何只有上帝才知道。但在我看来，在可知世界里最后感知到的、物有所值的东西，也是必须克服困难才能感知的东西，就是善的本质；一旦看清善的本质，就可以推断出它是一切万物中正义和价值的根源，在可见世界里发出光芒，是光的源头，而在可知世界本身，则是主宰真理和智慧的根源。无论是在公共生活当中，还是在私人生活当中，若要行事理智，就必须能看得到善的本质。”

“你的话当中我能理解的，”他说，“我都赞同。”

“那么你也许也会同意我的这个看法：那些达到此境界的人不愿意参与人间凡事，他们的心灵也希望被留在上面的那个可知世界中。如果真是这样的话，其实不足为怪。如果我们的那个比喻恰当的话，这种事情是会发生的。”

“是的，可以料到。”

“这种人从神圣的沉思当中返回到凡间，接踵而来的烦恼会令其苦不堪言。如果他此时仍看不见东西，还没有习惯周围的黑暗环境，就强行让他在法庭或其他什么地方，对正义的影子，或者对作为和构成影子的影像进行审判，对从未见过正义本身的人们所持有的、有关正义的观念进行辩论。如果是那样的话，你也不会认为很奇怪的。”

“这没有什么可奇怪的。”

“但凡有点理解力的人，”我说，“都会记得有两种方式可能会让人的眼睛失去视力，从亮处到暗处，或者从暗处到亮处。他们认为同样的情况也适用于心智。所以，当他看到一个受到困扰的、无法判明事理的心智时，他不会不加思索地大声嘲笑它，而是会先问一下自己，它是否来自于一个更清晰的世界，因不习惯这里的黑暗而受到困扰，或者它是否刚刚从先前的无知状态逃脱出来，被来自更清晰的世界发出的强烈光芒刺得眼花缭乱。生命的第一种状况有理由祝贺，生命的第二种状况则有理由同情。如果你想讥笑的话，就讥笑从上面的阳光世界下降到黑暗世界的心灵吧，这样就不会显得那么荒谬。”

“你讲得非常合乎情理。”

“如果这是事实的话，”我继续说，“那么，我们必须摒弃职业教育家的教育观念，他们宣称能够把知识灌输到原先没有知识的大脑中——就好像是说他们可以把视力赋予到失去视觉的眼睛里一样。”

“他们肯实这样说过。”他说。

“不过，我们的讨论表明了以下事实：对知识的接受能力是与生俱来的，而用于学习的器官像眼睛一样，是无法从暗处转向亮处的，除非整个身体能够转动；同样道理，必须让心智作为一个整体，从变革的世界中脱身出来，直至心智之眼可以承受直视现实，直视现实中最耀眼的东西，即我们称之为善的东西。难道不是这样的吗？”

“是这样。”

“那么，心智本身的这种转向，也可以作为一门专业技能，用来尽可能简单高效地完成这种转换。我们关心的不是植入视力，而是确保原本拥有视力的人既没有转错方向，也没有看错。”

“可能是这么一回事。”

“所以，剩下的我们通常称之为心灵美德的东西，也许与身体的优点十分相似，因为这些优点其实都不是与生俱来的，而是通过后天的训练和实践获得的；不过，学问看起来肯定拥有更加神圣的性质，一种从来不会丧失能力的东西。不过，其效果可能是有用的和有益的，也可能是无用的和有害的，视其调转的方向而定。你难道没有注意到，那种通常被称为坏人，但却很聪明的人，其目光有多敏锐？他们心胸狭窄，但在事关他们自身利益的事情上却目光敏锐，极为犀利；不是说他们的视力有多么微弱，而是说他们被用于邪恶的目的，所以，他们的视力越敏锐，就越邪恶。”

“这倒是真的。”

“但是，”我说，“假设从他们很小的时候，就把这种品性与这个多变的世界本该有的重负隔离开来，强加到他们身上的是各种感官享乐，如贪食。这些东西扭曲了他们的灵魂，使之变得低级趣味；再假设他们的这种品性得到了释放，转向了真理，那么同样这些人的同样器官，会对真理有同样敏锐的视力，就像现如今他们对所面对的事物具有的那种敏锐视力一样。”

“非常有可能。”

“没有受过教育、不懂真理的人，是永远管理不好这个社会的，那些终生单纯追求学术的人，同样也是永远管理不好这个社会的。难道不是这样的吗？实际上从我们讲过的东西里必然会得出这个结论。没有受过教育的人，其在公共场合和私下场合的所有行为，都没有一个专一的人生目标来指导；而知识分子则不愿采取任何实际行动，一心只想逃离这个世界，到某种人间天堂中生活。”

“同意。”

“那么作为立法者，我们的职责就是迫使最优秀的人才学到我们称之为最高级知识的东西，使他们上升到我们前面描述过的那种善的境界。当他们实现了这个目标，并且有了足够的洞察力时，要防止他们作出如今尚被允许的那些行为。”

“你这是什么意思？”

“我的意思是说他们会滞留在上面的世界里，拒绝再次回到下面洞穴里那些囚徒的身边，无论大事小事，都拒绝分担他们的劳动，拒绝分享他们的奖赏。”

“不过，”他抗议道，“这确实不公平。我们在强迫他们过一种比原先更差的生活。”

“我们立法的目的，”我再次提醒他说，“不是社会中某个特定阶层，而是整个社会享有的特殊福利；通过劝说或强制手段，让全体公民团结起来，一同分享每一个个体对社会提供的利益；培养这种态度的目的在于，不要让人们各自为战，而是让每个人都成为整个链上的一环。”

“你说得对；我把这茬忘了。”他说。

“那么，格老孔，”我接着说，“你也看到了，我们不应该不公平地对待我们的哲学家。可是，当我们要求他们对别人进行某种照顾和承担某种责任时，其实我们提的这些要求是相当公平的。我们应当告诉他们，出生在其他国家的哲学家是有理由拒绝参加辛苦的政治工作的，因为这些哲学家是完全自发产生的，或是在无意当中产生的。只有那些完全靠自己成长起来的事物，才会有这种感觉。它们不欠任何人的情，也不需要报答养育之恩。‘但是，’我们会说，‘我们为了你自己，也为了整个社会，而把你培养成了领导者和蜂巢里的蜂王；你受到了比其他人更好和更完整的教育，更有资格把哲学和政治实践相结合。因此，你们必须轮流下到洞穴里，和你的同伴一起生活，并养成在黑暗中观察的习惯；一旦你的习惯养成了，你的观察能力就会比他们好上一千倍。你能够区分不同的阴影，知道它们是什么东西的阴影，因为你已经看过了美好、公正和至善东西的真相。所以说我们的国家和你们的国家，对他们的影子战斗及被他们视为无比荣耀的政治权力争夺战，保持着真正的清醒，而不是像当今大多数社会那样仅仅生活在梦想之中。事实完全不同：由最不热心掌权的人治理的国家，其政府必定是最好的和最平和的政府，而由渴望权力的人统治的国家，其政府必定是最差的政府。’”

“我非常同意。”

“那么，我们的学生在听到了我们这番话以后，会不会表示异议，并拒绝分担他们在政府中的重任呢？尽管他们大部分时间其实都是在上面纯洁的世界中度过的。”

“他们不会拒绝，因为我们是向正义的人提出正义的要求。不过，当然了，他们会把治理国家当成无法回避的义务，这一点与现在的统治者不同。”

“是的，当然。”我表示同意，“事实上，你必须为未来的统治者找到一种他们喜欢的、比治理国家更好的生活方式，只有这样，国家才可能治理良好；只有到那个时候，政府才是由真正富有的人来统治。他们的富有不是用金子堆砌出来的，而是至善和理性的生活所带来的真正幸福。如果你找的都是些生活贫困、连个人需求都无法满足的人处理公共事务，这些人希望从政治生涯中捞取好处，来弥补自身的不富足，他们永远都不可能治理好国家。他们开始争权夺利，随之而来的内部冲突和国内冲突会毁掉他们自己和整个社会的。”

“你说得真对。”

“真正的哲学生活方式会蔑视政治权力地位。除此之外，还有其他什么生活方式吗？”

“没有其他方式。”

“不过，我们希望得到权力的人只能是那些不喜欢权力的人，否则，就会出现权力相争。”

“那是肯定的。”

“他们最懂治国方略，有着其他形式的满足，生活也过得比政客们更充实。除了这些人之外，你还能强迫谁去担当国家守护者的职责呢？”

“没有别的什么人了。”

译者导读

阿尔贝·加缪（Albert Camus，1913—1960），法国作家、记者、哲学家，出生于法属阿尔及利亚的蒙多维；幼年丧父，由做女佣的母亲抚养成人，通过半工半读取得哲学学士学位；曾加入法国共产党，后被驱逐出党。1960年1月4日，加缪在法国桑斯附近遇车祸身亡。

作为记者，加缪曾在多家报社发表过文章。加缪曾创办剧团，写过剧本，也做过演员，主要剧本有《误会》（1944）、《戒严》（1948）和《正义》（1949）等。此外，加缪写了很多著名的小说，其成名作《局外人》（1942）成为荒诞小说的代表作，长篇小说《鼠疫》（1947）曾获法国批评奖。1957年，加缪被授予诺贝尔文学奖。

加缪对哲学的首要贡献当属其关于荒谬的思想。他将荒谬视为我们对世界的“明晰性”和“意义”的欲望与无法满足这种欲望的状况相互作用的结果。他的思想集中表现于《西西弗斯神话》。1951年加缪发表哲学论文《反抗者》，开始了与萨特等存在主义者长达一年的论战，直到与萨特决裂。人们这才发现，一直被看作存在主义者的加缪原来是荒诞哲学及文学的代表人物。

《西西弗斯神话》是加缪的一部哲学论文集，1942年出版。加缪在书中阐释了自己的荒谬哲学，即人在面对一个没有上帝及永恒的真理或价值的世界时对意义、统一性及明晰性的无益探求。在书的一开始，加缪就提出了一个引人入胜的命题：“真正严肃的哲学问题只有一个，那就是自杀。”书中围绕这一问题对荒谬进行了详细阐述，并列举了几类荒谬的生活。最后一章对人们生活的荒谬性与反复推石头上山的西西弗斯的状况进行了比较。在书的最后，作者总结性地说：“迈向高处的挣扎足够填充一个人的心灵。人们应当想象西西弗斯是快乐的。”

《西西弗斯神话》出版时加缪二十九岁，而这不到三十年的人生历程对于加缪来说无疑是坎坷的：幼年丧父，在贫民区摸爬滚打地长大，在他人的资助与自己的努力下上了大学，又不幸染上肺结核，尝遍人间疾苦。艰辛的人生经历促使他不断进行命运的思索，探讨人生命题。和许多有责任感的学者一样，加缪关心时世，政治立场鲜明，是一位有态度的创作者。在第二次世界大战中，加缪在《阿尔及利亚报》任记者。反对绥靖政策的他因触犯当局而不得已回到法国。后又从《巴黎晚报》离开，迁居奥兰，也就是在那里他完成了本书的创作。

加缪曾在《笔记 Ⅱ》（1945）中写道：“为什么我是一个艺术家而不是哲学家？因为我是根据词而不是概念来思维的。”研读《西西弗斯神话》，读者能清楚地意识到这一点，对于译者而言体会则更深刻。文章字里行间传达的是至诚而实在的哲思，作者绝不会拿各种概念性的东西把读者引入虚幻的意境，有的只是诚恳的说理。正基于此，译者在传译的过程中不敢也不忍轻易舍一词一字，生怕断了作者的“思维”。因此，译文在保证思想流畅、表达准确的基础上，用心通过一字一词努力再现这位慎思的哲人诚挚的“思维”。

一种荒谬的推理

以下章节所述是在这个时代随处可见的一种荒谬的细腻情感，而不是我们这个时代（严格地说）尚未知晓的一种荒谬哲学。因此本书在一开始就指出书中哪些内容得益于某些当代思想家，是完全合理的。我丝毫没有掩盖这一点的意思，所以你会发现本书自始至终一直在引用与评论这些内容。

但同时注意到这一点也是有益的，那就是迄今已成结论的荒谬在本书则被当作一个出发点。从这个意义上讲，或许可以说，我的论述中存在暂时性的东西：人们无法对其立场作出预判断。你只能在书中发现对一种纯粹的思维病态的描写。诸如形而上学或者信仰，片刻也没有出现过，这就是本书的局限与仅有的偏见。作此澄清是出于某些个人的经历。

荒谬与自杀

真正严肃的哲学问题只有一个，那就是自杀。

判断生活是否有价值，无异于回答最基本的哲学问题。其他一切问题——诸如世界是否有三个维度，思想有九个还是十二个范畴——都在其次。这些不过是游戏；人们首先要做的是回答问题。倘若真如尼采所称，哲学家为赢得尊重就必须以身作则，那么你就能体会到回答那一问题的重要性了，因为这一回答是先于实际行动的。这些都是可以为心灵所感知的事实，却也需要先仔细地研究才能明白无误地理解。

我自问如何判断此问题急迫于彼问题，答案是人们可以从问题所牵涉的行动入手。我从未见过谁是为本体论[1]问题而死的。伽利略曾坚持一条非常重要的科学真理，但当这条真理危及自己的生命时，他极为轻松地放弃了它。从某种意义上说，他确实抗争过。[2]为这一真理而走上火刑柱赴死是不值得的。从深层次而言，地球和太阳哪个围绕哪个转是无关紧要的。说实话，这是一个无用的问题。同时，我又看见很多人因为觉得生活毫无价值而死去。我还看见，有的人自相矛盾，为了那些赋予他们生存意义的想法或幻想而结束了生命（这一所谓的生存理由同样也是一个绝佳的死亡动机）。因而我得出结论：生活的意义是所有问题中最急迫的。那么如何回答这一问题呢？对于一切基本的问题（我指的是构成死亡威胁的问题，或是强化生活热情的问题），或许只有两种思考方式，一种是帕里斯[3]的方式，一种是堂·吉诃德[4]的方式。唯有在事实与抒情之间找到平衡，才能让我们同时保持激情与清醒。对于一个既如此卑微又如此富于情感的主题，人们可以发现，学术性的、经典的逻辑论证法必须让步于一种更加朴素的思想立场，这种立场既出自人的直觉判断，又来源于人的理解能力。

自杀从来都是被作为一种社会现象来研究的，而我们的研究恰恰相反，我们在一开始关注的就是个体思想与自杀之间的关系。这种行为正如一件伟大的艺术作品，在心灵的静默中孕育，行为者本身并没有意识到。某个晚上，他扣动了扳机，或是纵身一跃。我曾听说过一个公寓经理自杀的例子。五年前他失去了自己的女儿，打那时起整个人就变了很多，而这一变故“侵蚀”着他。用这个词来形容再准确不过了。开始思考也就开始了被侵蚀。社会与这种开始没什么必然联系，问题出在人们心里，那才是应该探究的地方。这一死亡游戏是从清醒地面对生活体验过渡到逃离光明，人们须追踪并且理解这种游戏。

自杀有很多理由，总的来说，最显而易见的并非最具有杀伤力。自杀很少是由反思引起的（但也不能排除）。什么引发了危机，几乎总无法证实。报纸常会说是“内心的悲恸”，或是“不治之症”。这些解释是说得过去的，但是人们应该弄清楚，出事那天是不是有个朋友用一种冷漠的语调和这个绝望的人说话。如果有，那么这个朋友就是有罪的。因为这足以触发仍在酝酿中的怨恨与烦恼。[5]

然而，如果难以确定思想上决定自杀的微妙步骤——那一准确时刻，那么从这一行为本身推知它带来的后果则要容易得多。从某种意义上说，如在情节剧中一样，自杀等于是自白，承认生活对你来说已无法承受，抑或你不理解生活，但是，我们也不要把这些类比扯得太远，还是要回到日常话语中来，那么承认的就只是“不值得这么费力”地生活。诚然，生活从来都不容易。你不断接收生存发出的指令，并以某种姿态回应，回应的原因有很多，其中首要原因就是习惯。自愿结束生命意味着你已意识到，甚至是本能地意识到这种习惯的荒谬性，意识到找不到任何深刻的理由去生活，发现每天的忙忙碌碌愚蠢至极，遭受痛苦亦无益处。

那不可估量的感情夺去了生活中必要的精神昏睡，那么这种感情究竟是什么呢？世界即使需要用糟糕的理由来阐释，对于人来说也是熟悉的。相反，世界如果突然间失去了幻想与光明，人就会觉得自己是陌生人，是外星人。这种被流放的感觉是无可救药的，因为他被剥夺了对失去家园的记忆和对应许之乡的盼望。人与生活的这种分离，如同演员与舞台的分离一样，可以说正是荒谬感。如果那些有轻生念头的人都是健康人，那么无须多加解释人们就会发现，这种感情与对死的渴望之间有一种直接的关系。

本书的主旨就是表现荒谬与自杀之间的这种关系，揭示自杀究竟在何种程度上解决了荒谬这一问题。原则上可以肯定，对于一个诚实的人来说，对他信以为真的东西应当付诸行动。对存在的荒谬性的笃信必然要支配人的行为。人们可以理所当然地发出疑问——清楚明白而非故作哀伤地，如此重要的一条结论会不会要求人们尽快摆脱一种难以理解的环境呢。当然，我指的是想达到自身协调的人们。

表达得清楚一点，这一问题就显得既简单又不好解决。如果认为简单问题的答案也很简单，清晰明了带来的必是清晰明了，那就大错特错了。若先验地颠倒问题的各项，就如人是自杀还是不自杀的问题一样，只有两种哲理结果：是或不是，这就显得过于简单了，但是应当限制那些不停发问而不作定论的人。这里我只是稍作讽刺：这些人占了大多数。我还注意到，有些人嘴上说“不”，行为表现却好像他们想的是“是”。事实上，根据尼采[6]的标准，他们无论如何都会说：“是。”同时，那些自杀的人常常对生活的意义十分确信。这些矛盾屡见不鲜。甚至可以说，这些矛盾从来没有如此鲜明过，在这一点上，逻辑性变得十分可贵。把哲学理论与这些理论信仰者的行为加以比较，是再平常不过的了。必须指出，在拒绝赋予生活以意义的人中，除了文学作品中的人物基里洛夫[7]，传奇人物贝尔格里诺斯[8]和善于假说的朱尔斯·勒奎尔，没有一个人把否定逻辑推理发展到否定生活。叔本华[9]曾坐在一张华丽的桌子旁大赞自杀，他也因此常被拿来当笑柄。这没有什么可笑的。不把悲剧当回事没有那么可悲，但是却可以用来判断一个人。

面对这种矛盾与令人费解之事，我们还一定要得出结论说，一个人对生活的看法与他逃离生活的做法之间没有关系吗？我们不要在这方面夸大其词。在一个人与自己生活的关系中，有些东西比全世界的苦难加起来都要强大。身体的判断与心理的判断不相上下，而身体面对毁灭时会畏缩不前。我们先养成生活的习惯，然后才养成思考的习惯。在每天都催人走向死亡的竞赛中，身体保持着绝对的领先优势。简言之，这种矛盾的本质在于我所说的逃避行为，因为按照帕斯卡的说法，它既低于又高于消遣行为。逃避是始终不变的游戏。典型的逃避——对死亡的躲闪，是本书的第三个主题，那就是希望。这是对自己“应得”的另一种生活的希望，或者说是对那些不是为生活本身，而为了某些伟大思想继续生活的人的欺骗，这种生活的伟大目标将超越生活，使生活得到升华，赋予生活以意义，然后背叛生活。

如此，一切事物都会造成混乱。人们至今还在玩弄词句并且假装相信，拒绝赋予生活以意义必然得出生活没有价值的结论，而这些努力并没有白费。事实上，在这两种判断之间没有必然的共同标准。人们要做的只是不要受先前指出的混乱、分离与前后不一的误导，必须将一切置之不理，直入实际问题。人们自杀是因为生活不值得过，这确实是一个真理——只是因为不言自明而显得没有意义。但是这种对生存的侵犯，这种让生活深陷其中的断然否定是由生活无意义这一事实造成的吗？生活的荒谬性要求人们借助希望或者自杀来逃离生活吗？——这正是在将其他一切置之不理时必须阐明、追问以及解释的东西。这种“荒谬”操控了死亡吗？在所有思想方法与一切不偏不倚的心理活动之外，必须优先考虑这一问题。“客观”的心理总是将意义的阴影、矛盾与心理学引入所有问题，但这些因素在这种探索与热情中不占有任何位置。需要的只是一个不公正的思想，换句话说就是逻辑思想。这并非易事。做事合乎逻辑常常很容易，但要坚持到痛苦的最后则几乎是不可能的。因此，自杀的人通常顺由自己的情感变化走到终点。对死亡的思考让我借机提出唯一令我感兴趣的问题：至死不变的逻辑是否存在？我无从知晓，只有借助证据进行探寻——这里我指出了这种推理的源头，在探寻中不能有感情的冲动。这就是我所称的荒谬的推理。许多人已经开始这一探索，不知他们是否还在坚持。

卡尔·雅斯培[10]指出，世界不可能形成一个整体，当他大声疾呼“这样的限制让我找到自己，于是我不能再拿自己正表达的一个客观观点做挡箭牌，于是不管是我自己还是他人的存在都不再是我的对象”时，他其实是在继很多人之后又提到了那些无水的沙漠，在那里思想已山穷水尽。继很多人之后，没错，但是他们曾经多少渴望走出沙漠啊！许多人，即使是一些最卑微的人，都到达了那最后的十字路口，而思想在那里犹豫不决了，然后他们便放弃了自己最宝贵的东西，他们的生命。其他人，那些精神上的贵族，同样放弃了，只是他们采取了思想的自杀这种最纯粹的反叛。其实，真正的努力应该是尽可能待在原地，仔细考查那些边远地区的奇花异草。在这场非人性的表演中，荒谬、希望与死亡展开了对话，而坚持与明智则是拥有特权的观众。思想于是可以先分析这支灵巧的入门舞蹈的舞者们，然后加以阐释并再亲自体验一次。

荒谬的墙

正如伟大的作品一样，深邃的感情总是静水流深。心灵中规律性的冲动与排斥也同样发生在习惯性的做与想中，并且在心灵本身并不知情的诸多后果中重新上演。伟大的感情拥有自己的宇宙，或宏伟壮观，或惨不忍睹。这些感情用自己的热情点亮一个专属于自己的世界，并在这个世界里找到适合自己的基调。有忌妒的宇宙、利欲的宇宙、自私的宇宙，也有慷慨大度的宇宙。一个宇宙，换句话说也就是一种形而上学、一种思想立场。适合于这种已然自立门派的感情的，甚至会更适合于那种情感，它们像为我们创造美好、由荒谬所激起的东西一样基本不可预料，含混而又明确，遥远而又“存在”。

在任何一个街角，荒谬的感情都可能正面直击任何一个人。实际上，赤裸裸的荒谬是让人费神的，它发出光亮，却不甚耀眼，难以捉摸，但这一难题又值得人思索。事实上，某个人可能永远都会不为人所知，在他身上有某种不能克服的东西我们无从发现，然而在现实情况中，我通过人们的行为和全部活动，以及他们的存在给生活带来的影响来认识和辨认他们。同样，那些不合理性的感情没有为分析创造任何落脚点，对于它们我能够在现实中加以定义与领悟，方法就是收集他们在思维领域的影响，把握并记录它们的所有面貌特征，描画属于它们的宇宙。可以肯定的是，即使一个演员我见过上百次，我也不会因此多了解他一点，但是如果我总结他所演绎的英雄人物，说我在列数他所演的第一百个角色后对他有了更深的了解，这听起来还像是真的。这一浅显的悖论也是一则寓言，其中寓有深义。它倡导人们用伪装，同样也用发自内心的冲动来定义自己。因此，有一种更为低调的感情，处于内心深处，难以接近，却又通过所暗示的行动，以及所表现的思想立场而部分地展现出来。我显然是在用这种方式定义一种方法，而同样明显的是这是一种分析方法，而非认知方法，因为方法就意味着形而上学；形而上学则会无意中揭示一些往往自称毫不知情的结论。与此相类似的是，一本书最后几页的内容已经包含在头几页中了。这样一种联系是不可避免的。这里定义的方法承认这种观点——不可能有全然真实的认识。只有表象可以被列举，基调可以被感知。

或许我们可以在各不相同却又紧密相联的智力世界、生活艺术世界，或单纯艺术世界超越那种难以捉摸的荒谬感情。荒谬性的思潮是在初始阶段，结尾是那荒谬的宇宙，还有那种思想态度，它用自己真实的色彩点亮这个世界，展示出那种态度在这荒谬的宇宙中所辨识出的无可改变的特殊面貌。

一切伟大的行动与一切伟大的思想都有一个荒唐的开端。伟大的作品常常诞生于某个街角或某个餐厅的旋转门里，荒谬性也不例外。荒谬的世界更是从那种卑微的出身中孕育出了高贵。在某些情况下，一个人被问及他在想什么时，答道：“没什么”，那他可能是在伪装。那些受人喜爱的人非常了解这一点。然而，如果回答是真心的，如果此回答表现了特异的心理状态，此时无声就是雄辩，日常活动的链条就被打破了，而心灵却搜寻不到能把它再联结起来的纽带，那么可以说这就是荒谬性发出的最早信号。

碰巧舞台背景塌了。起床、乘电车，在办公室或工厂待四个钟头，吃饭、乘电车，工作四个钟头、吃饭、睡觉，周一、周二、周三、周四、周五、周六，都遵循着同样的节奏——大部分时候沿着这条路走是很容易的。但是有一天，“为什么”出现了，所有沉闷乏味的事物都开始兴奋地叮当作响，于是“就开始了”——这是至关重要的。厌倦来自一种机械生活的结束，但同时，它也激发了意识的冲动。它唤醒了意识，并驱动着随后的事物，而随后便是逐渐恢复那根链条，或者说这就是彻底的觉醒。当完全觉醒后，结果也如期而至：自杀或者恢复。厌倦本身就有一些令人生厌的东西。在此，我必须给出我的结论：厌倦是件好事。因为万事始于意识，若不经过意识，任何事情都是无价值的。这些观点没有什么独创之处，而是显而易见的，足够对荒谬性的起源作一粗略回顾。正如海德格尔[11]所言，单纯的“忧虑”乃万事之发端。

同样，在平平淡淡的生活中，每天都是时间带着我们走，但是也总有我们必须带着时间走的时候。我们指望着未来过活：“明天”“以后”“在你走出自己的路之后”“等你到了一定年龄就懂了”。这些无关紧要的事非常好，因为这终究是关系到死亡的问题，然而有一天，一个人注意到，或是跟人说，他三十岁了，他是在肯定自己的年轻，同时他也把自己和时间联系起来，在时间中他占有一席之位。他承认自己站在曲线的某一点上，并意识到必须走到曲线的尽头。他属于时间，那恐惧牢牢钳制住他，他才认清了自己最糟糕的敌人。明天，他在期待明天，但是体内的每一个细胞都应该是拒绝明天的。这种肉体的反抗就是荒谬。[12]

降低一个层次，陌生感就会伺机而入：察觉到世界是“密实”的，感觉到一块石头在多大程度上对于我们是陌生而不可简化的，以及自然或某处风景能多么强烈地否定我们。在一切美的内心都有一些非人性的东西，那些山、那柔和的天空、那树木的轮廓在这一刻失去了我们拿来装点它们的虚幻的意义，从此它们变得比失乐园还要遥远。世界最初就有的敌意会穿越几千年的光景来反对我们。转瞬间，我们不再理解这个世界，因为几个世纪以来，我们明白的只是我们事先赋予而这个世界的形象与设计，而自此以后，我们不再拥有这项技能。世界变回它本来的样子，从而从我们手中逃离。那被习惯所掩盖的舞台布景又恢复了原来的面貌，后退至和我们保持一段距离。这就好像是在某段时间里，我们几个月前或几年前曾爱过的一个女人的面孔由熟悉变得陌生起来。我们甚至开始渴望那些突然让我们变得孤身一人的东西，只是这一时机尚未成熟。唯有一事：世界的那种密实与陌生就是荒谬。

人也会隐藏非人性的东西。在某些清醒时刻，其姿态中机械的一面——那种无意义的哑剧，让周围的所有事物都变得愚蠢。一个人正在玻璃隔墙后打电话；你听不到他，只能看到他令人费解的哑剧表演：你在想，这人怎么会存在。面对自己非人性特质时的不适，看到自己的形象时不可估量的落差，这种被当代某作家称作“恶心”[13]的东西，也是荒谬。同样，有时与我们在镜中相会的陌生人，我们在自己照片中发现的那熟悉却又让人恐慌的兄弟，也是荒谬。

最后我要说到死亡以及我们对死亡的态度。关于这一点已有详尽论述，我只要避免引人哀惋即可。每个人似乎都在无人“知晓”的情况下生活，人们永远都会对这一点感到惊讶，因为在现实中，人们没有死亡的经历。确切一点说，人们经历过的只是生活中遇到并意识到的东西。这里，探讨别人死亡经历的希望十分渺茫，那只是一种替代物，一种错觉，不会让我们十分信服。这种悲伤的经历是没有说服力的。恐惧实际上来自事件那精确的方面。如果时间让我们感到害怕，那是因为它确定了问题，解决办法随之而来。所有关于灵魂的精彩言论都会让其反面得到令人信服的证明，至少在一段时期内如此。灵魂从一巴掌留不下任何痕迹的无生气的躯体中消失了，这一不寻常经历中基础而又具有决定性的那一面即为荒谬感。在这种命运的死亡之光下，其无用性显而易见。在操纵我们处境的残酷的确定性面前，任何一种道德、任何一种努力都无法先验地证明自己的正确性。

我重申：所有这些已不止一次被谈到。我在这里只是想做一个快速的归类，并指出这些显而易见的主题。这些主题贯穿于所有文学与哲学中，日常谈话为之提供养分，它们的重塑没有问题，然而要想随后自问这一基本问题，就有必要对这些事实了然于胸。我还要重申：我对荒谬之发现的兴趣不及对荒谬之后果的兴趣深厚。假如人们确信这些事实，那么会得出什么结论？又要做到什么程度才会不逃避任何事情呢？人们是自愿死亡，还是凡事都抱着希望呢？在此有必要对智力的程度预先作一次同样快速的清理归类工作。

思想上要做的第一步就是明辨是非，然而，思想一旦开始自省，首先发现的就会是矛盾，这一点是不言自明的。几个世纪以来，关于这一问题的论述，没有人能比亚里士多德更简洁而明白：“这些观点不攻自破，结果常常被人取笑。因为我们在肯定一切皆真实的同时也肯定了这种论点之反面的真实性，结果也就肯定了自己论题的谬误性（因为反面的论点不承认它是真实的）。而如果有人说一切皆谬误，这一论点本身就是错的。倘若我们宣称只有我们论点的反面是错误的，或者只有我们的论点不是错误的，我们则是被迫承认了无数真实或错误的判断。因为一个人在表达一种真实论点时宣称它是真实的，同时也承认了以此类推的无限论点。”

这一恶性循环只是系列中的第一环，在这一系列中，自省的思想迷失在令人晕眩的旋转中。正是这些悖论的简单性使它们变得不可克服。不论如何玩弄词藻，操纵逻辑，理解最重要的是一致。思想即使在最复杂详尽的过程中，其最强烈的欲望与人们在面对自己的宇宙时那种无意识的感情也是相似的。这是对熟悉事物的一种坚持，是对明晰性的一种渴望。对一个人来说，理解这个世界就是把它简化为人的状态，为之打上自己的印记。猫的宇宙不会是蚂蚁窝。“一切思想都是拟人化的”，这一不言而喻的真理没有其他含义。同样，旨在理解现实的思想只有把现实简化为思想领域的概念，才能得到满足。如果人们意识到宇宙同自己一样也可以有爱和遭遇，那么人们可能就会顺服了。倘若思想在闪亮的现象之镜中发现种种永恒的关系，既能把现象归纳为单一的原则，又能把它们自身归纳为单一的原则，那么此思想就可被看作一种思维上的愉悦，有福之人的神话不过是对这种愉悦的可笑模仿。那种对统一性的怀恋，那种对绝对性的渴望，阐明了这场人类大戏的基本冲动。这种怀恋的确存在，但并不意味着必须马上满足这种渴望。因为如果我们在分隔欲望与成功的鸿沟之上架起桥梁，我们就是肯定了巴门尼德[14]“一”（不论“一”为何物）的现实，我们就陷入了一种可笑的思想矛盾：这种思想肯定完全统一，并且用这种肯定证明自身的差异以及自称要解决的多样性。这另一个恶性循环足以扼杀我们的希望。

这些也是不言而喻的真理。我又要重申：它们本身没有什么有趣之处，有趣之处在于它们导致的结果。我知道还有一个自明之理，认为人终有一死。人们可以列数从这一真理推断出极端结论的种种思想。在我们幻想自己知道的与自己真正知道的之间，在实际赞成与假装无知之间，有着常见的差距。这种差距允许我们在生活中保有那种一旦真正投入试验便会颠覆我们整个生活的想法。我们有必要将这种差距作为本书一个不变的参考点。面对思想中这一纠缠不清的矛盾，我们应该完全掌控把我们与自己的创造相分离的裂缝。只要思想在这静止的希望世界里保持沉默，万事都会反映并被安排在这被怀念的统一性中，但是一旦破静为动，这个世界就开始破裂、倒塌：给认识留下无数闪光的碎片。对于重塑这个熟悉而平静、能给我们带来心理安宁的表象，我们一定是不抱任何希望的。经过这么多个世纪的探寻，许许多多的思想家选择了放弃，我们非常清楚，我们所有的知识都是这样。除了专业的理性论[15]者，如今人们对真正的知识已感到绝望。假使要书写唯一有意义的人类思想史，那么写的肯定是这些思想产出后接连不断的悔恨史与这些思想的无能史。

对于何人、何物，我可以说：“我知道！”我能感觉到我深藏的内心，我断定它是存在的。我能触摸到这个世界，我同样断定它是存在的。我所有的学识到此为止，余下要做的就是构建。因为如果我试图抓住真实可感的自我，如果我试图对之加以定义并总结，那么它就只能像水一样从我指间流走。我可以一个一个勾画出它能表现出来的所有面貌，以及那些同样归属于它的面貌，那种成长，那种源头，那种热情或那些沉默，那种高贵或那种邪恶。但是诸多面貌无法简单相加，这颗属于我的心对我而言永远都是不可定义的。在我对自身存在的确定性和我试图赋予这种确信的内容之间，存在着不可填充的沟壑，我对自己永远都是陌生的。如同在逻辑学中一样，在心理学中也是只有事实而没有真理。苏格拉底的“认识你自己”，同我们忏悔时的“守德”一样有价值。它们同时揭露了一种对过去的怀恋和一种无知，都是关于伟大主题的乏味游戏，这些游戏只有在严格的近似范围内才是可以被理解的。

树，我知道有嶙峋的表皮；水，我能品尝它的味道。那草木的清香与夜晚的星斗，那身心放松的晚上——我怎能否定这个世界？它的能量与力量我都可以感觉得到。然而世间的所有知识都不能向我保证说，这个世界是我的。你向我描述它，并教我给它分类。你列数它的规则，在我渴求知识时我承认这些规则都是对的。你拆分它的结构，于是我的希望增加了。最后，你教给我说这精彩纷呈、色彩斑斓的寰宇可以被还原为原子，原子又能被还原成电子。所有这一切都不错，我等着你继续说下去。可是你又告诉我有一个看不见的原子系统，电子在万有引力的作用下绕着一个核转动。你描绘了一个图像，为我解释这个世界。这时我发现你已被还原成了诗意：我永远也不会明白。我还有时间气愤吗？你已经改换了理论，于是本该教给我一切的科学以一个假设告终，那清醒的开创人以比喻收尾，那种不确定性成了一件艺术品。我还有什么必要作这么多努力呢？群山柔和的线条与夜晚之手对我那颗困扰之心的抚摸，教给我更多。我又回到了最初。我认识到即便通过科学我能掌握各种现象，并一一加以列举，我仍然不能领悟这个世界。当我用手指勾勒出世界的所有起伏后，我就不能再进一步了。而且你给了我一个二选一的题目，选项一是一个可以确定的描述，只是什么也没有教给我；选项二是一些假设，据称可以授予我知识，却都无法确定。我对于自身，对于这个世界都感到陌生，我有的只是在自我肯定后又迅速自我否定的思想。我只有不再去了解、不再去生活才能得到平静，对于征服的欲望遭遇了阻挡它进攻的墙，这是什么情况？有愿望就意味着要引出多个悖论。万事都以这种方式被安排，目的是形成由不经思考、不加用心与选择死亡产生的受荼毒的平静。

思智也以它的方式告诉我这个世界是荒谬的。其对立面——盲目的理性，很可能会宣称一切皆清晰。虽然我一直等待这一点被证明，并且期望它是正确的，但是多少自命不凡的年代后，我从那么多能言善辩之才的身上明白，这是错误的。至少在这一领域，如果我不知，就没有幸福。那一普遍的理性（现实的或是道德的）、那种宿命论、那些解释一切的范畴，足以贻笑大方。它们和精神毫不相干，否定了其将受到束缚的深刻真理，因而在这混沌不清的有限的宇宙中，人的命运承担了它的意义。大批不合理性涌现在他周围，直至他终老。人们业已恢复的洞察力如今变得审慎起来，于是荒谬的感情也变得清晰而明确。我说过这个世界是荒谬的，只是未免操之过急。只能说，这个世界本身是非理性的。而所谓荒谬，就是不合理性遭遇了对清晰性的极度渴望，这种渴望在人的内心回荡。荒谬同时取决于人和这个世界，它将两者捆绑在一起，正如只有仇恨才能把两物联结在一起一样。这是我在这个无限宇宙的探险之旅中能辨识出的所有。我们在此停顿一下。如果我承认这种决定我与生活之间关系的荒谬性，如果我在观赏这个世界的风景时充满惆怅与感伤，在追逐科学的过程中被迫变得头脑清晰，那么为了那些确定性我就必须牺牲一切，就必须正视它们以保持这种确定性。最重要的是，我必须使我的行为与之相适应，并且追踪其造成的所有影响。我指的是体面。但是在此之前我想知道思想能否在那些荒漠中生存。

我知道思想至少已进入了那些荒漠，在那里它找到了自己的面包，在那里它意识到之前一直是从幻象中汲取营养，证明了人类思考中最亟待解决的几个主题。

荒谬从它被承认的那一刻起，便成为一种强烈的感情，且是最折磨人的那种。不管人们能否和自己诸多强烈感情共处，能否接受这些感情的规则，这规则都可能烧毁他们同时在盛赞的心灵，这便是全部问题所在，但还不是我们马上要谈的问题。它属于这种经历的中心问题，还有时间再回到这一问题上。我们还是先来辨认一下那些源自荒漠的主题与冲动吧，列举这些因素便足够了，它们如今也已广为人知。过去，总会有人去捍卫非理性的权利。一种思想被冠以屈辱的标签，这种传统一直都有。对理性主义的批评不绝于耳，似乎也没有必要再发起一次。那些自相矛盾的体系力争绊倒理性，似乎理性真的一直遥遥领先，而这些体系的重建便是我们时代的标志。与其说这是理性效力的一个证明，不如说是其希望的强烈程度的一个证明。从历史角度看，两种立场的不变性阐明了人这种本质上的强烈感情被分裂，纠结在对统一的欲望和对包围自己的藩篱可能具有的清晰视觉之间。

然而，或许任何一个时代对理性的攻击都不及我们这个时代强烈。自从查拉图斯特拉[16]疾呼：“偶然乃是世上最古老的贵族，我把它交还给万物，我把万物从受制于目的的奴隶状态中解放出来。”自从克尔凯郭尔[17]染上不治之症——“这种疾病导致死亡，而身后一片什么也没了”之后，荒谬思想的主题便接踵而至，意味深长又折磨人心。或者至少，本书的附文——有关不合理性与宗教思想的主题，显得至关重要。从雅斯贝尔斯[18]到海德格尔，从克尔恺郭尔到舍斯托夫[19]，从现象学家到舍勒[20]，在逻辑学与道德范围内，构成了一个由幻想作为联系的思想家族，尽管其方法与目的各异，但他们都固执地阻挡着理性的光明之路，而去探索直通真理的道路。我在此设定的是那些为人知晓且被体验过的思想，不论其过去或现在的目标是什么，它们都源自那个无法描绘的宇宙——这里矛盾、对立、痛苦与无能横行，其共性正是已揭示出的主题。必须说明，对这些思想来说，最重要的也是从那些发现中得出的诸多结论，其重要程度要求人们必须对其单独进行分析。目前我们只关心其发现，及其独创性的试验，只注意指出它们一致的地方。如果说对其哲学进行研究有些冒昧，但无论如何我们可以阐释一下其共同的思想倾向，这也就足够了。

海德格尔冷静地观察了人类的状态，并表示这种存在是耻辱的。在整个生存链条中，唯一的现实是“焦虑”。对于迷失在世界及其岔路上的人而言，这焦虑是一种飞逝而过的恐惧。可是如果这种恐惧变得自知，它就会变成痛苦，这是头脑清醒之人（“存在集中表现在其身上”）永远的立场。这位哲学教授用世界上最抽象的语言坚定地写道：“人类存在的限定性与限制性特征比人类自身更原始。”他对康德[21]的兴趣仅限于认可其“纯粹理性”的限制性特征，他在分析的最后总结道：“世界无法再给予满怀痛苦的人任何东西。”这种焦虑在他看来，似乎比世界上所有的范畴都重要的多，以至于他的所想所谈都是关于它。他列举了焦虑的各个方面：当正常人企图平息他的焦虑时，他会感到厌烦；当思想在沉思死亡时，他感到害怕。海德格尔也没有将意识与荒谬分开。意识到死亡便是召唤了焦虑，“存在于是以意识为中介向自己发出了召唤”，这正是痛苦的声音，它恳请存在“从那无名的‘它们’中回归”。对他来说，人必须保持警觉，不到圆满结束不能睡去。他立于这个荒谬的世界中，指出它生命短暂的特性，在废墟中搜寻自己的路。

雅斯贝尔斯对任何本体论都感到绝望，因为他断言，我们已失去了“天真”。他明白我们没有办法超越显见的死亡游戏，他明白思想的终点就是失败。他在历史所揭示的精神冒险上徘徊，并且毫不怜悯地揭露每个体系中的缺陷，揭露那包罗万象的幻觉，揭露那什么也不加掩藏的说教。在这个遭受毁坏的世界，知识的不可能性已得到证实，永远的虚无似乎是唯一的现实，无法补救的绝望似乎是唯一的立场，而雅斯贝尔斯企图在其中找到指向天机的“阿里阿德涅之线”[22]。

就舍斯托夫而言，他的全部作品都异常枯燥，向着同样的真理不懈努力。他不辞劳苦地论证，最严密的体系、最普遍的理性主义最终总是在人类思想的非理性上栽跟头。他没有放过任何一个贬低理性的讽刺性事实或荒唐可笑的矛盾。无论是在心理范围还是思想范围，让他感兴趣的只有一件事，那就是反抗。通过陀思妥耶夫斯基[23]关于有罪之人的体验，通过尼采精神险象环生的奇遇，通过哈姆雷特的诅咒或某个易卜生的恶毒贵族，舍斯托夫追踪、阐明，并且放大了人类对无可救药的反抗。他拒绝赋予理性以节期，只有在这黯然无色的荒漠中才带着某种决心开始了他的行程，在这荒漠里所有确定性都幻化成石头。

在所有人中，与荒谬联系最紧密的大概要数克尔恺郭尔了。至少在他活着的一部分时间内，他不仅发现了荒谬，而且体验了荒谬。“最难对付的沉默不是缄口不言而是大谈特谈”，他从一开始就确信，没有真理是绝对的，或者没有真理能使一个本身就没有可能性的存在变得让人满意。他是思智领域的唐璜[24]，拥有众多笔名与矛盾，写过《两个启发性谈话》和《诱惑者的日记》，后者是悲观的唯灵主义的教科书。他拒绝接受慰藉、道德规范、可靠的准则，至于他心里能感觉到的那根芒刺，则小心翼翼地不去减轻刺痛，反而去唤醒它，像饱经沧桑的人一样感到绝望中的快乐并甘之如饴。在这快乐中，他一点一点地建立起被魔鬼附身之人的范畴——清醒、拒绝、假装。那张面孔温柔地冷笑着，那些优雅的舞蹈旋转动作伴随着从心底发出的呐喊，这些都是与难以理解的现实相搏斗的荒谬精神。而给克尔恺郭尔带来他所钟爱的丑闻的精神历险，同样开始于一种被剥夺了背景且跌至无逻辑的初始状态的混乱经历。

另一个方面，也就是在关于方法的问题上，胡塞尔[25]和现象学家们还原了世界的多样性，否定了理性至高无上的权力，由此精神宇宙丰富得不可估量。玫瑰花瓣、里程碑或人的手臂，同爱情、欲望或万有引力定律一样重要。思想不再追求统一，或者使外观在一种主法则的伪装下变得为人所熟悉。思考就是重新开始学习发现，学习聚精会神，学习关注意识；就是运用普鲁斯特[26]的方法，把每一种想法、每一种形象都变成一种特殊时刻。而为思想正名的是其极度清醒的意识。尽管胡塞尔前进的方式比克尔恺郭尔或舍斯托夫更积极，但在一开始，这种方式却否定理性的经典方法，消灭了希望，使直觉与心理感知到一种现象的激增，这种财富有种非人性的成分在里面。这些道路可能通往所有科学，也可能到达不了任何科学。这就等于说，在这种情况下，方法比结果更为重要。有关系的只是“一种理解的态度”，而不是一种慰藉。我再重复一遍：至少，开始时是这样。

我们怎能感觉不到这些思想的基本联系呢？怎能没发现他们处在一种特殊的痛苦时刻，此时没有希望的任何位置呢？我想听到一切都解释清楚，要么就什么都别解释。而理性即使听到内心的这一呼唤，也无能为力。被这种压迫唤醒的思想寻找着，却除了矛盾与荒唐念头之外一无所获，我不能理解的便是那荒唐念头。世界上尽是这种不理性的人。对于这世界的意义我丝毫不理解，而它本身就是非理性的。如果有人哪怕只说一次：“这是显而易见的”，就什么都省了。可是这些人争先恐后地宣称，什么都不清楚，一切都处在混乱之中，所有人都只保留了自己的洞察力，都只对包围自己的墙有着确切的认识。

所有这些体验都彼此协调，相互肯定。当思想到达自己的极限时，就必须作出判断，并得出结论，这时自杀与答案便出现了。但是我想颠倒一下查询的顺序，从思智的历险开始，然后回到日常活动中。这些忆起的体验都来自我们那不可遗忘的荒漠，至少有必要知道他们走了多远。人们努力至此，便和非理性正面交锋了，内心感到对幸福的期待和对理性的渴望。荒谬就产自人的需求与世界不合理的沉默之间的对抗，这一点不能遗忘，必须坚持下去，因为生活的整体结果便依赖于此。非理性因素、人的怀旧情绪，以及二者交汇产生的荒谬——这出戏剧的三个角色，必须以一种存在能达到的逻辑性收尾。

哲学性自杀

尽管如此，荒谬的感觉，不同于荒谬的概念。前者为后者奠定基础，仅此而已。荒谬的感觉并不限于这一概念，除了它对宇宙作判断的短暂时刻，而随后它有可能更进一步地发展。荒谬的情感是有生命的，换句话说，它要么死去，要么比以前声势更大。对于我们已汇集起来的主题而言，也是如此。但话又说回来了，我感兴趣的不是那些言论或者思想（对它们的批评需要换个形式和场合），而是发现它们结论的共同点。或许思想间如此巨大的差异前所未有，但我们将那些精神风景——思想的旅程——看作是同一的。同样，尽管知识领域不同，终止其旅行计划的呼唤却有着同样的振荡频率。显然，我们所回忆的这些思想具有共同的立场。说这种立场是致命的，差不多就是玩弄辞藻。在那样一种沉闷的天空下生活，人们被迫留下，要么就得逃离。重要的是弄清楚人们如何逃离，或者为何要留下。我就是这样确定自杀问题，以及对存在哲学结论的潜在兴趣的。

但首先我想从直达路径中绕出来。至此，我们已将荒谬与外界隔离。然而，人们还是可以对这一概念的清晰度产生疑问，并且通过直接分析发现其意义，以及它所包含的后果。

假如我指控一个清白之人犯了一项滔天大罪，假如我说一个品德高尚之人垂涎自己的姐妹，他会回答说这太荒谬了。他生气，是有些可笑，但也有其根本原因。那个有道德的人这样回答，说明我归到他身上的行为与他做人的原则之间存在着明确的对立。“这太荒谬了”，意思是说“这是不可能的”，但同样是说“这是有矛盾的”。假如我看到一个人仅仅手握一柄剑进攻一伙荷枪实弹的队伍，我会认为他的行为是荒谬的。然而得出这种结论只是因为，他的意图与他要面对的现实两者不相称，因为我注意到，他的实力与他要达到的目的之间存在矛盾。同样，当我们将一项裁定与另一项明显符合事实的裁定相对照时，会发现该判决很荒谬。类似的还有，取得一种荒谬的论证，要将这种推理的结果与人们想要建立的合乎逻辑的现实加以比校。在所有这些例子中，从最简单的到最复杂的，荒谬的程度与对比的双方之间的差距有直接关系。有荒谬的婚姻、荒谬的挑战、荒谬的怨恨、荒谬的沉默，荒谬的战争，甚至是荒谬的和平协定。每一种荒谬都源自一种比较。因而我可以理直气壮地说，荒谬的感情并非产生于对一个事实或一个想法单纯的仔细检查，而是源自一个赤裸裸的事实与一种确定的现实之间的对比，或是一种行为与超越行为的世界之间的对比。荒谬从根本上讲是一种分离，它不属于相比较的任何一方，而是产生于双方交锋时。

因此，针对这种特殊情况，从思维的角度看，我可以说荒谬不在于人（如果这样一种比喻有意义的话），也不在于这个世界，而在于二者的同时呈现。现在来看，荒谬是联结它们的唯一纽带。假如我只想谈论事实，我就能知道人们想要什么，这个世界能为他们提供什么，现在我可以说我还知道什么将他们联结在一起。我不必挖掘得再深一点，对于一个探索者来说一种确定性就足够了，他只须从这种确定性中得出所有的结果。

最直接的结果也是一种方法规则。用这种方法揭露的怪诞的三位一体论当然不会是一种惊人发现，但它和体验的数据却是相似的，因为它极其简单，又极其复杂。从这一方面来说，它的首要区别特征就是不可分性。毁掉其中一部分，就毁掉了整体。人的思想之外再无荒谬，于是和所有其他事物一样，荒谬止于死亡。可是世界之外也不再有荒谬。正是在这样一种初级标准下，我判断，荒谬的概念必不可少，并认为它可以作为我所发现的第一个真理。上文提及的方法规则在这里出现了。如果我判断某事是真的，我就必须保护它。如果我试图解决某个问题，那种解决办法至少不能让问题中的某些成分消失。对我而言，孤立的唯一根据就是荒谬。在我的探询中，首要的、唯一的条件是保留那摧毁我的东西，进而尊重其中我认为必不可少的东西。我已将之定义为一种反抗，一种不止的斗争。

这种荒谬的逻辑贯穿始终，我必须承认这一斗争意味着希望的完全缺失（与绝望无关），一种不断的剔除（不可与放弃相混淆）和一种有意识的不满（须与不成熟的躁动相区别）。任何破坏、去除、操纵这些要求的东西（首先是消除分离的协调），都会推翻荒谬，并且使人们随后可能会提出的态度失去价值。荒谬只有在不被人们认可的时候才有意义。

有一个完全合乎道德规范的显见事实，那就是，人总会成为自己所求真理的猎物。他一旦承认了真理，就无法从这些真理中抽身而出，就必须付出代价。意识到这种荒谬的人会永远为之束缚，全无希望并且意识到这一点的人不再属于未来，这是理所应当的。同样理所应当的是，他会努力逃脱这个亲手创造的宇宙。上述一切就是因为这一悖论才有意义。有些人从批评理性主义入手，承认了这种产生荒谬的环境。从这一点上看，对他们详述其结果的方法进行仔细检查，是再有益不过的了。

仅从存在哲学的角度看，我发现这类哲学无一例外都提到了逃遁。在一个仅限于人的密闭的宇宙，它们从理性废墟上的荒谬出发，通过不同寻常的推理，将击溃自己的东西神圣化，并且寻找理由对使自己穷困的事物产生希望。这种被迫的希望对他们来说就是一种宗教信仰，值得引起关注。

这里我只以舍斯托夫和克尔凯郭尔青睐的几个主题为例作个分析。雅斯贝尔斯则会以讽刺画的形式，为我们提供一个典型例子来表现这种立场，其他问题将随之变得更加清楚。而后，他无力实现超验之物，无法探察经验的深度，感知到这个被失败搅乱的世界。他是否会前进，或至少从这次失败中总结出什么呢？他没有得出什么新的东西。在体验中，除了承认自己无能为力之外，他一无所获，也不知道从何处推论出什么让人满意的原理，但是正如他自己所说，他突然就不加证实地一下子肯定了超验之物、经验的本质，以及生活的超常意义。于是他写道：“失败在任何可能的解释和说明之外揭露的不是超验之物的缺失，而是超验之物的存在，难道不是这样吗？”这种存在由于人们的盲目自信，突然就解释了一切，他将这种存在定义为“普通与特殊不可思议的联合”。于是荒谬成了神（从本词最广义的层面看），而这种理解上的无能成了阐明一切的存在。无法对这种推理进行有逻辑的准备，我可以把这叫作一种跨跃。而我们可以有悖常理地理解雅斯贝尔斯的主张，以及他为使超验之物的体验变得不可能而投入的无限耐心。因为这种近似越短暂，这种定义越空洞，这超验之物对他来说便越真实；因为他在肯定超验之物上投入的热情，和其解释能力与这个世界及经验的不合理性之间的差距，直接相关。因而似乎雅斯贝尔斯将理性的先入之见摧毁得越是彻底，他对这个世界的解释就越是激进。这位鼓吹耻辱思想的使徒会在受尽凌辱之后发现如何深入地实现重生。

玄妙的思想让我们熟悉这种手段，它们与所有思想立场一样合情合理。此刻我表现得好像是在认真对待某个问题。我没有事先判断这种立场的总体价值或其教育意义，我只想考虑它能否满足我自己设立的条件，是否值得我为之论战。某评论人引用了舍斯托夫的一段话，很有意思：“真正的解决办法只有一个，”他说，“正是出现在人们的判断找不到解决方案之时。否则，我们要上帝有什么用呢？我们求助于上帝只是为了实现不可能，至于可能之事，人就可以办到了。”如果有一种舍斯托夫哲学，我可以说它完全是用这种方式总结出来的。因为在其饱含激情的分析最后，舍斯托夫发现了所有存在根本的荒谬性。他没有说“这是荒谬的”，而是说“这是上帝：我们必须依赖他，即使他不符合我们任何理性的范畴。”为了使他的思想不致引起混乱，这位俄国哲学家甚至暗示道，这个上帝或许仇恨满腹，惹人憎恶，难以捉摸，还矛盾丛生；但他的面孔越是丑陋，他就越坚持自己的权力。他的伟大之处正是他的前后不一，他的非人性便是证明。人们一定要跃入上帝怀中，用这一跃把自己从理性的幻影中解放出来。因而，对于舍斯托夫来说，接受荒谬与荒谬本身是同时进行的。意识到荒谬就相当于接受了荒谬，其思想所作的所有逻辑上的努力就是为了引出荒谬，这样荒谬中包含的巨大希望便会同时喷薄而出。我重申一次，这种立场是合情合理的，但我还是坚持只考虑一个问题及其所有后果。我不必检验一种思想的情感，或是一种信仰行为的情感，我有一辈子的时间去这么做。我知道舍斯托夫的立场惹怒了理性主义者，但我还是觉得正确的是舍斯托夫，而非理性主义者。我只想知道舍斯托夫是否还忠实于荒谬的信条。

如今，倘若承认荒谬的反面是希望，则可见舍斯托夫的存在思想是以荒谬为前提的，但只是为了消除它才去证明它。思想的这种奸计是巫师玩的情感小把戏。当舍斯托夫在别处又把他的荒谬与被普遍接受的道德和理性相对立时，他把这种荒谬叫作真理与救赎。因此从根本上说，荒谬这一定义包含着舍斯托夫对它的一种认可。倘若承认，这一概念的所有能量都在于它与我们的低级希望相对抗的方式上；倘若意识到，要保持荒谬就不能得到认可，那么显然，为了达到令人满意又难以置信的永恒，荒谬失掉了自己的本真、自己的人性和相对性特征。如果有一种荒谬，那么它必在人的宇宙中。这一概念从把自己转化为永远的跳板那一刻起，就和人的清醒不再有关联了。荒谬不再是人们无须认同便能确定的显见之物，于是就避免了斗争。人们将荒谬合并为一，并且在这种情况下，消除了荒谬必不可少的特性——对立、撕裂、分离。这一跃便是逃遁。舍斯托夫喜欢引用哈姆雷特的话“时间脱节了”，他是带着一种狂野的希望写下这句话的，这种希望似乎为他所独有，因为哈姆雷特说这句话，或是莎士比亚写这句话时，都没有那种感觉。对这种不合理性的沉醉，以及天生的狂热，使一个清醒的头脑远离荒谬。对于舍斯托夫来说，理性是无用的，但理性之外别有他物；对于一个荒谬的头脑来说，理性也是无用的，而且理性之外什么也没有。

这一跃至少可以在荒谬的本质问题上给我们多一些启发。我们知道荒谬只有在平衡中才有价值，它首先产生于比较过程中，而非被比较的各项。可舍斯托夫恰恰是把所有的重点都放在了被比较的一项上，破坏了平衡。只有在我们可以理解并解释诸多事情时，我们对理解的渴望、对绝对性的怀恋才能得到解释。绝对否定理性是无益的，理性在自己的秩序中是有效的。我们正是想通过人们的经验澄清一切，由此我们想要让所有事情经受考验，假如做不到这一点，假如在这种情况下产生了荒谬，那么它正产生于有效而有限的理性与不断复苏的非理性交会的时刻。当舍斯托夫抨击黑格尔的一条主张，诸如“太阳系遵循永恒的规律运转，而这些规律就是太阳系的理性”的时候，当他狂热地冲击斯宾诺莎[27]的理性主义的时候，他恰恰肯定了一切理性的虚伪。由这个结论出发，他便通过一个不合情理的自然反转，肯定了非理性的优先地位。[28]但这种转变并不明显。这里会插入限度和层面的概念。自然法则可能会在某个限度内有效，超过这一限度它们就会违背自我，产生荒谬。否则，它们会在描述层面上使自己合乎情理，而在解释层面上并不因此成真。在这里，为达到非理性，所有一切都被牺牲，而对明晰性的要求被消除后，荒谬便携对比中的一方消失了。同时，荒谬之人没有经历这种保持平衡的过程。他承认斗争与非理性，并未绝对轻视理性。这样一来，他又在一瞥之间欣然接受了所有经历的细节，而不会在不知情的情况下轻易跨越。他只知道，在那样的敏锐的意识中已无希望的容身之所。

在里奥·舍斯托夫的思想中所能感知到的问题，或许在克尔凯郭尔的思想中更为突出。的确，要清楚概括这一难以捉摸之作家的言论，并非易事，但是，尽管其著作中存在明显的对立，排除种种化名、伎俩和玩笑，我们似乎可以从整部作品中预感到（同时也担忧）一种真理从其最后几部作品中最终迸发出来：克尔凯郭尔同样也纵身一跃。他的童年受到基督教的惊吓，最终他回到了这种宗教最严酷的一面。对他来说，矛盾与悖论也成了宗教标准。因而导致人们对生活的意义与深度感到绝望的东西，如今又赋予了生命以真实性与清晰性。基督教引起了公愤，克尔凯郭尔所需要的其实就是依格那丢·罗耀拉[29]所要求的第三牺牲，这一牺牲最讨上帝的欢心：“智力的牺牲”。[30]这一“跃”产生了异乎寻常的效果，但不应再让我们大吃一惊了。他在荒谬中确立了另一个世界的标准，但那只是这个世界的经验的残羹冷炙。“从失败中，”克尔凯郭尔说，“信徒找到了自己的胜利。”

我不必去考虑这种立场与什么鼓动人心的说教有关，我只须考虑荒谬的浩大声势以及它自己的特性能否证明自己的合理性。我明白，它做不到这一点。人们若再思索一下荒谬的内容，就更能理解启发克尔凯郭尔的那种方法了。在世界的非理性与荒谬反叛的怀旧情感之间，他没有保持住平衡，他也没有尊重构成（恰当地说是）荒谬感情的关联。当他明确自己无法从非理性中逃脱时，他至少想把自己从那令人绝望的怀旧情感中解救出来，这种情感对于他来说贫瘠而缺乏深意。可是如果在这一点上他的判断是对的，他不可能去否定自己。如果他用一种疯狂的信仰代替了对反抗的呼吁，他马上就会对曾启发自己的荒谬视而不见，而将他从此拥有的唯一确定性奉若神明，也就是非理性。加里亚尼神父[31]对德毕内夫人[32]说过：重要的并不是被治愈，而是与小病共存。克尔凯郭尔想要被治愈，那是他狂热的愿望，在他的日记中这种愿望随处可见。他在思智上所作的全部努力就是逃离人类命运的矛盾。他在谈到自己时会断断续续地意识到它的虚伪，于是作出更加绝望的努力，好像对上帝的恐惧或虔诚都不能让他回复平静。因此，他用一个不自然的托词给了非理性荒谬的外表，给了上帝荒谬的特性：不公平、不合逻辑、不可理解。唯有他的智慧试图扼杀人心灵深处的欲求。既然没有任何东西得到证明，那么一切都可以得到证明。

事实上，克尔凯郭尔本人向我们展示了走过的路。这里我不想多谈什么。我们在他的著作中，怎能无视为平衡荒谬中的损伤而对灵魂所作的几乎故意的损伤呢？这也是《日记》的主旨。“我所缺少的是动物性，这动物性同样是人类命运的一部分……那么请给我一个身体。”他进而说：“哦！特别是在我青春萌动的时代，为了成为一个人，我什么代价没付出啊，即使只有六个月的时间……说到底，我欠缺的就是一个身体及存在的各种肉体条件。”还是这个人，在另一部著作里却发出了对希望的伟大呼喊，这希望经历过那么多个世纪，鼓舞了那么多的心灵（除了那荒谬之人的心灵）。“但是对基督徒而言，死亡绝对不是一切的终结，它包含的希望远远多于生活所赋予我们的，即使那生活充满健康活力。”由耻辱而来的和解仍旧是和解。可见，或许这允许人们从死亡——希望的反面——中获取希望。即使人们出于同情而倾向于这种立场，还是必须指出，过度是什么也证明不了的。正如人们所言，这个超过了人们的尺度；因此它必须是超人的。然而这种“因此”是多余的，这里没有合乎逻辑的确定性，也没有试验的可能性。我只能说，事实上，这个超过了我的尺度。如果我从中找不到一个否定性的推论，至少我不想从这不可思议中建立任何东西。我想知道，凭借我所知道的能否生活，以及能否仅凭它生活。人们又告诉我，思智在这里必须牺牲掉自己的骄傲，理性必须低下高贵的头颅。可是如果我意识到了理性的限度，我不会因此否定它，我已经意识到它的相对力量。我只想保持在这条中间道路上，思智在这里可以保持清晰。如果这就是它的骄傲，我没发现足够的理由去抛弃它。比如，再没有比克尔凯郭尔的观点更深刻的了，在他看来，绝望不是一个事实而是一种状态：罪孽的状态。因为罪孽远离上帝，而荒谬作为有意识之人的超自然状态，并不通往上帝。[33]或许为使这一概念更清楚，我可以斗胆使用这种惊世骇俗的说法：荒谬就是没有上帝的罪孽。

这是一个在荒谬状态下生活的问题。我知道它产生的基础，这种思想与这个世界相互拉扯，却无法彼此包容。我想知道这种生活状态的规则，而所提供给我的答案漏掉了它的基础，否定了这种痛苦的对立中之一方，想要让我放弃。我又问，我所发现的自我状态都包含什么；我知道的是，它包含费解与无知；于是我确定，这种无知可解释一切，这种黑暗是我的光明。可是这样的回答不能满足我的目的，那种让人心潮澎湃的抒情无法对我掩藏那种悖论。因此，人们必须要走开。克尔凯郭尔会大声疾呼：“假如人们没有了永恒的意识，假如在一切事物的根源，只有一种野蛮而火热的力量主宰万物，在那黑暗激情的风暴中生发出或巨大或微小的东西，假如那无物可填充的无底的虚无正是万物之基，那么生活除了绝望还会是什么样呢？”这声呼喊不会阻止荒谬的人，寻找真实的东西不同于寻找期望的东西。如果为避免这一让人头疼的问题：“生活会是什么样？”，人们就得像驴子一样，从那虚幻的玫瑰中汲取营养，那么荒谬的思想更愿意接受无畏的克尔凯郭尔的回答——“绝望”，而不是屈从于谎言。万事考虑周全，一个坚定的灵魂什么都能应付得来。

在此我擅自把这种存在主义立场叫作哲学性自杀，但这并没有包含任何评论在里面，只是方便指出一种思想进行自我否定，并通过这种否定超越自我。对于存在主义者而言，否定是他们的上帝。确切地说，这一神明只有通过否定人的理性才得以维持，[34]但是同自杀一样，神明也因人而异。跨跃的方式有很多，重要的是要跨跃。那些作为弥补的否定，那些终极矛盾（否定尚未跃过的障碍），可能会从某种宗教启发中弹跳出来，正如从理性的秩序中弹出一样（这是此推理针对的悖论）。它们一直自以为永恒，也只有在永恒中他们才会跨跃。

必须重申，本书中的推理完全不理会我们这个开明时代传播最为广泛的精神态度：以一切皆理性的原则为基础，旨在解释这个世界。当我们接受世界必然是清晰的这一观点后，自然要给出一个关于世界的清晰观点。这甚至也是合情合理的，却和我们这里进行的推理无关。事实上，我们的目的在于阐明源于世界缺乏意义这种哲学的思想，以及最后从中发现一种意义与深度时所采取的步骤。其中最动人的步骤从本质上说是具有宗教意义的；在非理性的主题上变得更加明显，但最自相矛盾又最富有意义的肯定是将合理的理性归于这个原以为全无指导原则的世界。对于怀旧精神的这种新成就，如果人们不能给出一种观点的话，那无论如何也不可能得到与我们相关的结果。

我将只检验一下由胡塞尔和现象学家们带动的潮流——“意向”主题，前面也已提到过。起初，胡塞尔的方法否定理性的经典步骤。我再重复一遍，思考不是产生一致，或是使外表在一个大原则的伪装下变得为人熟知。思考是重新学习如何去看，操控人的意识，从每种形象中发现一种特殊位置。换句话说，现象学拒绝解释这个世界，它只想描述真实的经验。其早期论断中就有这种说法，没有真实只有真理，这肯定了荒谬的思想。从夜晚的微风，到我肩上的手臂，一切都有它的真实。意识关注它，并借此加以阐明。意识并没有形成其理解的对象，它只是找到重点，这是一种关注行为。借用柏格森[35]派的形象，它就像是一台突然聚焦到一个图像上的投影仪。不同之处在于，这里没有情节，只有一连串不连贯的图解。在那奇幻的灯下，所有画面都受到特别待遇。意识在经验中将其关注的对象定格，运用非凡的技艺将它们分离出来。自此，它们不再接受任何评价。这就是刻画意识的“意向”，但这个词语并不意味着最终定义，只限于“方向”的意义层面：它唯一的表面意义就是方向上的。

初看起来，在这种情况下，似乎没有什么违背荒谬的精神。这种只描述不解释的思想表面看上去很低调，这种意向性的学科自相矛盾地导致经验不断丰富，促使世界在冗长中重生，这些都是荒谬的步骤，至少初看起来如此。就思想方法而言，不论是在这种情况下还是其他情况下，它总会表现出两个方面：一个是心理学方面，另一个是形而上学方面。[36]因此它们包含两种真理。如果意向的主题只阐释一种心理学立场，致使现实没有得到解释反而被消耗殆尽，那么实际上什么也没有从荒谬精神中分离出来。它旨在列举自己无法超越的东西，只肯定在没有任何统一原则的情况下，思想仍然可以在描述并理解经验的各个方面时得到乐趣。由此，包含其中的真理从本质上说是心理学上的，它只是证实了现实可以提供的“兴趣”。这种方法唤醒了一个沉睡的世界，使其形象生动地浮现于脑海。如果试图拓展，为那个真理概念奠定一个合理性的基础，如果声称可以用这种方式发现知识的各种客体的“本质”，那么就恢复了经验的深度。对于一个荒谬的头脑来说，这是难以置信的。如今，正是这种在谦逊和显现在意向态度中的确信之间的摇摆，以及这种现象学思想的闪光，能最好地阐释荒谬的推理。

胡塞尔同样提到了由意向揭露的“超时间本质”，听起来像柏拉图。并非所有事物都能用一物来解释而必须用万物来解释，我觉得没什么不同。诚然，这些想法或本质要素都是意识在每种描述最后“实现”的，不会被作为完美的模范。不过可以确信，它们都直接出现在认识的每种依据中。单一的观点不再能解释一切，而是无数的本质要素为无数对象赋予一个意义。这个世界停顿了，但是也被点亮了。柏拉图现实主义变得直观起来，但它仍旧是现实主义。克尔凯郭尔被自己的上帝吞没；巴门尼德[37]使思想深陷于“同一”中。而思想把自己掷入一种抽象的多神论中，这还不够：幻觉与虚构同样属于“超时间本质”。在观念的新世界中，光怪陆离的物种与大都会人这一更谦逊的物种协调合作。

有一种纯心理学的观点认为：世界的各个方面都是特殊的，这种观点在一个荒谬之人看来真实而令人不快。说任何事都是特殊的就等于说任何事都是平等的，但是这一真理在形而上学方面影响极为深远，以致荒谬之人通过一个基本反应便感觉和柏拉图更接近了。实际上他被告知，每种形象都有一个平等的本质。在这个没有等级的理想世界，正式部队只由将军组成。诚然，至高无上被消除了，但思想中的突然转变让一种有缺陷的内在性回归到这个世界中，这种内在性恢复了这个宇宙的深度。

我是否该担心把这个被其创造者谨慎使用的主题扯得太远了呢？我只读过胡塞尔的这些观点：“就其本身而言，真实的东西是绝对真实的；真理有一个，与自身一致，不管认识真理的是谁，是人、魔鬼、天使，还是神。”这话表面来看自相矛盾，却有严密的逻辑性，但前提是要接受他先前的观点。理性胜利了，并且用这种声音吹响号角，我不可否认。其观点在这个荒谬的世界又有何意呢？天使或是神的认识对我来说都没有意义，神赐的理性准许给我的地位永远都让我难以置信。我从他的观点中也辨认出一种跨跃，尽管是以抽象形式出现的，但对我来说却意味着要忘记我不想忘记的。胡塞尔进一步感叹：“假如一切承受引力的质量都消失了，那么引力规律也不会因此被摧毁，只不过是没有再体现在实际中的可能罢了。”这时我明白，自己面对一种慰藉的形而上学。而如果我想发现思想在何时偏离了清晰之路，只须重读胡塞尔有关精神的相似推理：“倘若我们考虑清楚心理过程的确切规则，它们看上去也会一成不变，如同理论自然科学的基本规则一样。因此即使没有心理过程，它们也是有效的。”即使精神不存在，其诸多规则也会存在！于是我发现，胡塞尔旨在从一种心理学的真理中提出一个合理规则：在否定了人类理性的整合力后，他通过这一权宜之计跃入了永恒的理性。

我也不会对胡塞尔“具体宇宙”的主题感到惊讶。如果跟我说并非所有本质因素都是形式上的，而有些是物质上的，第一种是逻辑对象，第二种是科学对象，那么这只是一个定义问题。我读到，抽象的宇宙自身缺乏一致性，只表示具体宇宙的一部分，然而已得到注意的摇摆容许我阐明混乱的各项。因为这将意味着，我所关注的具体对象——天空、外套上水渍中的反射物——保留了我的兴趣在这世界中分离出的真实的声望。我不否认这一点，但这也意味着这件外套本身就具有普遍性，有自己独特而充分的本质，属于形式世界。我意识到，只是前进的次序被改变了，这个世界已不再能反射到更高层次的宇宙中，但形式的天堂在地球上的诸多形象中都有自己的倒影。这对我而言没什么改变。在此我没有形成对人类状态的意义——这一具体性——的鉴赏力，但我发现了一种不受束缚的唯理智论，可以将具体本身普遍化。

那种明显的悖论通过受辱的理性和胜利的理性这两条截然相反的道路，导致思想自我否定，惊异于这一悖论是徒劳无获的。从胡塞尔抽象的神到克尔凯郭尔光辉耀眼的神，两者相距并不遥远。理性与非理性宣传的是同一种东西。事实上用什么方法关系不大，只要有实现的愿望就足够了。抽象哲学家与宗教哲学家都从同样的无序出发，并在相同的焦虑中互相支持，然而解释是必要的，这里怀旧比知识更强。这个时代的思想立刻成为了受世界无意义论影响最深的哲学之一，也是结论分歧最多的哲学之一，这是很有意义的。它在现实的极端理性化与非理性化之间不停摇摆，前者倾向于将这种思想分化成诸多标准的理性，后者则倾向于神化这种思想，但这种分裂只是表面上的。这是一个妥协问题，在两种情况下，跨跃便足够了。认为理性概念是单向概念的想法一直都是错的。说实话，不管它对理想要求多么严格，这一概念与其他概念一样是不稳定的。理性有一种人性的面貌，但它也能被神化。普罗提诺[38]是第一个将之与永恒的思想态度相调和的人，自他以后，理性便学会了背离最受青睐的原则（即矛盾），以将相关要素中神奇的那一个、最奇特的那一个并入理性。[39]这是思想的一个工具，并非思想本身。最重要的是，一个人的思想就是他对旧事的怀恋。

正如理性可以抚慰普罗提诺的哀伤一样，它也在永恒熟悉的背景中找到了平息当代痛苦的方法。荒谬的头脑就没这么走运了，对于它来说，世界既没有那么合理，也没有那么不合理。它是不理性的，仅此而已。在胡塞尔那里，最终理性一点限度也没有了。相反，荒谬设立了自己的限制，因为它无力平息自己的痛苦。克尔凯郭尔从另一角度坚称，要否定那种痛苦，一种限度就够了。但荒谬并未走这么远，对荒谬而言，这一限制只是在理性的理想中发挥作用。如存在学家构想的那样，非理性的主题是，理性变得混乱，通过否定自身而逃遁。荒谬是注意到自身限制的清醒的理性。

只有在这条困径的尽头，荒谬之人才认出自己真正的动机。在将自己内心的极度渴望与摆在自己面前的事实相对比时，它突然感到自己想要逃离。在胡塞尔的宇宙中，世界变得清晰起来，人们内心对熟悉的渴望变得毫无用处。在克尔凯郭尔的启示中，那种对清晰性的渴望必须被放弃才能得到满足。罪孽与其说是知道（如果是这样，那么每个人都是无辜的），不如说是想知道。这的确是唯一的罪孽，荒谬之人从中感到，自己的罪恶与清白都来自它。他有一种解决办法可选，这种办法让过去所有的矛盾都变成了论战的游戏而已。荒谬之人并不是这样体验矛盾的，应该保留矛盾的真实性，这真实性在于不被满足。他不想布道。

我的推论要忠实于激发起这种推论的明晰性。这种明晰性是荒谬的，它是拥有渴望的头脑与带来失望的世界之间的分离，是我对统一性的怀恋，是这个支离破碎的宇宙，是将宇宙碎片联结在一起的矛盾。克尔凯郭尔抑制着我的怀旧情绪，胡塞尔将这个宇宙聚合在一起。这并非我的期待。问题是，要带着这些错乱生活与思考，要明白是接受还是拒绝。掩盖证据，或是通过否认等式一侧的因素来抑制荒谬，是没有问题的。有必要知道人们能否与之共存，或者另一方面，逻辑是否命令人们为之放弃生命。我感兴趣的是普通的自杀，而不是哲学性自杀。我只是想去除它的情感内容，弄清楚它的逻辑与整体性。其他任何立场都意味着荒谬想法的欺骗，以及思想在自己所揭露的东西面前的回避。胡塞尔宣称要服从欲求，以避免“在某种熟知而适宜的存在条件下生活与思考的积习”，然而最后的一跃又让他恢复了永久性与舒适性。这一跃并不是克尔凯郭尔意想中的极端危险，相反，危险存在于跨跃之前的微妙瞬间。能够停留在那让人晕眩的风口浪尖——这就是完整性，其余都是借口。我还知道，无助激发起的协调从来没有像克尔凯郭尔的那样出众，但如果说无助在历史那不动声色的风景中占有一席之地的话，那么它在那种需求已为人所知的推理中是没有位置的。

荒谬的自由

主要部分已论述完毕，但还有几件事我要坚持，无法割舍，其中主要有我所知道之事、我无法否认之事、我无法拒绝之事及确切之事。对于我身上依赖于模糊往事的那一部分，除了那种对统一性的欲求、对解决问题的渴望、对清晰性和内聚力的需要之外，我可以全盘否定。对于周遭冒犯我或愉悦我的东西，除了那种混乱、那种当权机会、那种源自无序状态的神授的自由之外，我可以一一加以驳斥。我不知道这世界是否有一种超越自身的意义，但我知道我不了解那种意义，让我现在就去了解它也不可能。一种存在于我的环境之外的意义，于我意义何在？我只能理解人类的语言。我所理解的是我触摸得到的、与我相对抗的东西。而我也知道这两种确定性——我对绝对性和统一性的欲望，以及把世界还原为一种合理而理性原则的不可能性，无法得到调和。还有什么真理我可以坦诚承认而不必撒谎，不需要引入一个我所欠缺的希望，而这种真理又在我生存条件的限度内毫无意义呢？

假如我是林中之木，兽中之猫，那么这种生活还会有某种意义，确切地说那种问题就不会出现，因为我将是属于这个世界的。我应该就是这个世界，这个我用自己的全部意识和对熟悉性的全部坚持而反对的世界。正是这一可笑的理性让我与世间万物为敌，我无法将之一笔勾销，我也必须因此坚守自己相信的真理。对我来说显而易见的事情，即使于我不利，我也必须坚持。而除了对这一理性的意识，还有什么会是这种冲突的基础，以及这世界与我的思想相分离的基础呢？因此，如果我想坚持这一理性，我就可以通过一种始终如一的意识永远保持清醒与警觉。这就是此刻我必须要记住的。此刻，那么明显而又那么难以赢得的荒谬，又回到了人的生活中，在那里找到了家的感觉。此刻，精神也可以远离清醒的努力，这条路贫瘠而干皱。这条路如今出现在日常生活中。它遭遇到不具名的无人称代词的世界，但自此人们带着反抗与清醒走进了这个世界。人们已经忘记了如何去应付，如今的地狱是其最后的王国。一切问题又都变得尖锐起来，抽象的明晰性在形式与色彩的诗意面前撤退了。精神冲突变得形象化，又归于人心卑贱而华丽的庇护。尽管它们都未安置下来，但形象都得到了改观。有谁打算结束生命，或是一跃而逃，或是重建一座规模等身的思想与形式大厦？相反，又有谁想在让人惊心动魄、心力交瘁的荒谬之赌上下一注呢？在此问题上让我们来个最后一搏，得出我们的所有结论。届时身体、爱慕、创造、行动、人的高尚在这个疯狂的世界上将各归各位。最终人们会在这里找到供养其伟大性的荒谬之酒与冷漠之粮。

我们再次强调方法吧：这是一个坚持的问题。在荒谬之人的路上，某个时候他会受到引诱。即使是没有神存在的历史也不乏宗教或先知。若被要求跨跃，他只能回应说自己没有完全理解，说这不甚清楚。实际上，除了自己完全理解的，他不想做任何事情。他确定这是傲慢产生的罪孽，但他不理解罪孽的概念；他也确信，地狱也许就在眼前，但没有足够的想象力去设想那个奇怪的未来；还有，他不朽的声明正在消失，但考虑这些对他来说却是徒劳。也有人试图使他承认自己的罪过，但他觉得自己是无辜的。事实上，他能感觉到的只有那给予自己一切的不可救药的清白。因此，他对自己的要求就是只带着自己知道的生活，适应确定之物，拒绝任何不确定之物。他被告知没有东西是确定的，但至少这句话是确定的。而他所关心的是这一点：他想确定是否可能毫无诉求地生活。

现在，我可以引出自杀的概念了。或许你已经预感到会有什么解决办法被提出来。现在这个问题倒过来了。一开始的问题是要发现生活是否一定要有意义才能过好，而如今显然相反，生活没有意义才会过得更好。体验一种经历、一种特定的命运，便是接受全部生活。现在，人们都知道了生活的荒谬，谁也不会体验这样的命运了，除非他的所作所为都是为保持由意识阐明的这一荒谬。他生活在对立之上，而否定对立的其中一方就相当于躲避它，取消有意识的反抗就是逃避问题，于是永恒变革的主题被引入个人体验，生活便是保持荒谬，而保持荒谬首先就要审视荒谬。荒谬与欧律狄刻[40]不同，只有当我们背离它时，它才会消亡。仅有的几个前后一致的立场之一便是反抗，这是人与自己的阴暗面之间的不断对抗，是对不可能得到的透明度的一种坚持，它每一秒都要重新挑战这个世界。正如危险为人们提供了抓住意识的独特时机一样，形而上学的反抗将意识扩展至体验的整个过程。它是不断出现在人们眼中的自我形象，而非什么强烈的愿望，因为它缺少希望。这种反抗必将带来一种不甘溃败的命运，并没有本该伴随一旁的顺从。

由此可以看出荒谬的体验在多大程度上是远离自杀的。人们或许认为反抗之后便是自杀——错了，自杀并非反抗的逻辑后果。情况恰恰相反，因为自杀是以自愿为前提的。自杀，同跨跃一样，是极端的接受。一切都结束了，人便回到了自己的本质性历史中。他的未来，他可怕而又独一无二的未来——他看到了，并飞快地冲向它。自杀用自己的方式解决了荒谬，它将荒谬吞没在同样的死亡中。但我知道，为将荒谬保持下去，就不能解决它。它在意识到死亡的同时，拒绝了死亡，因而便逃脱了自杀。在有罪之人产生最后一个念头时，荒谬是他在自己晕倒的片刻于几码以外看到的鞋带。实际上，自杀的反面是被判了死罪的人。

这一反抗赋予生命以价值。它贯穿于整个生命，使这种生命恢复了昔日的尊严。对于一个眼光不开阔的人而言，没有比与超越自己的现实相搏斗的思智更好的视野了。人的自豪感是无可匹敌的，任何轻蔑对之都无济于事。那种精神自我施加的纪律、无端冒出来的意愿、面对面的对抗都具有某种特殊性。现实的非人性成就了人的尊严，而让这种现实处于困顿状态就等于是让自己处于困顿状态。我于是明白了，为何那些学说向我解释一切的同时也损耗了我的体能。它们将我从生命的重量中解救出来，而从此我就必须独自肩负起这重量。此刻我难以想象，一种怀疑论的形而上学能与一种选择放弃的道德观相结合。

意识与反抗，这些是与放弃相对的否定。人心中一切不屈不挠和充满激情的东西都在用自己的生命驱动着人的意识和反抗。一定不要心甘情愿地去死，自杀是一种否认。荒谬之人只能耗干一切，最后让自己枯竭。荒谬是他的极端紧张状态，他孤军奋战，不断保持着这种状态，因为他知道，他用那种意识以及日复一日的反抗证实了自己唯一的真理，那就是反抗。这是我们得出的第一个结果。

如果我坚持这种预先设定的立场——只在于从一种新发现的概念中得出所有结论（别无他物），那么我就会遇到第二个悖论。为忠实于这种方法，我与形而上学的自由问题毫无干系。我对人是不是自由的这一问题没有兴趣，我体验的只是自己的自由。而关于这一问题，我没有什么笼统观点，只是有一些清晰的领悟。“自由本身”的问题是没有意义的，因为它以一种极其不同的方式与上帝的问题相关联。要知道人是否自由就要知道人能否有一个主人。这一问题独特的荒谬之处就在于，产生自由这一问题的观念同样剥夺了它的所有意义。因为有上帝在，自由问题就得让位于罪恶问题。你知道选项的：或者我们是不自由的，全能的上帝对罪恶负责；或者我们是自由的，我们对罪恶负责，而上帝不是全能的。学术界众技全施，而对于这一尖锐的悖论，既无以补充，又不可削减。

这就是为什么我不能迷失在对这种概念的吹捧和定义中，那种概念让我搞不懂，而且一旦脱离了我自身体验的参考框架它便失去了意义。我不明白，一种更高级的存在会给我一种什么样的自由，我已经没有了等级感。我对自由的概念只停留在囚犯以及国家之中的个体身上，我只知道思想与行动的自由。如果荒谬取消了我所有永久自由的可能性，它在另一方面就恢复并扩大了我的行动自由。这种对希望和未来的剥夺意味着人可以有更多自主权。

在与荒谬相遇之前，芸芸众生活得有目标，他们关心未来，希望得到正当的待遇（至于与何人何物有关则不是问题所在）。人们掂量自己的机会，指望着“某一天”、退休后的生活，或是子孙的事业，仍然觉得自己可以控制生活中的某些事。实际上，即使所有事实都与自由相背，他还是表现得好像自己是自由的，然而荒谬出现之后，所有事情都被搅乱了：那种“我是”的想法、那种似乎一切皆有意义（即使我有时会说什么都没有意义）的行为方式——这一切都被一种可能死亡的荒谬性以其令人眩晕的方式揭露无疑。思考未来，为自己设定目标，有所偏好——所有这些都预先假定了一种自由的信念，即使人们有时确信自己没有感觉到自由。但在那一刻我很清楚，那种更高的自由、那种可单独作为真理基础的存在的自由并不存在。死亡是此时唯一的现实，而死亡之后便是关键时刻。我甚至都无法自由地使自己不朽，只是一个奴隶，最重要的是一个没有永久革命的希望且无法求助于轻蔑的奴隶。而没有了革命与蔑视谁还会继续做奴隶呢？没了永恒的保证，哪种自由可以完整地存在呢？

荒谬之人同时意识到，他一直受制于假定的自由，他生活在这种幻象之上。从某种意义上说，这成了他的束缚。他想象出自己生活的目标，使自己适应于目标的要求，并且成了为自由服务的奴隶。因此，我只能扮演我准备成为的父亲（或工程师、国家领导人、邮局小职员）的身份，我想我可以作这种选择而不是其他选择。当然，这是我无意识的想法，以至于非常肯定。同时，周围人们的想法，还有我的人性环境中的假设（其他人对自由的状态深信不疑，而这种快乐情绪极具传染性），又进一步肯定了我的假设。人不论多么排斥道德或社会假设，他都会多少受其影响，而对于那些极品假设（假设也有好坏之分），人们甚至会改变自己的生活以与之相适应，所以荒谬之人意识到他并非真正自由。说白了，我为自己设立了种种障碍以限制我的生活，以至我有了希望，以至我开始对一种可能为我所独有的真理、一种存在或创造的方式而担忧，以至我安排了自己的生活，并且接受它有意义。我画地为牢，限制了自己的生活我表现得像诸多为我所厌恶的思想与心灵的官僚一般，而他们唯一的罪恶我如今已非常清楚，那就是认真对待人的自由。

荒谬在这一点上启发了我：不存在未来，这也为我内心的自由提供了理由。这里我要作两个对比。首先，神秘主义者在付出自我中找到自由。当他们献身于自己的神，并且接受他的规则时，他们获得了隐秘的自由。他们自愿成为奴隶，于是便重获了一种更深刻的独立性。然而这种自由意味着什么？或许可以说，最重要的是他们自身感觉到自由，尽管不是无拘无束的那种自由。同样，荒谬的人彻底转向死亡（这是最显见的荒谬性）时，感到那凝结在自己身上的强烈关注完全被释放。他享受一种与普遍规则有关的自由。从这一点可以看出，存在哲学的原始主题还保有其全部价值。回归意识，逃避睡眠，这些代表着荒谬自由的初始阶段。但是我们暗指的其实是存在性说教，随之还有基本逃离意识的精神跨跃。同样（下面是我的第二个对比），古时的奴隶不属于自己，但他们知道那种不用对谁负责的自由。[41]而死亡也有一双贵族长老之手，既镇压，也给人自由。

投身于那种无限制的确定性中，并因此感到远离自己的生活，远到足以增强这种确定性，且对此拥有一种广阔的眼界——这需要一种自由的原则。与任何行动上的自由一样，这种新的独立有一种明确的时间限制，而不会开一张永久性的支票，但它替代了自由的种种假象，那些假象均随死亡告终。监狱的大门在某个黎明向有罪之人打开，这种有罪之人的出现是天赐；对一切事物（除了纯粹的生活激情）都表现出不可思议的冷漠——死亡与荒谬明显是唯一的理性自由之准则。这是人心可以经历与体验的。这是另一个结果。荒谬之人于是发现了一个炽热而寒冷、透明而有限的宇宙，这里没有可能性，一切都是已知的，而在这之外不外乎崩塌与虚无。然后他便可以决定是接受这样一个宇宙，还是从中提取自己的力量、对希望的否定，以及一种无慰藉生活的有力证明。

但是在这样一个宇宙生活意味着什么呢？目前来看只意味着对未来的冷漠，耗尽一切现有事物的欲望。对生活意义的信念总会包含一种价值等级、一种选择及我们的偏好。根据我们的定义，相信荒谬则会得出相反的结论，但这是值得检验的。

我的一切兴趣所在就是知道人能否毫无诉求地生活。我不想力所不能及。生活的这一面正向我展开，我能适应吗？面对这一特殊问题，相信荒谬就相当于用体验的数量代替质量。如果我让自己相信生活除了荒谬就没有其他面貌，如果我感到生活的整体平衡取决于自己有意识的反抗与生活挣扎其中的黑暗间的永久对立，如果我承认我的自由若不涉及其有限的命运便毫无意义，那么我必须说，重要的不是活得最好，而是活得最多。至于这是粗俗的或恶心的，优雅的或恶劣的，我都没有义务去担心。在此我们彻底弃价值判断而取事实判断，而我只需从所见中得出结论，不冒任何假设的风险。如果说用这种方式生活是不体面的，那么真正的体面要求我不体面。

活得最多；从最广泛的意义上看，这种规则毫无意义。它需要定义，似乎数量的概念没有得到充分探索这一事实可作为开端，因为它可以解释人们的大部分体验。一个人的行为规则与他的价值等级是毫无意义的，除非他已经积累了大量的、各种各样的经验。如今，现代生活条件让大部分人都有了相同数量的体验，以及由此带来的相同的深刻体验。当然，还必须考虑到个体自发的贡献，其自身的“固有”元素。但是我不能对此作出评判，我重申，此处我的规则就是处理最直接的明晰性。于是我明白了，一种普遍道德规范的个体特征与其说在于其基础原则的理想重要性，不如说在于一种可以衡量的体验标准。把这一点稍微引申一下，希腊人在休闲时也有自己的准则，同我们每天八小时的工作准则一样。然而许多非常悲剧的角色已让我预见到，更长的体验会改变这种价值表。他们让我们想象，日常生活中的探险者只通过体验的数量便能打破所有纪录（我有意采用了这一体育用语），并会因此赢得自己的道德准则。[42]但我们还是避免浪漫主义，直截了当地问自己，对于一个决心打赌并仔细观察自认的游戏规则的人来说，这样一种立场意味着什么。

打破所有纪录首先就意味着尽可能频繁地面对这个世界。没有矛盾与文字游戏，这如何能完成呢？因为，一方面，荒谬告诉我们，所有体验都无关紧要；另一方面，荒谬又鼓励最大数量的体验。人怎么就不能像我之前提到的那么多人一样选择带给我们最具可能性的人性问题的生活形式，因而引入一种价值等级——那种他在另一方面声称要摒弃的价值等级呢？

然而给我们以启发的还是荒谬及其充满矛盾的生活。因为有种错误的观点认为如果体验的数量只取决于我们的话，那么它会取决于我们的生活境况。这里我们必须简之又简。对于两个度过等量岁月的人，世界总会提供等量的体验，而能否意识到这些体验，取决于我们本身。最大限度地了解一个人的生活、反抗、自由，便是最大限度的生活。清醒在哪里占了上风，哪里的价值等级就会变得无用。我们不妨更简化一点。我们说，有待改善的唯一阻碍、唯一缺陷产生于早亡。因此在荒谬之人的眼中（即使他想这么做），没有任何深度、感情、激情和牺牲可以把一段四十年的有意识生活等同于一个贯穿六十年的清晰性。[43]对他而言，疯狂与死亡是无法弥补的。人们不作选择。因此，荒谬及荒谬所包含的额外生活不依赖于人的意志，而依赖于相反面——死亡。[44]仔细权衡这些语句，这只是一个运气问题。人只要能够赞同这一点。二十年的生活与体验就永远都不会有替代品。

然而如此警觉的希腊民族居然声称，那些早亡之人是众神的宠儿，这未免显得前后不一。如果你愿意相信，进入这样一个荒谬的众神世界就相当于永远失去了最纯粹的快乐——感觉，在人间的感觉，那么他们的话就是真的。现在，以及在始终清醒的灵魂面前接二连三的当下，是荒谬之人的理想。但理想这个词在这种联系中听起来不合适，这甚至都算不上他的使命，只是其推理的第三个结果。关于荒谬的思索始于对非人性的一种痛苦的意识，在其行程的最后它又回到了人性反抗的激情火焰之心。[45]

因此，我从荒谬中推导出三个结果：我的反抗，我的自由，以及我的激情。我只通过保持清醒便将一种死亡的诱惑转化为一种生活准则——我拒绝自杀。当然，我也知道在这些日子里的单调的共振，但我只有一句话要说：那是必不可少的。尼采写道：“很明显，不论在天堂还是人间，最重要的就是绝对服从，并在一个方向坚持到底：从长远来看会出现一些值得费力生活在这个世上的事物，诸如美德、艺术、音乐、舞蹈、理性、精神——这些事物可以产生改观，它们精美、疯狂，或者神圣。”他以此阐明了一种真正卓越的道德规范，但他同样指明了荒谬之人的道路。服从于激情是最容易也是最困难的事情，但是人不时地自我评判对自己是有好处的，只有他自己能做到这一点。

“祷告，”阿兰[46]说，“就是夜晚降临在思想之上。”神秘主义者和存在主义者回应道：“但是精神必须与夜晚相会。”这没错，然而精神为投入其中而唤起的，并非那个单凭个人意愿就出现在眼皮底下的夜晚——那个黑暗而无法穿透的夜晚，精神集中起来，投入其中。如果说它必须际会一个夜晚的话，那么就让它是绝望的夜晚——极夜，精神不眠，这样还能保持清醒，由此或许还能诞生纯洁、发白的光亮，从而勾勒出思智灯下每一个对象。从这一层次上说，对等邂逅了充满激情的智慧。如此来看，这甚至已不再是对存在主义的跨跃进行评判的问题了，而是又呈现出人性立场的那种古董面貌。对于观众而言，假使他是清醒的，那么跨跃依旧是荒谬的。若它自认可以解决悖论，那么它便会回复到完好状态。在这一点上，它是鼓舞人心的。在这一点上，一切都各归各位，这个荒谬的世界也得到了重生，恢复了往日的壮丽与多姿。

然而，阻止所有精神力量中或许最细微的一种是糟糕的，只用一种方式去看难以收到满意的效果，也很难不产生矛盾。以上只是对一种思考方式的定义，而重点是去生活。

荒谬的人

如果斯塔夫罗金信教，他不认为他信教。

如果他不信教，他不认为他不信教。

——陀思妥耶夫斯基《群魔》

歌德[47]说：“我的领地，就是时间。”这实在是荒谬的言论。荒谬的人其实是什么样的？他做事不求永恒，他自己也不否认这一点，他对怀旧并不陌生，但更偏爱自己的勇气与推理。勇气教他在生活中不怀有追求，珍惜所拥有的东西；推理让他清楚自己的界限。他确信，他的自由短暂而有限，他的反抗没有未来，对于生死也已经觉悟，于是在有生之年他要实践自己的冒险旅程。这便是他的领地，这便是他的行动，对此他不会接受来自他人的任何评判。对他而言，一种更伟大的生活并不意味着另一种生活。这是不公平的。我所谈的甚至也不是那种无价值的永生，也就是人们所说的香火长传。罗兰夫人[48]的依靠是自己，而这一鲁莽行为也得了教训。其后人非常乐意引用她的言论，但却忘了对之加以判断。罗兰夫人对后人保持一种冷漠的态度。

对道德规范进行长篇大论不存在任何问题。我见过大德之人行为不端，平常也注意到，没有必要为正直诚实设立规范。只有一种道德规范可以为荒谬之人所接受，它是与上帝分不开的：由上帝口授的命令。可是碰巧他的生活中没有上帝。至于其他的（我指的是非道德主义），荒谬之人除了正当理由什么也没发现，而他不需要理由去证明什么。这里我就从保证其无辜的原则谈起。

这种无辜是可怕的。伊凡·卡拉马佐夫[49]宣称：“一切都是被允许的”，这同样有点荒谬的味道，但前提是不要用一种庸俗的观念去看待它。我不知是否已充分说明：这并非一种解脱或喜悦的发泄，而是对一个事实痛苦的承认。确信一个上帝赋予生命以一种意义，这在吸引力上远远超过了可使恶行免受惩罚的能力。选择不难做，可是没有选择，这时痛苦便来了。荒谬不会释放，而是要束缚，它不会允许所有的行为。一切都被允许不意味着一切都不被禁止。荒谬仅仅是为那些行为的结果找到一种等价物。它并不支持犯罪，因为那将很幼稚，但他再一次承认了悔恨是无用的。同样，倘若所有的生活经历都是无差异的，那么关于责任的经历就会和其他经历一样合理。做一个有道德的人可以凭借一闪之念。

一切道德体系都建立在这一观点上，即一种行为的结果或者使这种行为合乎情理，或者抵消这种行为。一个被灌输以荒谬的头脑只会判断要冷静思考那些结果，作好了偿还债务的准备。换句话说，在这种观点看来，负责的人可能是有的，但却没了有罪之人。这种思想最多会把过去的经验作为将来行动的基础。时间拖延时间，生活为生活服务。在这个充满可能性的有限领地，他自身的一切，除了清醒的头脑，在他看来都是不可预见的。那么，从这种不理性的秩序中，又能生发出什么规则呢？似乎对他有益的唯一真理并非形式上的：真理开始形成，便在人们身上发生作用。在推理的最后，荒谬的头脑可以预见的不是道德准则，而是对人们生活的阐释与人们生活的迹象。以下几个人物形象都属于这种类型，他们对荒谬的推理表现出一种特定的立场，并投入了自己的热情，以此拖延荒谬的推理。

一个范例未必要去效仿（在荒谬的世界甚至更是如此），因而下面要举的例子也并非典范。我是否还需要对这种观点加以阐释呢？为此需要某种使命感，除此之外，在考虑周全的情况下，如果人们从卢梭[50]的思想里得出人要爬行，从尼采的思想里得出人要虐待自己的母亲，那势必是荒唐可笑的。一位当代作家写道：“荒谬是必要的，而受骗不是必要的。”[51]我将要论述的立场只有通过考虑其对立面，才能呈现完整的意义。邮局工作的小职员与帝王将相是平等的，只要他们都有觉悟。在这一点上，所有生活经历都是无差别的，其中有的对人有利，有的有害。如果是有意识的人，那么就会对他有利，否则便无关紧要了：一个人的失败在于对自身的评判，而非对环境的评判。

我所选择的人物，都只有一个目的——消耗自己，或者我认为他们在消耗自己。这不牵扯深层含义。此刻我只想谈论一个思想、生活在其中都没有未来的世界。促使人们工作与兴奋的任何事情都要用到希望，因而只有无效的思想才不是虚假的。在这个荒谬的世界，一个观念或一种生活的价值要由其无效性来衡量。

唐璜主义

如果只要爱就够了，那么事情就太简单了。一个人爱得越多，荒谬就越多。唐璜找了一个又一个女人，不是因为缺少爱。把他描写成一个追求真爱的神秘主义者真是太可笑了，但的确是因为他把同样的热情投入每一份爱，每次都是全身心投入，他才一定要重复利用这份天赋，不断寻求。因此每个女人都希望给予他没人给过他的东西，可每次她们都大错特错，只能让他感觉到对这种重复的需求。“终于，”其中一个女人大呼，“我把爱给了你。”唐璜付诸一笑，“终于？不，”他说，“只是又一次。”我们还会惊讶于此吗？为什么只有减少爱的次数，才能保证爱得深情呢？

唐璜忧郁吗？不可能。我不会去参考那些传说。他的笑，那种征服者的傲慢、那种玩世不恭，还有对剧院的钟爱都清楚明白，充满欢乐。所有健康的生灵都想自我复制，唐璜也不例外。而忧郁的人之所以忧郁是因为：他们不知道，或者他们有希望。唐璜知道，他也没有希望。他让我们联想起那些明白自身局限的艺术家，他们从不逾越这一局限，而且在那个表明自己精神立场的不靠谱的间隙，他们享受作主人的美妙与悠闲。这的确是非凡的才能：一种知道自身局限的智慧。直到生命的尽头，唐璜对忧郁仍是一无所知。在他知道的那一刻，他放声大笑，笑声让人原谅了一切。当他有希望的时候，他是忧郁的。现在，从那个女人的口中，他尝到了这唯一知道的事情带给自己的苦涩与安慰。苦涩？不过是：让幸福被察觉到的必要瑕疵。

如果试图把唐璜看成是依据《传道书》[52]培养出来的人，那就大错特错了，因为在他眼里，除了对另一种生活的希望外没有任何东西是虚空的。他之所以证明了这一点，是因为他用那另一种生活来赌天堂。渴求欲望，得到满足之后欲望便终止，这种无能之人的共性不属于他。对于笃信上帝而把自己出卖给魔鬼的浮士德[53]来说，这没什么。对唐璜来说，事情就更简单了。莫利纳[54]的“骗子”每次受到下地狱的威胁时，总是回答：“你给我的缓期太长了！”死后之事都是那么没有意义，而那些知道如何活着的人，又有多么漫长的岁月在等着他们啊！浮士德渴求世间的美好；这个可怜人要做的只是伸出手。当他无法得到满足时，就相当于在出卖自己的灵魂了。说到满足，唐璜恰恰相反，他坚持要满足。如果他离开一个女人，绝对不是因为他不再爱她了，漂亮的女人总是勾人欲望的。只是他又对另一个产生了欲望，而这不是同一回事，不是的。

这样的生活满足了他的每个愿望，没有比失去这种生活更糟糕的了。这个狂人是个大智者。但是靠希望生活的人不会在这个宇宙得势，在这里，仁慈要屈从于慷慨，爱慕要屈从于强大的沉默，同舟共济要屈从于个人英雄主义。大家都匆匆下结论说：“他是一个懦夫、一个理想主义者，或者一个圣人。”人们必须贬低那些无礼的伟大。

人们受够了（或者露出同谋者的微笑，从而降低那种欣赏的成分）唐璜的演说，还有他用在所有女人身上的同一套话。但对于追求快乐数量的人来说，唯一要紧的是效力问题。如果各种口令都经受住了考验，那还有什么必要使之复杂化呢？无论男女，没有人去听从这些口令，他们听的是发出这些口令的声音。这些口令是规则、惯例，也是礼貌。发出这些口令后，最重要的还没完成，唐璜已为此作好了准备。他为何要给自己提出一个道德上的问题呢？他不像米洛兹[55]剧中的马纳拉，因为渴望成为圣人而诅咒自己。地狱在他看来是一件需要被激发的东西。对于神灵的愤怒他只有一种回答，这就是人的荣耀。“我有荣耀，”他对骑士长[56]说，“我会遵守我的诺言，因为我是一个骑士。”可是如果把他当作一个伤风败俗之人，就又大错特错了。在这一方面，他“和其他人一样”：他有自己好恶的道德准则。要正确认识唐璜，只能不断参照通常他所代表的形象：平平常常的引诱者，处处拈花惹草。他是一个普通的引诱者，[57]其不同之处只在于他是有意识的，这就是为什么说他是荒谬的。尽管如此，一个清醒的引诱者不会有所改变，引诱是他的生活状态。只有小说里的人才会改变生活状态，或是自己变得更好，但也可以说什么也没有改变，同时一切都转变了。唐璜付诸行动的是一种数量上的道德标准，而圣人则青睐于质量。不相信事物的深层含义，是荒谬之人的专属。至于那些热诚或者大吃一惊的面庞，他会投以目光，加以储存，但并不有所停留。时间与她们并进，而荒谬之人与时间不可分割。唐璜没有想要“收集”女人，他穷尽了她们的数量，与此一起耗尽的还有他生活中的可能性。“收集”就等于是依靠自己的过去生活，但他反对懊悔，这是希望的另一种形式。翻看照片不是他能做出来的事情。

尽管如此，他是自私的吗？以他的行为方式来看或许是的，但这里我们也有必要相互理解一下。有的人是为生活而生，有的人是为爱而生。至少唐璜倾向于这种说法。他可能会长话短说，讲他有能力去选择。因为我们这里所说的爱穿着永恒的幻衣。正如所有情感专家教导我们的，只有受到挫折的爱情才能成为永恒，几乎没有一帆风顺的爱情。这样一种爱只有在终极的矛盾——死亡——到来时才会到达极致。人应该要么成为维特[58]，要么什么也不是。而自杀的方式也有很多，其中之一就是全力付出与忘我。唐璜和其他人一样，知道这会带来不平静，但他又是知道这事无关紧要的少数几人之一。他还知道，那些出于一种伟大的爱而忽视个人生活的人或许是充实自己，但必定也让自己爱的人一无所有。一位母亲或一位感情热烈的妻子必定有一颗封闭的心，因为那颗心已背离了这个世界。一份感情、一个人、一张面孔，这一切都被吞食了。搅扰唐璜的是一份很不同的爱，这份爱随心所欲。它有着世上所有的面貌特征，它知道自己不能永生，于是还带着颤抖。唐璜选择变得一无是处。

对他来说，这一问题就是把眼睛擦亮。我们把爱看成将我们与其他生灵联结在一起的东西，凭借的只是一种共同的看问题方式，而这一共识往往由书籍和传奇故事促成。然而关于爱，我只知道那种欲望、爱慕以及智慧的混合体，它把我和这个或那个生灵联系在一起。这种复合物因人而异，我无权用同一个名字指称所有这些体验，这就避免了人们的行为方式千篇一律。荒谬的人此时便会又一次将他无法统一的东西加倍复制，于是他发现了一种新的存在方式，这种方式解放了他自己，也解放了那些靠近他的人。没有高贵的爱，只有自知短命而独特的爱。所有那些死亡与重生如花束般聚集到一起，偿还了唐璜的余生，这便是他付出与活跃的方式。请读者自己判断这能否叫作自私。

我想到了那些坚持要惩罚唐璜的人，他们认为他不仅应在来世受罚，即便在今世也应受罚。我想起了那些关于老年唐璜的故事、传说，还有笑话。但是唐璜已经准备好了。对于一个有意识的人来说，衰老及其延伸出来的事物都不足为奇。的确，他并没有无视衰老的恐怖，只有在这一点上，他才是有意识的。雅典有一座专为老年人而建的庙宇，孩子们会被带到那里。唐璜认为，嘲笑他的人越多，他的形象就越突出。因此他拒绝接受那些浪漫主义者为他塑造的形象。没有人愿意去嘲笑饱受折磨、惹人怜悯的唐璜。他是被同情的；天堂能拯救他吗？但情况并非如此。在这个被唐璜瞥了一眼的宇宙里，荒唐也包含其中。他会认为受惩戒是正常的，这是游戏规则。他典型的贵族表现就是接受所有的游戏规则，但他知道自己是对的，不可能会受罚。命运不是一种惩罚。

这是他所犯的罪，而要理解上帝的子民为何要惩罚他再容易不过了。他获得一种没有幻觉的认识，这种认识否定了那些人的所有信仰。爱和占有，征服和消耗——这就是他的认识方式（圣经中将这种肉体行为称作“知道”，圣书偏爱这个词是有意义的）。作为那些人最坏的敌人，他是无视他们的。一位编年史学家说真正的“骗子”死于法兰西斯派[59]的暗杀，该派想“结束生来便被赋予免罚权的唐璜那放肆和亵渎的行为”。之后他们宣称是上帝将他击倒，这一离奇的结局没有人去证明，也没有人去推翻。如果有这种可能性，那么我可以不加质疑地说这是符合逻辑的。在这一点上我只想把“生来”一词单挑出来推敲一下：正是活着这一事实确保了他的无辜。正是从死亡那里他获取了现在已成为传说的罪恶。

那个骑士长石像被用来惩罚敢于思想的血肉与勇气，除此之外，它又有什么代表意义呢？秩序、永恒的理性，以及普遍道义的所有能量，一个喜怒无常的上帝让人感到陌生的所有伟大，都集合到他的身上。这个没有灵魂的巨石象征的只是唐璜永远都否定的力量，但该骑士长的任务仅止于此。雷电会回归到那个仿造的天国，也就是它们被唤起的地方。真正的悲剧在发生时离它们很远。不，唐璜不是死在一个石头的手上。我倾向于相信那故弄玄虚的传说，相信一个健康的人用疯癫的笑声惹到了一个不存在的上帝。然而我尤为相信，那个晚上，当唐璜在安娜住所等待时，骑士长没有出现，午夜过后，这个亵渎神灵之徒必定感受到了那些正人君子的可怕的痛苦。关于其生平，我更愿意接受，他最终被葬于一个修道院的说法，但关于这个故事给人的启示意义就不太可信了。他能向上帝要求什么庇护呢？但这却代表了一种完全荒谬生活的合理结果、一种追求短命快乐的悲惨结局。在这一点上，肉体上的享乐终结于禁欲主义。必须认识到，它们可以说是同一种穷困命运的两个方面。一个人被自己的躯体出卖，只因没有及时死去，所以在生命终结之前，他的生活一直是喜剧，而与那个不被自己崇拜的上帝面对面，像侍奉生活那样侍奉他，屈膝于虚无，手伸向一个明知没有雄辩术也没有深度的天国，我们还能想到比这更恐怖的形象吗？

我看到唐璜栖身于西班牙山顶的一个废弃修道院的一间净室内。倘若他有所思，思考的不会是其旧爱的幽灵，或许——透过阳光烘烤的墙上的一条窄缝——是某个沉寂的西班牙平原，一方高贵而没有灵魂的土地，在那里他认清了自己。没错，伴着这个忧郁而灿烂的画面，幕布应该拉下来了。结局，我们等待但绝不期待，结局是可以忽略不计的。

戏剧

哈姆雷特说：“演戏就是重要的事，凭借它我将抓住国王的意识。”就是这个词，抓住，因为意识动作迅速，或者还会退缩，所以必须在它行进时下手，在它匆匆扫视自己的当口抓住它，那时不易被察觉。庸人都不爱耽搁，所有事都在催着他往前走，但与此同时，除了他自己，特别是自己的潜能，什么事也提不起他的兴趣。由此他对戏剧、对表演产生了兴趣，这为他展现了那么多的命运，他可以在感觉不到悲伤的情况下体味诗意。至少这里可以看到没有思想的人，而他继续匆匆地奔向某个希望或其他什么东西。荒谬之人的起点在他人离开的地方，在停止欣赏戏剧的头脑欲进入的地方。进入那些生活，体验它们的多姿多彩，就等于是把它们演绎出来。我并不是说演员一般都会服从于那种冲动，也不是说他们都是荒谬之人，而是说他们的命运是一种荒谬的命运，可能会让一颗冷静的心陶醉、沉迷。为使读者在理解以下内容时不至于产生误解，有必要先作此说明。

演员的职业生涯是转瞬即逝的。在已知的所有名声中，演员的名声最为短暂，至少人们在谈话中是这样说的，然而所有名声都很短暂。从天狼星的角度看，歌德的作品在一万年后将化成尘埃，他的名字也将被遗忘。或许一批考古学家还会为我们这个时代寻找“证据”来证明它的存在。这一观点总会包含教育意义。认真思考这一观点后，我们对于冷漠之中深远的高贵，会减少一些不安情绪。最重要的是，它把我们的注意力移向了最确定之事，即最直接之事。在所有的名声中，欺骗性最小的要属已被验证过的名声。

因此，演员选择了多样的名声，这名声已被神圣化，并经受了考验。一切事物终将消亡，他从这一事实出发作出了最佳判断。一个演员或成功，或不成功。一个作家即使不被赏识，也有某种希望，他可以用自己的作品见证自己的过去。演员最多留给我们一张照片，关于他的自身——他的姿态、他的沉默、他对爱的汲汲渴望，我们将一无所知。对他来说，不为人知就是不演戏，而不演戏就是和他曾赋予生命或唤醒的角色一同死去，多达百次。

我们为何要讶异于最短暂生命基础之上的昙花一现的名声呢？演员有三个小时的时间去做埃古[60]、阿尔切斯特、费德尔或格洛斯特，在这段很短的时间内，他让这些角色有了生命，最后又倒在这五十码见方的舞台上。荒谬从来没有被这么详尽地、这么长篇累牍地论述过。除了这些令人赞叹的生命，这些几个小时内在一个小舞台上展现的卓越而完整的命运，我们还能想象出更有启示性的典范吗？下了台，西基斯蒙德[61]不再是西基斯蒙德。两小时后你可能就看到他出去吃饭了。那么或许，生活就是一场梦，但西基斯蒙德之后还有后来人。在不确定性中煎熬的英雄人物取代了那个为复仇而咆哮的人。因而演员驰骋过几个世纪，演绎过无数角色，在尽可能真实地模仿别人的过程中，与另一个荒谬个体——游客有了很多共性。和他一样，游客也耗尽了某些东西，并且还在不断前进。他是时间中的游客，或最多是被追捕的游客，被灵魂追逐着。数量上的道德观若要找到赖以存在的基础，那么肯定是这个奇怪的台子。很难说演员在多大程度上受益于角色，但这是无关紧要的，问题只在于，要知道自己和这些不可替代的角色有多大关联。他经常随身带着这些角色，而这些角色则超越了它们诞生的时间与空间，与这个无法把自己和一直以来所演的角色轻易分开的人结伴同行。有时拿一个杯子，他会用哈姆雷特的姿势举起杯子。他与自己注入生命的角色之间，距离并不遥远，绝不。他每个月或每一天都在充分阐释这一内含深意的事实，即一个人想要成为的人与他自己之间没有界限。他总是关心如何更好地去展现，阐释在多大程度上表象构成了存在。因为这就是他的艺术——十足的模仿，把自己尽可能深地投入另一种生活。努力到最后，他的使命便明晰了：全心致力于变得空虚，或者分饰多角。塑造角色时所受的限制越小，就越需要发挥他的才智。在今天佩戴的面具下，他能活三个小时。在这三个小时内，他会体验，并且表现一种独特生活的全貌。这就叫迷失自己以发现自我。在这三个小时内，他走完了这条死胡同的全程，而坐在观众席上的人却要花一生才能走完这段路。

在对这种短暂生活的模仿上，演员只在表面上训练并完善自己。戏剧表演的惯例是，通过姿态与肢体来表现和沟通内心世界——或者通过与肢体表达能力相当的灵魂的声音。这种艺术的规则就是，把一切都夸大并用身体语言表现出来。倘若在舞台上爱一个人就必须真心去爱，说话必须用心里那个独一无二的声音，看东西时必须像人们在生活中那样凝视，那么我们的讲话就成了暗语。这时沉默就必须派上用场。爱的声音越大，静默就更加壮观。身体就是国王。不是每个人都能“表演”，这一词语被不公正地丑化了，它包含一种完整的美学和一种完整的道德观。人的一半生命都用在暗示、背离和沉默上，而演员成了入侵者。他要打破束缚灵魂的魔咒，激情才能冲上它们的舞台。他们的语言表现在每个姿态中，他们只有通过大喊大叫才能生活，所以说演员塑造自己的角色就是为了展示。他描绘或刻画他们，一下子穿上为他们虚构的外衣，并为他们的幻象输入自己的血液。当然，我所指的是伟大的戏剧，可以使演员借机实现自己完全的实际命运的那种戏剧。以莎士比亚为例，在其冲动横行的剧中，身体的激情推动着剧情的发展，可以用以解释所有事情。没有了这些激情，一切都要烟消云散。若没有流放考荻利娅[62]和惩处爱德伽[63]的粗暴行为，李尔王永远也不会坚守那源自疯狂的约定。此后悲剧的展开便充斥着那种疯狂，灵魂都给了恶魔及其萨拉邦德舞。这出戏至少有四个疯子：一个由于交易，一个出自意愿，还有两个是遭受了苦难——四个错乱的身躯，一种状态的四个不可言说的方面。

光靠人的肢体还不够，面具和厚底靴，减弱或强调面部本来特征的化妆，起夸张或简化作用的服饰——在这个宇宙里所作的一切牺牲都是为了表象，只是为眼睛服务。身体通过一种荒谬的奇迹同样可以获得认识。如果我不扮演埃古这个角色，我永远也不会真正理解这个人。光听他说话是不够的，因为我只有在看见他的时候才能了解他。演员最后会从荒谬的角色中感到乏味，那是一种单一的、让人感到压抑的黑色轮廓，既陌生又熟悉，要跟着他从一个角色到另一个角色。同样伟大的戏剧作品可以促成这种格调的一致性，[64]这正是演员的自我矛盾之处：一模一样而又千姿百态，那么多的灵魂汇集到一个身体里。这便是荒谬的矛盾本身：那想得到一切、经历一切的个体，那毫无价值的尝试，那无效的坚持。自我矛盾的事物总会与他相结合，正是在这时，他的身心合二为一，而已厌倦了挫败的精神转向它最忠实的同盟。哈姆雷特说：“能够把感情和理智调和得那么适当，命运也无法将他玩弄于股掌之间，这样的人是有福的。”

教会怎能不去谴责演员的这样一种行为呢？她否认了这种艺术复制灵魂的异端行为、情感上的道德败坏，以及对精神的侮辱性假设，这种假设反对只过一种生活，致力于各种形式的过火行为。她还禁止他们偏爱当下时光，阻止普罗特斯[65]的胜利，它们对其所有教诲都加以否定。永恒不是一种游戏。愚蠢到喜欢喜剧胜过喜欢永恒的人已经没救了。在“到处”与“永远”之间没有中间道路，由此这一备受毁谤的职业会引起一场激烈的精神论战。“要紧的，”尼采说，“不是永生，而是永乐。”实际上，所有的戏剧都是在这种选择之中。

阿德里亚娜·莱科芙露尔[66]临终时很想忏悔并领到圣餐，但拒绝放弃自己的职业，于是她没有得到忏悔的好处。这实质上不也等同于宁可选择无法抗拒的热情也不要上帝吗？而这个临终饱受痛苦的女人，含着热泪拒绝割舍自己口中的艺术，明明白白地表现出她在舞台灯光之后永远也没有达到的一种伟大。这是她扮演过的最佳角色，也是最难演的一个。在上帝与一种可笑的忠诚之间作出选择，投身于永恒还是现身于上帝，这是自古就有的悲剧，在这场剧中每个人都要扮演自己的角色。

那个时代的演员知道自己被逐出了教会，进入这个职业就等于是选择了地狱。而教会则把他们看作最坏的敌人。有些文学家抗议：“什么！拒绝为莫里哀做临终祈祷！”但那是正当的，特别是针对那些把生命结束在舞台上的人，他们在演员的装束下完成了自己整个被流放的人生。至于莫里哀，他是个天才，于是什么都可以原谅，但是天才又什么都不原谅，因为它拒绝这么做。

这个艺术家当时已经知道了什么样的惩罚在等着他。可是比起生活为他保留的最后惩罚，这种含糊不清的威胁又有何意义呢？前者是他提前就预感到了，并且照单全收的。对于一个演员来说，如同对于荒谬之人一样，早逝是不可避免的。什么都抵偿不了如此多数量的面孔和他穿越过的这么多个世纪。无论如何人终有一死，演员无疑是无所不在的，但席卷而过的时间同样会把他带走，留下的印记中还带有他的痕迹。

只需要一点想象就可以体会到一个演员的命运意味着什么。他正是在时间中塑造并表达着自己的角色，同样是在时间中学着掌控这些角色。体验的不同生活越多，他对之便越淡漠。他终会为了这个世界死在舞台上。曾经经历过的就在面前，他看得一清二楚，他感受到这种历险令人痛苦而又不可替代的特质。这些他都知道，现在他可以走了。年老的演员有自己的家园。

征服

“不，”征服者说，“不要以为我热爱行动我就一定会忘了如何思考。相反，我完全可以明确自己的信念，因为我坚定我的信念，并把它看得清楚明白。有人说：‘我对此太了解了，以至于难以把它表达出来了。’请当心这些人，如果他们做不到那一点，那是因为他们不了解，或者是懒得深入探索。”

“我没有多少观点。在生命将要终结的时候，人发现自己花了那么多年时间，只是为了搞明白一个真理，然而如果真理是显见的，那么它足以指引一种存在。关于个体，我倒是有些话要说。而谈到个体，人们一定要直言不讳，必要时还要带上适当的轻蔑。”

“比起所言之事，所隐秘之事更能凸显人的价值。我所隐秘的东西有很多，但我坚定地相信，所有那些评判个体的人，在做这方面工作时凭借的经验——作为其评判基础——比我们要少的多。智慧，那鼓舞人心的智慧或许预见到了须引起注意的东西，然而时代及时代用事实呈现给我们的毁灭与鲜血，让我们措手不及。对于古老的国度，甚至对于我们机器时代的现代国家而言，有可能去权衡社会美德与个人美德孰轻孰重，并试图发现谁应该为谁服务。首先，人心有一种顽疾，由此人或生来服务别人，或生来被别人服务；其次，社会与个人尚未展露自己的全部能力。”

“我知道，许多智慧的头脑对在佛兰德斯[67]战场的血雨腥风中诞生的荷兰画家们的伟大作品大为惊异，对恐怖的三十年战争[68]中西里西亚[69]神秘主义者的祈祷惊叹不已。永恒的价值在世俗纷扰的惊异眼光中完好无损，然而自那以后便有了变化。今天的画家已丧失了这种淡定，即使他们拥有创作者需要的基本心理状态，我指的是一颗封闭的心，也无济于事；对于每个人来说，包括圣人，都被动摇了。这或许就是我感受最深之处。在战壕失败的每一种形式中，在被钢铁压碎的每一个概述、隐喻或祈祷中，永恒都输了一局。我意识到不能对自己的时间不闻不问，便决心成为时间不可分割的一部分。这就是我尊重个体的原因，只因他给人的印象是荒唐可笑、丧失尊严的。我知道没有胜利的事业，便爱上了失败的事业：这种事业需要一个未受玷污的灵魂，对其挫败与暂时的胜利一视同仁。对于感到自己和这个世界的命运息息相关的任何人而言，不同文明之间的冲突让人痛苦不堪。在我想要加入这个行列的同时，我便也具有了这种痛苦。在历史与永恒之间，我选择了历史，因为我喜欢确定性。至少我对它感到确信，叫我如何否定这种压迫我的力量？”

“总有那么个时候，人必须在思考与行动之间作出选择，谓之成人。这种抉择的痛苦是可怕的，但对于一颗高傲的心来说，没有中间道路可走。要么是上帝，要么是时间；要么是那个十字架，要么是这把剑。这个世界有更高一层的含义，超越了它的烦恼，或者除了这些烦恼便没有真实的东西了。人必须与时间共存亡，否则就得为了一种更伟大的生活而撇开时间。我知道人们可以选择一条折中道路——生活在这个世界上，同时又相信那种永恒，这叫作接受。我厌恶这种说法，我要么想得到一切，要么就什么都不要。倘若我选择行动，不要以为我会把思考撇到一边，它给不了我所有，于是丧失了永恒的我愿与时间为伍。我不想把怀旧或苦难记在账上，我只是想看清楚一些。我告诉你，明天你也要被动摇，这对你我都是一种解放。个体什么都做不了，但他又可以做任何事情。在那样一种无所羁绊的绝佳状态，你会理解我为何要在颂扬他的同时立刻又把他打压下去。是世界摧毁了他，而我解放了他。我给了他应有的一切权利。”

“征服者知道行动本身毫无益处，只有一种有益的行动，那便是改造人与地球。我永远不会去改造人，但人必须‘煞有介事’地去做。斗争的道路引我找到了肉体，即使失去了尊严，肉体也是我唯一确信的东西，我可以仅靠它生活。人本身就是我的故土，这就是我为何要选择这种荒谬而无效的努力，这就是我为何要支持斗争。正如我所说，这个时代适合于这一点。迄今为止，一个征服者的伟大仍表现在地理上，是由所征服领地的大小来衡量的。这个词的意义已发生了改变，不再表示获胜的将领，也是有原因的。伟大已变换了阵营，它体现在抗议以及走投无路时的牺牲上。同样，这也不是由对失败的偏爱造成的。人们渴望胜利，但只有一种胜利，那便是永恒。这是我永远也得不到的，这是我跌倒的地方，也是我不忍割舍的地方。革命总是针对神明的，普罗米修斯[70]是革命的鼻祖，他是第一位现代征服者。与自己命运过不去的是人自己的需求，穷人的需求只是一个借口。我只能在它的历史事件中抓住这种精神，我与它在这里相会，然而，不要以为我以此为乐：我维持着自己的人性矛盾，与本质矛盾相对。我的清醒建立在四面树敌的环境中。面对摧毁人的威胁，我高唱对人的赞歌，而我的自由、我的反抗、我的激情悉数进入了这种紧张的关系、这种清醒、这种大量的重复之中。”

“没错，人是自己的终点，也是自己唯一的终点。如果他的目标是成为什么，那么这个目标一定就在他的生活之中。我非常了解这一点。征服者们有时会谈到战胜与击败，但他们的意思一直都是‘战胜自己’。你很清楚这意味着什么。某些时候每个人都会感觉自己和神是平等的，至少它是通过这种方式表现出来的，但这缘于一个事实，即他在一闪念间发觉了人思想中惊人的伟大。征服者只是这样一群人，他们十分清楚自己的能力，可以久立高处，也非常明白这种伟大。这只是一个算术问题，一个得多或得少的问题。征服者有能力得的多，但他们最多也只能得到人想得到的极限。因此，他们从不离开人的这副皮囊，投入那火热的革命灵魂。”

“他们发现这一生灵受尽残害，但他们同样在这里邂逅了自己所爱慕的仅有的价值：人及其沉默，这既是他们的贫乏又是他们的财富。在此他们只有一种奢侈品：人们之间的感情。在这个脆弱的世界，所有具有人性并只具有人性的东西都包含一种更生动的意义，人怎么能没有意识到这一点呢？紧绷的面孔，受到威胁的手足情，人们之间这种强烈而纯洁的友谊——这些都是真正的财富，因为它们转瞬即逝。在它们中间，思想非常清楚自己的力量与局限，也就是自己的效力。有的人还说过天才这个词，但天才说起来容易，我偏向于智慧一词。可以说此时智慧是宏伟壮观的，它照亮了这个沙漠，并在此确立了自己的统治地位。它知道自己的责任，并一一加以阐释。它与这个躯体同生共死，但知道这一点它便是自由的。”

“所有教会都反对我们，我们无法忽视这一事实，一颗紧张的心逃避永恒，而所有的教会，不论是神圣的还是政治的，都声称对永恒拥有权利。快乐与勇气，报应或正义，对他们而言都处于从属地位。这是他们的教义，必须服从。但我既不关心思想也不关心永恒，在我的视野内真理都触手可及，我无法与之相分离。所以你无法以我为基础建立任何东西：征服者的一切都不会持久，哪怕是他的信条。”

“无论是什么，这一切的终点，便是死亡。我们也知道它能终结一切。正因为如此，遍布欧洲的坟墓都面目可憎，而且也困扰着我们当中的某些人。人们只美化自己喜爱的事物，而死亡让我们感到厌恶，磨灭了我们的耐心，可它同样是要被征服的。被囚禁在帕多瓦[71]的最后一个卡拉拉人，当这个被瘟疫洗劫一空的城池被威尼斯人围困住后，他狂呼着跑遍自己废弃的宫殿：他在召唤魔鬼，请求赐自己一死。这便是战胜死亡的一种方式，而这同样也是西方勇气的一种标志，把死亡自以为荣的地方变得丑陋不堪。在反叛者的世界，死亡赞颂的是非正义。这是最高层次的虐待。”

“其他人也不加妥协地选择了永恒，谴责这个世界的假象。他们的坟茔在鸟语花香之中微笑。这很适合于征服者，为他描绘了一个他曾拒绝接受的清晰形象。而他选择了黑色的铁栅或义冢。上帝子民中的佼佼者有时会被一种恐惧攫住，恐惧的同时还对那些脑中有这样一种死亡印象的人表示关心与怜悯，而那些人正是从这里获得他们的理由与力量。我们的命运就在我们面前，而我们要去激发他。我们同样也会怜悯自己——更多的是由于意识到自己无能为力的处境，与自尊关系甚微，这是唯一可为我们所接受的同情：一种你或许理解不了的情绪，而且你绝不会觉得它有何刚强可言，然而感觉到其存在的却是我们当中的勇者。我们认为清醒之人才是刚强的，我们不希望得到一种与清醒撇开关系的力量。”

我重申，这些形象不夹带道德准则，不包含任何评判：它们是一些概述，只代表一种生活方式。情人、演员或冒险家都扮演了荒谬的角色，但如果他想的话，还可以扮成贞洁之人、行政人员，或者共和国首脑，扮得一样好。知道，并不加任何掩饰，便足矣。在意大利博物馆中你有时会发现被轻微涂过的挡板，那是牧师用来挡住有罪之人眼睛的，为的是不让他们看见绞刑架。各种形式的跨跃，冲入了神灵或永恒之中，屈从于平庸或是观念的幻影中——所有这些都是挡板，把荒谬挡在后面，但是也有那些没有挡板的政府工作人员，他们便是我要说的人。

我选取的是最极端的例子。从这一层面上说，荒谬赐予他们一种王权。的确，这些王子没有王国，但他们有一种优势：他们知道所有王权都是虚幻。他们知道，这是他们全部的高贵所在。对他们谈论潜在的灾祸或幻灭的烟尘，是没有用的。丧失了希望不代表绝望。大地的火焰完全可以与天国的芳香相媲美。不仅是我，谁都无法对他们作出评判。他们并非努力做到更好，他们试着做到前后一致。如果说“智者”是依靠自己所拥有的生活，而不去思考自己没有的，那么他们就可以称得上是智者。他们之中有人比任何人都更明白，“你把自己亲爱的温顺的小绵羊养得恰到好处，你绝不会因此在人间和天堂得到一种特权；你最多还是一只亲爱的有角的小绵羊，仅此而已——即使你没有虚荣自负，也没有以一个装腔作势的法官身份制造一件丑闻。”他是思想领域的征服者，知识层面的唐璜，智慧上的演员。

无论如何都有必要为荒谬的推理提供更多诚恳的例子。我们还可以想象出更多的人——与时间和流亡不可分割的人，他们同样知道如何与一个没有未来与弱点的世界和睦共处。那时，在这个没有神灵的荒谬的世界，居住的是思想清晰、停止希望的人们。而我还没有说到最荒谬的角色——创造者。

荒谬的创造

哲学与小说

所有在荒谬的稀薄空气之中维持的生活，如果没有某种深刻而恒定的思想为之灌输力量，它们是无法持之以恒的。就在这里，它只能是一种忠实的奇怪感觉。清醒之人总在最愚蠢的战争中完成自己的任务，他们不会认为自己处于矛盾之中，因为必须无所逃避。因此，在忍受这个世界的荒谬时就有一种超自然的荣誉。征服或演戏、花心、荒谬的反抗，都是人在一场未战先败的战役中向自己的尊严致敬。

这只是遵守这场战斗规则的问题。那种思想或许足够维持一种精神；它一直在支持并将继续支持全部文明。战争无法被否定，人们必须经历战争，要么就得死于战争。荒谬也是如此：关键是要与之同呼吸共命运，承认从中得到的教训，并重获其真谛。在这一点上，荒谬之极乐便是创造。尼采说：“艺术，除了艺术别无他物，我们有了艺术才不至于死于真理。”

在我试图描述并要强调几种模式的体验中，各种折磨必定是此起彼伏的。对健忘的幼稚找寻，满意带来的吸引，如今已少了附和。持续的紧张状态使人一直要面对这个世界，有序的精神错乱鼓励他易于接受任何事物，而这给了他另一种狂热。在这个宇宙，艺术作品便成了保持其清醒并确定这种冒险经历的唯一机会。创造就是加倍生活。普鲁斯特式的摸索着的、急切的探求，他精心收集的鲜花、墙纸和焦虑，就意味着这种创造。同时，这种创造并不比演员、征服者及所有荒谬之人将每天生活都投入其中的持续不断而又不易察觉的创造，意义更大。所有人都想尝试去模仿，去重复，去重建属于他们的现实。我们总是在有了真理的外表时便宣告结束。一个人的所有存在如果背弃了永恒，就不过是在荒谬面具之下的超级模仿。创造是伟大的模仿。这种人首先是知道，然后他们的全部努力便是去查验、扩大，并丰富刚在那里着陆的无望岛，但首先，他们必须得先知道，因为荒谬的发现会伴有一个停顿，那时未来的激情已准备就绪并得到证实。每个没有信条的人都有自己的橄榄山[72]，而人们不可以在自己的山上睡去。对于荒谬之人来说，这一问题不关乎阐释与解决，而关乎体验与描述。一切始于清醒的冷漠。

描述——这是一种荒谬思想的最后目标。同样，科学到达其悖论的终点时便停止提议、思考，以及描绘永远纯洁的现象风景。心灵认识到，在我们看到世界的种种面貌时愉悦我们的情感，并非来自世界的深度，而是来自世界面貌的多样性。解释是无用的，而感觉会保持着，与之一起的还有在数量上没有穷尽的宇宙所产生的不断吸引。艺术作品的地位可以从这一点上得到理解。

它标示出一种体验的终结与增殖。这是对世界已精心安排的主题的一种重复，单调乏味又充满激情，其中包括：身体、庙宇楣外饰上无穷尽的画面、形式或颜色、数字或伤痛。因此，在这个精彩而幼稚的创造者的世界，再次邂逅本书的首要主题，作为总结，并非没有差别。如果从这个世界里看到一种象征，并且认为艺术作品最终可作为荒谬的避难所，那就错了。它本身就是一种荒谬的现象，而我们只关心对它的描述。它并不提供逃避思想疾病的方法，其实它是这种疾病的症状之一，在一个人的整个思想过程中都有所体现。它第一次让精神脱离了自身，将之与他物对立，并不是想让精神迷失，而是要明白地指给它那条所有人都已踏上的盲道。在荒谬的推理中，创造会跟随冷漠与发现，它标示出荒谬的激情爆发点，而这也是理性停止的点。创造在本书中的地位就是用这种方式被确认的。

要在艺术作品中发现关于荒谬的所有思想矛盾，只需阐明创造者与思想者共有的几个主题便足够了。实际上，与其说证明各思想相联系的是相同的结论，不如说是他们共有的矛盾。思想与创造亦然，更不消说共同的苦恼促使人们形成这两种立场，这是他们在初始时的一致之处。在所有源自荒谬的思想中，我发现极少有思想能一直保持在荒谬的范围内，而通过它们的各种偏差和变体，我能够在最大限度上判断什么是属于荒谬范畴的。同样，我必须提出疑问：荒谬的艺术作品可能存在吗？

过多强调前一种对立——艺术与哲学之间的对立——的任意性是不可能的。假如你坚持从一种有过多限制的角度来看他，肯定是错的。假如你的意思只是，这两个学科各自具有独特立场，这极有可能是真的，但语焉不详。唯一可接受的论断在于被自己的体系困住的哲学家和面对自己作品的艺术家之间的矛盾，但这适合于我们在此列为第二位的艺术与哲学的某个特定形式。把一件艺术品与其创造者分开的想法不仅已经过时，也是错误的。有人指出，与艺术家相对的是，没有哪个哲学家曾创造过多个体系。实际上，没有艺术家以不同面貌进行过多种表达，就这一点而言，该观点是成立的。对艺术所作的瞬间美化对于它的更新是必要的——只有从预先形成的观点来看这一点才成立，因为艺术作品同样是一种建构，每个人都清楚伟大的创造者能有多么无聊。和思想者的理由一样，艺术家献身于自己的艺术，并在艺术中找到自我。这种潜移默化提出了最重要的美学问题，并且，对于任何相信思想具有单一目的的人而言，没有什么比建立在方法与对象之上的那些差别更无用的了。在人们为了理解和爱而为自己设立的学科之间没有边界，它们相互串连，被相同的焦虑连接在一起。

我们有必要在开头作此说明。若想得到荒谬的艺术品，必须使思想保持最清醒的形式。同时，思想又不能太显而易见，除非是作为起调节作用的智慧。这一悖论可由荒谬来解释。艺术品的诞生是由于智慧拒绝思考具体的事物，这标志着肉体上的胜利。激起它的正是清醒的思想，而思想正是以这一行为否认自己。它不会抵挡不住诱惑而去增加那种被描述为深层含义的东西，它知道那是不合逻辑的。艺术品体现了一种智慧的戏剧，但只是间接证明了这一点。荒谬的作品需要一个艺术家和一种艺术，这艺术家意识到这些局限，这艺术中包含的确定性除了自己没有其他意味。它不可能是一种生活的终点、意义和慰藉。创造，还是不创造都不会有什么变化。荒谬的创造者不会嘉奖自己的作品。他可以否认它，有时他的确会否认它。就像兰波[73]的情况一样，一个阿比西尼亚[74]便足够了。

同时从这里还可以发现一个美学规则，真正的艺术品总是按照人的标准来创造的。从本质上说它展示出的东西“更少”。在艺术家总的体验与反映这种体验的作品之间，在威廉·麦斯特[75]与歌德的成熟之间，存在着某种关系。如果作品意欲在说明性文学的花边纸上展开全部体验，那么那种关系便是坏的。如果作品只是摘自体验的一小段，如钻石的一面，内部的光泽展露无余，那么那种关系便是好的。第一种情况属于超载，自负地想要达到永恒；第二种情况则使作品显得饱满，因为全面的体验含而不露，其丰富性任由人们去猜测。荒谬艺术家的问题是，他们要获得这种超越社交本领的彬彬有礼。最后，持这种立场的伟大的艺术家首先是一个伟大的生灵，生活在这种情况下被认为是体验与反思并重。因而这些作品便体现了一种思智上的戏剧。荒谬的作品表明，思想背弃了它的威信，心甘情愿地成为逐步建立外表并为无理性之物包装形象的思维。如果世界是清晰的，那么艺术就不会存在。

这里我谈的不是形式或色彩艺术，对于那种艺术，只有最质朴的描述才能占据上风。[76]思想结束了，表达就会开始。那些被人们置于庙宇和博物馆中的眼窝空空的青少年，他们的哲学已经用肢体表达出来。对于一个荒谬的人来说，这比所有图书馆都更具教育意义。另一方面，同样的情况也适用于音乐。如果说有一种艺术是没有教育意义的，那肯定是音乐。它与数学的关系太近了，无法借用数学的无凭无据。精神根据已确定的精确规则与自己玩了一场游戏，这游戏就发生在我们可接收的声波范围内，超出这个范围，就会振动，就发生在非人性的宇宙中了。再没有比这更纯粹的感觉了。这些例子都过于简单，荒谬之人会把这些协调性和这些形式都当作自己的。

但这里我还要说到一种作品，对于这种作品而言，解释的诱惑仍是最大的，错觉会自动现身，而结论几乎是必不可少的。我指的是小说创作。我计划探询一下荒谬能否在这里扎根。

思考首先就意味着创造一个世界（或者说限制自己的世界，其实指的是同一件事）。它从把人与其体验相分离的基本的一致性出发，目的是按照人对旧事的怀恋发现一个共同点，一个用理性设限或者说由怀旧点亮的宇宙，但不管怎样，这个宇宙提供了一个机会以取消那种不堪忍受的分离。一个哲学家，即使他是康德，也是一个创造者。他有自己的性格、自己的标志、自己的秘密行动。他有自己的故事结局。相反，位于诗歌与散文之上的小说，不看表面，它所作的榜样只是代表了一种更伟大的艺术理智化。关于这一点不可出现半点差池；我指的是最伟大的。一种文学形式的积淀与重要性常常是由它所包含的糟粕来衡量的。我们一定不能因为那么多糟糕的小说而忘记了最佳小说的价值。实际上，那些作品都拥有自己的宇宙。小说拥有自己的逻辑、自己的推理、自己的直觉和自己的假设。它同样还有自己对明晰性的要求。[77]

以上所述的经典对立在此特殊例子中被阐释得更少。假如容易把哲学与其作者分开的话，那么它会保持在时间里。如今，思想不再主张普遍性，最好的历史或许要算它的悔恨史，于是我们知道了，这种体系如果有用的话，是不会和其作者相分离的。伦理学，从某一方面说，只是一段详尽的长篇个人自述。抽象的思想最终回到了支撑自己的肉体。同样，身体与激情的虚构活动更多是按照这个世界的某个幻象之要求来调控的。作家停止了讲“故事”，开始创造自己的宇宙。最伟大的小说家是哲学小说家，恰是论文家的对立面。略举几个例子，如巴尔扎克[78]、萨德[79]、梅尔维尔[80]、司汤达[81]、陀思妥耶夫斯基、普鲁斯特、马尔罗[82]、卡夫卡[83]。

他们对用形象而非推理性论断来写作表现出偏爱，但事实上，这揭示出他们所共有的某种思想，他们确信，任何解释原则都是无用的，而可感知的外表传达出具有教育意义的信息。他们把艺术作品既当作终点，又当作起点。它是一种常常不明说的哲学之结果，是对这种哲学的阐释，是这种哲学的极致，但只有将这种哲学暗含其中才算圆满。有极少一部分思想会使一种旧题的变体远离生活，大多思想则会使这种主题无奈地接受生活，而艺术作品最终证实了这种变体的合理性。思想无法完善现实，于是便中途暂停开始模仿它。我们所说的小说是那种既有关联又取之不尽的知识之工具，正如爱的工具一般。关于爱，小说创作具有原创的精彩与丰富的思想。

这些至少是我一开始从中发现的魅惑。我同样在那些拥有耻辱思想的佼佼者中发现了这些，后来我便见证了这些人的自杀。实际上，我感兴趣的是去了解并描述把他们带回到幻觉之普遍道路上的力量。在此同样的方法会最终帮我一把。我已经运用过这种方法，于是我便可以缩短论述，用一个特殊的例子马上加以总结，不必在某个特定的例子上耽搁太久。我想知道，如果一个人接受了无所欲求、无所诉求的生活，那么他能否同样愿意无所诉求地去工作和创造，还有，通向这些自由的方法是什么。我想释放我的宇宙中的幽魂，并且只让有血有肉的真理居住其中，我无法否认这些真理的存在。我可以从事荒谬的工作，选择创造性的立场而非其他，然而一种荒谬的立场必须对其无凭无据保持清醒，倘若它有这种意愿的话。艺术作品的情况亦然。如果荒谬的诫律没有得到尊重，如果这一作品没有阐明分离与反抗，如果它崇尚幻象，激起希望，那么它就不再无凭无据了。我无法再让自己离开它。我的生活或许可以从中发现一种意义，但那只是微不足道的。它不再是超然与激情中的行为，为一个人生活中的辉煌与徒劳加冕。

在那种对解释的诱惑最为强烈的创造中，人能抵挡住诱惑吗？在那虚构的世界中，对现实世界的意识是最敏锐的，我能忠实于荒谬而不屈服于那种想作评判的欲望吗？有那么多问题要包含进最后的考虑中来，而其所指也肯定已经弄清楚。这些问题是对一种意识的最后顾虑，这种意识害怕为了一种最终的幻觉而放弃自己初始的艰难教训。适用于创造的，被认为是意识到荒谬的人可能持有的一种立场，那也同样适用于他可以选择的所有生活方式。征服者或演员，创造者或唐璜，或许已忘记，自己在生活中的所作所为无法离开对其疯狂特性的了解。人很快就能适应。一个人想通过赚钱获得幸福，于是他的全部努力和生活的精华部分都用来赚钱。幸福被遗忘了；赚钱是为了生命的终结。同样，那位征服者的全部努力可以转化为雄心壮志，这只是更伟大的生活之路。唐璜同样会转而服从于自己的命运，满意于那种只有通过反抗才能获得有价值之高贵的存在。对一个人来说这是意识，而对另一个人来说便成了反抗；在两种情况下荒谬都消失了。人心中有太多顽固的希望，最穷困之人最后常常会接受幻觉。这种因需要内心平和而激起的认可与有关存在的赞同相当。因而便出现了光芒四射的神和泥塑的偶像，然而我们有必要找到一条通往人之多面性的中间道路。

至此，关于它是什么，荒谬之危急关头的一次次失败已给了我们最好的答案。当我们得知答案时，同样也会注意到，小说创作可以表现出同某些哲学一样的含糊性。因此我可以选择一种包含一切表示荒谬意识的事物的作品以作说明，有一个清晰的起点和一个清醒的思想态度，其结果必将给我们以启发。倘若荒谬在其中未得到重视，那么我们就可以知道幻觉靠什么趁虚而入了。一个特例，一个主题，一个创造者的忠诚，对他们就足够了。更加细致的相同分析也包含其中。

我要查验陀思妥耶夫斯基最爱的一个主题。我也可以研究其他作品，[84]但是关于已讨论过的存在哲学，这部作品从高尚与情感的意义上直接探讨了问题。这种一致性恰合我的目的。

基里洛夫

陀思妥耶夫斯基的所有主人公都问自己同一个问题——生活的意义问题。由此看出他们都很现代：他们不害怕荒唐。当代情感与传统情感的区别就是，后者在道德问题上收获颇丰，而前者则是形而上学的问题。在陀思妥耶夫斯基的小说中，这一问题的提出饱含强烈的感情，以至于只能采用极端办法解决。存在是虚幻的，或者说它是永恒的。假如陀思妥耶夫斯基满意于这种探寻的话，他便成了一位哲学家，然而他阐明了这种思维上的消遣在人的生活中可能产生的结果，就此而言，他是一名艺术家。在那些结果中，他的注意力尤其被最后的结果所俘获，这一结果在他的《作家日记》中被称为合乎逻辑的自杀。在1876年12月的日记中，他设想了“合乎逻辑的自杀”的合理性。这个绝望的人已经确信，存在对于任何不相信永生的人而言，都是一种绝对的荒谬，于是他得出以下结论：

“因为在回答我关于幸福的问题时，以我的意识为媒介，我被告知说，除非是与伟大的一切和谐相处，否则我是不会幸福的，而这是我无法想象的，我也永远不会想象到，那么显然……”

“因为，最终在这种联系中，我既充当了原告的角色，也充当了被告的角色，既充当了被控者的角色，也充当了法官的角色；因为我认为这出自然所导演的喜剧愚不可及；因为我甚至觉得让我屈尊去演绎是一种耻辱……”

“以我无可指责的原告与被告、法官与被控者的身份，我谴责自然，它厚颜无耻，把我带到世间就是为了受苦——我诅咒它和我一起毁灭。”

这种立场尚存一丝幽默。自杀者之所以结束自己的生命，是因为他在形而上学的层面被惹恼了。从某种意义上说，他是在复仇。他用这种方式证明自己“不会被拥有”，然而我们知道，在《群魔》的基里洛夫身上体现出相同的主题，只是用了最精彩的概述方式，这部作品同样是提倡合乎逻辑的自杀。工程师基里洛夫在某处宣称，他要结束自己的生命因为这“是他的意念”。显然必须从其本来意义上看这个词，它指的是一种想法，一种思想，这思想就是，他为死作好了准备。这是一种高层次的自杀。在基里洛夫的脑中逐渐闪现出一系列的画面，其中就有驱使他的那种致命意念，该意念渐渐显露在我们面前。事实上，这个工程师回到《日记》的论断中来。他感觉上帝是必不可少的，而他必须存在下去，但他知道，他不会也不能存在。他惊呼道：“你为何没有意识到，这是自杀的充分理由呢？”这一态度对他来说同样包含了某些荒谬的结果。由于淡漠，他同意让他的自杀为自己所鄙视的一项事业所用。“我昨晚下定决心，我不在乎。”而最终他的行为中带有一种反抗与自由相混合的感情。“我要结束自己的生命，为的是坚定我的不屈，和我全新而又可怕的自由。”这已不再是复仇问题了，而成了反抗问题。因此基里洛夫是个荒谬的角色——但还有一种不可或缺的保留：他自杀了。他自己解释了这一矛盾，解释的方式使他同时暴露了最纯粹的荒谬之秘密。事实上，他又为其致命的逻辑平添了一份企望，这便全方位展现了这一角色：他想要自杀以成为神。

这种逻辑具有传统的明晰性。如果上帝不存在，基里洛夫就是神；如果上帝不存在，基里洛夫必须自杀。因此基里洛夫必须自杀才能成为神。这种逻辑是荒谬的，但也是必要的。然而有趣的是要为那种被带到世上的神明赋予意义，这就等于是澄清这一前提：“如果上帝不存在，我就是神，”但仍是晦涩不明。一开始我们就要注意到，夸耀这种疯狂宣言的人确实属于这个世界，这一点很重要。为保持健康，他每天早上锻炼身体；他为查托夫找回妻子时的喜悦而感动。他死后，人们在一张纸上发现了他画的一张脸，正对“他们”吐着舌头。他稚气未脱、性情暴躁、饱含热情、神经过敏、做事有条不紊。说到超人，他只具有超人的思维与沉迷，却有人的全套特征，而平静谈论自己的神性的正是他。他没疯，要不然就是陀思妥耶夫斯基疯了。因此，刺激他的不是一种妄自尊大的幻觉，而在此例子中取词句的具体意义会显得荒唐可笑。

基里洛夫自己也在帮助我们理解。他澄清说自己不是在谈论一个神人，这算是对斯塔夫罗金所提问题的回应。或许人们会认为，这是出于把自己与基督区别开来的考虑，但事实上这是一个将基督归为己有的问题。实际上，基里洛夫一度想象，耶稣死后并没有升入天堂，于是他发现自己所受的折磨都白费了。这个工程师说：“自然法则让基督生活在谎言之中，并且为了一个谎言死去。”只是从此意义上说，耶稣才是整部人类戏剧的化身。他是完整的人，是意识到这种最荒谬状态的人。他不是神人，而是人神。我们每个人都像他一样，会被钉在十字架上，会代人受过——只是在某种程度上。

因此，我们所谈的神明完全是人间的。基里洛夫说：“三年来我一直在找寻我的神明有何特性，我最终找到了。我之神明的特性便是独立。”这就可以看出基里洛夫的前提——“如果上帝不存在，我就是神”——有何意义了。成为神仅仅意味着在这个地球上获得自由，而非一个永生的存在效力。当然最重要的是，它是从那种痛苦的独立中作出所有推断的。如果上帝存在，那么一切便有赖于他，我们便无法做任何有悖于他的事。如果他不存在，一切便都取决于我们。对于基里洛夫而言，正如对于尼采而言，杀死上帝便是使自己成为神，便是在这个地球上实现福音书中所说的永生。[85]

可是，如果这种抽象的犯罪足够一个人达到圆满，为何还要自杀呢？为何在赢得自由后又要结束生命，离开这个世界呢？这是矛盾的。基里洛夫非常清楚这一点，因为他补充说：“如果你感觉到那个，你就是一位沙皇，你非但不会自杀，反而会荣耀一生。”但是一般人不会知道，他们不会感觉到“那个”。在普罗米修斯时代，他们怀有盲目的希望。[86]他们需要有谁给自己指明道路，并无法离开布道。因此，基里洛夫肯定是出于对人性的爱而自杀，他必定为自己的教友指明了一条忠实而艰难的道路，而他是开路者。这是一种教学式的自杀，而基里洛夫作了自我牺牲。可是如果他被钉上十字架，他不会是代人受过。他仍然是人神，确信一种没有未来的死亡，被灌输入福音书式的忧郁。他说：“我不快乐，因为我必须维护我的自由。”可一旦他死了，人们也最终摆脱了无知，那时这个世界上将遍地沙皇，要由人性的光辉去照亮。基里洛夫的那声枪响将成为最后一场革命的信号，所以促使他走向死亡的不是绝望，而是为了自己对邻居的爱。一种无法形容的精神历险终结于血泊之中，基里洛夫死前说了一句与人类的苦难一样古老的话：“一切安好。”

那么，陀思妥耶夫斯基作品中的这种自杀主题的确是一种荒谬的主题。继续论述之前，我们只需注意，基里洛夫又化为其他人物，而这些人物自己又论及其他荒谬的主题。斯塔夫罗金和伊万·卡拉马佐夫在实际生活中实践了荒谬的事实，他们是因基里洛夫的死而获得解放的人，试着用自己的能力成为沙皇。斯塔夫罗金过着一种“讽刺”的生活，至于在哪一方面我们已清楚。他激起了周围人对他的反感，而理解这一人物的关键在于他的道别语：“我还没能让自己对什么产生厌恶。”他是一个淡漠的沙皇。伊万同样通过拒绝妥协而成为精神的忠实力量。对于那些和他兄弟一样，用自己的生活证明有必要羞辱自己以得到信念的人，他回答，这种状态是可耻的。他关键的一句话是“一切都是被允许的”，带有一些得体的忧郁色彩。当然，和尼采这一最有名的行刺上帝者一样，他最终疯掉了，但还是值得冒这个险的，而面对这种悲剧的结局，荒谬精神中的本质冲动会问：“这证明了什么呢？”

因此，陀思妥耶夫斯基的小说，比如《日记》，提出了荒谬的问题。它们为死亡、欣喜、“可怕的自由”创造了逻辑，沙皇的荣耀变得人性化起来。一切都好，什么都被允许，没有可恶的东西——这些是荒谬的判断。但这又是多么惊人的创造啊，其中的火与冰等创造物对我们来说是那么熟悉。这个激情四射的冷漠世界——冷漠在它们内心深处轰鸣，对于我们来说根本就不恐怖，我们在其中发现自己每天都有的焦虑。或许没有人像陀思妥耶夫斯基那样，赋予这个荒谬的世界那样熟悉而又折磨人的魅惑。

但是他的结论是什么呢？有两段话表明了完全抽象的逆转，这引导了作者收获新的启示。那个采取了合乎逻辑的自杀行为之人的论断激起了批评者的抗议，而陀思妥耶夫斯基在以下的《日记》部分详述了此人的立场，并且这么总结道：“如果对永生的信任对人类十分必要（以至于没了它人就要发展到自杀），那么它必定是正常的人性状态。鉴于此，人类灵魂中的永生无疑是存在的。”然后在他最后一部小说的最后几页，在与上帝之间那种宏大的搏斗最后，几个孩子问阿辽沙：“卡拉马佐夫，宗教说的是真的吗，我们会死而复生，我们还会重逢？”阿辽沙回答：“当然，我们还会重逢，我们会高兴地告诉对方都发生了什么事情。”

于是基里洛夫、斯塔夫罗金，还有伊万都输了。《卡拉马佐夫兄弟》对《群魔》回答。而这确实是一个结论。阿辽沙的话没有梅什金公爵[87]的话含糊，后者生活在永远的现在中，略带微笑与冷漠，而这种幸福的状态或许正是公爵所说的永生。相反，阿辽沙清楚地说：“我们会重逢。”不再有自杀和发疯的问题，对于确信永生及其带来的愉悦的人来说，有什么用呢？人用自己的神性换来了幸福。“我们会高兴地告诉对方都发生了什么事情。”于是基里洛夫的枪声再一次回响在俄国的某个地方，然而世界仍在珍视自己盲目的希望。人们无法理解“那一点”。

因此，向我们娓娓诉说的不是一个荒谬小说家，而是一个存在主义小说家。这一跨跃同样动人，并且为激发自己的艺术赋予了高贵的气质。这是一种激动人心的默许，受到怀疑、不确定和热情的严重影响。陀思妥耶夫斯基在谈到《卡拉马佐夫兄弟》时写道：“本书自始至终贯穿的一个主要问题就是我一生都有意识或无意识地深受其折磨的问题，那就是上帝的存在。”难以置信的是，一部小说便足以将一生遭受的苦痛转化为令人愉快的确定性。某评论员[88]准确地指出，陀思妥耶夫斯基站在伊万一边，积极乐观的章节耗费了三个月的工夫，而他所称的“亵渎行为”只用了三周便在一种兴奋的状态中写就。他的人物没有一个不带那种肉中刺，没有一个不使之恶化，没有一个不在情感与非道义中寻求补救方式。[89]无论如何，让我们保留这一疑问。这里涉及的作品在对比下显得比白昼的阳光还要耀眼，这可以让我们把握人与其希望间的斗争。到达终点后，创造者会作出对其人物不利的选择。而这种矛盾可以让我们作出一个区分，这里所论及的不是一部荒谬的作品，而是一部提出荒谬问题的作品。

陀思妥耶夫斯基的答复是屈辱，用斯塔夫罗金的话说就是“羞耻”。相反，荒谬的作品不会给出答复；这便是全部差异所在。在最后我们要特别注意这一点：在这部作品中与荒谬产生矛盾的不是其基督徒的特性，而是它对一种未来生活的昭示。既信仰基督又表现出荒谬，这是可能的。基督徒不相信未来生活的例子是有的。因而对艺术作品来说，应当可以确定一种荒谬分析的方向，而这也应该能从前几章中预见到。它促进了“福音书之荒谬性”的提出，阐明了确信并不妨碍怀疑这一观点，影响颇丰。但是显然，《群魔》的作者尽管熟悉这些套路，最后还是选择了一条极其不同的道路。这个创造者对其人物的回答，也就是陀思妥耶夫斯基对基里洛夫的回答，让人大吃一惊，实际上该回答可以总结为：存在是虚幻的，也是永恒的。

昙花一现的创造

我于是从这一点意识到，无法永远回避希望，希望甚至可以困扰那些想要摆脱它的人，这是我在此讨论的作品中发现的兴趣所在。至少在创造的领域内，我可以列举一些真正荒谬的作品。[90]然而凡事必有一个开端，此论述的对象是某种忠实性。教会对异教徒一直都严酷无情，只因她认为没有比一个误入歧途的孩子更糟糕的敌人了。有关诺斯替教派[91]厚颜无耻的记录与摩尼教[92]坚忍不拔的精神，比所有的祷文对建立正统教义的贡献都要大。在一定程度上，同样的情况也适用于荒谬。人们认清自己的路线是通过发现背离路线的路径。在荒谬推理的最后，从其逻辑所持有的一种立场看，这问题不是对又扮上自己最动人伪装的希望表现得无动于衷的问题。这显示出荒谬的禁欲行为之艰难，尤其是显示了时刻保持警觉的必要性，并因此确认了本书的大体框架。

如果说列举荒谬的著作仍为时尚早，但至少可以针对创造性的立场得出一个结论，这是一个可以让荒谬的存在达到圆满的结论。消极的思想更能满足艺术的要求，理解一部伟大的作品必须看到其灰暗与耻辱的部分，正如认识白就要知道黑一样。用泥去雕塑，“徒劳”地去工作和创造，知道自己的创造没有未来，眼见自己的作品毁于一旦，同时又意识到，从根本上说，这同矗立了几个世纪的建筑一样无关紧要——这是荒谬思想好不容易认可的智慧。否定一个，放大另一个，同时执行这两个任务，是向荒谬的创造者打开的道路。他必须赋予虚无以颜色。

这促成了对艺术品的一种特殊构想。一位创造者的作品常常被当作一系列孤立的见证，于是艺术家与作家困惑不已。一种深刻的思想一直处在“形成”的状态中；它吸收了一种生活的体验，并表现出它的形态。同样，一个人唯一的创造在其后续多样的面貌——作品——中得到强化。这些作品接二连三地出现，相互补充，相互纠正或相互赶超，也相互矛盾。如果说有什么会结束一种创造的话，那它不是失明的艺术家胜利而虚幻的呼喊：“我已尽言”，而是创造者的死亡，他关闭了自己的体验，合上了关于自己的天才之书。

那种努力，那种超人的清醒头脑不一定对读者显而易见。人类创造中没有奥秘，意愿完成了这一奇迹，然而至少没有无秘密的真正创造。诚然，接连不断的作品只是同一种思想的一系列相似品，但还有可能设想另一种创造者，他们并肩前进。他们的作品之间似乎没有什么关联，从某种程度上说还是相互矛盾的，但如果整体来看的话，便显示出其本质上的同类性。例如，它们都从死亡中获取确定性的意义，都从其作者的生活中得到最明亮的光。在作者去世的那一刻，他一系列的作品便只是一堆败笔。可是如果这些败笔之间产生了共振，那么创造者就成功复制了自我状态的形象，从而空气中便回荡着被他占有的毫无意义的秘密。

在此，为取得支配地位已付出了巨大的努力，然而人类的智慧则要大的多，它只会清楚地指明由意志控制的那一面创造。我在其他地方已经指出了一个事实，那就是人类的意志除为了保持清醒外别无他图，但这也无法离开锤炼。在有关耐心与清醒的练习中，创造是最行之有效的，它同样也惊人地证明了人类仅有的尊严：对自身状况的不屈反抗，锲而不舍于一种所谓无果的努力。这需要每天的努力，对自我的克制，对真理局限性的准确估计，分寸与实力。这就是禁欲，为了重复与标注时间，一切都是“徒劳”。或许伟大的艺术品本身没有那么重要，其重要之处在于它期待一个人承受的苦难，在于它为这个人所提供的克服自身幻觉并一步步靠近自己赤裸裸的现实的机会。

不要在美学上出错。我在此并非要求，一篇论文要不厌其烦地探询，不断地进行无果的阐述。如果你清楚地理解了我的论述，你会发现我的要求恰恰相反。论述小说是一种想要证明什么的作品，是最惹人厌恶的那种，它经常是由一种自以为是的思想激发而成。你会论证那种确信自己占有的真理，而那些只是人们提出的观点，是与思想相对的。其创造者是那些自惭形秽的哲学家。相反，我所说的或者我所想象的那些人，他们是清醒的思想者。在思想对自己置之不理的时刻，他们高举自己作品的形象，正如一种受到限制而又充满反抗精神的致命思想的显著标志。

或许他们证明了什么，可是那些证明是小说家为自己而不是为整个世界提供的。最重要的是，小说家应该在具体事物中取得胜利，这是他们的高贵所在。让种种抽象的力量在其中蒙羞的思想，已经为他们准备好了这种完全的肉体上的胜利。当他们完全如此的时候，肉体便会同时让创造散发出自己所有荒谬的光辉。毕竟，讽刺性哲学家创作充满激情的作品。

任何弃绝一致性的思想都颂扬多样性，而多样性是艺术的归宿。唯一使精神得到释放的思想是不去打扰它的思想，这思想明确它的限制与行将到来的结局。没有什么理论学说能对它产生诱惑，它静候着工作与生活的成熟。如果作品脱离了精神，它就会再一次用一种近乎低沉的声音表达一种永远没有希望的灵魂。或者，假如厌倦于自我行为的创造者意欲转身而去，它便什么也不会表达。这是对等的。

于是我期望从荒谬的创造中获取我从思想中得到的东西——反抗、自由和多样性。不久它就会彰显出自己完全的无用性。在日复一日的努力尝试中，智慧与激情相互结合，相互取悦，而荒谬之人从中发现了一种可使其实力最大化的锻炼方式。于是必需的勤奋、顽强与清醒类似于征服者的立场。创造就像是赋予一个人的命运以一种形状，对于所有这些人物而言，作品对他们的定义至少不亚于他们对作品的定义。演员教给我们：在“是什么”与“表现为什么”之间没有界线。

我要重申，所有这些都没有什么实际意义。在通往自由的过程中仍有一段路要走，对这些相互联系的头脑（不管是创造者还是征服者）所作的最后努力，就是把他们也从自己的事业中解脱出来：做到承认那作品，不论是否是征服、爱情或创造；使任何个体生活都达到完全无用这一圆满结果。实际上，那在作品的完成上给予了他们更多的自由，正如开始意识到他们被赋予的这种生活的荒谬性，从而不遗余力地投入其中。

剩下的就是命运了，其唯一的出路是致命的。在死亡这种单独的致命性以外，一切都是自由，毋论是喜悦还是快乐。这个世界仍是人主宰的世界，对他形成限制的是对另一个世界的幻觉。其思想的结果不再是自我否定，而是开出形象的花朵。它只是在嬉戏——肯定是在虚构之中，然而这些虚构除了人类忍受的痛苦外没有其他深度，而且同人类的痛苦一样没有穷尽。不是从供人消遣并蒙蔽人心的神话传说中，而是从人间的面孔、姿态及戏剧中，可以总结出一种艰难的智慧与短暂的热情。

西西弗斯[93]神话

众神判处西西弗斯永不休止地把一块大石头滚上山顶，到了山顶石头又在自身重量的作用下滚落下去。他们的理由是，再没有比看不到希望的徒劳更可怕的惩罚方法了。

如果你相信荷马的话，那么西西弗斯便是凡人中最聪明、最审慎的一个。在另一个传说中，他又被安排去扮演拦路强盗的角色。这里我没发现什么矛盾，而关于他是怎么成了地狱里只能做无用功的苦力，众说纷纭。首先，有指责说他怠慢了诸神，窃取了他们的机密。伊索普斯[94]的女儿伊琴娜被朱庇特[95]劫走，父亲对女儿的失踪大为震惊，便向西西弗斯诉怨。西西弗斯知道这起绑架的原委，便主动告诉了他，但有一个条件，就是伊索普斯要为科林斯堡供水。比起天火雷电，西西弗斯更喜欢水带来的恩泽。为此他被罚下地狱。而荷马告诉我们，西西弗斯用锁链缚住了死神，普路托[96]无法忍受地狱的荒凉、落寞，便派战神去把死神从她的征服者手里解救出来。

还说，西西弗斯临死前，突然想考验一下妻子对他的爱，便命妻子不要埋葬自己的尸体，而是把它扔到公共广场的中央。西西弗斯在地狱醒了过来。在那里他要处处服从，与他在人间享受的爱完全不同，使他饱受困扰，于是他从普洛托那里获准重回人间去惩戒自己的妻子。可是当再一次见到这个世界的面貌时，他享受着阳光的照耀和水流的滋润，还有那温暖的石头和大海，再也不想回到那黑暗的地狱了。来自地狱的召唤、怒气、警告都无济于事。他面对蜿蜒的海湾、闪光的海水、微笑的大地，又在人间生活了多年。诸神是时候采取措施了。于是墨丘利[97]来了，他抓住这个无耻之人的衣领，将他从快乐中拽了出来，强行把他带回了地狱，在那里巨石已为他备好了。

你已经看明白了，西西弗斯是荒谬的英雄。他的激情和他的痛苦成就了这个英雄人物。他对诸神的蔑视、对死亡的痛恨、对生活的热情为他带来了那不可言状的惩罚——运用全身心的精力去完成无用功。这是世俗的热情必须要付出的代价。关于西西弗斯在地狱的事情我们一无所知。神话都是用想象吹活的，至于这个神话，人们看到的只是一个人的全部劳作，他费力抬起一块巨石，然后滚动巨石，成百上千次把它推上一个斜坡；人们看到的是一张拧紧的脸，面颊紧贴着石头，肩膀撑着沾满泥土的大石块，双脚插入土里，每迈出新的一步双臂都要伸展拉伸，人身安全只有靠那双沾满泥土的手来保障。漫长劳作的最后是紧贴头顶的天空和没有边际的时间，此时目标便达成了。然后西西弗斯看着石头冲下山去，没一会便到了下面的世界，从那里，他又得重新把石头推上山顶。他又回到了平地。

正是这种往返、停歇，使我对西西弗斯产生了兴趣。那张磨炼得如石头般的脸已然成了石头。我看着这个人走回山下，迈着沉重而稳健的步伐，走向一种他永远不知道终点的折磨。这段喘息时间和他所要遭受的折磨一样，定时回来，这便是意识的时刻。每当他走下山顶，慢慢陷入众神的巢穴，他都高过自己的命运，强于那块巨石。

如果说这个神话是个悲剧，那是因为它的主人公是有意识的。如果他每迈一步都充满了胜利的希望，那么何谓对他的折磨呢？今天的劳动人民每天都在完成同样的任务，这种命运堪称荒谬，但是只有到了意识出现时（这种情况很少出现），它才是悲惨的。西西弗斯是众神的无产者，手无缚鸡之力，心有反抗精神，他完全明白自己的悲惨处境；这正是他下山期间所思考的。清醒的头脑是他痛苦的原因，但同时也加冕了他的胜利。没有轻蔑征服不了的命运。

因此，倘若走下坡路时可以充满悲伤，那么也可以充满欢乐。这话并不过分。我想象着西西弗斯走向他的石头，悲伤开始酝酿。如果大地的形象深深地刻入记忆，如果快乐的召唤已十分迫切，那么悲伤在心中郁积：这便是石头的胜利，这就是那个石头。无尽的忧伤难以承受，这就是我们的客西马尼[98]之夜。然而雄辩的真理一旦被认识就要幻灭。因而俄狄浦斯[99]在起初不知情的时候是服从于命运的，而从他知道的那一刻起，他的悲剧便开始了。同时，失明而又绝望的俄狄浦斯意识到，联系他与这个世界的唯一纽带是一个女孩冰冷的手臂。于是便有了一段掷地有声的精彩话语：“尽管历经种种磨难，我年事已高，灵魂高尚，这让我最终发现，一切安好。”所以说索福克勒斯[100]的俄狄浦斯，同陀思妥耶夫斯基的基里洛夫一样，都给出了荒谬胜利的法则。先贤的智慧肯定了现代的英雄主义。

人们要发现荒谬，就肯定要忍不住写一本幸福指南。“什么！用这种狭隘的方式？……”然而，只有一个世界，快乐与荒谬是同一块土地的两个儿子，是不可分的。如果说要得到快乐就必须发现荒谬，那就错了，同样地，说荒谬来自于快乐，也是不正确的。俄狄浦斯说“我觉得，一切安好”，这一说法是神圣的。它在荒芜而有限的人类宇宙间回响，告诫人们一切都没有耗尽，从来就没有耗尽过。一个神带着不满与对无效痛苦的偏爱进入这个世界，而它把这个神驱逐了出去。它还把命运变成了一种人的事情，必须在人中间得到解决。

西西弗斯所有静默的快乐都包含其中。他的命运属于他自己，他的石头受他左右。同样，当荒谬的人思考自己的痛苦时，他令所有被人膜拜的偶像都哑然失声。在这个突然间恢复沉寂的世界，大地上无数游荡的细微声音纷纷升起。来自所有面孔的无意识的、秘密的召唤、诱惑，它们是胜利必然付出的代价，并与之相对。有阳光就会有阴影，我们必须认识黑夜。荒谬的人说“好”，然后便会不停地努力。如果有属于个人的命运，那么便不存在更高层次的命运，或者至少只有一种命运被他认为是不可避免而又可鄙的。对其余而言，他则自知是自己生活的主人。就在人回看自己生活的微妙时刻，也就是西西弗斯又回到石头那去的时候，在那微不足道的转折处，他会思索其命运中那一系列毫无关联的行动，由自己施行，在记忆中组合，由他的死亡封存。因此，他相信有关人性的一切完全源自人性，如渴望光明并且知道黑暗无边的盲人，仍然在前进。石头还在滚动。

我把西西弗斯留在山脚！人们总会一次又一次地找回自己的负担。西西弗斯告诫我们，还有更高的忠实，它可以否定神灵，举起巨石。他最终也发现，一切安好。从此，这个没有主人的宇宙在他看来，既不贫瘠，也非无用。那块石头的每一颗微粒，那座夜色笼罩的山上的每一片矿石，本身都是一个世界。迈向高处的挣扎足够填充一个人的心灵。人们应当想象西西弗斯是快乐的。

附录　卡夫卡作品中的希望与荒谬

卡夫卡的全部艺术所在就是强迫读者重读。其作品的结尾，或作品结尾的缺失，反映的是一种阐释意义，但是没有用清楚明白的语言揭示出来，反而需要读者从另一个视角重读故事，直至意义得到证实。有时对作品的阐释可能会有两种结果，所以有必要进行二次阅读，这便是作者想要的，但是如果对卡夫卡作品中的所有东西都细致入微地进行解读，也不合适。象征总是普遍意义上的，不论其翻译多么精准，艺术家也只能还原它动作的含义：不存在字对字的翻译。况且，没有比象征作品更难理解的东西了。一种象征往往超越了运用这种象征的人，使他实际所说多于他有意识要表达的。从这一点来说，把握这种象征的最可靠办法就是不要去激发意象，不要抱着一种先入为主的态度开始这项任务，不要去找寻藏匿的暗流。特别是对于卡夫卡而言，遵循他的规则，通过外部因素看戏剧冲突，通过形式读他的小说，是说得过去的。

对于漫不经心的读者来说，乍看，它们都是些让人不安的历险，人物在颤抖中坚韧不拔，探索着自己从不明确的问题。在《审判》中，约瑟夫·K被指控了，但他不知道因何罪名。他无疑极想为自己辩护，但还是不知道为什么。律师觉得他的案子很难办，在此期间他也不忘吃饭、读报、恋爱。然后他被审判了，但法庭很黑暗。他有很多不理解，只知道自己被判有罪，但是是什么罪他也不去想。有时他会对这事产生一些怀疑，但还是继续活着。没过多久，两个穿着考究的绅士模样的警官找到他，请他和他们走一趟。他们非常客气地把他引到一个废弃的郊外，将他的头搁在一块石头上，割破了他的喉咙。死前这个有罪之人只是说了一句：“像条狗。”

你可以看到，在一个最明显的特征恰好是自然性的故事里，很难扯上象征。自然性是很难理解的一种范畴，有些作品中的事件对读者而言是自然的，而在其他（当然很少）作品中，对角色而言，他认为发生在自己身上的事是自然的。有一个奇怪但是很明显的悖论，角色的经历越不同寻常，故事的自然性就越显著：一个人的生活是怪异的，而他则简简单单地接受了这种生活，两者之间存在着不一致，而我们由这种不一致感受到的分歧决定了这种自然性。似乎这种自然性就是卡夫卡式的，而人们也非常了解《审判》的意思是什么。人们已经论及人类状况的一种形象，这是毋庸置疑的，但这让问题既简单又复杂起来。我是指小说的意义更加为卡夫卡个人所专有。从某种程度上看，拥有发言权的是他，尽管他承认说是我们在发言。他在生活，他被判有罪。从小说的前几页中，他就认识到了这一点，那是他在这个世界上的追求，然而一旦他力求应付这一点，他丝毫不惊奇自己能够做到。对自己缺乏惊诧之情，他永远也不会表现出诧异。荒谬作品的初始迹象正是通过这些矛盾被辨认出来。思想会把自己的精神悲剧投射到具体的事物上，而该做法凭借的只是一种永久性的悖论，这种悖论为色彩赋予了表达虚无的能力，为日常行为赋予了传达永恒企望的力量。

同样，《城堡》或许是某种行动上的神学，但首先它是一个个体的历险，一种心灵的历险，一种人的历险，那心灵追求优雅，那人向世界客体追问他们高贵的秘密，向女人们诘问沉睡在她们心中的诸神的信息。自然，《变形记》进而代表了一种清醒的道德准则的可怕意象，而这种结果的出现同样是由于人们在意识到自己不费吹灰之力便表现出的兽性时，会感到惊愕不已。在这种基本的晦涩中便掩藏着卡夫卡的秘诀。这些永久性的振动——从自然到特别，从个体到普遍，从悲剧到平庸，从荒谬到逻辑，贯穿于他的作品，赋予它共鸣与意义。必须一一列举这些悖论，强化这些矛盾，方能理解荒谬的作品。

实际上，一种象征表现了两个平面，思想与感觉的两种世界，以及包含他们之间一致性的词典。这一词典是最难拟定的，然而意识到这两个面对面的世界就相当于找到了其诀窍之间关系的踪迹。在卡夫卡那里，这两个世界一方是日常生活的世界，另一方是超自然渴望的世界。[101]似乎在这里我们见证了尼采的话被没完没了地利用：“重大问题比比皆是。”

人的生活状况（而且这是所有文学作品的共性）中不仅有一种不可替代的高贵，还有一种基本的荒谬性，两者巧遇，天然成趣。我重申，人类精神中的非人性部分与肉体的短暂快乐之间产生了荒唐的分裂，而在这种分裂中两者都得到了突显。荒谬的是，产生这种分裂的应该是属于这个身体的心灵，而它不加节制地超越了这身体。任何想表现这种荒谬性的人都必须在一系列相似的对比中赋予其生命，所以卡夫卡用平庸来表达悲剧，用逻辑来表达荒谬。

演员对一个悲剧角色投入的精力越多，他就越会小心翼翼不去夸大。如果他的表现有节制，那么他激起的恐惧就会没有节制。在这一方面，希腊悲剧让人受益匪浅。在一部悲剧作品中，命运往往在逻辑性与自然性的伪装下得到更好的突显。俄狄浦斯的悲剧提前就得到昭示。他会实施谋杀与乱伦，这是冥冥之中就已经确定的。戏剧完全致力于表现这种逻辑体系，这种体系会通过一步步的推理最终让主人公的不幸达到顶点。仅仅告知我们这种不寻常的命运几乎没什么恐怖可言，因为那是不可能发生的事，但是如果其发生的必然性是通过由日常生活、社会、状态、熟悉的情感构成的体系展示给我们的，那么恐惧就变得神圣起来。使人产生动摇的反抗逼迫人说“那是不可能的”，而在这种反抗中有一种让人感到绝望的确定性元素，而这种确定性可能就是“那一点”。

这便是希腊悲剧的全部奥秘，或者至少是其奥秘的一个方面，因为还有一种相反的方式可以帮助我们更好地理解卡夫卡。人心有一种不良倾向，只把让它崩溃的东西称为命运。但是快乐同样也是不需要理由的，它会以自己的方式出现，因为它是不可避免的，然而，现代人一旦意识到了这一点，他就会把功劳都归到自己身上。相反，关于希腊悲剧的特殊命运，以及那些被传奇故事所钟爱的人物，有很多值得大书特书的内容。这些处在最困难处境的人，如尤利西斯[102]，脱离了自我。要返回伊萨卡岛[103]并没有那么容易。

无论如何一定不能忘了将逻辑、平庸与悲剧联系到一起的秘密同谋。这便是为何《变形记》的主人公，有着怪异经历的萨姆沙是一个推销员。这也是为什么他在变成一只虫子后，唯一困扰的是，老板会对他的缺勤而生气。他身上长出了多条腿和触角，脊椎拱起，肚子上出现了白点——我不能说这不令他惊讶，因为那样的话艺术效果会变质——这给他造成了“一丝烦恼”。卡夫卡的全部艺术所在就是这种特色。在其核心之作《城堡》中，平庸生活的细节突显出来，但在这部没有终结而一切又重新开始的怪诞小说中，表现出的是一种追求优雅的灵魂所必经的历险。在每一个属于伟大创造者的小伎俩中，同样可以找到那种问题到行动的转化，那种一般与特殊的重合。在《审判》中，主人公或许该取名为史密特或弗兰兹·卡夫卡，可是他却被叫作约瑟夫·K。他不是卡夫卡，可他又是卡夫卡。他是一个普通的欧洲人，同所有其他人一样，但他同样是一个实体的K，是这一有血有肉的等式中的未知数。

同样，如果卡夫卡想表达荒谬的话，他可以运用一致性。你一定知道那个疯子在浴缸钓鱼的故事。一个精神病治疗医师问他“鱼有没有上钩”，他得到了毫不客气的回答：“当然没有，你个傻瓜，这是浴缸。”这是一个具有巴罗克风格的故事，但是从故事中可以非常清晰地体会到这种荒谬的影响在多大程度上与一种过度的逻辑相联系。卡夫卡的世界事实上是一种难以描绘的宇宙，人们在其中恣意享受这种在浴缸钓鱼的折磨人的奢华，明知自己会一无所获。

因此我看到的是一个有着荒谬原则的作品。例如，就《审判》而言，我的确可以说这是一次完全的胜利。肉体胜出，什么也不缺失：不缺少那种未明确表达的反抗（但这显示在文字之中），不缺少清醒而沉默的绝望（但这显示在创造之中），也不缺少小说人物直至最后死亡还在展示的那种令人惊叹的自由态度。

这个世界并没有它看起来那么封闭。在这个停滞不前的宇宙，卡夫卡将引入一种特殊形式的希望。从这一点上说，《审判》与《城堡》没有遵循同样的方向，它们之间是相互补充的关系。这种由此及彼的前进，代表了逃避领域中一种巨大的征服，很难被察觉。《审判》提出一个问题，《城堡》从某种程度上解决这一问题。前者按照一种类科学的方法描述，没有作结论；后者从一定程度上说，采用了解释的方式。《审判》作诊断，《城堡》设想了一种治疗方法，但这里提出的补救办法不会治愈病情，只是把这种病又带回到正常生活中，使人们从某种意义上（我们可以想见克尔凯郭尔）对之加以珍视。土地测量员K除了折磨自己的焦虑外，无法想象还有其他焦虑。他四周那些人依附于那种虚无的无名之痛，似乎痛苦显现出一种特权面貌。弗丽达对K说：“自从认识了你，当你不在的时候，我是多么地需要你，我感到那么的孤独。”这种巧妙的补救办法让我们去爱摧毁自己的东西，使希望从一个没有出口的世界一跃而起，这一突然的“跨跃”让一切都改变了，而这便是这场存在主义革命与《城堡》本身的奥秘。

很少有作品能在其发展中比《城堡》还要严密。被任命为城堡土地测量员的K到了村子里，可是从村子到城堡，要沟通是很难的。在数百页的描写中，K坚持搜寻自己的道路，不断前进，运用花招与各种权宜之计，从不愠怒，试图带着一种令人不安的善意来承担托付给自己的责任。每一章都有一种新的障碍，也是一个新的开始，它不是一种逻辑的方法，却是连贯的。这种连贯性的范围便构成了作品的悲剧特征。当K打电话给城堡时，他听到的是困惑而混杂的声音，模糊不清的笑声，从远方传来的诱惑。这足以满足他的愿望，正如那些出现在夏日天空中的若干迹象，或是那些夜晚的期盼一样，它们是我们生活下去的理由。这里我们发现了为卡夫卡所独有的忧郁的奥秘。实际上，在普鲁斯特的作品或者普罗提诺[104]的领域中，也能发现同样的东西：对一种失去的天堂的怀恋。奥尔加说：“巴纳巴斯早上跟我说他要去城堡时，我很伤心，那很可能是徒劳的旅程，没有希望，还浪费时间。”卡夫卡把他整个作品的赌注都压在这一暗示性的表达上——“很可能”，然而于事无补，这里对永久性的追求是小心翼翼的。卡夫卡的人物，那些被激发起的机械人，为我们提供了一种精确形象，即当我们被剥夺了自己的消遣[105]并被完全移交给神圣的耻辱时所具有的形象。

在《城堡》中，那种对平庸的屈从成了一种道德准则。K非常希望城堡能接收他，由于无法独自达成这一愿望，他便竭尽全力想成为这个村子的居民，丢掉大家对他的陌生感，以此赢得那种特权。他想要的是一份职业，一个家，一个健康的正常人应有的生活。他再也忍受不了这种疯癫，他想变得理性起来。他想摆脱那种奇特的诅咒，这种诅咒让他与这个村子形同陌路。有关弗丽达的插曲从这一点上说是有意义的。倘若他让这个认识一名城堡官员的女人做自己的情妇，那是因为她的过去。他从她身上得到一些超越自己的东西——同时他也知道是什么让她永远也配不上城堡。这会让人想起克尔凯郭尔对雷吉娜·奥尔森异常的爱情。在有些人身上，燃烧他们的永恒之火足够他们烧毁离自己最近之人的心。把不是上帝的东西交给上帝这一致命的错误，同样是《城堡》中这一段插曲的主题，但是对于卡夫卡来说，这似乎算不上错误，而是一种教义，一种“跨跃”。没有什么东西不是上帝的。

更加意味深长的是，土地测量员和弗丽达分手这一事实，分手为的是走近巴纳巴斯的姐妹们，要知道巴纳巴斯家可是村子里唯一被城堡还有这个村子完全遗弃的。大女儿阿马利娅拒绝了一个城堡官员给她的可耻建议，而那随之而来的咒骂让她永远也得不到上帝的爱。不能为了上帝而失去自己的荣誉，就等于说不配得到上帝的恩慈。你会看出一个为存在哲学所熟悉的主题：与道德相反的真实，在这一点上还是有深远意义的。因为卡夫卡的主人公所追寻的——从弗丽达到巴纳巴斯的姐妹，正是从相信爱到崇拜荒谬的道路。在这里卡夫卡的思想又与克尔凯郭尔的相类似。“巴纳巴斯”的故事被安置在书的最后，这是不足为奇的。土地测量员的最后一次尝试是通过否定他的东西重新捕获上帝，是去辨识上帝，根据的不是我们美好与美丽的范畴，而是在他的冷漠、不公和仇恨中那空虚、可怕的方面之后。那个请求城堡接收自己的陌生人在行程的最后更加感到自己被放逐了，因为他没有忠于自己，抛弃了道义、逻辑以及思智上的真理，为的是进入上帝慈悲的荒漠，而他与生俱来的只是狂热的希望。[106]

“希望”这个词用在这里并不荒唐。相反，卡夫卡所描绘的状态越悲剧，希望就变得越坚定、越有攻击性。《审判》越表现出真实的荒谬，《城堡》表现出的慷慨激昂的“跨跃”就越动人，越不合情理，但是在这一种纯粹的状态中我们又发现了存在主义思想的悖论，正如人们对它的论述一样。例如，克尔凯郭尔说：“一定要扼杀掉世俗的希望；只有到那时人才能被真正的希望[107]所拯救。”这句话可以这么解释：“人要想了解《城堡》必先写作《审判》。”

诚然，论及卡夫卡的大部分人将他的作品定义为一种绝望的呼喊，不给人任何求助的希望，然而这话有待考量。他的作品中不止一种希望。在我看来，亨利·波尔多[108]乐观向上的作品独有一种沮丧，这是因为他的作品毫无值得品鉴之处，相反，马尔罗[109]的作品总是让人感到神清气爽，但关于两部作品共同的希望与绝望都没有疑义。我只发现，荒谬的作品本身就能导致我想要避免的不忠。这种作品只是一种无果状态的无效重复，是对短暂生命的冷静赞美，在此成了幻想的摇篮。它作解释，它赋予希望以形状。创造者再也无法将自己置身事外，它并非昔日的那个悲剧游戏，而是赋予作者的生命以意义。

奇怪的是，不管怎样，卡夫卡也好，克尔恺郭尔也好，甚至是舍斯托夫——简言之这些都是存在主义的小说家和哲学家，都旨在揭示荒谬及其后果，他们那有着相关启发性的作品从长远来看，应该会激起那声对希望的嘹亮的呼唤。

他们拥抱这位吞噬自己的上帝。希望正是通过谦卑才借机进入，因为这种存在的荒谬性向他们确保了一种更加超自然的现实。倘若这种生活轨迹最终引向上帝，那么毕竟还是有一种结果的。而克尔凯郭尔、舍斯托夫和卡夫卡的主人公们在行程中的坚持不懈与锲而不舍，为那种确定性所带来的振奋人心的力量提供了一种特殊保证。[110]

卡夫卡拒绝将自己道德上的高贵、清晰、美德与连贯性托付于自己的神，只想更好地落入其怀抱。荒谬被认可与接受，人要顺从于它，但从那时起我们知道它已不再是荒谬了。在人类状态的范围内，还有比容许从这种状态中逃脱更伟大的希望吗？正如我再次所见，存在主义思想在这方面（且对立于现下观点）如置身于浩瀚希望之海的一叶扁舟。正是这种早期基督教的希望和信息的传播点燃了旧世界。然而在塑造了一切存在主义思想特征的跨跃中，在那种坚持中，在对一种没有表象的神明的调查中，怎能看不到那否定自身的清醒之标志呢？人们仅仅把这称之为骄傲，为了自我救赎而可放弃的骄傲。这样一种否定应是成果颇丰的，但这改变不了那一事实。在我眼里，清醒的道德标准同所有骄傲一样，不会因被称作无效而降低，要知道，一种真理在其定义下也是无效的。一切事实皆如此。在一个万物既定、无所解释的世界，一种价值或超自然的多产性，是一种没有实义的概念。

无论如何，于此你可以了解卡夫卡的作品遵循了何种思想传统。把从《审判》到《城堡》的发展看作不可避免，这是明智的。约瑟夫·K和土地测量员K只是吸引卡夫卡的两极。[111]用他的话说就是，其作品很有可能并不荒谬，但这不应成为我们发现其高贵性与普遍性的阻碍。它们的出现得益于这一事实，即他极其充分地表现了从希望到忧伤，从绝望的智慧到有意的盲目这种平庸的过程。他的作品具有普遍性（一种真正荒谬的作品不具有普遍性），它表现了人受情感触动的面容；这种人逃避人性，从自己的诸多矛盾中得到信仰的理由，并在丰富的绝望中发现希望之光，把生活当作为准备死亡而进行的恐怖练习。这具有普遍性，因为其灵感具有宗教性质。像一切宗教一样，信仰它的人不会感到自己生命的重量。如果我知道这一点，如果我甚至可以赞赏它，我同样也能知道我追寻的不是普遍性的东西，而是真实的东西。两者完全不可能共存。

如果我说，真正无望的思想碰巧是由相反的标准界定的，悲剧作品或许描写的是一个乐天派的生活，其所有未来的希望都被放逐了，或许那一特殊的观点会更好理解。生活越是有波澜，想失去它的想法就越荒谬。这或许是在尼采作品中所感觉到的那种高傲的乏味之奥秘。在这种联系中，尼采似乎是从荒谬中得出一种美学的极端后果的唯一艺术家，因为他传递给我们的最后信息就是一种贫瘠而具有征服性的冷静，以及一种对任何形而上慰藉的坚决否定。

尽管如此，以上足以突出卡夫卡在本书结构中的重要地位，我们在此涉及了人类思想的局限。从这个词最广泛的意义上看，可以说其作品没有一处是不必要的。不管怎样，它全面提出了荒谬问题。假如有人想将这些结论与我们之前的论述作对比，将内容与形式作对比，将《城堡》的隐秘含义与塑造它的自然艺术作对比，将K充满激情与自豪感的追求与它发生的平庸背景作对比，那么人们就会意识到它的伟大所在了。如果怀旧是人类的标志，或许没有人会赋予这些悔恨的幽灵以这种热血与空间。同时人们也会感知到这种荒谬作品需要什么独特的高贵，或许在这里是找不到的。如果艺术的本质就是联结普通与特殊，联结一滴水的短暂永恒与其光彩的闪烁，那么通过他所展现的这两种世界间的距离来判断这位荒谬作家的伟大性，将变得更加合理。他的诀窍就是找到两种世界在最不相称之时的相遇点。

老实说，心底纯净的人到处都能发现这种人性与非人性交汇的几何轨迹。如果说浮士德与堂吉诃德是杰出的艺术创作，那是因为他们用自己世俗的双手为我们指出了那些不可计量的高贵性。可是头脑对他们双手触及的事实会加以否定，这一刻终会到来。这一刻来了，创造便不再被当作悲剧看待，只是被严肃地对待。那时的人是有希望的，但这不是他要做的事，他要做的是远离欺骗。而这正是我在卡夫卡对整个宇宙发出的强烈诉求之末所发现的。他的令人难以置信的裁决是：在这个丑陋而搅乱人心的世界里，即使鼹鼠也敢奢谈希望。[112]

[1]本体论是探究世界的本原或基质的哲学理论。——编者注

[2]此处是基于真理的相对价值的观点。而从男子气概的角度来看，对于此学者的软弱我们大可以付诸一笑。

[3]荷马史诗中的特洛伊王子，他骗走希腊斯巴达王墨涅拉奥斯的美貌妻子海伦，引发了特洛伊战争。——译者注

[4]西班牙作家塞万提斯所著小说《堂·吉诃德》中的主人公。——译者注

[5]在此不应忘记本书的论述是有相对性的。实际上，自杀可能会与更高尚的事件有关。例如，在中国革命中所谓的持不同政见者的政治自杀。

[6]尼采（1844—1900），德国哲学家、诗人，唯意志论的主要代表，创立“权力意志说”和“超人哲学”。——译者注

[7]陀思妥耶夫斯基的小说《群魔》中的主人公。——译者注

[8]我曾听说有一个贝尔格里诺斯的效仿者，是个战后作家，他完成第一本书后就自杀了，为的是引起人们对其著作的关注。关注的确引来了，但是书还是没被看好。

[9]阿瑟·叔本华（1788—1860），德国哲学家，唯意志论的创始人，认为意志是人的生命的基础，也是整个世界的内在本性，著有《意志和表象的世界》《论自然界的意志》等。——译者注

[10]卡尔·雅斯培（1883—1969），二十世纪德国的存在哲学大师。——译者注

[11]马丁·海德格尔（1889—1976），德国哲学家，在现象学、存在主义、解构主义、诠释学、后现代主义、政治理论、心理学及神学领域都有举足轻重的影响。——译者注

[12]这里所取并非荒谬的原意。这不是定义，而是对可能包含荒谬的诸多感情的一种罗列。并且，这种罗列有穷尽时，而荒谬却无法尽言。

[13]指萨特的小说《恶心》。——译者注

[14]巴门尼德（公元前515—前450？），古希腊哲学家，爱利亚学派创始人，认为思想与存在是同一的、无生灭的、不动的、单一的，著有用诗体写成的哲学著作《论自然》，现仅存残篇。——译者注

[15]理性主义承认，人的推理可以作为知识来源。一般认为随着笛卡尔的理论而产生。十七至十八世纪间主要在欧洲大陆上得以传播，本质上体现科学和民主，是启蒙运动的哲学基础。——编者注

[16]语出尼采《查拉图斯特拉如是说》第三部中“日出之前”一节。超人将万物从理性的绝对精神控制下解放出来，让偶然重新成为主宰。——译者注

[17]索伦·克尔凯郭尔（1813—1855），丹麦宗教哲学心理学家、诗人，现代存在主义哲学的创始人，后现代主义的先驱。——译者注

[18]卡尔·西奥多·雅斯贝尔斯（1883—1969），德国存在主义哲学家、神学家、精神病学家。——译者注

[19]列夫·舍斯托夫（1866—1938），俄国思想家、哲学家。——译者注

[20]马克斯·舍勒（1874—1928），德国哲学家和社会学家，哲学人类学的主要代表。——译者注

[21]康德（1724—1804），德国哲学家、德国古典唯心主义哲学创始人，主张自在之物不可知，人类知识是有限度的，提出星云假说。——译者注

[22]源于古希腊神话。阿里阿德涅是克里特岛上的公主，她为帮助心爱之人忒修斯杀掉迷宫中的米诺牛，解救雅典，交给他一只线团，引他破解了迷宫。这个线团称为阿里阿德涅之线，是忒修斯在迷宫中的生命之线。——译者注

[23]陀思妥耶夫斯基（1821—1881），俄国作家，其作品反映“小人物”的痛苦，人物异化心理刻画入微，主要作品有《白痴》《罪与罪》《卡拉马佐夫兄弟》等。——译者注

[24]西班牙传奇中的一个浪荡子，屡见于西方诗歌、戏剧中。——译者注

[25]埃德蒙德·胡塞尔（1859—1938），德国哲学家，二十世纪现象学学派创始人。——译者注

[26]马赛尔·普鲁斯特（1871—1922），法国小说家，其创作强调生活的真实和人物的内心，以长篇小说《追忆逝水年华》闻名。——译者注

[27]巴鲁克·斯宾诺莎（1632—1677），后改名为贝内迪特·斯宾诺莎（Benedictus Spinoza），荷兰哲学家，西方近代哲学史重要的欧陆理性主义者，与法国的笛卡尔和德国的莱布尼茨齐名。——译者注

[28]尤其有关特例的概念，是反对亚里士多德的。

[29]依格那丢·罗耀拉（1491—1556），西班牙人，是罗马天主教耶稣会的创始人，也是圣人之一。他在罗马天主教内进行改革，以对抗由马丁·路德等人所领导的基督新教宗教改革。——译者注

[30]可能有人认为这里我忽略了本质问题——信仰问题。但我并不是在检验克尔凯郭尔的哲学，或者舍斯托夫的哲学，再或者后面谈到的胡塞尔的哲学（那将需要一个不同的场合与一个不同的思想立场）；我只是从他们那里借来一个主题，并检验一下其结果是否适合于已确立的规则。这只是一个坚持问题。

[31]加里亚尼（1728—1787），意大利外交家、经济学家和作家。——译者注

[32]法国文化名流，常主持沙龙汇集知识分子，与卢梭、狄德罗和格里姆等名人交往甚密。——译者注

[33]我并不是说“排除上帝”，这么说仍等同于肯定。

[34]我再声明一次：这里质疑的并非是对上帝的肯定，而是这种肯定的逻辑。

[35]亨利·柏格森（1859—1941），法国哲学家，文笔优美，思想富于吸引力，曾获诺贝尔文学奖。——译者注

[36]即使是最严格的认识论也设定了形而上学的方法。正是从这点上讲，很多当代思想家的形而上学就在于没有他物，却拥有一种认识论。

[37]巴门尼德（约公元前515年——公元前5世纪中叶以后）是一位诞生在爱利亚（南部意大利沿岸的希腊城市）的古希腊哲学家，他第一次提出了“思想与存在是同一的”命题。——译者注

[38]普罗提诺（205—270），罗马帝国时代的希腊哲学家，新柏拉图主义奠基人。——译者注

[39]A—在那个时候，理性要么适应，要么就得消失。它选择了适应。在普罗提诺看来，变得有逻辑以后就会变得有了审美。隐喻取代了三段论法。
B—而且，这并非普罗提诺对现象学的唯一贡献。这一整体思想立场已包含在概念中，亚历山大时代的思想家对之极为钟爱，以致不仅有人的观点，也有苏格拉底的观点。

[40]希腊神话中的人物，歌手俄耳浦斯之妻，新婚夜被蟒蛇杀死，其夫以歌喉打动冥王，冥王准许她回生，但要求其夫在引她回阳世的路上不得回头看她，其夫未能做到，结果她仍被抓回到阴间。——译者注

[41]我所关注的是一种事实上的对比，而非一种谦逊的勉强替代品。荒谬之人与妥协之人是相对立的。

[42]有时数量构成质量。倘若最近重新阐释的科学理论可信，那么所有物质都是由能量中心构成的，其数量的多少决定其特性是否突出。十亿个离子与一个离子的差异不仅在数量上，也在质量上。从人类的经历中找到一个类似例子很容易。

[43]同样的思考也适用于与永久虚无状态这一观念一样有差别的一个概念。它既不从现实中索取，也不为其贡献。在虚无状态的心理学体验上，我们自己的虚无状态只有考虑到两千年之后所发生的事才能真正拥有意义。从其某一个方面来看，永久的虚无状态正是由将来的一定量生活构成，那些生活不属于我们。

[44]这里的意志只是施动者：意在保持清醒。它提供了一种生活的准则，可以察觉得到。

[45]重要的是一致性。我们在这里从接受世界出发，但是东方思想教导我们，人通过选择反对世界而能够沉溺于同样的逻辑尝试。这个同样合理，并给予了本文的视角和限度。然而当同样严格程度地追求世界的否定时，诸如关于作品的冷漠性，人们常常（用某些吠陀派的说法）获得同样的结果。在一部重要的著作——《选择》中，让·格勒尼埃以这种方式确立了名副其实的“冷漠哲学”。（吠陀是印度最古老的宗教文献和文学作品的总称。——译者注）

[46]阿兰（1868—1951），法国现象学家，受德国现象学家胡塞尔影响很大。——译者注

[47]歌德（1794—1832），德国诗人、作家，青年时代为狂飙运动的代表人物，集文学、艺术、自然科学、哲学、政治等成就于一身，写有不同体裁的大量文学著作，代表作为诗剧《浮士德》、小说《少年维特之烦恼》等。——译者注

[48]罗兰夫人（Manon Jeanne Phlipon，1754—1793），法国大革命时期著名的政治家，吉伦特党领导人之一。——译者注

[49]陀思妥耶夫斯基小说《卡拉马佐夫兄弟》的主人公。——译者注

[50]卢梭（1712—1778），法国思想家、文学家，其思想和著作对法国大革命和十九世纪欧洲浪漫主义文学产生巨大影响。在社会观方面，主张人们经协议订立契约，建成公民的社会；在教育观方面，提出“回归自然”，让儿童的身心自由发展。著作有《民约论》、小说《爱弥尔》和自传《忏悔录》等。——译者注

[51]参见拉歇尔·贝斯帕洛夫的《途径与十字路口》。——译者注

[52]《圣经·旧约》的一部，作者为古犹太国王所罗门，大约成书于公元前930年。——编者注

[53]德国中世纪传说中的一位术士，为获得青春、知识和魔力，将灵魂出卖给魔鬼；德国作家歌德曾创作同名诗剧。——译者注

[54]蒂尔索·德·莫利纳（约1582—1648），西班牙喜剧作家，写有喜剧四百多种，出版八十余种。在西班牙戏剧史上有一定的地位。《塞维利亚的骗子》创造出欧洲文学中的典型人物之一唐璜，莫里哀的讽刺喜剧《唐璜》，拜伦的长诗《唐璜》，都仿照剧中这一形象而写成。——译者注

[55]奥斯卡·米洛兹（1877—1939），诗人，外交官。生于当时归于俄罗斯皇帝（现今属白俄罗斯）统治之下的立陶宛地区。后前往巴黎，在那里度过了人生的最重要时刻，并偶遇鼎鼎大名的奥斯卡·王尔德。在欧洲游历多年，并参加了一战，加入立陶宛阵营，担任过外交官。在1931年，以被授予法国荣誉骑士勋章为契机，加入了法国籍。他的《米格尔·马纳拉》（Miguel Manara），描写了一个唐璜式的英雄，最终皈依于神无私的爱，找到心灵安慰的故事。——译者注

[56]剧情交代：唐璜潜入骑士长邸宅，企图调戏骑士长之女安娜。安娜呼救，骑士长闻声赶来，唐璜拔剑刺死骑士长后逃跑。后来当唐璜在墓地游荡时，发现了骑士长的塑像，于是他戏邀塑像共进晚餐，塑像点头应允。结局是骑士长塑像如约前来。地面裂开，火焰喷出，唐璜被拖下地狱。——译者注

[57]从完整意义上说，就他的错误而言。一个健全的立场同样包含谬误。

[58]歌德著作《少年维特之烦恼》中的主人公。——译者注

[59]又称方济各会，是天主教托钵修会之一。——译者注

[60]莎士比亚悲剧《奥赛罗》中狡猾残忍的反面人物，暗施毒计诱使奥赛罗出于嫉妒和猜疑将无辜的妻子苔丝德蒙娜杀死。——译者注

[61]神圣罗马帝国皇帝、匈牙利国王和波希米亚国王。——译者注

[62]莎士比亚悲剧《李尔王》中李尔王的诚实、善良的幼女。——译者注

[63]《李尔王》中葛罗斯特伯爵的儿子，改装后化名为“汤姆·白德兰”，继续服侍瞎眼的父亲，最后成为国王。——译者注

[64]我在此想到莫里哀的阿尔塞斯特。一切都是那么简单、明了、粗俗。阿尔塞斯特反对费兰特，色利曼纳反对艾里雅特，一种极端本质的荒谬结果之中的全部主题，还有诗句本身，“糟糕的诗句”，极少会像角色本质的乏味那样被强调。（以上提到的人物均为莫里哀剧作《恨世者》中的人物。——译者注）

[65]希腊神话中的海神，可以随心变幻自己的形状。——译者注

[66]歌剧《阿德里亚娜·莱科芙露尔》的女主角，剧本由阿图罗·柯劳替所作，是意大利作曲家契莱亚（1866—1950）最广为人知的作品。——译者注

[67]佛兰德斯是西欧的一个历史地名，泛指古代尼德兰南部地区，位于西欧低地西南部、北海沿岸，包括今比利时的东佛兰德省和西佛兰德省、法国的加来海峡省和北方省、荷兰的泽兰省。1337至1453年，英法两国曾为争夺它而展开‘百年战争’。——译者注

[68]三十年战争（1618—1648），是由神圣罗马帝国的内战演变而成的全欧参与的一次大规模战争。——译者注

[69]中欧一地区，包括波兰西南部、捷克和斯洛伐克北部以及德国东南部。——译者注

[70]希腊神话中的人物，因盗取天火予人而触怒宙斯，被罚锁于高加索山崖上，遭神鹰折磨，后被海格立斯所救。——译者注

[71]意大利东北部城市。——译者注

[72]位于耶路撒冷旧城东面，该山为犹太教和基督教的圣山。耶稣在橄榄山上度过了很多时间，教导门徒并作预言，也是耶稣被出卖后度过最后一夜的地方。——译者注

[73]阿尔蒂尔·兰波（1854—1891），十九世纪法国著名诗人，早期象征主义诗歌的代表人物，超现实主义诗歌的鼻祖。——译者注

[74]埃塞俄比亚旧名。兰波在这里度过了人生的大部分时间。——译者注

[75]歌德的长篇小说《威廉·麦斯特的学习时代》的主人公。——译者注

[76]奇怪的是，绘画中最需要理解力的一种，说到底只是一种视觉享受，它试图将现实还原为它的本质元素。它所保留的世界只有颜色。（这一点在雷捷身上表现得特别明显。）
雷捷（1881—1955），色彩立体派的代表。——译者注

[77]假如你停下来想一想，这其实解释了最糟糕的小说。几乎所有人都认为自己具备思考的能力，而从某种程度上说，无论对错，大家的确都在思考，但几乎没有人会设想自己是诗人或语言大师。从思想胜过风格的那一刻起，人们一窝蜂地侵入了小说的领域。
这并没有人们所说的那么致命。最好的会在引导下对自己提出更多严苛的要求，至于那些屈服的人，他们就不该存在。

[78]巴尔扎克（1799—1850），法国小说家，他的总标题为《人间喜剧》的巨著包括小说九十一部，反映了法国社会剧烈变革时期的现实生活，描绘了法国的人情风俗。——译者注

[79]萨德（1740—1814），法国作家，军人出身，著有长篇小说《美德的厄运》《朱莉埃特》等。——译者注

[80]梅尔维尔（1819—1891），美国小说家，作品多反映航海生活，富于现实感，代表作有《白鲸》《皮埃尔》等。——译者注

[81]司汤达（1783—1842），法国小说家，十九世纪法国现实主义文学的先驱，代表作有《红与黑》《巴马修道院》等。——译者注

[82]马尔罗（1901—1976），法国作家、政治活动家，戴高乐的追随者，著有长篇小说《征服者》《人类的命运》等。——译者注

[83]卡夫卡（1883—1924），奥地利小说家，现代派文学的先驱，作品象征着二十世纪的忧虑和渗透于西方社会的异化，著有长篇小说《判决》《城堡》等。——译者注

[84]如马尔罗的作品。但实际上，同时也有必要论述无法被荒谬思想所忽视的社会问题（即使这一问题可以提出若干彼此差别很大的解决办法）。然而，人必须要限制自己。

[85]“斯塔夫罗金：‘你相信在另一个世界中的永生吗？’基里洛夫：‘不相信，但我相信在这个世界里的永生。’”

[86]“人创造了上帝只是为了不至于自杀。这是对到这一刻为止的普遍历史所作的总结。”

[87]陀思妥耶夫斯基小说《白痴》中的主人公，即书中的“白痴”。——译者注

[88]俄国的乐评家席洛兹。

[89]纪德的评论古怪而又尖锐：几乎陀思妥耶夫斯基笔下的所有英雄都是一夫多妻。纪德（Andre Gide，1869—1951），法国作家、文艺评论家，曾获1947年诺贝尔文学奖。——译者注

[90]例如梅尔维尔的《白鲸》。

[91]诺斯替教（Gnosticism）是基督教异端派别，是罗马帝国时期在地中海东部沿岸各地流行的许多神秘主义教派的统称。——编者注

[92]摩尼教（Manichaeism）是三世纪在巴比伦兴起的世界性宗教。一般认为，摩尼教主要吸收犹太教、基督教等教义而形成自己的信仰。——编者注

[93]罗马神话中的人物，他是科林斯的建城者和国王。希腊古时的暴君，死后坠入地狱，被罚推石上山，但石在近山顶时又滚下，于是重新再推，如此循环不息。——译者注

[94]罗马神话中的河神。——译者注

[95]罗马神话中的人物，天空的统治者，部分神和人间英雄的父亲。——译者注

[96]罗马神话中的人物，地狱的统治者。——译者注

[97]罗马神话中的人物，众神的使者，商业、发明之神，盗窃的守护神。——译者注

[98]客西马尼园，福音书中所说的耶稣被犹大出卖而被大祭司抓捕前所在的地方，位于橄榄山下。耶稣在此作了最后的祷告，而门徒此时都在沉睡。——译者注

[99]希腊神话中忒拜的国王拉伊奥斯和王后约卡斯塔的儿子，他在不知情的情况下，杀死了自己的父亲并娶了自己的母亲。得知真相后，俄狄浦斯刺瞎了自己的双眼，在安提戈涅（他与母亲所生的女儿）的牵引之下漂泊四方。——译者注

[100]索福克勒斯（约公元前496—公元前406），雅典人，雅典三大悲剧作家之一，代表作为《俄狄浦斯王》。——译者注

[101]值得注意的是，卡夫卡的作品可以从一种社会批评的角度去非常合理地解读（如《审判》），而且极有可能没有选择的必要，两种解读都不错。从荒谬层面来看，我们前面已提到，对人的反抗针对的同样是上帝：伟大的革命总是形而上的。

[102]古希腊史诗《奥德赛》中的英雄。——译者注

[103]希腊西部爱奥尼亚海中群岛之一，是尤利西斯的故乡。——译者注

[104]普罗提诺（约205—270），罗马新柏拉图派哲学家。——译者注

[105]在《城堡》中，似乎帕斯卡式的“消遣”是由把K从他的焦虑中“分离”出来的助手来表现的。如果弗丽达最终成了其中一个助手的情妇，那是因为她更喜欢现实中的舞台，那可以分享痛苦的平庸生活。

[106]显然这只适用于卡夫卡所留给我们的《城堡》的未完成版本，但让人疑惑的是，作者在最后几章可能破坏了其小说基调的一致性。

[107]心灵的纯粹。

[108]亨利·波尔多（1870—1963），法国作家，传统主义流派的代表人物之一，法兰西学院院士。——译者注

[109]安德烈·马尔罗（1901—1976），法国小说家、评论家。——译者注

[110]《城堡》中唯一不怀希望的人物是阿马利娅，土地测量员与她形成最强烈的对比。

[111]有关卡夫卡思想的两个层面可比较《南方杂志》（以及美国的《党派评论》）出版的《在流放地》中的：“（人类的）罪行是毋庸置疑的。”以及《城堡》中的片段：“土地测量员K的罪行很难成立。”

[112]以上所述显然是对卡夫卡作品的一种解读，然而除解读外，只有说明没有什么可以阻挠人们从一种纯美学视角去思考它，才是合理的。比如，B.格罗图森在他给《审判》所作的精彩的序中，就只限于阐述他所谓的空想家（这种说法极为引人注目）的种种痛苦幻想，他比我们要明智得多。小说描述了一切，又什么也没有肯定，这是命运，或许也是该作品的伟大之处。

The Absurd Man

‘If Stavrogin believes, he does not think he believes.

If he does not believe, he does not think he does not believe.’

—THE POSSESSED

‘My field,’ said Goethe, ‘is time.’ That is indeed the absurd speech. What, in fact, is the absurd man? He who, without negating it, does nothing for the eternal. Not that nostalgia is foreign to him. But he prefers his courage and his reasoning. The first teaches him to live without appeal and to get along with what he has; the second informs him of his limits. Assured of his temporally limited freedom, of his revolt devoid of future and of his mortal consciousness, he lives out his adventure within the span of his lifetime. That is his field, that is his action, which he shields from any judgement but his own. A greater life cannot mean for him another life. That would be unfair. I am not even speaking here of that paltry eternity that is called posterity. Madame Roland relied on herself. That rashness was taught a lesson. Posterity is glad to quote her remark but forgets to judge it. Madame Roland is indifferent to posterity.

There can be no question of holding forth on ethics. I have seen people behave badly with great morality and I note every day that integrity has no need of rules. There is but one moral code that the absurd man can accept, the one that is not separated from God: the one that is dictated. But it so happens that he lives outside that God. As for the others （I mean also immoralism）, the absurd man sees nothing in them but justifications and he has nothing to justify. I start out here from the principle of his innocence.

That innocence is to be feared. ‘Everything is permitted,’ exclaims Ivan Karamazov. That, too, smacks of the absurd. But on condition that it be not taken in the vulgar sense. I don’t know whether or not it has been sufficiently pointed out that it is not an outburst of relief or of joy but rather a bitter acknowledgement of a fact. The certainty of a God giving a meaning to life far surpasses in attractiveness the ability to behave badly with impunity. The choice would not be hard to make. But there is no choice and that is where the bitterness comes in. The absurd does not liberate; it binds. It does not authorize all actions. Everything is per mitted does not mean that nothing is forbidden. The absurd merely confers an equivalence on the consequences of those actions. It does not recommend crime, for this would be childish, but it restores to remorse its futility. Likewise, if all experiences are indifferent, that of duty is as legitimate as any other. One can be virtuous through a whim.

All systems of morality are based on the idea that an action has consequences that legitimize or cancel it. A mind imbued with the absurd merely judges that those consequences must be considered calmly. It is ready to pay up. In other words, there may be responsible persons but there are no guilty ones, in its opinion. At very most such a mind will consent to use past experience as a basis for its future actions. Time will prolong time and life will serve life. In this field that is both limited and bulging with possibilities, everything in himself, except his lucidity, seems unforesee able to him. What rule, then, could emanate from that un reasonable order? The only truth that might seem instructive to him is not formal: it comes to life and unfolds in men. The absurd mind cannot so much expect ethical rules at the end of its reasoning as rather, illustrations and the breath of human lives. The few following images are of this type. They prolong the absurd reasoning by giving it a specific attitude and their warmth.

Do I need to develop the idea that an example is not necessarily an example to be followed （even less so if possible in the absurd world）and that these illustrations are not, therefore, models? Besides the fact that a certain vocation is required for this, one becomes ridiculous, with all due allowance, when drawing from Rousseau the conclusion that one must walk on all fours and from Nietzsche that one must maltreat one’s mother. ‘It is essential to be absurd,’ writes a modern author, ‘it is not essential to be a dupe.’ The attitudes of which I shall treat can assume their whole meaning only through consideration of their contraries. A sub-clerk in the post-office is the equal of a conqueror if consciousness is common to them. All experiences are indifferent in this regard. There are some that do either a service or a disservice to man. They do him a service if he is conscious. Otherwise, that has no importance: a man’s failures imply judge-ment, not of circumstances, but of himself.

I am choosing solely men who aim only to expend themselves or whom I see to be expending themselves. That has no further implications. For the moment I want to speak only of a world in which thoughts like lives are devoid of future. Everything that makes man work and get excited utilizes hope. The sole thought that is not mendacious is therefore a sterile thought. In the absurd world the value of a notion or of a life is measured by its sterility.

Don Juanism

If it were sufficient to love, things would be too easy. The more one loves the stronger the absurd grows. It is not through lack of love that Don Juan goes from woman to woman. It is ridiculous to represent him as a mystic in quest of total love. But it is indeed because he loves them with the same passion and each time with his whole self that he must repeat his gift and his profound quest. Whence each woman hopes to give him what no one has ever given him. Each time they are utterly wrong and merely manage to make him feel the need of that repetition. ‘At last,’ ex claims one of them, ‘I have given you love.’ Can we be surprised that Don Juan laughs at this? ‘At last? No,’ he says, ‘but once more.’ Why should it be essential to love rarely in order to love much?

Is Don Juan melancholy? This is not likely. I shall barely have recourse to the legend. That laugh, the conquering in solence, that playfulness and love of the theatre are all clear and joyous. Every healthy creature tends to multiply himself. So it is with Don Juan. But furthermore melancholy people have two reasons for being so: they don’t know or they hope. Don Juan knows and does not hope. He reminds one of those artists who know their limits, never go beyond them, and in that precarious interval in which they take their spiritual stand enjoy all the wonderful ease of masters. And that is, indeed: genius: the intelligence that knows its frontiers. Up to the frontier of physical death Don Juan is ignorant of melancholy. The moment he knows, his laugh bursts forth and makes one forgive everything. He was melancholy at the time when he hoped. Today, on the mouth of that woman he recognizes the bitter and comforting taste of the only knowledge. Bitter ? Barely: that nece sary imperfection that makes happiness perceptible!

It is quite false to try to see in Don Juan a man brought up on Ecclesiastes. For nothing is vanity to him except the hope of another life. He proves this because he gambles that other life against heaven itself. Longing for desire killed by satisfaction, that commonplace of the impotent man, does not belong to him. That is all fight for Faust who b lieved in God enough to sell himself to the devil. For Don Juan the thing is simpler. Molina’s ‘Burlador’ ever replies to the threats of hell: ‘What a long respite you give me!’ What comes after death is futile and what a long succession of days for whoever knows how to be alive! Faust craved worldly goods; the poor man had only to stretch out his hand. It already-amounted to selling his soul when he was unable to gladden it. As for satiety, Don Juan insists upon it, on the contrary. If he leaves a woman it is not absolutely because he has ceased to desire her. A beautiful woman is always desirable. But he desires another, and no, this is not the same thing.

This life gratifies his every wish and nothing is worse than losing it. This madman is a great wise man. But men who live on hope do not thrive in this universe where kindness yields to generosity, affection to virile silence, and communion to solitary courage. And all hasten to say: ‘He was a weakling, an idealist or a saint.’ One has to disparage the greamess that insults.

People are sufficiently annoyed （or smile that smile of complicity that debases what it admires）by Don Juan’s speeches and by that same remark that he uses on all women. But to anyone who seeks quantity in his joys, the only thing that matters is efficacy. What is the use of complicating the passwords that have stood the test? No one, neither the woman nor the man, listens to them, but rather to the voice that pronounces them. They are the rule, the convention, and the courtesy. After they are spoken the most important still remains to be done. Don Juan is already getting ready for it. Why should he give himself a problem in morality? He is not like Milosz’s Manara who damns himself through a desire to be a saint. Hell for him is a thing to be provoked. He has but one reply to divine wrath and that is human honour: ‘I have honour,’ he says to the Commander, ‘and I am keeping my promise because I am a knight.’ But it would be just as great an error to make an immoralist of him. In this regard, he is ‘like everyone else’: he has the moral code of his likes and dislikes. Don Juan can be properly understood only by constant reference to what he commonly symbolizes: the ordinary seducer and the sexual athlete. He is an ordinary seducer.[1] Except for the difference that he is conscious, and that is why he is absurd. A seducer who has become lucid will not change for all that. Seducing is his condition in life. Only in novels does one change condition or become better. Yet it can be said that at the same time nothing is changed and everything is transformed. What Don Juan realizes in action is an ethic of quantity, whereas the saint on the contrary tends towards quality. Not to believe in the profound meaning of things belongs to the absurd man. As for those cordial or wonderstruck faces, he eyes them, stores them up, and does not pause over them. Time keeps up with them. The absurd man is he who is not apart from time. Don Juan does not think of ‘collecting’ women. He exhausts their number and with them his chances of life. ‘Collecting’ amounts to being capable of living off one’s past. But he rejects regret, that other form of hope. He is incapable of looking at portraits.

Is he selfish for all that? In his way probably. But here, too, it is essential to understand one another. There are those who are made for living and those who are made for loving. At least Don Juan would be inclined to say so. But he would do so in a very few words such as he is capable of choosing. For the love we are speaking of here is clothed in illusions of the eternal. As all the specialists in passion teach us, there is no eternal love but what is thwarted. There is scarcely any passion without struggle. Such a love culminates only in the ultimate contradiction of death. One must be Werther or nothing. Then, too, there are several ways of committing suicide, one of which is the total gift and forgetfulness of self. Don Juan, as well as anyone else, knows that this can be stirring. But he is one of the very few who know that this is not the important thing. He knows just as well that those who turn away from all personal life through a great love enrich themselves perhaps but certainly impoverish those their love has chosen. A mother or passionate wife necessarily has a closed heart, for it is turned away from the world. A single emotion, a single creature, a single face, but all is devoured. Quite a different love disturbs Don Juan, and this one is liberating. It brings with it all the faces in the world and its tremor comes from the fact that it knows itself to be mortal. Don Juan has chosen to be nothing.

For him it is a matter of seeing clearly. We call love what binds us to certain creatures only by reference to a collective way of seeing for which books and legends are responsible. But of love I know only that mixture of desire, affection and intelligence that binds me to this or that creature. That compound is not the same for another per son. I do not have the right to cover all these experiences with the same name. This exempts one from conducting them with the same gestures. The absurd man multiplies here again what he cannot unify. Thus he discovers a new way of being which liberates him at least as much as it liberates those who approach him. There is no noble love but that which recognizes itself to be both short-lived and exceptional. All those deaths and all those rebirths gathered together as in a sheaf, make up for Don Juan the flowering of his life. It is his way of giving and of vivifying. I let it be decided whether or not one can speak of selfishness.

I think at this point of all those who absolutely insist that Don Juan be punished. Not only in another life, but even in this one. I think of all those tales, legends, and laughs about the aged Don Juan. But Don Juan is already ready. To a conscious man old age and what it portends are not a surprise. Indeed, he is conscious only in so far as he does not conceal its horror from himself. There was in Athens a temple dedicated to old age. Children were taken there. As for Don Juan, the more people laugh at him the more his figure stands out. Thereby he rejects the one the romantics lent him. No one wants to laugh at that tormented, pitiful Don Juan. He is pitied; heaven itself will redeem him ? But that’s not it. In the universe of which Don Juan has a glimpse, ridicule too is included. He would consider it normal to be chastised. That is the rule of the game. And, indeed, it is typical of his nobility to have accepted all the rules of the game. Yet he knows he is right and that there can be no question of punishment. A fate is not a punishment.

That is his crime, and how easy it is to understand why the men of God call down punishment on his head. He achieves a knowledge without illusions which negates everything they profess. Loving and possessing, conquering and consuming — that is his way of knowing. （There is significance in that favourite Scriptural word that calls the carnal act ‘knowing’.）He is their worst enemy to the extent that he is ignorant of them. A chronicler relates that the true ‘Burlador’ died assassinated by Franciscans who wanted ‘to put an end to the excesses and blasphemies of Don Juan whose birth assured him impunity’. Then they proclaimed that heaven had struck him down. No one has proved that strange end. Nor has anyone proved the contrary. But without wondering if it is probable, I can say that it is logical. I want merely to single out at this point the word ‘birth’ and to play on words: it was the fact of living that assured his innocence. It was from death alone that he derived a guilt now become legendary.

What else does that stone Commander signify, that cold statue set in motion to punish the blood and courage that dared to think? All the powers of eternal Reason, of order, of universal morality, all the foreign grandeur of a God open to wrath are summed up in him. That gigantic and soulless stone merely symbolizes the forces that Don Juan negated forever. But the Commander’s mission stops there. The thunder and lightning can return to the imitation heaven whence they were called forth. The real tragedy takes place quite apart from them. No, it was not under a stone hand that Don Juan met his death. I am inclined to believe in the legendary bravado, in that mad laughter of the healthy man provoking a non-existent God. But, above all, I believe that on that evening when Don Juan was waiting at Anna’s the Commander didn’t come and that, after midnight, the blasphemer must have felt the dreadful bitterness of those who have been fight. I accept even more readily the account of his life that has him eventually burying himself in a monastery. Not that the edifying aspect of the story can be considered probable. What refuge can he go to ask of God ? But this symbolizes rather the logical outcome of a life completely imbued with the absurd, the grim ending of an existence turned towards short-lived joys. At this point sensual pleasure winds up in asceticism. It is essential to realize that they may be as it were the two aspects of the same destitution. What more ghastly image can be called up than that of a man betrayed by his body who, simply because he did not die in time, lives out the comedy while awaiting the end, face to face with that God he does not adore, serving him as he served life, kneeling before a void and arms outstretched towards a heaven without eloquence that he knows to be also without depth?

I see Don Juan in a cell of one of those Spanish monasteries lost on a hill-top. And if he contemplates anything at all, it is not the ghosts of past loves, but perhaps, through a narrow slit in the sun-baked wall, some silent Spanish plain, a noble soulless land in which he recognizes himself. Yes, it is on this melancholy and radiant image that the curtain must be rung down. The ultimate end, awaited but never desired, the ultimate end is negligible.

Drama

‘The play’s the thing,’ says Hamlet, ‘wherein I’ll catch the conscience of the king.’ Catch is indeed the word. For con science moves swiftly or withdraws within itself. It has to be caught on the wing, at that barely perceptible moment when it glances fleetingly at itself. The everyday man does not enjoy tarrying. Everything, on the contrary, hurries him onward. But at the same time nothing interests him more than himself, especially his potentialities. Whence his interest in the theatre, in the show, where so many fates are offered him, where he can accept the poetry without feeling the sorrow. There, at least, can be recognized the thought less man, and he continues to hasten towards some hope or other. The absurd man begins where that one leaves off, where, ceasing to admire the play, the mind wants to enter in. Entering into all these lives, experiencing them in their diversity, amounts to acting them out. I am not saying that actors in general obey that impulse, that they are absurd men, but that their fate is an absurd fate which might charm and attract a lucid heart. It is necessary to establish this in order to grasp without misunderstanding what will follow.

The actor’s realm is that of the fleeting. Of all kinds of fame, it is known, his is the most ephemeral. At least this is said in conversation. But all kinds of fame are ephemeral. From the point of view of Sirius, Goethe’s works in ten thou sand years will be dust and his name forgotten. Perhaps a handful of archaeologists will look for ‘evidence’ as to our era. That idea has always contained a lesson. Seriously meditated upon, it reduces our perturbations to the profound nobility that is found in indifference. Above all, it directs our concerns towards what is most certain, that is towards the immediate. Of all kinds of fame the least deceptive is the one that is lived.

Hence the actor has chosen multiple fame, the fame that is hallowed and tested. From the fact that everything is to die some day he draws the best conclusion. An actor succeeds or does not succeed. A writer has some hope even if he is not appreciated. He assumes that his works will bear wimess to what he was. At best the actor will leave us a photograph, and nothing of what he was himself, his gestures and his silences, his gasping or his panting with love, will come down to us. For him, not to be known is not to act, and not acting is dying a hundred times with all the creatures he would have brought to life or resuscitated.

Why should we be surprised to find a fleeting fame built upon the most ephemeral of creations? The actor has three hours to be Iago or Alceste, Phèdre or Gloucester. In that short space of time he makes them come to life and die on fifty square yards of boards. Never has the absurd been so well illustrated or at such length. What more revelatory epitome can be imagined than those marvellous lives, those exceptional and total destinies unfolding for a few hours within a stage set? Off the stage, Sigismundo ceases to count. Two hours later he is seen dining out. Then it is, perhaps, that life is a dream. But after Sigismundo comes another. The hero suffering from uncertainty takes the place of the man roaring for his revenge. By thus sweeping over centuries and minds, by miming man as he can be and as he is, the actor has much in common with that other absurd individual, the traveller. Like him, he drains something and is constantly on the move. He is a traveller in time and, for the best, the hunted traveller, pursued by souls. If ever the ethics of quantity could find sustenance, it is indeed on that strange stage. To what degree the actor benefits from the characters is hard to say. But that is not the important thing. It is merely a matter of knowing how far he identifies himself with those irreplaceable lives. It often happens that he carries them with him, that they somewhat overflow the time and place in which they were born. They accompany the actor, who cannot very readily separate himself from what he has been. Occasionally when reaching for his glass he resumes Hamlet’s gesture of raising his cup. No, the distance separating him from the creatures into whom he infuses life is not so great. He abundantly illustrates every month or every day that so suggestive truth that there is no frontier between what a man wants to be and what he is. Always concerned with better representing, he demonstrates to what a degree appearing creates being. For that is his art — to simulate absolutely, to project himself as deeply as possible into lives that are not his own. At the end of his effort his vocation becomes clear: to apply himself whole heartedly to being nothing or to being several. The narrower the limits allotted him for creating his character the more necessary his talent. He will die in three hours under the mask he has assumed today. Within three hours he must experience and express a whole exceptional life. That is called losing oneself to find oneself. In those three hours he travels the whole course of the dead-end path that the man in the audience takes a lifetime to cover.

A mime of the ephemeral, the actor trains and perfects himself only in appearances. The theatrical convention is that the heart expresses itself and communicates itself only through gestures and in the body — or through the voice which is as much of the soul as of the body. The rule of that art insists that everything be magnified and translated into flesh. If it were essential on the stage to love as people really love, to employ that irreplaceable voice of the heart, to look as people contemplate in life, our speech would be in code. But here silences must make themselves heard. Love speaks up louder and immobility itself becomes spectacular.

The body is king. Not everyone can be ‘theatrical’ and this unjustly maligned word covers a whole aesthetic and a whole ethic. Half a man’s life is spent in implying, in turning away, and in keeping silent. Here the actor is the in truder. He breaks the spell chaining that soul, and at last the passions can rush on to their stage. They speak in every gesture; they live only through shouts and cries. Thus the actor creates his characters for display. He outlines or sculptures them and slips into their imaginary form, transfusing his blood into their phantoms. I am, of course, speaking of great drama, the kind that gives the actor an opportunity to fulfil his wholly physical fate. Take Shakespeare, for instance. In that impulsive drama the physical passions lead the dance. They explain everything. Without them all would collapse. Never would King Lear keep the appointment set by madness without the brutal gesture that exiles Cordelia and condemns Edgar. It is just that the unfolding of that tragedy should thenceforth be dominated by madness. Souls are given over to the demons and their sarabande. No fewer than four madmen: one by trade, another by intention, and the last two through suffering — four disordered bodies, four unutterable aspects of a single condition.

The very scale of the human body is inadequate. The mask and the buskin, the make-up that reduces and accentuates the face in its essential elements, the costume that exaggerates and simplifies — that universe sacrifices everything to appearance and is made solely for the eye. Through an absurd miracle, it is the body that also brings knowledge. I should never really understand Iago unless I played his part. It is not enough to hear him, for I grasp him only at the moment when I see him. Of the absurd character the actor consequently has the monotony, that single, oppressive silhouette, simultaneously strange and familiar, that he carries about from hero to hero. There, too, the great dramatic work contributes to this unity of tone.[2] This is where the actor contradicts himself: the same and yet so various, so many souls summed up in a single body. Yet it is the absurd contradiction itself, that individual who wants to achieve everything and live everything, that useless attempt, that ineffectual persistence. What always contradicts itself nevertheless joins in him. He is at that point where body and mind converge, where the mind, fired of its defeats, turns towards its most faithful ally. ‘And blest are those,’ says Hamlet, ‘whose blood and judgement are so well commingled that they are not a pipe for fortune’s finger to sound what stop she please.’

How could the Church have failed to condemn such a practice on the part of the actor? She repudiated in that art the heretical multiplication of souls, the emotional debauch, the scandalous presumption of a mind that objects to living but one life and hurls itself into all forms of excess. She proscribed in them that preference for the present and that triumph of Proteus which are the negation of everything she teaches. Eternity is not a game. A mind foolish enough to prefer a comedy to eternity has lost its salvation. Between ‘everywhere’ and ‘forever’ there is no compromise. Whence that much maligned profession can give rise to a tremendous spiritual conflict. ‘What matters,’ said Nietzsche, ‘is not eternal life but eternal vivacity.’ All drama is, in fact, in this choice.

Adrienne Lecouvreur on her deathbed was willing to con fess and receive communion but refused to abjure her profession. She thereby lost the benefit of the confession. Did this not amount, in effect, to choosing her absorbing passion in preference to God? And that woman in the death-throes refusing in tears to repudiate what she called her art gave evidence of a greatness that she never achieved behind the footlights. This was her finest role and the hardest one to play. Choosing between heaven and a ridiculous fidelity, preferring oneself to eternity or losing oneself in God is the age-old tragedy in which each must play his part.

The actors of the era knew they were excommunicated. Entering the profession amounted to choosing Hell. And the Church discerned in them her worst enemies. A few men of letters protest: ‘What! Refuse the last rites to Molière!’ But that was just, and especially in one who died on stage and finished under the actor’s make-up a life entirely de voted to dispersion. In his case genius is invoked, which excuses everything. But genius excuses nothing, just because it refuses to do so.

The actor knew at that time what punishment was in store for him. But what significance could such vague threats have compared to the final punishment that life itself was reserving for him? This was the one that he felt in advance and accepted wholly. To the actor as to the absurd man a premature death is irreparable. Nothing can make up for the sum of faces and centuries he would otherwise have traversed. But in any case one has to die. For the actor is doubtless everywhere, but time sweeps him along too and makes its impression with him.

It requires but a little imagination to feel what an actor’s fate means. It is in time that he makes up and enumerates his characters. It is in time likewise that he learns to dominate them. The greater number of different lives he has lived the more aloof he can be from them. The time comes when he must die to the stage and for the world. What he has lived faces him. He sees clearly. He feels the harrowing and irreplaceable quality of that adventure. He knows and can now die. There are homes for aged actors.

Conquest

‘No,’ says the conqueror, ‘don’t assume that because I love action I have had to forget how to think. On the contrary, I can thoroughly define what I believe. For I believe it firmly and I see it surely and clearly. Beware of those who say: “I know this too well to be able to express it.” For if they cannot do so, this is because they don’t know it or because out of laziness they stopped at the outer crust.

‘I have not many opinions. At the end of a life man notices that he has spent years becoming sure of a single truth. But a single truth, if it is obvious, is enough to guide an existence. As for me, I decidedly have something to say about the individual. One must speak of him bluntly and, if need be, with the appropriate contempt.

‘A man is more a man through the things he keeps to himself than through those he says. There are many that I shall keep to myself. But I firmly believe that all those who have judged the individual have done so with much less experience than we on which to base their judgement. The intelligence, the stirring intelligence perhaps foresaw what it was essential to note. But the era, its ruins and its blood over whelm us with facts. It was possible for ancient nations, and even for more recent ones down to our machine-age, to weigh one against the other the virtues of society and of the individual, to try to find out which was to serve the other. To begin with, that was possible by virtue of that stubborn aberration in man’s heart according to which human beings were created to serve or be served. In the second place, it was possible because neither society nor the individual had yet revealed all their ability.

‘I have seen bright minds express astonishment at the masterpieces of Dutch painters born at the height of the bloody wars in Flanders, be mazed by the prayers of Silesian mystics brought up during the frightful Thirty Years’ War. Eternal values survive secular turmoils before their astonished eyes. But there has been progress since. The painters of today are deprived of such serenity. Even if they have basically the heart the creator needs, I mean the closed heart, it is of no use; for everyone, including the saint himself, is mobilized. This is perhaps what I have felt most deeply. At every form that miscarries in the trenches, at every outline, metaphor, or prayer crushed under steel, the eternal loses a round. Conscious that I cannot stand aloof from my time, I have decided to be an integral part of it. This is why I esteem the individual only because he strikes me as ridiculous and humiliated. Knowing that there are no victorious causes, I have a liking for lost causes: they require an uncontaminated soul, equal to its defeat as to its temporary victories. For anyone who feels bound up with this world’s fate, the clash of civilizations has something agonizing about it. I have made that anguish mine at the same time that I wanted to join in. Between history and the eternal I have chosen history because I like certainties. Of it at least I am certain, and how can I deny this force crushing me?

‘There always comes a time when one must choose between contemplation and action. This is called becoming a man. Such wrenches are dreadful. But for a proud heart there can be no compromise. There is God or time, that cross or this sword. This world has a higher meaning that transcends its worries or nothing is true but those worries. One must live with time and die with it or else elude it for a greater life. I know that one can compromise and live in the world while believing in the eternal. That is called accepting. But I loathe this term and want all or nothing. If I choose action, don’t think that contemplation is like an unknown country to me. But it cannot give me everything and, deprived of the eternal, I want to ally myself with time. I do not want to put down to my account either nostalgia or bitterness and I merely want to see clearly. I tell you, tomorrow you will be mobilized. For you and for me that is a liberation. The individual can do nothing and yet he can do everything. In that wonderful unattached state you understand why I exalt and crush him at one and the same time. It is the world that pulverizes him and I who liberate him. I provide him with all his rights.

‘Conquerors know that action is in itself useless. There is but one useful action, that of remaking man and the earth. I shall never remake men. But one must do “as if ”. For the path of struggle leads me to the flesh. Even humiliated, the flesh is my only certainty. I can live only on it. The creature is my native land. This is why I have chosen this absurd and ineffectual effort. This is why I am on the side of the struggle. The epoch lends itself to this, as I have said. Hitherto the greatness of a conqueror was geographical. It was measured by the extent of the conquered territories. There is a reason why the word has changed in meaning and has ceased to signify the victorious general. The greatness has changed camp. It lies in protest and the blind-alley sacrifice. There, too, it is not through a preference for defeat. Victory would be desirable. But there is but one victory and it is eternal. That is the one I shall never have. That is where I stumble and cling. A revolution is always accomplished against the gods, beginning with the revolution of Prometheus, the first of modem conquerors. It is man’s demands made against his fate; the demands of the poor are but a pretext. Yet I can seize that spirit only in its historical act and that is where I make contact with it. Don’t assume, however, that I take pleasure in it: opposite the essential contradiction, I maintain my human contradiction. I establish my lucidity in the midst of what negates it. I exalt man before what crushes him and my freedom, my revolt and my passion come together then in that tension, that lucidity and that vast repetition.

‘Yes, man is his own end. And he is his only end. If he aims to be something, it is in this life. Now I know it only too well. Conquerors sometimes talk of vanquishing and overcoming. But it is always “overcoming oneself ” that they mean. You are well aware of what that means. Every man has felt himself to be the equal of a god at certain moments. At least, this is the way it is expressed. But this comes from that fact that, in a flash, he felt the amazing grandeur of the human mind. The conquerors are merely those among men who are conscious enough of their strength to be sure of living constantly on those heights and fully aware of that grandeur. It is a question of arithmetic, of more or less. The conquerors are capable of the more. But they are capable of no more than man himself when he wants. This is why they never leave the human crucible, plunging into the seething soul of revolutions.

‘There they find the creature mutilated, but they also encounter there the only values they like and admire, man and his silence. This is both their destitution and their wealth. There is but one luxury for them — that of human relations. How can one fail to realize that in this vulnerable universe everything that is human and solely human assumes a more vivid meaning? Taut faces, threatened fraternity, such strong and chaste friendship among men — these are the true riches because they are transitory. In their midst the mind is most aware of its powers and limitations. That is to say, its efficacy. Some have spoken of genius. But genius is easy to say; I prefer the intelligence. It must be said that it can be magnificent then. It lights up this desert and dominates it. It knows its obligations and illustrates them. It will die at the same time as this body. But knowing this constitutes its freedom.

‘We are not ignorant of the fact that all churches are against us. A heart so keyed up eludes the eternal, and all churches, divine or political, lay claim to the eternal. Happiness and courage, retribution or justice are secondary ends for them. It is a doctrine they bring, and one must subscribe to it. But I have no concern with ideas or with the eternal. The truths that come within my scope can be touched with the hand. I cannot separate from them. This is why you cannot base anything on me: nothing of the conqueror lasts, not even his doctrines.

‘At the end of all that, despite everything, is death. We know also that it ends everything. This is why those cemeteries all over Europe, which obsess some among us, are hideous. People beautify only what they love and death repels us and tires our patience. It, too, is to be conquered. The last Carrara, a prisoner in Padua emptied by the plague and besieged by the Venetians, ran screaming through the halls of his deserted palace: he was calling on the devil and asking him for death. This was a way of overcoming it. And it is likewise a mark of courage characteristic of the Occident to have made so ugly the places where death thinks itself honoured. In the rebel’s universe, death exalts in justice. It is the supreme abuse.

‘Others, without compromising either, have chosen the eternal and denounced the illusion of this world. Their cemeteries smile amid numerous flowers and birds. That suits the conqueror and gives him a clear image of what he has rejected. He has chosen, on the contrary, the black iron fence or the potter’s field. The best among the men of God occasionally are seized with fright mingled with consideration and pity for minds that can livewith such an image of their death. Yet those minds derive their strength and justification from this. Our fate stands before us and we provoke him. Less out of pride than out of awareness of our ineffectual condition. We, too, sometimes feel pity for ourselves. It is the only compassion that seems acceptable to us: a feeling that perhaps you hardly understand and that seems to you scarcely virile. Yet the most daring among us are the ones who feel it. But we call the lucid ones virile and we do not want a strength that is apart from lucidity.’

Let me repeat that these images do not propose moral codes and involve no judgements: they are sket-ches. They merely represent a style of life. The lover, the actor, or the adventurer plays the absurd. But equally well, if he wishes, the chaste man, the civil servant, or the President of the Republic. It is enough to know and to mask nothing. In Italian museums are sometimes found little painted screens that the priest used to hold in front of the face of condemned men to hide the scaffold from them. The leap in all its forms, rushing into the divine or the eternal, surrendering to the illusions of the everyday or of the idea — all these screens hide the absurd. But there are civil servants without screens and they are the ones of whom I mean to speak.

I have chosen the most extreme ones. At this level the absurd gives them a royal power. It is true that those princes are without a kingdom. But they have this advantage over others: they know that all royalties are illusory. They know, that is their whole nobility, and it is useless to speak in relation to them of hidden misfortune or the ashes of disillusion. Being deprived of hope is not despairing. The flames of earth are surely worth celestial perfumes. Neither I nor anyone can judge them here. They are not striving to be better, they are attempting to be consistent. If the term ‘wise man’ can be applied to the man who lives on what he has without speculating on what he has not, then they are wise men. One of them, a conqueror but in the realm of mind, a Don Juan but of knowledge, an actor but of the intelligence, knows this better than anyone: ‘You nowise deserve a privilege on earth and in heaven for having brought to perfection your dear little meek sheep; you nonetheless continue to be at best a ridiculous dear little sheep with horns and nothing more — even supposing that you do not burst with vanity and do not cream a scandal by posing as a judge.’

In any case it was essential to restore to the absurd reasoning more cordial examples. The imagination can add many others, inseparable from time and exile, who likewise know how to live in harmony with a universe without future and without weakness. This absurd, godless world is then peopled with men who think clearly and who have ceased to hope. And I have not yet spoken of the most absurd character, who is the creator.

[1]In the fullest sense and with his faults. A healthy attitude also includes faults.

[2]At this point I am thinking of Molière’s Alceste. Everything is so simple, so obvious and so coarse. Alceste against Philinte, Célimene against Elianthe, the whole subject in the absurd consequence of a nature carded to its extreme, and the verse itself, the ‘bad verse’ , barely accented like the monotony of the character’s nature.

Absurd Creation

Philosophy and Fiction

All those lives maintained in the rarefied air of the absurd could not persevere without some profound and constant thought to infuse its strength into them. Right here, it can be only a strange feeling of fidelity. Conscious men have been seen to fulfil their task amidst the most stupid of wars without considering themselves in contradiction. This is because it was essential to elude nothing. There is thus a metaphysical honour in enduring the world’s absurdity. Conquest or play-acting, multiple loves, absurd revolt are tributes that man pays to his dignity in a campaign in which he is defeated in advance.

It is merely a matter of being faithful to the rule of the Battle. That thought may suffice to sustain a mind; it has supported and still supports whole dvilizations. War cannot be negated. One must live it or die of it. So it is with the absurd: it is a question of breathing with it, of recognizing its lessons and recovering their flesh. In this regard the absurd joy par excellence is creation. ‘Art and nothing but art,’ said Nietzsche; ‘we have art in order not to die of the truth.’

In the experience that I am attempting to describe and to stress on several modes, it is certain that a new torment arises wherever another dies. The childish chasing after forgetfulness, the appeal of satisfaction are now devoid of echo. But the constant tension that keeps man face to face with the world, the ordered delirium that urges him to be receptive to everything, leave him another fever. In this universe the work of art is then the sole chance of keeping his consciousness and of fixing its adventures. Creating is living doubly. The groping, anxious quest of a Proust, his meticulous collecting of flowers, of wallpapers, and of anxieties, signifies nothing else. At the same time, it has no more significance than the continual and imperceptible creation in which the actor, the conqueror, and all absurd men indulge every day of their lives. All try their hands at miming, at repeating, and at re-creating the reality that is theirs. We always end up by having the appearance of our truths. All existence for a man turned away from the eternal is but a vast mime under the mask of the absurd. Creation is the great mime.

Such men know to begin with, and then their whole effort is to examine, to enlarge, and to enrich the ephemeral island on which they have just landed. But first they must know. For the absurd discovery coincides with a pause in which future passions are prepared and justified. Even men without a gospel have their Mount of Olives. And one must not fall asleep on theirs either. For the absurd man it is not a matter of explaining and solving, but of experiencing and describing. Everything begins with lucid indifference.

Describing — that is the last ambition of an absurd thought. Science likewise, having reached the end of its paradoxes, ceases to propound and stops to contemplate and sketch the ever-virgin landscape of phenomena. The heart learns thus that the emotion delighting us when we see the world’s aspects comes to us not from its depth but from their diversity. Explanation is useless but the sensation remains and, with it, the constant attractions of a universe inexhaustible in quantity. The place of the work of art can be understood at this point.

It marks both the death of an experience and its multiplication. It is a sort of monotonous and passionate repetition of the themes already orchestrated by the world: the body, inexhaustible image on the pediment of temples, forms or colours, number or grief. It is, therefore, not in different, as a conclusion, to encounter once again the principal themes of this essay in the wonderful and childish world of the creator. It would be wrong to see a symbol in it and to think that the work of art can be considered at last as a refuge for the absurd. It is itself an absurd phenomenon and we are concerned merely with its description. It does not offer an escape for the intellectual ailment. Rather, it is one of the symptoms of that ailment which reflects it throughout a man’s whole thought. But for the first time it makes the mind get outside of itself and places it in opposition to others, not for it to get lost but to show it clearly the blind path that all have entered upon. In the time of the absurd reasoning, creation follows indifference and discovery. It marks the point from which absurd passions spring and where the reasoning stops. Its place in this essay is justified in this way.

It will suffice to bring to light a few themes common to the creator and the thinker in order to find in the work of art all the contradictions of thought involved in the absurd. Indeed, it is not so much identical conclusions that prove minds to be related as the contradictions that are common to them. So it is with thought and creation. I hardly need to say that the same anguish urges man to these two attitudes. This is where they coincide in the beginning. But among all the thoughts that start from the absurd, I have seen that very few remain within it. And through their deviations or infidelities I have best been able to measure what belonged to the absurd. Similarly, I must wonder: is an absurd work of art possible?

It would be impossible to insist too much on the arbitrary nature of the former opposition between art and philosophy. If you insist on taking it in too limited a sense, it is cer tainly false. If you mean merely that these two disciplines each have their peculiar climate, that is probably true but remains vague. The only acceptable argument lay in the contradiction brought up between the philosopher enclosed within his system and the artist placed before his work. But this was pertinent for a certain form of art and of philosophy which we consider secondary here. The idea of an art detached from its creator is not only outmoded; it is false. In opposition to the artist, it is pointed out that no philosopher ever created several systems. But that is true insofar, indeed, as no artist ever expressed more than one thing under different aspects. The instantaneous perfection of art, the necessity for its renewal — this is true only through a preconceived notion. For the work of art likewise is a construction and everyone knows how monotonous the great creators can be. For the same reason as the thinker, the artist commits himself and becomes himself in his work. That osmosis raises the most important of aesthetic problems. Moreover, to anyone who is convinced of the mind’s singleness of purpose, nothing is more futile than these distinctions based on methods and objects. There are no frontiers between the disciplines that man sets himself for understanding and loving. They interlock and the same anxiety merges them.

It is necessary to state this to begin with. For an absurd work of art to be possible, thought in its most lucid form must be involved in it. But at the same time thought must not be apparent except as the regulating intelligence. This paradox can be explained according to the absurd. The work of art is born of the intelligence’s refusal to reason the concrete. It marks the triumph of the carnal. It is lucid thought that provokes it but in that very act that thought repudiates itself. It will not yield to the temptation of adding to what is described a deeper meaning that it knows to be illegitimate. The work of art embodies a drama of the intelligence, but it proves this only indirectly. The absurd work requires an artist conscious of these limitations and an art in which the concrete signifies nothing more than itself. It cannot be the end, the meaning, and the consolation of a life. Creating or not creating changes nothing. The absurd creator does not prize his work. He could repudiate it. He does some times repudiate it. An Abyssinia suffices for this, as in the case of Rimbaud.

At the same time a rule of aesthetics can be seen in this. The true work of art is always on the human scale. It is essentially the one that says ‘less’. There is a certain relationship between the global experience of the artist and the work that reflects that experience, between Wilhelm Meister and Goethe’s maturity. That relationship is bad when the work aims to give the whole experience in the lace-paper of an, explanatory literature. That relationship is good when the work is but a piece cut out of experience, a facet of the diamond in which the inner lustre is epitomized without being limited. In the first case there is overloading and pretension to the eternal. In the second, a fecund work because of a whole implied experience, the wealth of which is suspected. The problem for the absurd artist is to acquire this savoir-vivre which transcends savoir-faire. And, in the end, the great artist under this climate is above all a great living being, it being understood that living in this case is just as much experiencing as reflecting. The work then embodies an intellectual drama. The absurd work illustrates thought’s renouncing of its prestige and its resignation to being no more than the intelligence that works up appearances and covers with images what has no reason. If the world were clear, art would not exist.

I am not speaking here of the arts of form or colour in which description alone prevails in its splendid modesty.[1] Expression begins where thought ends. Those adolescents with empty eye-sockets who people temples and museums — their philosophy has been expressed in gestures. For an absurd man it is more educative than all libraries. Under another aspect the same is true for music. If any art is devoid of lessons, it is certainly music. It is too closely related to mathematics not to have borrowed their gratuitousness. That game the mind plays with itself according to set and measured laws takes place in the sonorous compass that belongs to us and beyond which the vibrations nevertheless meet in an inhuman universe. There is no purer sensation. These examples are too easy. The absurd man recognizes as his own these harmonies and these forms.

But I should like to speak here of a work in which the temptation to explain remains greatest, in which illusion offers itself automatically, in which conclusion is almost inevitable. I mean fictional creation. I propose to inquire whether or not the absurd can hold its own there.

To think is first of all to create a world （or to limit one’s own world, which comes to the same thing）. It is starting out from the basic agreement that separates man from his experience in order to find a common ground according to one’s nostalgia, a universe hedged with reasons or lighted up with analogies but which, in any case, gives an opportunity to rescind the unbearable divorce. The philosopher, even if he is Kant, is a creator. He has his characters, his symbols and his secret action. He has his plot-endings. On the contrary, the lead taken by the novel over poetry and the essay merely represents, despite appearances, a greater intellectualization of the art. Let there be no mistake about it; I am speaking of the greatest. The fecundity and the importance of a literary form are often measured by the trash it contains. The number of bad novels must not make us forget the value of the best. These, indeed, carry with them their universe. The novel has its logic, its reasonings, its intuition, and its postulates. It also has its requirements of clarity.[2]

The classical opposition of which I was speaking above is even less justified in this particular case. It held in the time when it was easy to separate philosophy from its authors. Today when thought has ceased to lay claim to the universal, when its best history would be that of its repentances, we know that the system, when it is worth while, cannot be separated from its author. The Ethics itself, in one of its aspects, is but a long and reasoned personal confession. Abstract thought at last returns to its prop of flesh. And likewise, the fictional activities of the body and of the passions are regulated a little more according to the requirements of a vision of the world. The writer has given up telling ‘stories’ and creates his universe. The great novelists are philosophical novelists, that is the contrary of thesis-writers. For instance, Balzac, Sade, Melville, Stendhal, Dostoievsky, Proust, Malraux, Kafka, to cite but a few.

But, in fact, the preference they have shown for writing in images rather than in reasoned arguments is revelatory of a certain thought that is common to them all, convinced of the uselessness of any principle of explanation and sure of the educative message of perceptible appearance. They consider the work of art both as an end and a beginning. It is the outcome of an often unexpressed philosophy, its illustration and its consummation. But it is complete only through the implications of that philosophy. It justifies at last that variant of an old theme that a little thought estranges from life whereas much thought reconciles to life. Incapable of refining the real, thought pauses to mimic it. The novel in question is the instrument of that simultaneously relative and inexhaustible knowledge, so like that of love. Of love, fictional creation has the initial wonder and the fecund rumination.

These at least are the charms I see in it at the outset. But I saw them likewise in those princes of humiliated thought whose suicides I was later able to witness. What interests me, indeed, is knowing and describing the force that leads them back towards the common path of illusion. The same method will consequently help me here. The fact of having already utilized it will allow me to shorten my argument and to sum it up without delay in a particular example. I want to know whether, accepting a life without appeal, one can also agree to work and create without appeal and what is the way leading to these liberties. I want to liberate my universe of its phantoms and to people it solely with flesh and blood truths whose presence I cannot deny. I can perform absurd work, choose the creative attitude rather than another. But an absurd attitude, if it is to remain so, must remain aware of its gratuitousness. So it is with the work of art. If the commandments of the absurd are not respected, if the work does not illustrate divorce and revolt, if it sacrifices to illusions and arouses hope, it ceases to be gratuitous. I can no longer detach myself from it. My life may find a meaning in it but that is trifling. It ceases to be that exercise in detachment and passion which crowns the splendour and futility of a man’s life.

In the creation in which the temptation to explain is the strongest, can one overcome that temptation? In the fictional world in which awareness of the real world is keenest, can I remain faithful to the absurd without sacrificing to the desire to judge? So many questions to be taken into consideration in a last effort. It must be already clear what they signify. They are the last scruples of an awareness that fears to forsake its initial and difficult lesson in favour of a final illusion. What holds for creation, looked upon as one of the possible attitudes for the man conscious of the absurd, holds for all the styles of life open to him. The conqueror or the actor, the creator or Don Juan may forget that their exercise in living could not do without awareness of its mad character. One becomes accustomed so quickly. A man wants to earn money in order to be happy and his whole effort and the best of a life are devoted to the earning of that money. Happiness is forgotten; the means are taken for the end. Likewise the whole effort of this conqueror will be diverted to ambition, which was but a way towards a greater life. Don Juan in turn will likewise yield to his fate, be satisfied with that existence whose nobility is of value only through revolt. For one it is awareness and for the other, revolt; in both cases the absurd has disappeared. There is so much stubborn hope in the human heart. The most destitute men often end up by accepting illusion. That approval prompted by the need for peace inwardly parallels the existential consent. There are thus gods of light and idols of mud. But it is essential to find the middle path leading to the faces of man.

So far, the failures of the absurd exigence have best informed us as to what it is. In the same way, if we are to be informed it will suffice to notice that fictional creation can present the same ambiguity as certain philosophies. Hence I can choose as illustration a work comprising everything that denotes awareness of the absurd, having a clear starting point and a lucid climate. Its consequences will enlighten us. If the absurd is not respected in it, we shall know by what expedient illusion enters in. A particular example, a theme, a creator’s fidelity will suffice them. This involves the same analysis that has already been made at greater length.

I shall examine a favourite theme of Dostoievsky. I might just as well have studied other works.[3] But in this work the problem is treated directly, in the sense of nobility and emotion, as for the existential philosophies already discussed. This parallelism serves my purpose.

Kirilov

All of Dostoievsky’s heroes question themselves as to the meaning of life. In this they are modern: they do not fear ridicule. What distinguishes modem sensibility from classical sensibility is that the latter thrives on moral problems and the former on metaphysical problems. In Dostoievsky’s novels the question is propounded with such intensity that it can only invite extreme solutions. Existence is illusory or it is eternal. If Dostoievsky were satisfied with this inquiry, he would be a philosopher. But he illustrates the conse- quences that such intellectual pastimes may have in a man’s life and in this regard he is an artist. Among those consequences, his attention is arrested particularly by the last one, which he himself calls logical suicide in his Diary of a Writer. In the instalments for December 1876, indeed, he imagines the reasoning of ‘logical suicide’. Convinced that human existence is an utter absurdity for anyone without faith in immortality, the desperate man comes to the following conclusions:

‘Since in reply to my questions about happiness, I am told, through the intermediary of my consciousness, that I cannot be happy except in harmony with the great all, which I cannot conceive and shall never be in a position to conceive, it is evident . . .’

‘Since, finally in this connection, I assume both the role of the plaintiff and that of the defendant, of the accused and of the judge, and since I consider this comedy perpetrated by nature altogether stupid, and since I even deem it humiliating for me to deign to play it . . .’

‘In my indisputable capacity of plaintiff and defendant, of judge and accused, I condemn that nature which, with such impudent nerve, brought me into being in order to suffer — I condemn it to be annihilated with me.’

There remains a little humour in that position. This suicide kills himself because, on the metaphysical plane, he is vexed. In a certain sense he is taking his revenge. This is his way of proving that he ‘will not be had’. It is known, however, that the same theme is: embodied, but with the most wonderful generality, in Kirilov of The Possessed, likewise an advocate of logical suicide. Kirilov the engineer declares somewhere that he wants to take his own life because it ‘is his idea’. Obviously the word must be taken in its proper sense. It is for an idea, a thought that he is getting ready for death. This is the superior suicide. Progressively, in a series of scenes in which Kirilov’s mind is gradually illuminated, the fatal thought driving him is revealed to us. The engineer, in fact, goes back to the arguments of the Diary. He feels that God is necessary and that he must exist. But he knows that he does not and cannot exist ‘Why do you not realize,’ he exclaims, ‘that this is sufficient reason for killing oneself?’ That attitude involves likewise for him some of the absurd consequences. Through indifference he accepts letting his suicide be used to the advantage of a cause he despises. ‘I decided last night that I didn’t care.’ And finally he prepares his deed with a mixed feeling of revolt and freedom. ‘I shall kill myself in order to assert my insubordination, my new and dreadful liberty.’ It is no longer a question of revenge, but of revolt. Kirilov is consequently an absurd character — yet with this essential reservation: he kills himself. But he himself explains this contradiction, and in such a way that at the same time he reveals the absurd secret in all its purity. In truth, he adds to his fatal logic an extraordinary ambition which gives the character its full perspective: he wants to kill himself to become god.

The reasoning is classic in its clarity. If God does not exist, Kirilov is god. If God does not exist, Kirilov must kill himself. Kirilov must therefore kill himself to become god. That logic is absurd, but it is what is needed. The interesting thing, however, is to give a meaning to that divinity brought to earth. That amounts to clarifying the premise: ‘If God does not exist, I am god,’ which still remains rather obscure. It is important to note at the outset that the man who flaunts that mad claim is indeed of this world. He performs his gymnastics every morning to preserve his health. He is stirred by the joy of Chatov recovering his wife. On a sheet of paper to be found after his death he wants to draw a face sticking out his tongue at ‘them’. He is childish and irascible, passionate, methodical, and sensitive. Of the superman he has nothing but the logic and the obsession, whereas of man he has the whole catalogue. Yet it is he who speaks calmly of his divinity. He is not mad or else Dostoievsky is. Consequently it is not a megalomaniac’s illusion that excites him. And taking the words in their specific sense would, in this instance, be ridiculous.

Kirilov himself helps us to understand. In reply to a question from Stavrogin, he makes it clear that he is not talking of a god-man. It might be thought that this springs from concern to distinguish himself from Christ. But in reality it is a matter of annexing Christ. Kirilov, in fact, fancies for a moment that Jesus at his death did not find himself in Paradise. He found out then that his torture had been useless. ‘The laws of nature,’ says the engineer, ‘made Christ live in the midst of falsehood and die for a false- hood.’ Solely in this sense Jesus indeed personifies the whole human drama. He is the complete man, being the one who realized the most absurd condition. He is not the Godman but the man-god. And, like him, each of us can be crucified and victimized — and is to a certain degree.

The divinity in question is therefore altogether terrestrial. ‘For three years,’ says Kirilov, ‘I sought the attribute of my divinity and I have found it. The attribute of my divinity is independence.’ Now can be seen the meaning of Kirilov’s premiss: ‘If God does not exist, I am god.’ To become god is merely to be free on this earth, not to serve an immortal being. Above all, of course, it is drawing all the inferences from that painful independence. If God exists all depends on him and we can do nothing against his will. If he does not exist, everything depends on us. For Kirilov, as for Nietzsche, to kill God is to become god oneself; it is to realize on this earth the eternal life of which the Gospel speaks.[4]

But if this metaphysical crime is enough for man’s fulfilment, why add suicide? Why kill oneself and leave this world after having won freedom? That is contradictory. Kifilov is well aware of this, for he adds: ‘If you feel that, you are a Czar and, far from killing yourself, you will live covered with glory.’ But men in general do not know. They do not feel ‘that’. As in the time of Prometheus, they enter tain blind hopes.[5] They need to be shown the way and cannot do without preaching. Consequently Kirilov must kill himself out of love for humanity. He must show his brothers a royal and difficult path on which he will be the first. It is a pedagogical suicide. Kirilov sacrifices himself then. But if he is crucified, he will not be victimized. He remains the man-god, convinced of a death without future, imbued with evangelical melancholy. ‘I,’ he says, ‘am unhappy because I am obliged to assert my freedom.’ But once he is dead and men are at last enlightened, this earth will be peopled with Czars and lighted up with human glory. Kirilov’s pistol-shot will be the signal for the last revolution. Thus it is not despair that urges him to death but love of his neighbour for his own sake. Before terminating in blood an in describable spiritual adventure, Kirilov makes a remark as old as human suffering: ‘All is well.’

This theme of suicide in Dostoievsky, then, is indeed an absurd theme. Let us merely note before going on that Kirilov reappears in other characters who themselves set in motion additional absurd themes. Stavrogin and Ivan Karamazov try out the absurd truths in practical life. They are the ones liberated by Kirilov’s death. They try their skill at being Czars. Stavrogin leads an ‘ironic’ life, and it is well known in what regard. He arouses hatred around him. And yet the key to the character is found in his farewell letter: ‘I have not been able to detest anything.’ He is a Czar in indifference. Ivan is likewise by refusing to surrender the royal powers of the mind. To those who, like his brother, prove by their lives that it is essential to humiliate oneself in order to believe, he might reply that the condition is shameful. His keyword is ‘Everything is permitted’ , with the appropriate shade of melancholy. Of course, like Nietzsche, the most famous of God’s assassins, he ends in madness. But this is a risk worth running and, faced with such tragic ends, the essential impulse of the absurd mind is to ask: ‘What does that prove?’

Thus the novels, like the Diary, propound the absurd question. They establish logic unto death, exaltation, ‘dreadful’ freedom, the glory of the Czars become human. All is well, everything is permitted and nothing is hateful — these are absurd judgements. But what an amazing creation in which those creatures of fire and ice seem so familiar to us. The passionate world of indifference that rumbles in their heart does not seem at all monstrous to us. We recognize in it our everyday anxieties. And probably no one so much as Dostoievsky has managed to give the absurd world such familiar and tormenting charms.

Yet what is his conclusion? Two quotations will show the complete metaphysical reversal that leads the writer to other revelations. The argument of the one who commits logical suicide having provoked protests from the critics, Dostoievsky in the following instalments of the Diary amplifies his position and concludes thus: ‘If faith in immortality is so necessary to the human being （that without it he comes to the point of killing himself）it must therefore be the nor mal state of humanity. Since this is the case, the immortality of the human soul exists without any doubt.’ Then again in the last pages of his last novel, at the conclusion of that gigantic combat with God, some children ask Aliocha: ‘Karamazov, is it true what religion says, that we shall rise from the dead, that we shall see one another again?’ And Aliocha answers: ‘Certainly, we shall see one another again, we shall joyfully tell one another everything that has happened.’

Thus Kirilov, Stavrogin, and Ivan are defeated. The Brothers Karamazov replies to The Possessed. And it is indeed a conclusion. Aliocha’s case is not ambiguous as is that of Prince Muichkin. III, the latter lives in a perpetual present, tinged with smiles and indifference, and that blissful state might be the eternal life of which the Prince speaks. On the contrary, Aliocha clearly says: ‘We shall meet again.’ There is no longer any question of suicide and of madness. What is the use, for anyone who is sure of immortality and of its joys? Man exchanges his divinity for happiness. ‘We shall joyfully tell one another everything that has happened.’ Thus again, Kirilov’s pistol rang out somewhere in Russia, but the world continued to cherish its blind hopes. Men did not understand ‘that’.

Consequently, it is not an absurd novelist addressing us but an existential novelist. Here, too, the leap is touching and gives its nobility to the art that inspires it. It is a stirring acquiescence, riddled with doubts, uncertain and ardent. Speaking of The Brothers Karamazov, Dostoievsky wrote: ‘The chief question that will be pursued throughout this book is the very one from which I have suffered consciously or unconsciously all life long: the existence of God.’ It is hard to believe that a novel sufficed to transform into joyful certainty the suffering of a lifetime. One commentator[6] correctly pointed out that Dostoievsky is on Ivan’s side and that the affirmative chapters took three months of efforts whereas what he called ‘the blasphemies’ were written in three weeks in a state of excitement. There is not one of his characters who does not have that thorn in the flesh, who does not aggravate it or seek a remedy for it in sensation or immorality.[7] In any case let us remain with this doubt Here is a work which, in a chiaroscuro more gripping than the light of day, permits us to seize man’s struggle against his hopes. Having reached the end, the creator makes his choice against his characters. That contradiction thus allows us to make a distinction. It is not an absurd work that is in volved here but a work that propounds the absurd problem.

Dostoievsky’s reply is humiliation, ‘shame’ according to Stavrogin. An absurd work on the contrary does not provide a reply; that is the whole difference. Let us note this carefully in conclusion: what contradicts the absurd in that work is not its Christian character but rather its announcing a future life. It is possible to be Christian and absurd. There are examples of Christians who do not believe in a future life. In regard to the work of ‘art, it should therefore be possible to define one of the directions of the absurd analysis that could have been anticipated in the preceding pages. It leads to propounding ‘the absurdity of the Gospel’. It throws light upon this idea, fertile in repercussions, that convictions do not prevent incredulity. On the contrary, it is easy to see that the author of The Possessed, familiar with these paths, in conclusion took a quite different way. The surprising reply of the creator to his characters, of Dostoievsky to Kirilov, can indeed be summed up thus: Existence is illusory and it is eternal.

Ephemeral Creation

At this point, I perceive therefore that hope cannot be eluded for ever and that it can beset even those who wanted to be free of it. This is the interest I find in the works discussed up to this point. I could, at least in the realm of creation, list some truly absurd works.[8] But everything must have a beginning. The object of this quest is a certain fidelity. The Church has been so harsh with heretics only because she deemed that there is no worse enemy than a child who has gone astray. But the record of Gnostic effronteries and the persistence of Manichean currents have contributed more to the construction of orthodox dogma than all the prayers. With due allowance, the same is true of the absurd. One recognizes one’s course by discovering the paths that stray from it. At the very conclusion of the absurd reasoning, in one of the attitudes dictated by its logic, it is not a matter of indifference to find hope coming back in under one of its most touching guises. That shows the difficulty of the absurd ascesis. Above all, it shows the necessity of unfailing alermess and thus confirms the general plan of this essay.

But if it is still too early to list absurd works, at least a conclusion can be reached as to the creative attitude, one of those which can complete absurd existence. Art can never be so well served as by a negative thought. Its dark and humiliated proceedings are as necessary to the understanding of a great work as black is to white. To work and create ‘for nothing’ , to sculpture in clay, to know that one’s creation has no future, to see one’s work destroyed in a day while being aware that, fundamentally, this has no more importance than building for centuries — this is the difficult wisdom that absurd thought sanctions. Performing these two tasks simultaneously, negating on the one hand and magnifying on the other, is the way open to the absurd creator. He must give the void its colours.

This leads to a special conception of the work of art. Too often the work of a creator is looked upon as a series of isolated testimonies. Thus artist and man of letters are con fused. A profound thought is in a constant state of becoming; it adopts the experience of a life and assumes its shape. Likewise, a man’s sole creation is strengthened in its successive and multiple aspects: his works. One after another, they complement one another, correct or overtake one another, contradict one another too. If something brings creation to an end, it is not the victorious and illusory cry of the blinded artist: ‘I have said everything’ , but the death of the creator which closes his experience and the book of his genius.

That effort, that superhuman consciousness are not necessarily apparent to the reader. There is no mystery in human creation. Will performs this miracle. But at least there is no true creation without a secret. To be sure, a succession of works can be but a series of approximations of the same thought. But it is possible to conceive of another type of creator proceeding by juxtaposition. Their works may seem to be devoid of inter-relations. To a certain degree, they are contradictory. But viewed all together, they resume their natural grouping. From death, for instance, they derive their definitive significance. They receive their most obvious light from the very life of their author. At the moment of death, the succession of his works is but a collection of failures. But if those failures all have the same resonance, the creator has managed to repeat the image of his own condition, to make the air echo with the sterile secret he possesses.

The effort to dominate is considerable here. But human intelligence is up to much more. It will merely indicate clearly the voluntary aspect of creation. Elsewhere I have brought out the fact that human will had no other purpose than to maintain awareness. But that could not do without discipline. Of all the schools of patience and lucidity, creation is the most effective. It is also the staggering evidence of man’s sole dignity: the dogged revolt against his condition, perseverance in an effort considered sterile. It calls for a daily effort, selfmastery, a precise estimate of the limits of truth, measure and strength. It constitutes an ascesis. All that ‘for nothing’ , in order to repeat and mark time. But perhaps the great work of art has less importance in itself than in the ordeal it demands of a man and the opportunity with which it provides him of overcoming his phantoms and approaching a little closer to his naked reality.

Let there be no mistake in aesthetics. It is not patient inquiry, the unceasing, sterile illustration of a thesis that I am calling for here. Quite the contrary, if I have made myself clearly understood. The thesis-novel, the work that proves, the most hateful of all, is: the one that most often is inspired by a smug thought. You demonstrate the truth you feel sure of possessing. But those are ideas one launches, and ideas are the contrary of thought. Those creators are philosophers, ashamed of themselves. Those I am speaking of or who I imagine are on the contrary lucid thinkers. At a certain point where thought turns back on itself, they raise up the images of their works like the obvious symbols of a limited, mortal, and rebellious thought.

They perhaps prove something. But those proofs are ones that the novelists provide for themselves rather than for the world in general. The essential is that the novelists should triumph in the concrete and that this constitutes their nobility. This wholly carnal triumph has been prepared for them by a thought in which abstract powers have been humiliated. When they are completely so, at the same time the flesh makes the creation shine forth in all its absurd lustre. After all, ironic philosophies produce passionate works.

Any thought that abandons unity glorifies diversity. And diversity is the home of art. The only thought to liberate the mind is that which leaves it alone, certain of its limits and of its impending end. No doctrine tempts it. It awaits the ripening of the work and of life. Detached from it, the work will once more give a barely muffled voice to a soul for ever freed from hope. Or it will give voice to nothing if the creator, tired of his activity, intends to turn away. That is equivalent.

Thus I ask of absurd creation what I required from thought — revolt, freedom, and diversity. Later on it will manifest its utter futility. In that daily effort in which intelligence and passion mingle and delight each other, the absurd man discovers a discipline that will make up the greatest of his strengths. The required diligence, the doggedness and lucidity thus resemble the conqueror’s attitude. To create is likewise to give a shape to one’s fate. For all these characters, their work defines them at least as much as it is defined by them. The actor taught us this: there is no frontier between being and appearing.

Let me repeat. None of all this has any real meaning. On the way to that liberty, there is still a progress to be made. The final effort for these related minds, creator or conqueror, is to manage to free themselves also from their undertakings: succeed in granting that the very work, whether it be conquest, love, or creation, may well not be; consummate thus the utter futility of any individual life. Indeed, that gives them more freedom in the realization of that work, just as becoming aware of the absurdity of life authorized them to plunge into it with every excess.

All that remains is a fate whose outcome alone is fatal. Outside of that single fatality of death, everything, joy or happiness, is liberty. A world remains of which man is the sole master. What bound him was the illusion of another world. The outcome of his thought, ceasing to be renunciatory, flowers in images. It frolics — in myths to be sure — but myths with no other depth than that, of human suffering and, like it, inexhaustible. Not the divine fable that amuses and blinds, but the terrestrial face, gesture, and drama in which are summed up a difficult wisdom and an ephemeral passion.

[1]It is curious to note that the most intellectual kind of painting, the one that tries to reduce reality to its essential elements, is ultimately but a visual delight. All it has kept of the world is its colour. （This is apparent particularly in Léger.）

[2]If you stop to think of it, this explains the worst novels. Almost everybody considers himself capable of thinking and, to a certain degree, whether right or wrong, really does think. Very few, on the contrary, can fancy themselves poets or artists in words. But from the moment when thought won over style, the mob invaded the novel.
That is not such a great peril as is said. The best are led to make greater demands upon themselves. As for those who succumb, they did not deserve to survive.

[3]Makaux’s work, for instance. But it would have been necessary to deal at the same time with the social question which, in fact, cannot be avoided by absurd thought （even though that thought may put forward several solutions, very different from one another）. One must, however, limit oneself.

[4]‘Stavrogin: “Do you believe in eternal life in the other world?” Kirilov: “No, but in eternal life in this world.”’

[5]‘Man simply invented God in order not to kill himself. That is the summary of universal history down to this moment.’

[6]Boris de Schloezer.

[7]Gide’s curious and penetrating remark: almost all Dostoievsky’s heroes are polygamous.

[8]Melville’s Moby Dick, for instance.

Appendix

Hope and The Absurd in the Work of Franz Kafka

The whole art of Kafka consists in forcing the reader to re-read. His endings, or his absence of endings, suggest explanations which, however, are not revealed in clear language but, before they seem justified, require that the story be reread from another point of view. Sometimes there is a double possibility of interpretation, whence appears the necessity for two readings. This is what the author wanted. But it would be wrong to try to interpret everything in Kafka in detail. A symbol is always in general and, however precise its translation, an artist can restore to it only its movement: there is no word for word rendering. Moreover, nothing is harder to understand than a symbolic work. A symbol always transcends the one who makes use of it and makes him say in reality more than he is aware of expressing. In this regard, the surest means of getting hold of it is not to provoke it, to begin the work without a preconceived attitude and not to look for its hidden currents. For Kafka in particular it is fair to agree to his rules, to approach the drama through its externals and the novel through its form.

At first glance and for a casual reader, they are disturbing adventures that carry off quaking and dogged characters into pursuit of problems they never formulate. In The Trial, Joseph K. is accused. But he doesn’t know of what. He is doubtless eager to defend himself, but he doesn’t know why. The lawyers find his case difficult. Meanwhile he does not neglect to love, to eat, or to read his paper. Then he is judged. But the courtroom is very dark. He doesn’t understand much. He merely assumes that he is condemned, but to what, he barely wonders. At times he suspects just the same and he continues living. Sometime later, two well- dressed and polite gentlemen come to get him and invite him to follow them. Most courteously they lead him into a wretched suburb, put his head on a stone and slit his throat. Before dying the condemned man says merely: ‘like a dog’.

You see that it is hard to speak of a symbol in a tale whose most obvious quality just happens to be naturalness. But naturalness is a hard category to understand. There are works in which the event seems: natural to the reader. But there are others （rarer, to be sure）in which the character considers natural what happens to him. By an odd but obvious paradox, the more extraordinary the character’s adventures are, the more noticeable will be the naturalness of the story: it is in proportion to the divergence we feel between the strangeness: of a man’s life and the simplicity with which that man accepts it. It seems that this naturalness is Kafka’s. And precisely, one is well aware what The Trial means. People have spoken of an image of the human condition. To be sure. Yet it is both simpler and more complex. I mean that the significance of the novel is more particular and more personal to Kafka. To a certain degree, he is the one who does the talking, even though it is us he confesses. He lives and he is condemned. He learns this on the first pages of the novel he is pursuing in this world, and if he tries; to cope with this, he nonetheless does so without surprise. He will never show sufficient astonishment at this lack of astonishment. It is by such contradictions that the first signs of the absurd work are recognized. The mind projects into the concrete its: spiritual tragedy. And it can do so solely by means of a perpetual paradox which confers on colours the power to express the void and on daily gestures the strength to translate eternal ambitions.

Likewise, The Castle is perhaps a theology in action, but it is first of all the individual adventure of a soul in quest of its grace, of a man who asks of this world’s objects their royal secret and of women the signs of the god that sleeps in them. Metamorphosis, in turn, certainly represents the horrible imagery of an ethic of lucidity. But it is also the product of that incalculable amazement man feels at being conscious of the beast he becomes effortlessly. In this funda mental ambiguity lies Kafka’s secret. These perpetual oscillations between the natural and the extraordinary, the individual and the universal, the tragic and the everyday, the absurd and the logical, are found throughout his work and give it both its resonance and its meaning. These are the paradoxes that must be enumerated, the contradictions that must be strengthened, in order to understand the absurd work.

A symbol, indeed, assumes two planes, two worlds of ideas and sensations, and a dictionary of correspondences between them. This lexicon is the hardest thing to draw up. But awaking to the two worlds brought face to face is tantamount to getting on the trail of their secret relationship. In Kafka these two worlds are that of everyday life on the one hand, and, on the other, that of supernatural anxiety.[1] It seems that we are witnessing here an interminable exploitation of Nietzsche’s remark: ‘Great problems are in the street.’

There is in the human condition （and this is a common place of all literatures）a basic absurdity as well as an implacable nobility. The two coincide, as is natural. Both of them are represented, let me repeat, in the ridiculous divorce separating our spiritual excesses and the ephemeral joys of the body. The absurd thing is that it should be the soul of this body which it transcends so inordinately. Whoever would like to represent this absurdity must give it life in a series of parallel contrasts. Thus it is that Kafka expresses tragedy by the everyday and the absurd by the logical.

An actor lends more force to a tragic character the more careful he is not to exaggerate it. If he is moderate, the horror he inspires will be immoderate. In this regard Greek tragedy is rich in lessons. In a tragic work fate always makes itself felt better in the guise of logic and naturalness. Oedipus’s fate is announced in advance. It is decided super naturally that he will commit the murder and the incest. The drama’s whole effort is to show the logical system which, from deduction to deduction, will crown the hero’s misfortune. Merely to announce to us that uncommon fate is scarcely horrible, because it is improbable. But if its necessity is demonstrated to us in the framework of everyday life, society, state, familiar emotion, then the horror is hallowed. In that revolt that shakes man and makes him say: ‘That is not possible,’ there is an element of desperate certainty that ‘that’ can be.

This is the whole secret of Greek tragedy or at least of one of its aspects. For there is another which, by a reverse method, would help us to understand Kafka better. The human heart has a tiresome tendency to label as fate only what crushes it. But happiness likewise, in its way, is without reason, since it is inevitable. Modem man, however, takes the credit for it himself, when he doesn’t fail to recognize it. Much could be said, on the contrary, about the privileged fates of Greek tragedy and those favoured in legend who, like Ulysses, in the midst of the worst adventures, are saved from themselves. It was not so easy to return to Ithaca.

What must be remembered in any case is that secret complicity that joins the logical and the everyday to the tragic. This is why Smsa, the hero of Metamorphosis, is a travelling salesman. This is why the only thing that disturbs him in the strange adventure that makes a vermin of him is that his boss will be angry at his absence. Legs and feelers grow out on him, his spine arches up, white spots appear on his belly and — I shall not say that this does not astonish him, for the effect would be spoiled — it causes him a ‘slight annoyance’. The whole art of Kafka is in that distinction. In his central work, The Castle, the details of everyday life stand out and yet in that strange novel in which nothing concludes and everything begins over again, it is the essential adventure of a soul in quest of its grace that is represented. That translation of the problem into action, that coincidence of the general and the particular are recognized likewise in the little artifices that belong to every great creator. In The Trial the hero might have been named Schmidt or Franz Kafka. But he is named Joseph K. He is not Kafka and yet he is Kafka. He is an average European. He is like everybody else. But he is also the entity K. who is the x of this flesh and blood equation.

Likewise if Kafka wants to express the absurd, he will make use of consistency. You know the stow of the crazy man who was fishing in a bathtub. A doctor with ideas as to psychiatric treatments asked him ‘if they were biting’ , to which he received the harsh reply: ‘Of course not, you fool, since this is a bathtub.’ That story belongs to the baroque type. But in it can be grasped quite clearly to what a degree the absurd effect is linked to an excess of logic. Kafka’s world is in truth an indescribable universe in which man allows himself the tormenting luxury of fishing in a bathtub, knowing that nothing will come of it.

Consequently I recognize here a work that is absurd in its principles. As for The Trial, for instance, I can indeed say that it is a complete success. Flesh wins out. Nothing is lacking, neither the unexpressed revolt （but it is what is writing）, nor lucid and mute despair （but it is what is creating）, nor that amazing freedom of manner which the characters of the novel exemplify until their ultimate death.

Yet this world is not so closed as it seems. Into this universe devoid of progress, Kafk a is going to introduce hope in a strange form. In this regard The Trial and The Castle do not follow the same direction. They complement each other. The barely perceptible progression from one to the other represents a tremendous conquest in the realm of evasion. The Trial propounds a problem which The Castle, to a certain degree, solves. The first describes according to a quasiscientific method, and without concluding. The second, to a certain degree, explains. The Trial diagnoses, and The Castle imagines a treatment. But the remedy proposed here does not cure. It merely brings the malady back into normal life. It helps to accept it. In a certain sense （let us think of Kierkegaard）, it makes people cherish it. The Land Surveyor K. cannot imagine another anxiety than the one that is tormenting him. The very people around him become attached to that void and that nameless pain, as if suffering assumed in this case a privileged aspect. ‘How I need you,’ Frieda says to K. ‘How forsaken I feel, since knowing you, when you are not with me.’ This subtle remedy that makes us love what crushes us and makes hope spring up in a world without issue, this sudden ‘leap’ through which everything is changed, is the secret of the existential revolution and of The Castle itself.

Few works are more rigorous in their development than The Castle. K. is named Land Surveyor to the Castle and he arrives in the village. But from the village to the Castle it is impossible to communicate. For hundreds of pages K. persists in seeking his way, makes every advance, uses trickery and expedients, never gets angry, and with disconcerting good-will tries to assume the duties entrusted to him. Each chapter is a new frustration. And also a new beginning. It is not logic but consistent method. The scope of that insistence constitutes the work’s tragic quality. When K. telephones to the Castle, he hears confused, mingled voices, vague laughs, distant invitations. That is enough to feed his hope, like those few signs appearing in summer skies or those evening anticipations which make up our reason for living. Here is found the secret of the melancholy peculiar to Kafka. The same, in truth, that is found in Proust’s work or in the landscape of Plotinus: a nostalgia for a lost paradise. ‘I become very sad,’ says Olga, ‘when Barnabas tells me in the morning that he is going to the Castle: that probably futile trip, that wasted day, that probably empty hope.’ ‘Probably’ — on this implication Kafka gambles his entire work. But nothing avails; the quest of the eternal here is meticulous. And those inspired automata, Kafka’s characters, provide us with a precise image of what we should be if we were deprived of our distractions[2] and utterly consigned to the humiliations of the divine.

In The Castle that surrender to the everyday becomes an ethic. The great hope of K. is to get the Castle to adopt him. Unable to achieve this alone, his whole effort is to deserve this favour by becoming an inhabitant of the village, by losing the status of foreigner that everyone makes him feel. What he wants is an occupation, a home, the life of a healthy, normal man. He can’t stand his madness any longer. He wants to be reasonable. He wants to cast off the peculiar curse that makes him a stranger to the village. The episode of Frieda is significant in this regard. If he takes as his mistress this woman who has known one of the Castle’s officials, this is because of her past. He derives from her something that transcends him — while being aware of what makes her for ever unworthy of the Castle. This makes one think of Kierkegaard’s strange love for Regina Olsen. In certain men, the fire of eternity consuming them is great enough for them to bum in it the very heart of those closest to them. The fatal mistake that consists in giving to God what is not God’s is likewise the subject of this episode of The Castle. But for Kafka it seems that this is not a mistake. It is a doctrine and a ‘leap’. There is nothing that is not God’s.

Even more significant is the fact that the Land Surveyor breaks with Frieda in order to go towards the Barnabas sisters. For the Barnabas family is the only one in the village that is utterly forsaken by the Castle and by the village itself. Amalia, the elder sister, has rejected the shameful pro positions made her by one of the Castle’s officials. The immoral curse that followed has forever cast her out from the love of God. Being incapable of losing one’s honour for God amounts to making oneself unworthy of his grace. You recognize a theme familiar to existential philosophy: truth contrary to morality. At this point things are far-reaching. For the path pursued by Kafka’s hero from Frieda to the Barnabas sisters is the very one that leads from trusting love to the deification of the absurd. Here again Kafka’s thought runs parallel to Kierkegaard. It is not surprising that the ‘Barnabas story’ is placed at the end of the book. The Land Surveyor’s last attempt is to recapture God through what negates him, to recognize him, not according to our categories of goodness and beauty but behind the empty and hideous aspects of his indifference, of his injustice, and of his hatred. That stranger who asks the Castle to adopt him is at the end of his voyage a little more exiled because this time he is unfaithful to himself, forsaking morality, logic, and intellectual truths in order to try to enter, endowed solely with his mad hope, the desert of divine grace.[3]

The word ‘hope’ used here is not ridiculous. On the contrary, the more tragic the condition described by Kafka, the firmer and more aggressive that hope becomes. The more truly absurd The Trial is, the more moving and illegitimate the impassioned ‘leap’ of The Castle seems. But we find here again in a pure state the paradox of existential thought as it is expressed, for instance, by Kierkegaard: ‘Earthly hope must be killed; only then can one be saved by true hope’[4] which can be translated: ‘One has to have written The Trial to undertake The Castle.’

Most of those who have spoken of Kafka have indeed de fined his work as a desperate cry with no recourse left to man. But this calls for review. There is hope and hope. To me the optimistic work of Henri Bordeaux seems peculiarly discouraging. This is because it has nothing for the discriminating. Malraux’s thought on the other hand is always bracing. But in these two cases neither the same hope nor the same despair is at issue. I see merely that the absurd work itself may lead to the infidelity I want to avoid. The work which was but an ineffectual repetition of a sterile condition, a lucid glorification of the ephemeral, becomes here a cradle of illusions. It explains, it gives a shape to hope. The creator can no longer divorce himself from it. It is not the tragic game it was to be. It gives a meaning to the author’s life.

It is strange in any case that works of related inspiration like those of Kafka, Kierkegaard or Chestov, those in short of existential novelists and philosophers completely oriented towards the absurd and its consequences, should in the long run lead to that tremendous cry of hope.

They embrace the God that consumes them. It is through humility that hope enters in. For the absurd of this existence assures them a little more of supernatural reality. If the course of this life leads to God, there is an outcome after all. And the perseverance, the insistence with which Kierkegaard, Chestov and Kafka’s heroes repeat their itineraries are a special warrant of the uplifting power of that cer tainty.[5]

Kafka refuses his god moral nobility, evidence, virtue, coherence, but only the better to fall into his arms. The absurd is recognized, accepted, and man is resigned to it, but from then on we know that it has ceased to be the absurd. Within the limits of the human condition, what greater hope than the hope that allows an escape from that con dition? As I see once more, existential thought in this regard （and contrary to current opinion）is steeped in a vast hope. The very hope which at the time of early Christianity and the spreading of the news inflamed the ancient world. But in that leap that characterizes all existential thought, in that insistence, in that surveying of a divinity devoid of surface, how can one fail to see the mark of a lucidity that repudiates itself? It is merely claimed that this is pride abdicating to save itself. Such a repudiation would be fecund. But this does not change that. The moral of lucidity cannot be diminished in my eyes by calling it sterile like all pride. For a truth also, by its very definition, is sterile. All facts are. In a world where everything is given and nothing is explained, the fecundity of a value or of a metaphysic is a notion devoid of meaning.

In any case, you see here in what tradition of thought Kafka’s work takes its place. It would indeed be intelligent to consider as inevitable the progression from The Trial to The Castle. Joseph K. and the Land Surveyor K. are merely two poles that attract Kafka.[6] I shall speak as he does and say that his work is probably not absurd. But that should not deter us from seeing its nobility and universality. They come from the fact that he managed to represent so fully the everyday passage from hope to grief and from desperate wisdom to intentional blindness. His work is universal （a really absurd work is not universal）to the extent to which it represents the emotionally moving face of man fleeing humanity, deriving from his contradictions reasons for believing, reasons for hoping from his fecund despairs, and calling life his terrifying apprenticeship in death. It is universal because its inspiration is religious. As in all religions, man is freed of the weight of his own life. But if I know that, if I can even admire it, I also know that I am not seeking what is universal but what is true. The two may well not coincide.

This particular view will be better understood if I say that truly hopeless thought just happens to be defined by the opposite criteria and that the tragic work might be the work that, after all future hope is exiled, describes the life of a happy man. The more exciting life is, the more absurd is the idea of losing it. This is perhaps the secret of that proud aridity felt in Nietzsche’s work. In this connection, Nietzsche appears to be the only artist to have derived the extreme consequences of an aesthetic of the absurd, in as much as his final message lies in a sterile and conquering lucidity and an obstinate negation of any supernatural consolation.

The preceding should nevertheless suffice to bring out the capital importance of Kafka in the framework of this essay. Here we are carried to the confines of human thought. In the fullest sense of the word, it can be said that everything in that work is essential. In any case it propounds the absurd problem altogether. If one wants to compare these conclusions with our initial remarks, the content with the form, the secret meaning of The Castle with the natural art in which it is moulded, K.’s passionate, proud quest with the everyday setting against which it takes place, then one will realize what may be its greamess. For if nostalgia is the mark of the human, perhaps no one has given such flesh and volume to these phantoms of regret. But at the same time will be sensed what exceptional nobility the absurd work calls for, which is perhaps not found here. If the nature of art is to bind the general to the particular, ephemeral eternity of a drop of water to the play of its lights, it is even truer to judge the greamess of the absurd writer by the distance he is able to introduce between these two worlds. His secret consists in being able to find the exact point where they meet in their greatest disproportion.

And to tell the truth, this geometrical locus of man and the inhuman is seen everywhere by the pure in heart. If Faust and Don Quixote are eminent creations of art, this is because of the immeasurable nobilities they point out to us with their earthly hands. Yet a moment always comes when the mind negates the truths that those hands can touch. A moment comes when the creation ceases to be taken tragically; it is merely taken seriously. Then man is concerned with hope. But that is not his business. His business is to turn away from subterfuge. Yet this is just what I find at the conclusion of the vehement proceedings Kafka institutes against the whole universe. His unbelievable verdict is this hideous and upsetting world in which the very moles dare to hope.[7]

[1]It is worth noting that the works of Kafka can quite as legitimately be interpreted in the sense of a social criticism （for instance in The Trial）. It is probable, moreover, that there is no need to choose. Both interpretations are good. In absurd terms, as we have seen, revolt against men is also directed against God: great revolutions are always metaphysical.

[2]In The Castle it seems that ‘distractions’ in the Pascalian sense are represented by the assistants who ‘distract’ K. from his anxiety. If Frieda eventually becomes the mistress of one of the assistants, this is because she prefers the stage setting to truth, everyday life to shared anguish.

[3]This is obviously true only of the unfinished version of The Castle that Kafka left us. But it is doubtful that the writer would have destroyed in the last chapters his novel’s unity of tone.

[4]Purity of heart.

[5]The only character without hope in The Castle is Amalia. She is the one with whom the Land Surveyor is most violently contrasted.

[6]On the two aspects of Kafka’s thought, compare ‘In the Penal Colon’ published by the Cahiers du Sud （and in America by Partisan Review— translator’s note）: ‘Guilt [“of man” is understood] is never doubtful’ and a fragment of The Castle （Momus’ report）: ‘The guilt of the Land Surveyor K. is hard to establish.’

[7]What is offered above is obviously an interpretation of Kafka’s work. But it is only fair to add that nothing prevents its being considered, apart from any interpretation, from a purely aesthetic point of view. For instance, B. Groethuysen in his remarkable preface to The Trial limits himself, more wisely than we, to following merely the painful fancies of what he calls, most strikingly, a day dreamer. It is the fate and perhaps the greatness of that work that it offers everything and confirms nothing.

导读

巴达萨尔·卡斯蒂廖内（Baldesar Castiglione，1478—1529），意大利文艺复兴时期外交家、人文主义作家。

卡斯蒂廖内出身于意大利北部曼托瓦城的一个贵族家庭，14岁就被父亲送进米兰大学，学习文化知识和军事技能，18岁在米兰大公宫廷学习礼仪。1499年父亲去世，21岁的卡斯蒂廖内回乡继承家业，在曼托瓦的弗朗西斯科·贡萨加（Francesco Gonzaga）侯爵宫廷任职，卡斯蒂廖内文武双全，得到重用。

1501年，乌尔比诺被攻占，乌尔比诺公爵吉多贝多·蒙特费特罗（Guidobaldo di Montefeltro）来到曼托瓦避难，与卡斯蒂廖内相识。为缓和双方的矛盾，卡斯蒂廖内首次作为外交官出使斡旋。1503年，卡斯蒂廖内随贡萨加侯爵出征那不勒斯，战争结束后在罗马偶遇吉多贝多公爵，两人惺惺相惜，卡斯蒂廖内决定离开曼托瓦，加入吉多贝多公爵麾下效力。在任期间，卡斯蒂廖内为公爵出使罗马、英国等地。

1508年，吉多贝多公爵去世，卡斯蒂廖内决定写书纪念公爵，由于公务繁忙，直到1527年，花了将近20年才写完，1528年此书在威尼斯出版发行，书名《宫廷侍臣的故事》（The Book of the Courtier），次年（1529年），卡斯蒂廖内病逝于西班牙。

吉多贝多公爵去世后，卡斯蒂廖内继续辅佐公爵的继承人弗朗西斯科·玛利亚·德拉·罗维尔（Francesco Maria della Rovere），1508至1514年，乌尔比诺卷入多场混战。1516年，新任教皇剥夺了弗朗西斯科的领地，卡斯蒂廖内回到故乡曼托瓦隐居。1519年，新任曼托瓦侯爵费德里科·贡萨加起用卡斯蒂廖内作为大使常驻罗马，两年后，由于他的努力，旧主弗朗西斯科收回了乌尔比诺的领地，卡斯蒂廖内由此获得很高的声誉。1524年，卡斯蒂廖内成为教皇克莱门特七世（Clement VII）的使臣，连续几年往返于罗马和西班牙之间，代表教皇与神圣罗马帝国皇帝查理五世（Charles V）沟通，1529年卡斯蒂廖内病逝后，查理五世称赞他为”世上最好的骑士之一”。

卡斯蒂廖内本人是一位优秀的宫廷侍臣，一位朋友评价《宫廷侍臣的故事》说：“你写的就是你自己。”《宫廷侍臣的故事》出版后不久，就被翻译成多种语言，影响了整个欧洲，一度被当成经典来学习。虽经教会大幅删改，但因版本众多、流传甚广，且有手稿存世，所以我们今天看到的，基本上还是作者的原始文本。

《实现卓越》（How to Achieve True Greatness）从《宫廷侍臣的故事》中节选出来，分为两个部分。第一部分主要讨论完美侍臣的个人修养；第二部分以君臣关系、男女爱情关系为主。

“宫廷侍臣的故事（一）”以较大的篇幅讨论了侍臣的军事才能，在作者所处的时代，军事才能的确非常重要。11世纪，诺曼人侵入原属东罗马帝国（拜占庭）的意大利南部，建立王国。12—13世纪，“神圣罗马帝国”对意大利北部、中部的统治瓦解，该地区分裂成许多王国、公国、自治城邦和小封建领地。文艺复兴时期（14—16世纪）的意大利处于混乱的战国时期，法国、西班牙虎视眈眈，所有的势力都不能独善其身。在这样的环境中，一个完美的侍臣，要有能力辅佐他的主公打胜仗，最好是不战而屈人之兵，这样他就不仅需要能战斗，还需要有学识、有智慧，还需要“风度”来处理上下、内外关系，当然，他也要像个人一样有能力享受生活，而不是工作狂。

在“宫廷侍臣的故事（二）”中提到：“一些统治者尽管对如何治理国家一无所知，还是厚颜无耻地试图统治整个世界而非眼前的一小班人马。”欧洲最早的资本主义萌芽出现在意大利，12世纪，一位主教来到意大利，观察到这里出现以商人和商业为基础的社会组织形式；14世纪初，人们开始表达反君主制思想。在这样的大背景下，如下观点还算是客气得体的：完美侍臣对君主，不是阿谀奉承，而是指引他向善，防止他成为昏君；不该给他送财物，而该给他送美德。

黑暗的中世纪，教会控制着社会，文学、艺术、哲学都不能违背教义，然而黑死病的蔓延动摇了神的权威，人们需要“以人为本”的生活。在“宫廷侍臣的故事（二）”中，皮埃特罗·贝博这一角色关于美和爱的长篇大论，受着古希腊哲学的影响，却又归结到上帝的身上。一些听者看似猥琐的质疑，也在客观上挑明一个事实，这种轻视形体审美和肉体享乐的纯粹灵魂之美与纯粹精神恋爱已届暮年，且不属人间所有。

早在公元476年，西罗马帝国就已经灭亡；公元1453年，东罗马帝国灭亡；意大利长期遭受西班牙、法国侵略，意大利人会希望看到正统的罗马帝国的重生。于是，资本主义、人文主义、罗马荣耀等因素，就戴着“希腊、罗马古典文化重生”的面具出现在意大利，并蔓延到整个欧洲，这就是文艺复兴。

故事中的乌尔比诺，位于意大利中部，接近欧洲文艺复兴发源地佛罗伦萨。吉多贝多公爵的父亲费德里科（Federico da Montefeltro）公爵热爱文化，藏书丰富。五百多年历史的公爵宫，现在被列为世界文化遗产。15世纪下半叶，在费德里科公爵的治理下，乌尔比诺人民安居乐业，各得其所。文艺复兴后期“三杰”之一，画家拉斐尔的家乡就在乌尔比诺，卡斯蒂廖内肖像画是他的代表作之一。

余雄杰

宫廷侍臣的故事（一）

亲爱的阿方索，对于应该拒绝还是接受你一再要我做的事情，我思索了很久，这确实是个很难的决定。一方面，我好像很难拒绝我由衷喜欢并真心喜欢我的人提出的要求，尤其是那些值得赞赏的要求；另一方面，我又觉得让我这样一个在意别人批评意见的人去做一件自己没有把握的事，好像是个错误。但最后，经过反复考虑，我还是决定接受挑战，看看自己在友情的激励和感召下，能够多么勤奋认真地去做事。

如今你要求我描述出我心目中最适合的宫廷侍臣的标准。达到标准的绅士将既有才学又有能力辅佐君王，从而赢得君王的喜爱和他人的赞誉。总而言之，你想知道什么样的人才能不辱完美侍臣的美名，做到毫无瑕疵。鉴于你的这个请求，我必须承认，我接受它的原因在于我更看重朋友的情谊，而不是他人的怀疑态度。但是我本该拒绝这个苦差事的，因为我害怕被人指责为轻率，要知道从信奉基督教的皇室所遵循的众多风俗中选出完美的典范，也就是完美侍臣的精髓，是一件多么艰难的事情。因为人们对于熟知的风俗也经常是时而崇尚，时而唾弃，即一段时期内被认可的风俗习惯、行为礼仪及生活方式随着时间的推移会遭到鄙视，而曾经受到鄙视的又会渐渐得到认可。所以，在引进新事物、摒弃旧事物的时候，我们可以清楚地看到，惯例比理性更起作用。无论任何人想要在这些事情上做到完美都是在自欺欺人。由于深知这些因素以及这个话题所涉及的许多其他问题，我想替自己找个借口，此外我还想证实，我犯的错（若可以这样讲）你也有责任，我受到责备，你也必须受到责备，我接受了这个任务有错，但是，是你将这个超出我能力范围的苦差事强加给了我。

现在我们还是开始讨论一下我们选定的这个话题吧，如果可能的话，我们共同打造出一个完美侍臣，从而使那个值得他辅佐的君王，即使统治疆域不够辽阔，也可以认为自己是一位真正伟大的统治者。在这些侍臣手册里，我们无需采用传授知识的常规做法，去遵循任何严格的法规或者戒律；只需循着古人的足迹，唤回美好的记忆，重新审视几个对此话题见地颇深的人曾经进行过的讨论。虽然我没能亲自参与讨论（举行讨论的时候，我在英国），但参加讨论的人在我回来之后，立即原原本本地向我讲述了讨论的内容。我现在要尽可能精确地将它们重新呈现出来，以便让你们了解学识出众的人对这一话题的见解，他们的见解是完全令人信服的。为了故事叙述的逻辑性，我先描述一下这场讨论发生的背景，希望这并不会偏离主题。

众所周知，乌尔比诺是一个靠近意大利中心的小城市，它面朝亚得里亚海，坐落于亚平宁山脉的山坡上。虽说环绕在它周围的小山景致平平，比不上许多其他地方，这座城市依然得到了大自然的恩宠，物产丰富，健康宜居。在它享有的众多恩惠和优势中，我认为最重要的是，这里一直不乏杰出的统治者，尽管它也曾在意大利被卷入战乱之时，一度脱离了明君的管辖。远的不说，费德里科公爵[1]的辉煌过去就是个极好的例子。他是当时的意大利之光，时至今日，仍可找出大量有关他的审慎、仁爱、公正、无私、宽宏以及不屈精神的见证。此外，他的军事才能更是非比寻常，他曾多次取得战斗的胜利，占领坚不可摧的阵地，用兵神速果断，以少胜多，甚至战无不胜。因此，将其与许多古代著名的人物相提并论毫不为过。他还做了很多其他令人钦佩的事情，例如在乌尔比诺的丘陵之地建起一座意大利最美丽的宫殿，这座宫殿装修之精致，简直堪与一座城市相媲美。因为在装饰这座宫殿的时候，公爵不仅选用了最常用的装饰品，比如银花瓶和用金线、丝线以及其他珍贵材料编织而成的挂毯等，还选用了不计其数的古式大理石和铜制雕像、绘画珍品以及各种乐器，总之，他把最罕见、最出色的宝物都汇聚到了这里。随后，他又斥巨资收藏了大量最精美和珍贵的以希腊文、拉丁文和希伯来文撰写的书籍，用金银加以装饰，并将之视为其伟大宫殿的最高荣耀。

生老病死是自然规律，费德里科在六十五岁时便带着一生的荣耀永远地离开了人世，唯留一子，名叫吉多贝多，他年幼丧母，年方十岁便继承了爵位。吉多贝多不仅继承了父亲留下的基业，还传承了他的美德，他的不凡性情注定使其成为又一位非凡的君王。总之，大家认为在费德里科公爵所做的令人赞叹的事情中，最伟大的事情就是养育了这样一个儿子。但是他的伟大品质遭到命运女神嫉妒，她不遗余力地打击这位出身如此高贵的年轻人。吉多未满二十岁时就患上了痛风，随着病情的加重，他遭受了极大的痛苦，没多久便残疾了，他的病情十分严重，不能站立也无法行走。从此，一个世界上最优秀、最帅气的人，在年纪尚轻的时候就肢体残疾了。然而命运女神并没有就此罢手，她总是挫败吉多的计划，致使他很少成功；尽管吉多是个深思熟虑、拥有不屈精神的人，但其经手的事情，无论大小，无论是战争还是其他，总是不得善终。这点我们可以从他的各种悲惨遭遇中看出来，而他总是用坚韧不拔的精神来面对这一切。他不但没有被命运击垮，反而蔑视命运的打击，表现出强大的适应能力和不屈的精神。在疾病和困境缠身的情况下，度过健康而幸福的一生，并赢得了真正的尊严和公认的美誉。因此，尽管身体孱弱，他还是以最高统帅的身份统领部队作战，为尊贵的国王阿方索以及年轻的那不勒斯王费迪南德效力；此后还与教皇亚历山大六世以及威尼斯和佛罗伦萨的统帅们协同作战。教皇朱利斯二世继位后，他被任命为教会的首领。在这期间，他除了保持以往的生活方式外，还经常邀请高尚可敬的绅士们来家中做客。有了他们的陪伴，最普通的任期也变得愉快万分。吉多擅长用拉丁语和希腊语作诗，为人和蔼可亲并且知识渊博，因此他带给周围人的欢乐丝毫不亚于别人带给他的欢乐。此外，即使他无法像以前一样参与骑马运动，他还是喜欢观看你追我赶的骑马场面，并作出精妙的评价，根据不同的人的长处进行指正或赞扬。而陪伴他的那些出身高贵的绅士们总是在各种场合力争上佳表现，如格斗、比赛、马术、兵器表演、节日、游戏、音乐演奏，等等，以不辜负公爵对自己的赏识。

于是乌尔比诺每天都举行各种高雅并且令人身心愉悦的活动。可是由于公爵身体虚弱，晚饭过后通常需要回到自己的卧房稍事休息，所以这段时间大家都跑去陪伴公爵夫人伊丽莎贝塔·贡萨加，她身边有位伊米莉亚·派亚夫人，要知道，这位夫人可不一般，她活泼风趣、聪明睿智，好像有能力安排好一切，并能时刻让人感受到她的精明和善意。大家在一起时，礼貌的谈话和单纯的幽默让每个人的脸上都洋溢着笑容和快乐，整个屋子真可谓是快乐驿站。我可以很肯定地说，在乌尔比诺，挚友们给彼此带来的快乐和享受他处难寻。在这里，除了以上我所描述的，每个人因辅佐公爵而获得的荣誉感外，我们还因伯爵夫人的存在而感到无比愉悦和满足。这种满足感在我们之间形成了一条强大的感情纽带，使得我们意见和谐一致，真心相爱，找到了亲兄弟之间都难以找到的亲密感觉。对于尊贵的女士们，我们享有自由而单纯地追随左右的权利，我们可以跟她们坐在一起聊天、说笑，当然我们所享受的自由要受到最谨慎的自我约束，一定要尊重公爵夫人的愿望。大家一致认为最令人愉悦的事情就是讨她欢心，而世界上最不幸的事情就是令她不快。正因为这些原因，她的这个团体成了同时拥有最好的教养和最大的自由的统一体；她出席时，我们的游戏和笑话都充满了最犀利的俏皮话和优美而朴素的尊贵感。公爵夫人在打趣的时候总是那样言辞得体、举止端庄，即便是第一次见到她的人，都会发现她是一位多么伟大的女性。从她影响周围人的方式来看，好像她总能使我们不知不觉地学习她的性格和品质，每个人都努力模仿她的行为方式，并试图从这位伟大又聪明的女性身上总结出一种优秀的品行模式。在此我不打算详述她的高尚品质，不仅是因为这已超越了我的语言表述能力，还因描述她的品质并不是我的目的所在，因为这些品质早已经是众所周知的了。但我还必须补充一些在公爵夫人身上隐藏着的某些其他品质。好像命运女神也倾慕这位世间罕有的伟大女性，命运选择了用逆境和残酷的打击来证实这位温柔的女性除了拥有非凡的美貌之外，还拥有在最坚定的男人身上都难以找到的审慎和勇气。

故事继续进行，依照惯例，所有的绅士在晚饭后都会立刻赶往公爵夫人那里，那儿安排了各种各样的娱乐活动，美妙的音乐、迷人的舞蹈一个接着一个。有时大家会提出一些非常有趣的问题，或者（根据这人或那人的提议）玩一些巧妙有趣的游戏。比如在场的人会用寓意很深的语言来掩饰自己的想法，请其他人猜。有时候，大家会讨论各种各样的话题，或者以即兴问答的方式说些犀利的俏皮话。在这种场合，大家通常会运用我们现在所说的“象征”的手法，所有人都非常享受这种交流，因为在场的人都是我所说的那种非常高贵而且聪明的人。

……

按规矩，参加公爵夫人聚会的人会围坐成一圈，大家可以随意坐，如果有女士在场，就要男女交替而坐，但男士的数量通常多于女士。然后大家都等着公爵夫人主持大局，这时公爵夫人总是把主持大权交给伊米莉亚夫人。所以教皇离开的第二天，他们就按照原定的时间相聚在老地方，进行一番愉悦的讨论后，公爵夫人请伊米莉亚夫人宣布游戏开始。

……

每个人都等着伊米莉亚夫人发话，可她没有对贝博说一句话，却转向费德里科·弗莱高索，意思是请他提议做个游戏。他立刻说道：“夫人，……为了教训一下那些自以为是，荒谬地认为自己可以被称为优秀侍臣的人，我建议今晚我们做一个游戏：从我们之中选一个人描述一下完美侍臣的标准，具体说明应具备什么样的性格和特别品质才配得上这个称号。这次争论只停留在哲理层面，如果有任何不恰当的观点，我们每个人都可以进行反驳。”

费德里科刚要继续往下说，伊米莉亚夫人突然打断他，说道：“如果这是公爵夫人希望的，今晚我们就玩这个游戏。”

于是，公爵夫人回答：“没错，这正是我所希望的。”

接下来，几乎所有在场的人都开始议论起来，有的跟其他人说，有的跟公爵夫人说，总之他们认为这是最好的游戏，已经迫不及待要听听大家的高见了，他们急切地想知道伊米莉亚夫人要谁第一个发言。于是，只见她转向公爵夫人，说道：“夫人，我可不想从他们中间选出第一个人，这样做好像是在表明我认为这个人最有能力似的，我会因此得罪了其他人，还是您来决定让谁先说吧。”

公爵夫人回答道：“不，必须你来选，不服从我的命令的话，你会给其他人树立一个坏榜样的。”

于是，伊米莉亚夫人面带笑容地对来自卡诺萨的洛多维科伯爵说道：“好吧，为了不浪费更多的时间，您就做费德里科提议的这个游戏的第一人吧。我想说的是，不是因为我们认为您是位很出色的侍臣，所以一定知道侍臣应该具备什么品质。而是因为我们希望您说的不正确，那样每个人都有理由反驳您，游戏也会很有趣。但如果把这个任务交给一个比您学识渊博的人，他说的话就成了真理，人们就无法挑战他的观点了，如果真是这样，这个游戏就会十分无趣了。”

伯爵立即回应道：“不过，夫人，有您的在场，我们完全不必担心，相信真理一定会被反复推敲的。”

……

“首先我想说，从任何事物中找到真正的完美都是很艰难的事情，甚至是不可能的。这是因为不同观点会导致对完美的不同定义。因此，有人喜欢健谈的人，认为他们是令人愉悦的好伙伴；有些则喜欢慎言的人；还有些喜欢活跃的人；而有的就喜欢做事稳重的人，由此可见，每个人都是根据自己的观点来判断事物的好坏。因此经常会本末倒置，以相应的优点来掩盖缺点，或是以相应的缺点来掩盖优点。例如，你可以把一个冒失的人说成是坦率，一个朴实的人说成是无趣，一个头脑简单的人说成是心地善良，还可以把一个无赖说成是精明的人，诸如此类的事情不胜枚举。但是我仍相信一切事物皆有完美，即便它可能被掩藏了起来，我们还是可以通过多方的推理和论证找到它。正如我之前所言，真相总是掩藏在那里。我称不上是个学识渊博的人，所以只能赞扬自己景仰的那类侍臣是个什么样子，以及在我的判断力所及的范围内如何做才是正确的。若您觉得我的观点正确，您可以表示赞同；若您和我的观点不一，您可以坚持自己的观点。我不会去争辩我的看法比您的更好，不仅因为我们的想法可以有所不同，还因为我自己的想法也在不断变化。”

伯爵继续说：“我认为，侍臣应该出身高贵并且具有良好的家庭背景。这是因为普通人品行的好坏对他的重要性远不及贵族。如果一位绅士偏离了祖辈的正道，他就辱没了他的家族，不仅一事无成还要落得个前功尽弃的下场。高贵的出身就像一盏明灯，将善行和恶举暴露于亮光之下，它鼓励和激发高贵的人为荣誉和赞美多做善事。而对普通人来说，他们的行为不在高贵光环的照耀之下，他们没有受到这种光环的激励，也不必担心颜面尽失，并且他也没有一定要超越自己祖先的压力。与之相反，出身高贵的人认为自己的成就没能达到或是超越先辈，就应该受到谴责。因此，通常情况下，在战争和其他重要活动中取得卓越成就的人大都是贵族。这是因为，大自然在所有的事物中都埋藏了一颗秘密的种子，这颗种子影响着那些源自它的所有事物，使其具备自己的核心特征，同自己有相似之处。这一点我们可以从马匹等动物的繁殖以及植物的衍生中清楚地发现。树木的枝杈总是与树干十分相似。如果有时候它们长得不好，那也是人们疏于照管的原因。人也是一样的道理，若得到悉心的照料和精心的培养，他就会像先辈一样出色，甚至更胜一筹；若没有得到足够的关爱，就会肆意疯长无法成才。当然，下面这种情况也确实存在，有些人天生就是大自然的宠儿，生来就被赋予某种非凡的脑力和体力，以至于他们好像不是简单地来到这个世界，而是得到了上帝的保佑，由上帝之手细心雕琢而成。同样，人们也发现有些人是如此粗俗、荒唐，以至于我们只能认为他们是大自然出于怨恨和嘲弄的目的才将其带到这个世界上来的。正是因为如此，后者即使不停地努力，得到精心的培养，也通常难成正果，而前者只要稍作努力就会达到杰出的顶峰。以费拉拉的红衣主教唐·艾波尼多·德·伊斯特为例，幸运的身世影响了他的性格、外表、言语及行为。因为老天的偏爱，年纪轻轻的他虽身处最德高望重的红衣主教之中，仍拥有相当的权威，与其说他是在受教不如说他是在施教。在跟人交流、游戏以及说笑时也是一样，他的个人魅力和优雅的举止是那样令人叹服，使得所有和他交谈的人，甚至只看过他一眼的人都会深深地喜爱上他并回味良久。但是言归正传，我认为在这种极致的优雅和荒谬的愚笨之间还有一种中间形式，即那些没有得到大自然恩赐的完美，却通过用心和努力来提高自己并且尽可能弥补天生的缺点的人。因此除了出身高贵的绅士之外，我也很偏爱这类侍臣，他们不仅从大自然那里获得了智慧、美丽的外表和良好的为人，还获得了某种风度和优雅，使他很快吸引并取悦遇见他的人，他的优雅表现在举手投足之间，很轻易就会赢得大人物的亲近和喜爱。”

话音刚落，加斯帕雷·帕拉维契诺先生就已经按捺不住了，他说道：“既然我们的游戏要像事先说好的那样进行，为了体现出我们并未忘记使用反驳的特权，请允我表明，我并不认为侍臣必须要出身高贵。如果有人觉得我的话很奇怪，我愿意进行引证说明，许多人即使身上流淌着最高贵的血也会道德极度败坏；相反，许多出身卑微的人却通过自身的美德为其后世子孙赢得荣耀。假设事实真如您所言，也就是，每个事物都受最初掩藏的那颗种子的影响，那么既然我们在最初时是一样的，现在的性格也应该是一样的，何以现在一些人比另一些人更高尚些呢？事实上，我认为我们之间高低贵贱之分是有许多其他原因的。第一个，也是最重要的一个原因，就是命运，她掌控着世间万事，但她经常由着自己的性子，根本不考虑是否合适就将某人抬举一番，而将那些最值得抬举的人重重摔下。您说那些一出生就有完美身心的人很幸福，这我完全同意；然而无论是出身卑微还是高贵，世上都有这样的好运之人，因为大自然显然不懂所谓高贵和卑微的差别。相反，正如我所说的，大自然往往将最杰出的才能赋予出身卑微的人。既然高贵的出身既不是通过才能也不是通过武力或技能获得的，它只是用于鼓励其祖先的东西，跟他本人没有关系。因此有人若继续坚持认为侍臣的父母出身卑微就会破坏他所有的优良品质，并且无法培养出您所提及的完美品质，如才能、美貌、良好性情以及只消一眼就能使他人如沐春风的优雅举止，这听起来是多么奇怪。”

洛多维科伯爵答道：“我并不否认出身低微的人也一样可以具有高贵的美德。但是，除了我们已经讨论的，我还想再给出一个来说明我赞美高贵出身的原因。实践证明了美好的东西会带来好的效果，所以大家都认同这一点，即我们所创造出来的侍臣（毫无缺点，天生具有各种优点）最好是个贵族，只有这样他才会立刻给周围的人留下好印象。例如，宫廷里的两位绅士，在他们还未通过行为举止来展现自己的时候，不论为人好坏，只要人们发现其中一个人出身很好，另一个不好，那就会更加尊重前者；而后者只有通过长期的努力才会赢得这种好感，但前者只是因为出身高贵就唾手可得。我们都很清楚这些印象是多么重要。就说我们自己吧，走进这间屋子的某些人，他们虽然是整个意大利都公认的伟臣，但有些实际上却十分愚笨无趣，即使后来被发现了，他们依然能迷惑我们很长时间，因为在他们到来之前，那种先入为主的好印象会使我们忽略在与之交往中发现的缺点。我们也见过一些人，开始时并不被人看好，最后却取得很大成功。导致这些误会的原因多种多样，其中有一种是因为君王们固执己见，期待发生奇迹般的转变，所以有时明知某人不堪大任，却仍有意宠信。当然，有时候也会出现君王被自己欺骗这种情况，因为君王们拥有无数的效仿者，君王的偏爱会给他的爱臣带来极高的声誉，从而影响到其他人的看法。而且即使人们发现一些看似与普遍观点背道而驰的事情，他们总会认为自己看错了，然后等着真相揭晓。因为人们似乎相信，大家普遍认同的事情一定是以真实合理的事实为依据的。再有，我们很容易迫不及待地表明立场，盲目地支持一方或者反对一方，这种情形在公开竞技、游戏或各种比赛等场合随处可见——旁观者们总是毫无缘由地支持其中的某个选手，急切地希望他赢得漂亮，对手输得很惨。而至于那人的性格与名声的好坏，只有当我们听说了他们的过去，心中才会产生某种喜恶，并以此来判定是否该支持那人。由此可见，第一印象是多么重要，尤其是对一个立志要成为一名优秀侍臣的人来说，努力留下良好的第一印象十分必要。

“但是如果把标准落到实处的话，我认为侍臣最首要的职责应该是军事才能，并且应该成为他第一位的追求目标。此外，他还应该具备出众的进取精神、胆识以及对主人的忠诚。他还应该随时随地全力展示出这些品质，来赢取美名，否则便会招致严重的责难。就像一名贞洁女子的名声一旦被玷污，就再也无法挽回，一名参战的绅士因为胆小或其他有失颜面的行为而毁掉自己的名誉，即使仅仅一次，在所有人眼中永远都是污点，其名誉会永远受损。在我看来，一位优秀侍臣的军事才能也不一定要多么具有专业水准，但是毋庸置疑，他在军事方面做得越出色，就越会得到更多的赞誉。然而，既然我们谈到了这里，就需要深入探讨一下一位伟大的统帅需要具备什么品质，正如我们所言，令我们感到满意的优秀侍臣应该表现出无比的忠诚以及大无畏的精神。人们在小事上总是比在大事上更容易展示出勇气。常见的情况是，在面临极度的危险时，常常会看见一些人虽然怕得要死，却碍于羞耻心或有他人在场，双眼紧闭，奋力向前，履行他们的职责，只有上帝知道究竟是怎么回事儿。但在一些微不足道的小事上，却可以看到他们在确保可以躲避危险又不会被察觉的情况下，早就溜之大吉，不愿意去冒险。而有些人即使知道没有其他人注意或认识自己，还是出于良心，充满热情地做好每件小事，他们身上有着我们要找的侍臣应具有的性情和品质。当然，我们所希望的侍臣不是在作秀，假装自己很勇猛，总是夸夸其谈，号称自己从不脱掉护胸甲，像贝多一样目中无人、怒视一切。曾听一位可敬的女士讲过这样的笑话，她在一次聚会中出于礼貌，邀请某位男士（在此我不想透露他的姓名）跳舞，而该男子不仅拒绝了她，还拒绝听音乐，也不参加其他娱乐活动，说这些风花雪月的事情和他无关。最后，女士问什么与他有关时，他一脸愁容地答道：‘打仗……’

“‘那好，’女士回应道，‘我觉得既然现在未逢战事，您最好给自己上上油，和其他武器装备一起放到壁橱里收藏起来，以免变得比现在更锈迹斑斑。’

“这位女士对他愚蠢行为的讽刺令每个人都爆笑不止。”

“因此，”洛多维科伯爵继续说道，“我们要寻找的那个人一定是在敌人面前勇猛、粗犷并且永远冲锋在前；而在其他的场合，他又应该是友善、谦虚、沉默，尤其是避免炫耀，或可恶的自我称颂，因为这常常引起那些不得不听他说话的人的厌恶和反感。”

“依我看，”加斯帕雷阁下回答道，“我认识的那些出众的人才很少有人不喜欢夸耀自己。在我看来，当一个值得关注的人发现他所做的好事被人忽略，因自己的才能不为人知而气愤，于是被迫以某种方式来表现自己，以免其真正努力应得的荣誉被骗走，这种自夸的方式是可以接受的。因此，古时候的作家们很少有人不赞扬自己。当然，胸无点墨却还硬要称颂自己的人肯定让人无法忍受，但是我们认为我们的侍臣不会是那种人。”

听到这儿，伯爵说道：

“希望你认真听了我所说的话，我方才是在指责那些过分而盲目颂扬自己的人。但是一个真正有才学的人适度地自夸是无可厚非的；当然如果这种赞颂来自于他人则更有说服力。我的意思是说，一个人以正确的方式赞美自己且没有引起嫉妒或反感，那么这是他的自由；他应该得到别人和自己的赞颂，因为他为之付出了极大的努力。”

“那您一定要教教我们该怎样做。”加斯帕雷阁下说道。

“嗯，”伯爵回答，“以前有人曾经教过古时候的作家们如何应对这种情况。但在我看来，正确的做法是注意说话的方式，一种好的说话方式会让人听起来不是为了炫耀自己，而是自然而然、恰到好处；在自夸的时候不能给别人留下自夸的印象，但又不像一些夸夸其谈的人在信口胡说，就像我们中间某人某天曾经说过的那样，他在比萨被长矛刺穿了大腿后，自称就像有一只苍蝇叮了他一下；还有人说他之所以不在房间里放镜子，是因为他发怒时表情非常恐怖，足以把自己吓死。”

大家听了伯爵的话都大笑起来，接着塞萨尔·贡萨加又补充道：

“你们在笑什么？难道你们没听过下面这个故事。亚历山大大帝从某个哲学家那里听说除了这个世界之外还有很多其他的世界，他竟然哭了起来。当大家问他为什么哭的时候，他回答说：‘因为我尚未征服任何一个’——好像他就应该征服所有的世界一样，你们说，这难道不比那个关于苍蝇的说法更离谱吗？”

伯爵接着说道：

“亚历山大大帝可比刚才提到的那个家伙要伟大得多。我们一定要原谅杰出的大人高估自己这种事。毕竟一个成就伟业的人一定要有勇气去做事，也一定要对自己有信心。他不应该怯懦或是卑躬屈膝，但是他在用词上应该谨慎点儿，对自己取得的成就谦虚点儿，并且做事小心一点儿，这样就不会被人指责自以为是了。”

伯爵沉默片刻后，伯纳多·比别纳微笑着说：

“我记得您之前说过，我们的完美侍臣应该有一副天生英俊的脸庞和外表，并且拥有迷人的风度。嗯，我很肯定自己既有风度又有英俊的容貌，正因如此，很多女人都疯狂地爱着我。但是说到体型，我就很没信心了，尤其是我的双腿，它们没能长得如我所愿；还有，我对我的胸和其他的一些身体部位都不是非常满意。所以请更详细地解释一下一个人应该有怎样的体形，以便我能从自我怀疑的痛苦中解脱，放下心来。”

在大家一阵大笑之后，伯爵开口说道：

“你确实有刚才我所说的优雅容貌，我也不需要其他的例子来阐明这一点；虽然你的容貌不是非常的精致，但是毫无疑问，你的外表非常讨人喜欢并令人愉快，另外，你看上去也有男子的气概和风度。许多不同类型的面孔都可以达到这种效果。我希望我们的侍臣也是这样。我不希望他们看上去很温柔、很女性化，像有些侍臣想竭力做到的一般，他们不仅烫卷发、拔眉，还将自己打扮成最放荡荒唐的样子，简直让人难以想象。实际上，他们在走路、站立或做其他事情时，看上去十分女人气并且软弱无力，以至于他们的四肢像要散架；他们说话时是那么地有气无力，像要当场断气似的。而且越是跟随在有身份的人身边，他们的这种表现越明显。既然大自然没能让他们投胎成他们想要的女性，那么我们就不能把他们当成女人来看待，而只应该视其为男妓，并将其逐出绅士的群体，更不用说高贵的宫廷了。

“至于侍臣的外貌，我想说的是，只要不太高或太矮就行，因为不论是太高还是太矮都会引发非议，被视为怪物。然而，如果不得不在两者之间作出选择的话，那么最好是选择矮一点而不是太高；因为太高的人一般都比较笨，更糟糕的是，他们不适宜参加体育和娱乐活动，而我认为这两项活动对于侍臣来说是最重要的。所以我希望我们的侍臣有健美的身材，比例匀称，他是力量、敏捷和柔韧的化身，擅长所有适合勇士的体育运动。在这里，我还想说他的首要任务就是学会如何徒步或在马上熟练地使用各种兵器，真正地了解各种兵器，尤其是要熟知绅士们常用的兵器。因为除了在战争中需要这种知识以外，绅士们之间因为意见不合而导致决斗也是常事，那时使用的兵器通常是顺手拿到的，所以，为了安全起见，知道所有兵器的用法很重要。当然我以上的观点不代表我认为在战斗中可以忽略技巧，因为此时没有技巧的人恰恰说明他已经让恐惧夺走了勇气和智慧。

“此外，我认为学会摔跤也至关重要，因为它在徒步搏斗中很起作用。再有，我还认为侍臣为了自己和他的朋友，应该学会如何讨回自己应得的一切并据理力争，他应该善于抓住优势，最重要的是他必须显示出勇气和审慎。除非遇到为了荣誉而战的紧急情况，否则应该慎行；因为在对结局没有把握的情况下，这样做很危险，若不是紧急情况、形势所迫，草率行事的人都应该受到严肃批评，即便能侥幸成功，也是一样。但是如果一个人已经深陷其中、无路可退的时候，他就要在开始和决斗的过程中都非常谨慎，表现出胸有成竹并且毫无畏惧，而不是像那些总是在口头上大谈什么是荣誉的人一样怯懦，你若让他们选择兵器，他们就选那些既不会割伤又不会刺伤对方的，还把自己武装得像要接受炮轰似的，战斗还没开始，他们就已经做好精神准备，如果败下阵来，就要一直后退，做好防守，完全一副胆小如鼠的样子。这种决斗的场面看起来就像是一场孩子们的游戏，就像那两个不久前在佩鲁贾打架的安科纳人一样，让每个看到他们的人都忍俊不禁。”

“他们是谁呀？”加斯帕雷·帕拉维契诺问道。

“一对表兄弟。”塞萨尔回答道。

“他们在打斗中更像一对亲兄弟。”伯爵说。接着他继续说道：

“他们使用的兵器也是和平时期的各种体育活动中常用的，绅士们的荒唐表演在众人、女士和贵族们面前公开上演。所以我希望我们的侍臣是一位有造诣又多才多艺的骑手，精通关于马以及一切有关骑马的知识，他应该竭尽全力在各个方面都争取超过其他的人，这样他才能做到出类拔萃。就像阿西维亚德斯那样超越周围所有人，并且每次都是在别人宣称是自己最棒的项目上胜出，所以我们的侍臣也应该在别人熟知的事情上更胜一筹。比如意大利人在用缰绳驭马、驯服烈马、马上持长矛冲刺以及长矛比武方面能力出众，那我们这位优秀的侍臣在这方面的技艺就应该和最好的意大利选手相媲美。在马上比武的比赛中，一位优秀的侍臣又可以跟最擅于坚守阵地和冲锋向前的法国人一争高下；在射击、奔牛比赛、投掷长矛和标枪方面，他应该比西班牙人更出众。但是如果他想赢得每个人都渴望的一致认同，最重要的就是，他在做这些事情的时候，还必须表现出很好的风度和判断力。

“也有许多其他的体育项目不直接要求使用兵器，但与兵器密切相关，并且要求参与者非常具有男子气概。在这些运动中，我认为打猎是最重要的，因为打猎在很多方面都与战争有相似之处；此外，它是贵族们真正喜爱的娱乐方式，因此它也应该是侍臣从事的运动，要知道打猎在古代就很流行了。另外，侍臣还应该会游泳，擅长跳跃、跑步和投掷，因为这些技能除了在战争中很有用以外，还可以帮助他树立起良好的声誉，尤其是博取大众的欢心。另外一个适合侍臣的高尚运动便是网球，因为打网球可以显示出他良好的体魄、运动的迅速和敏捷，以及他是否真的具有在其他大多数运动项目中表现出的素质。我还觉得在马背上的表现很重要，这种运动非常容易令人疲惫，难度也很高，但是它比其他任何运动都能显示出一个人灵活和敏捷的一面；另外，除了这些好处以外，在马背上的敏捷再加上优雅的风度，在我看来，比其他运动更加赏心悦目。如果我们的侍臣在所有这些运动中都能表现出高水平，那么他就可以忽略其他运动，如侧手翻、高空走钢索等。因为这些运动更像是杂技，实在不适合绅士。既然一个人不能总是参加这样紧张的活动（而且不断地重复会让人感到厌烦，破坏我们对事物的新鲜感），他必须通过做不同的事情来让生活变得丰富多彩。所以我希望这位侍臣偶尔也可以屈尊做些平静的、不那么剧烈的游戏，并通过做其他人常做的事情来避免他人的嫉妒，从而能融洽地与人相处；但是他还必须时刻用良好的教养和正确的判断指导自己的行为，避免做蠢事。总之，他开怀大笑、开玩笑、调侃还有跳舞都可以，就是不能忘记表现出良好的控制力、谨慎以及做事的风度。”

接着，塞萨尔·贡萨加说道：“很显然现在打断这个讨论有点为时尚早，但是如果再继续保持沉默，我就无法行使我说话的权利，也将失去学习更多东西的机会。我希望大家能够原谅我，我只是想问一个问题而不是进行什么反驳。刚才伯纳多就曾因为太想证实自己长得英俊而违反了游戏规则，相信我也可以吧。”

“你们看到了吧，”公爵夫人评论道，“这就是为什么一个错误可以导致更多的错误。所以一个人犯了错，树立了一个坏的榜样，就像伯纳多那样，他就不仅仅要为他自己的错误行为受罚，还要为导致其他人跟着犯错受罚。”

接着塞萨尔又问：“如果是这样的话，夫人，既然伯纳多既要为自己犯规受罚又要为我犯规受罚，那么我就可以不用受罚了。”

“恰恰相反，”公爵夫人说，“你们二人必须都要受罚两次：因为他不但自己做错事还导致你跟着犯错，而你要为了自己犯错和模仿别人犯错而受罚。”

“夫人，”塞萨尔答道，“我到目前为止还什么错事都没做呢，所以为了只让伯纳多一人受罚，我还是不说了。”

他停下来后，伊米莉亚夫人笑道：

“请尽管说吧，如果公爵夫人允许的话，我将原谅你们两个，不管是已经犯了规的人，还是那个差点儿要犯规的人。”

公爵夫人说：“那好吧。但是要注意不要欺骗自己并认为仁慈应比公正得到更多的赞扬。因为如果一个人太容易原谅犯规的人，那么他就伤害了没有犯规的人。然而，我严厉地责备你的放纵，并不意味着我们不能听听塞萨尔想要问的是什么。”

接着，在公爵夫人和伊米莉亚夫人的示意下，他立刻开口道：

“我亲爱的伯爵，如果我没记错的话，您今天晚上重复了好几次，一个侍臣的一举一动以及做事方式，或简而言之，就是他所有的行动都要保持风度。照我的理解来看，您认为任何事都要有风度当作辅料，否则所有其他品质似乎都一文不值。我承认现在我们每个人都很赞同这一点，就风度本身的意义来讲，一个举止有风度的人在其他方面也同样有风度。您说过风度通常是天生的，是上帝的赐予，即使它不是那么完美，也可以通过实践和努力得到很大的提高。在我看来，我们周围就有这样的人，他们是上天的宠儿，天生就有这些品质，不需要什么进一步指导，因为上天是那样地抬举他们，赐予他们的风度简直超越他们的期待，这使得每个人都喜欢和仰慕他们。我不想争论这一点，因为我们没有能力自己去获得。但是对于那些得到的天赐较少，只能通过进取、实践和努力获得风度的人，我想知道通过什么技巧、培训和方法可以让他们获得风度，包括您认为非常重要的在体育和娱乐中的风度，以及在其他场合中的风度。既然您已经如此高度地赞扬了这种品质，我相信您已经激起了我们所有人想拥有这种风度的强烈愿望，因为伊米莉亚夫人把这个任务交给了您，您有义务教我们如何去做。”

“我没有义务，”伯爵说，“去教你们如何获得风度，或其他任何的东西，我的义务只是告诉你们完美的侍臣应该是什么样的。我也不会承担教你们如何获得风度的任务，尤其是刚才我提到侍臣应该学会摔跤、跳马和很多其他的技能，因为我自己并没有学过这些，我肯定你们都非常清楚我能教出什么样儿来。这就好像一位出色的士兵能对铁匠说出他想要的盔甲的样式、形状和质量就够了，不必教铁匠怎样去锤炼和锻造，我只能告诉你们一个完美侍臣的标准，但是却不能教你们怎样变成他。然而，尽管众所周知风度是学不来的，为了尽最大能力满足你们的要求，我说如果有人想拥有运动员或体育家的风度的话（首先要确定他天生是这块料），他应该从小就开始练习并且找到最好的老师。例如，马其顿王国的菲利普国王就曾请最伟大的哲人亚里士多德来教他的儿子亚历山大。再如，我们同时代的法国侍卫队长加里亚佐·桑瑟夫内洛先生，他有着优雅的风度和敏捷的身手，除了有天资的原因，他还竭尽全力向好老师们学习，并与杰出的人为伴，学习他们的优点。因此，在摔跤、跳马和各种兵器的使用方面，他向大家所熟知的毫无争议的、精通所有与力量和灵活相关项目的大师皮埃特罗·蒙特学习。在骑马、马上长枪比武等方面，他也一直向在各个项目上人所共知的高手学习。

“因此，任何一个想成为好学生的人都必须将事情做好，还要持续努力地模仿，如果有可能的话，一定要完全模拟他的老师。当他觉得自己有一些进步的时候，就去观察不同的侍臣，他应该具有正确的判断力，以便在此指引下，不断学习不同侍臣身上的长处，这将会对他非常有益。就像在夏天的田野里，蜜蜂们忙着在花丛中采蜜，侍臣必须向那些看似很有风度的人学习，并从每个人身上学到最闪光的优点。他当然不能像我们的一位朋友那样，名字我就不说了，他认为自己很像阿拉贡王国的斐迪南德国王，但他只是模仿了这位国王抬头和撇嘴的方式，而这只是国王在生病时养成的习惯。还有许多类似这样的例子，他们认为只要能在某方面像伟人就很了不起了，而很多时候他们抓住的却恰恰只是伟人唯一的缺点。关于如何拥有优雅的风度我已经思索了很久，除了那些天生运气好的人，我还发现了一个普遍规律，这个规律非常适用于人们的行为和言语：即不惜任何代价远离矫揉造作，好似远离一座粗糙而危险的暗礁，（可能要用一种小说语言）在做任何事时都学着表现出一种化技巧于无形的平和，让自己在说话和做事的时候看起来是那样的浑然天成而驾轻就熟。我确信风度更重要的来源在于此，因为每个人都知道完美地建立丰功伟业是多么困难的一件事，因此如果轻而易举就做到了，一定会引来人们极大的好奇心；然而，恰恰相反的是，如果费尽心力做成一件事，就显示出缺乏优雅的风度，从而导致在人们心目中的形象大打折扣。所以我们可以非常肯定地说，真正的技巧是让人看不出来的技巧；这里最重要的环节是把技巧隐藏起来，因为如果技巧暴露了，就会让人颜面尽失、名誉扫地。我记得曾经读过古代某些杰出演说家的故事，他们所做的事情中有一件让我印象深刻，那就是他们曾非常努力地让大家相信他们是目不识丁的人；掩饰自己的学识，让他们的演讲看似是由非常简单的词句构成，看似是在顺应天意和真理，而非用心雕饰和杜撰什么。因为如果人们知道他们的伎俩，就会害怕被欺骗。所以你们现在明白为什么运用太多技巧的东西都变得风度无存了吧。当皮埃尔·保罗以其特有的方式：轻轻地跳跃，用脚尖点地，伸直双腿，头一动也不动地跳舞，看上去就像是用木头做成，他跳得那么吃力，像是在数每一个舞步，你们中间有谁没有发笑，谁会这么没有眼力以至于看不出这笨拙的做作？相反，我们今天在场的很多男士和女士，他们所表现出的风度和平静才被称为自然，因为他们在说话、大笑或约束自己等方面没有很刻意去做，看到他们的人就会认为他们天生优雅，根本不会也不知道怎样去犯错。”

……

这时伊米莉亚夫人打断了一下：“在我看来你们的争论太冗长沉闷了。将这个话题推迟到另外的时间再谈吧。”

费德里科还想继续回答，但是伊米莉亚夫人没有给他机会；最终伯爵说道：

“有些人想对语言的风格、韵律和模仿的问题作些评论，然而自己却不知风格、韵律为何物，也不知如何给模仿下定义，更不知道为何维吉尔从荷马或其他人的作品中引用了很多东西，却被人看作是改进而非剽窃。我不明白的原因或许在于我的理解能力有问题。而教授作品的人是应该要理解所教内容的，可是我觉得，恐怕连他们自己都不大理解，他们既赞扬维吉尔又赞扬西塞罗，是因为他们知道很多人都在赞扬这两个人，而不是自己认识到二者与其他人的区别。他们的区别肯定不在于是否保留了几个语句，或用法与其他人不同。在萨卢斯特[2]、恺撒[3]、瓦罗[4]和其他伟大作家的作品里，我们发现一些术语的用法与西塞罗使用的不同；但是这两种方式都是完全可以接受的，因为语言的力量和精髓不在于这些细枝末节：就像埃斯基涅斯[5]挖苦狄摩西尼[6]，问他所使用的一些非雅典式的词语是怪物还是异物时，狄摩西尼只是笑了笑，回答说这不是什么关乎希腊命运的大事。所以如果一些托斯卡纳人再指责我用的词，比如应该用satisfatto而非sodisfatto, onorevole而非orrevole, causa而非cagione, populo而非popolo等时[7]，我又有什么好担心的呢？”

这时费德里科站了起来，大声说：“我现在请求你们听我说一小会儿。”

但是伊米莉亚夫人笑着说：“不，无论现在你们中的任何人还想继续这个话题，我都会非常不开心，因为我想等另外一个晚上再进行讨论。但是我亲爱的伯爵，请继续讨论您的侍臣，并且让我们看看你的记忆力有多好，因为我觉得您应该从刚才停下来的地方讲起，这可不是件容易的事儿。”

“恐怕，”伯爵回答道，“我已经乱了头绪，如果我没说错的话，我们刚才在说做作能毁掉风度，最优雅的风度应该是朴素和自然的，我们赞颂优雅，谴责做作，在这方面还有很多可谈的。但是，我只想再多说一点。现在每个女人都特别想漂亮，如果无法做到，至少也想看起来漂亮。所以当她有一些天生的缺点的时候，她力图通过人工的方式来纠正这个缺点。这就是为什么女士们如此仔细地修饰她们的面容，有时甚至是通过痛苦的方式，比如拔眉、修前额、使用各种方式遭受各种小痛苦，你们女士以为男士对此一无所知，事实上他们十分清楚。”

这时，科斯坦萨·弗莱高索夫人笑了，她说：“出于礼貌，你们还是继续刚才的讨论，谈谈风度的源泉及侍臣的事情吧，不要再讨论女性的缺点这个与此不相干的话题了。”

“相反，我说的与该话题息息相关，”伯爵回答道，“因为我刚才提到的那些毛病会让你们优雅全无，而原因就在于做作，也正是这一点让每个人都清楚地看到你们有多么渴望变得美丽。你们肯定知道什么是更优雅的女人，如果她的确想要优雅，与那个脸上化着浓妆，像是戴了面具的女人相反，她会将自己打扮得很简朴，只施很淡的妆，她是如此地简朴雅致以至于看到她的人都不确定她是不是化过妆。那个化浓妆的女人因为害怕‘面具’破裂都不敢大笑，只有在早晨穿衣服的时候才能看到她的本色，这之后的一天里她都像个呆板的木雕一样，并且只让别人在昏暗的光亮下看到自己，就像是一个狡猾的商人在昏暗的角落里展示自己的布料。与此相反，一个完全没有化妆的美丽女人比其他浓妆艳抹的女人更加有魅力。她的脸色既不太白也不太红，看上去很自然，有一点苍白（但偶尔会因为害羞或其他原因而脸红），她让她那未经修饰的头发自然地散落，她的姿态简单而自然，没有一丝努力或渴望漂亮的迹象。这就是自然简单之美，最能让男人着迷，因为男人常常害怕被假象所戏弄。对于女人来说，可爱的牙齿总是讨人喜欢的，因为大多数情况下牙齿都是不在视线范围之内的，人们通常不会费很多力气来让牙齿看起来漂亮，而把精力放在了脸的其他部位；然而当一个人无故大笑，只是为了秀出牙齿，就暴露了她的做作。不管牙齿有多好看，都会让人感觉非常不雅，就像卡图卢斯[8]笔下的伊格内修[9]一样。这个道理同样适用于手，如果手指纤巧美丽，并在适当的时间露出来，比如说当需要用手而不是展示其美丽的时候，就会让人忍不住想多看一会儿，尤其是在给它戴上手套以后，更让人想再多看一会儿。因为那个给手戴上手套的人根本就没有在乎她的手是否被人注意，她美丽的双手更多是天生的而不是经过雕饰或刻意美化的。当然，你有时候也会无意看到这样的情景，一个女人在去教堂的路上沿街而行的时候，也许因为好玩或什么其他原因，偶尔将裙子掀起，正好能露出脚踝，甚至一小部分腿。如果你正好看到这一幕，你是不是会觉得那才是真正的优雅——穿着漂亮袜子、系着天鹅绒丝带的快乐女性？毫无疑问，我相信你们和我一样都觉得那将非常令人愉快，因为每个人都认为难得一见的优雅是自然的而非细心雕琢的，并且也不是以赢得赞美为目的的。

“这样一来，做作就可以被避免或隐藏；现在你就明白了，做作是怎样地不容于风度，还有它如何在身体和灵魂的一举一动中夺走魅力，关于这一点，我们必须承认迄今为止我们几乎没怎么谈。然而，我们不能忽视这一点；因为精神比肉体更有价值，更需要陶冶和修炼。至于我们的侍臣在这方面需要怎么做，我想我们应该把伟大哲人们的训诫先放在一边，不必讨论精神美的定义或是详细讨论它的价值；相反，我们应该牢记我们的目的，简单地说，他只要是一个讲信义、正直的男人就够了。这囊括了审慎、善良、坚韧、克己精神以及其他适合这一美名的品质。我相信他自己就是一个不断向善的真正的思想家；这样的话，他除了志向本身之外，不需要什么训诫。因此，苏格拉底的断言是完全正确的，他说当某人努力想知道并理解美德的时候，那么对这个人的教导就算是有了好的成果；因为当这些人到达除了想要变得优秀而别无他求的境界时，他在学习所有必要的品质方面就都不成问题了，所以这一点我就不必再多说了。

“然而，想变得优秀，除了善良以外，我们最需要的是用知识来武装自己的头脑；尽管我知道法国人只崇尚武力，除此之外其他都不重视；所以他们不仅不重视学习，还厌恶学习，把那些有知识的人视为卑劣的人，如果称某人是学者的话就是对其极大的侮辱。”

接着，尊贵的朱利亚诺说道：

“您说的很对，这个错误在法国人当中已经持续了很长时间；但是如果昂古莱姆先生能如大家所愿，有幸继承王位的话，我相信知识会像武力一样在法国盛行，大放光辉。因为不久前我在他的宫廷的时候，注意观察了那个君王，在我看来他除了长得英俊外，身上还散发着一股伟人的气息，还不乏优雅的仁慈，显然他甚至有能力治理一个比法国更大的国家。随后，我从许多法国和意大利绅士那里也听到了很多赞扬他的话，包括他的礼貌、他的慷慨、他的英勇以及他的宽宏大量；另外，我还听说他非常喜爱和尊重知识，并尊重所有的学者，他谴责法国人反对知识，尤其是他们有巴黎这样一座宏伟的大学，吸引着来自世界各地的人们聚集在此。”

紧接着伯爵又说道：“他年纪轻轻，极有天分，不轻易苟同于国人普遍持有的态度，真是好极了，他一定会前途无量的。并且，正如你们所说，既然臣民总是愿意效仿他们统治者的所作所为，法国人也很可能因此认识到知识的真正价值。如果他们理性地去思考，就很容易被说服，因为人们对知识的渴望是天生的，只有愚昧至极的人才会觉得这不是一件好事。

“如果我能有机会同他们或是其他持有不同意见的人交流，我会尽力说服他们，让他们知道学问对于一个人的尊严和生命有多么重要。因为这是上帝赐予人类的最神圣的礼物。我可以举出很多古代伟人的实例，他们不仅英勇善战，还学识渊博。比如，大家都知道的亚历山大，他非常敬重荷马，总是把荷马的那部《伊利亚特》放在床边。除此之外，他还十分关注亚里士多德的哲学思考，认真地去研究。亚西比德[10]则在苏格拉底的教导下，学习更多的知识，提升自己的优秀品质。恺撒的那些充满灵感的文章也恰恰证实了他对知识的追求。据说西庇阿·阿非利加努斯[11]也时常阅读色诺芬[12]的作品，其中就有赛勒斯如何成为一位出色国王的故事。我还可以找到卢库勒斯[13]、苏拉[14]、庞培[15]、布鲁特斯[16]等许多其他罗马人和希腊人的例子来说明这一点；此外，我还想说即使是汉尼拔那样骁勇的战将，一个天生凶悍、毫无人性、人神共愤的人，也是知识渊博，精通希腊语的。如果我没说错，他还曾经用希腊文写过一本书。其实我觉得说这些是多余的，因为我知道你们并不赞同法国人所谓的学文不利于尚武的观点。众所周知，战斗能激励人们奋勇向前的动力来自于人们对荣耀的渴望，但人若是为私利或达成某种目的而战就会变得一文不值，因为这种做法使他更像一个唯利是图的商人，而不是一位绅士。走入知识圣殿的人才能获得真正的荣耀，这一点是大家的共识，只有可怜虫还对此一无所知。当一个人从书中读到恺撒、亚历山大、西庇阿、汉尼拔以及其他人的丰功伟绩时，谁会不为之热血沸腾、壮志凌云，不希望在有限的生命里作出一番留名青史、光耀后世的大事业，而甘心做一个胆小如鼠的窝囊废呢？那些无法体会到知识的乐趣的人根本意识不到他们为之努力奋斗的荣耀究竟有多伟大，他们眼中的荣耀只是一时的荣耀，局限在有限的一两代人的时间内而已。所以他们所经历的这种荣耀与那种他们不懂但却几近永恒的荣耀相比，毫无价值。既然真正的荣耀对于这些人来说并不意味着什么，所以我们有理由认为，这些人跟那些深谙荣耀本质的人相反，不愿意去追求真正的荣耀。谈到这里，可能有人会对我所说的话提出异议并给出反例：例如意大利人很有学识但是他们近年来却在战场上连连失利。这是一个事实，但是可以很肯定地说，是几个人的软弱导致了众人遭受巨大的不幸并长久地为之背负恶名，这几个人应该对我们的失败以及志气的削弱（如果没有被摧毁）负责。但是，这件事情败坏了我们在全世界的名声，比法国人对知识的无知更让我们感到惭愧；所以，对于我们不堪回首的往事，最好还是让它悄悄地流逝吧，别再谈这个主题（我非常不愿意提起的），让我们重新回到侍臣的问题上来吧。

“我希望我们的侍臣比普通学者博学多才，至少在那些我们称之为人文学科方面是这样；他应该像精通拉丁文一样精通希腊文，因为很多好作品是用希腊文写成的。他还应该熟知一些诗人、演说家和历史学家，并擅长写一些韵文和散文，尤其是用本国语来写；因为这些不仅能给他自己带来满足感，还能满足非常喜欢这些的女士们的要求。但是如果他由于忙于其他事情或是疏于学习而导致写作水平较差，那么他应羞于将自己的作品示人，以免遭人耻笑，而只将自己的作品与信任的朋友一起分享。练习写作至少对于如何评赏他人的作品会有帮助。因为对于一个没有经验的作家来说，即使他很博学，也不可能完全理解其他作家苦心孤诣所写的作品并且欣赏他们的写作风格和成就，更不能理解古代作家作品的风格技巧和细微精妙之处。此外，这些研究还会使我们的侍臣博学多闻，能言善辩（如亚里斯提卜对暴君所说），并且无论跟谁讲话都充满自信。但是，我还是希望侍臣牢牢记住一点：那就是，在我刚刚讨论过的以及其他的事情中，他应该做到谦虚低调，并且切忌不懂装懂。因为我们天生喜欢听取别人的赞美之词，这感觉犹如欣赏天籁一般；别人的赞美就像女海妖赛壬[17]的歌声，让水手深深地迷醉却最终导致海难的发生。远古时代的很多哲学家们已经意识到了这种危险性，他们著书来告诫人们如何分辨真正的朋友与谄媚的人。即便如此，我们还是会问这到底有什么用处，因为我们经常看到有很多人明明知道自己在听奉承话，却乐此不疲，反而厌恶那些说实话的人。事实上，他们觉得谄媚者说的话还不够动听，他们还要鼓励那些人多说一些让世上最能阿谀奉承的人都感到难为情的话。让那些瞎眼的傻瓜们继续犯错吧，只要保证我们的侍臣不这样颠倒黑白，不在自己不确定的情况下轻率推测就好，尤其不要犯那些错误，如果你们还记得的话，就是那晚塞萨尔提议的游戏中提到的那些蠢人蠢事。为了不犯错误，侍臣们应该反其道而行，明知他所得到的赞许是应得的，也不要公开地欣然接受或者没有任何评论地接受。相反，他应该谦虚地否认，让人总能感觉到军事才是（事实上也应该是）他的强项，而其他的成就仅仅是在他个人能力上锦上添花而已；尤其是与战士们在一起的时候，他的态度更应如此，以免他被看成是学者中的战士或者战士中的学者。这样才会如我们所说，他会避开矫揉造作，让那些普通的成就也显得很伟大。”

……

宫廷侍臣的故事（二）

“我非常赞同以上关于侍臣的讨论，我认为在那些我们称之为好的品质里，有些属于他们本人，例如自控能力、刚毅、健康以及其他让他心灵安宁的美德；另外一些则表现在其他方面并且要视其带来的效果而定，例如法律、宽容、财富等。因此，我认为正如洛多维科伯爵和费德里科伯爵所言，最优秀的侍臣要想得到真正的赞许，不仅仅局限于他自己的品质，还取决于他所做的一切和带来的结果。因为，说实话，如果贵族出身的人只具有优雅、魅力和技能，他还是不配成为一个出色的侍臣。相反，我想说，他的那些技能，如跳舞、娱乐、唱歌以及做游戏等，都是些无聊而轻佻的东西，一个拥有尊贵地位的人如果只会做这些事情，只会招来唾骂而非赞许。华丽的着装、耍手段、信誓旦旦以及类似的浪漫本应属于女人，大多数人都认为，这些东西只会使男人变得女人气，年纪轻轻就走向歧途，变得放荡风流。它带来的严重后果是，令整个意大利蒙羞，几乎没有人还存着冒险的勇气，更别说去牺牲了。比起这种无聊的为臣之道，在和平与战争年代，不知有多少值得我们去努力学习的品质，可以让我们从中受益。如果侍臣们能以我所期待的那个高尚目标作为行动指南，我个人认为，他们的行为不但不会有害，不会徒劳无功，还会带来诸多益处，并赢得无限的赞美。

“因此在我看来，一位出色的侍臣（到目前为止我们还未讨论过）的职责是通过绅士们认为他应具备的种种才能来赢得君王的信任和喜爱，从此他可以对君王说真话，让君王知道该知道的事情，并且不必担心引起君王的不快。如果他意识到君王要做一些无益的事情，就敢于站出来反对，用他那优良的品性赢得的宠信来改变君王的每一个罪恶动机并劝服他回归正途。因此，如果一位侍臣具有这些绅士所希望的美德：反应灵敏、优雅迷人、明智谨慎、学识渊博等，他就有能力让他的君王明白，一个君王应该具备正义、慷慨、宽宏、高贵以及其他美德，使其成为一个真正的统治者，并为他本人及家族赢得荣誉和崇高地位；相反，他的恶行和不道德行为也会带给他狼藉的声名和重大的损失。因此，我认为像音乐、庆典、游戏以及其他那些让人开心放松的行为只能让为臣之道锦上添花而已，而其真正的职责是鼓励和辅佐他的君主成其美德，远离罪恶。所以我们认为良好行为带来的好处包括两个主要方面：为我们的行动指明一个真正高尚的方向，以及寻找最便捷最合适的方式来实现它。所以一个优秀的侍臣应该竭尽全力，确保君主不受人欺骗，不听信谗言、诽谤及谎言，明辨善恶，爱憎分明，朝着为全民造福的方向去努力。

“我也觉得绅士们期望侍臣具备的美德和才能，正是我希望侍臣达到的目标。因为我们从当前的统治者身上发现的最大的问题就是无知和自负。这两种问题的根源在于那些神和人都为之不齿的谎言，而这对国君的影响尤甚。因为国君缺乏的正是他们所最必需的，即有人能跟他们说实话，提醒他们什么是正确的。因为那些对国君不怀好意的人是不会喜欢做这种事的，相反，他们希望国君昏庸地活着，永远不改正他所犯的错误。另外，他们还因为怕受惩罚而不敢公然地反对国君。并且，在国君的朋友中，只有小部分人能接近他，而这一小部分人又不敢像指责普通人一样指责国君，相反，他们为了得到国君的恩惠和好感，只提那些令人愉快的、有趣的建议，即便是无耻而邪恶的，他们也不在乎。这样，他们从朋友变成了谄媚者，所言所行只是为了令国君高兴，用谎话来蒙蔽国君，让国君对周围的一切包括他自己都一无所知，从而获得更多的好处。让一个不知情的人不断地欺骗自己，可以说是世上最大最可怕的欺骗。

“这样做的结果就是国君永远听不到真话，滥用职权，寻欢作乐，他们的思想逐步堕落（觉得自己受人尊崇，周围尽是别人敬畏和赞扬的话语，没有半点责备和反驳之声），渐渐从无知走向了极度的自负。结果，他们变得再也听不进任何人的建议和意见，而且还会觉得统治国家非常简单，不需要任何手段或是训练，只需要暴力就足矣。因此他们一心只想着如何维护权力，并相信真正的快乐就是得到自己想要的一切。所以，我们看到很多排斥理性和正义的国君，因为他们觉得这些会约束他们的欲望，成为束缚他们的枷锁，进而剥夺他们统治别人的快感和满足感；他们认为如果听从责任和荣誉的召唤，他们的权力就不再至高无上，听别人摆布的国君不是真正的国君。于是他们开始变得妄自尊大、不可一世、专横无理、着装华丽、珠光宝气，并很少在公共场合露面，企图在国民中树立威信，被奉为神明。但是，在我看来，这些国君很像是去年在罗马阿贡广场的节日庆祝会上的那些巨大雕像，表面看上去像是凯旋的伟人和马匹，其实里面塞满了破布和稻草。事实上，上面所说的那种国君比这雕像更糟糕，因为这些巨大的雕像是由于它们自身的重量才能高高屹立，不过，内部的严重失衡及其与底座的比例失调，使其随时可能倒下；而这些统治者的倒台源自他们自身以及一个错误，从而导致满盘皆输。那个错误就是无知，他们觉得自己永远不会犯错误，觉得自己的权力来源于自己的智慧，所以不遗余力地去滥用权力，并一有机会就不择手段地去霸占更多的领地。

“要是他们意识到了自己的职责，就会做他们应该做的事，以一种与现在截然不同的方式来治理国家。因为他们会意识到当被统治者比统治者还要更英明的时候，情况是多么糟糕。你也许认为不懂弹琴、跳舞或是骑马没有什么大不了；然而，如果一个人不懂音乐，会感觉没有面子和羞愧，因而不敢在公共场合唱歌，不懂跳舞则不敢跳舞，马术不精则不敢骑马。可是，如果一个国君不知道如何统治一个国家就没这么简单了，这会引发罪恶、死亡、破坏、战火甚至是毁灭，可以说是全民的灭顶之灾。但是，一些统治者尽管对如何治理国家一无所知，还是厚颜无耻地试图统治整个世界而非眼前的一小班人马，因为他位高权重，所有的目光都投向他，从此，他们的最重大和最细小的错误都会被大家看个清清楚楚。

……

“因此，我认为既然如今的统治者生活如此穷奢极欲，又无知狂妄，就很难让他们认清真理、树立美德。既然有人通过谎言、奉承以及其他恶劣的手段获得了国君的青睐，侍臣也可以通过洛多维科伯爵和费得里科伯爵所传授的高贵品质轻易地获得国君对他的喜爱，从而可以自由地找国君讨论问题。如果他可以轻而易举地达到这个目的，他日后就可以及时把每一件事情的真相都告知国君。而且，他还可以逐渐将美德灌输给国君，让国君懂得自律、刚毅、正义和节制，并让试图摆脱堕落的他在经历一番努力之后，初次品尝到苦涩后的一丝甘甜。从而使他意识到罪恶的行为是有害的，会让人恶名远播，而美德则让人受益无穷，得到广泛赞誉。侍臣还可以列举些例子来激励国君以美德治理天下，那些著名的首领以及那些被人们做成雕像的古代伟人就是很好的榜样，人们习惯用铜、大理石，有时也用黄金来铸造他们的雕像，立于广场之上，表彰他们的丰功伟绩，同时也鼓励其他人向他们学习，争取同样的荣耀。

“这样，侍臣就可以引导国君走向美德之路，虽然道路崎岖，但有了阴凉的树荫和美丽的鲜花作点缀，即使国君的耐性不佳，也不会在这条艰难的道路上感到沉闷；或者偶尔配上音乐、比武、马匹，再配上诗歌或爱情的对话，以及那些绅士建议的所有方法，就会确保国君渐渐被这些简单的快乐所吸引。在此过程中，如我所说的，在陪伴君王散心时要一再强调道德的重要性，这样，就在潜移默化中改变他，正如一个精明的医生总是会让一个因生病而虚弱的孩子在吃下苦药前尝到他悄悄抹在杯沿上的甜甜液体。这样，在快乐的掩盖下，无论什么时候，什么地方，或是什么工作，侍臣总能顺利地达到目的，为此这个侍臣应该获得更多的赞美和奖励。

因为世上没有比拥有一个明智的国君更好的事，当然也没有比遇到一个罪恶的国君更可怕的事；同样，如果一个侍臣利用礼貌优雅的举止和高贵的身份去做邪恶的事情，极力向自己的国君谄媚并使国君偏离美德之路，走向邪恶，那么无论对这个侍臣施以多残酷的惩罚都不为过。原因在于，他的行为就像在公共水井里投毒一样有害，毒害的可不仅仅是一个人呀。”

奥塔维亚诺先生陷入了沉默，似乎不愿意再说下去了。但是加斯帕雷阁下说道：

“奥塔维亚诺先生，我并不认为国君可以在侍臣的引导下学会那些仁慈、自制以及其他美德，相反，我觉得他们所拥有的美德是大自然和上帝赋予的。你会发现世上没有人坏到愿意承认自己就是邪恶、坏心肠、放纵或是不正义的。相反，每一个人无论有多么邪恶，都希望被视为是正直的、有自制力的以及善良的；所以如果美德可以通过学习获得，情形就会大不相同了。一个人如果因为缺乏学习而无知是无须感到羞愧的，但是如果天生就缺乏某些东西，当然会感觉到羞耻。

“所以，每个人都极力掩饰自己思想上或是身体上的缺陷，比如失明、跛足或残疾等丑陋的一面。因为即使把这些缺陷归结为大自然的力量，也没有人希望拥有它，这种天生的缺陷就像是大自然有意给他们烙上的邪恶烙印。我的这个想法和厄毗米修斯[18]讲述的故事是一致的，他不知道该怎样把大自然的天分分配给众人，以至于分给人类的天分比其他生物要少得多；因此普罗米修斯才从弥涅耳瓦[19]和伏尔坎[20]那里偷走了让人类生存下去的智慧和知识。但是人们还是缺乏公民道德和精神法规，但是这些知识都被关在奥林匹斯山上朱庇特的城堡里，并且守护森严，使得普罗米修斯不敢靠近。因此，朱庇特由于同情人类（因为公民道德的缺失使得他们无力反抗野兽的攻击）就派墨丘利[21]来到人间，教人们学会正义和自尊，使得城市更美好，人民更团结。他认为这些美德无法像分配其他天赋一样分配给人类，只能是让其中一人学会（就像治病一样），然后逐渐传授给周围的每一个人。他依法铲除了那些没有正义之心也不知羞耻的人，以儆效尤。所以啊，奥塔维亚诺先生，你看，这些美德是上帝赋予人类的，是学不会的，他们来源于大自然。”

奥塔维亚诺先生笑着说道：

“所以加斯帕雷阁下，你已经看到，人们对于他们自己的判断力感到很不满意且执迷不悟，所以人们曾经试图驯服大自然中的野兽，熊、狼以及狮子，并希望用同样的方法让一只可爱的小鸟按照他们的意愿飞翔，然后主动地飞离森林，放弃自由，飞进鸟笼被囚禁起来，但是无论人们怎么勤奋和钻研，也始终找不到既能让他们自己受益又能提高自己思想的办法。所以在我看来，这就像是医生埋头钻研治愈指甲疼痛和婴儿皮疹的方法，而忽视了治愈发热、胸膜炎和其他重病的方法；我们都会认为这样做是荒谬的。因此，我认为伦理道德不是完全来自天性，因为没有什么东西会自然地往相反方向发展，比如石头，即便你把石头往天上扔一万次，石头也不会自己飞向天空。所以，如果对我们来说美德是天生的，像石头天然有重量一样，我们就永远不可能对恶行习以为常。同理，罪恶也不是天生的，否则我们也不会有道德。所以为一个人天生就有的缺陷而惩罚某人就是愚不可及的。如果考虑到一个罪犯在未来可能不再犯罪，也不会导致其他人的效仿，而不追究一个罪犯所犯下的罪行（事情已经发生了，无法挽回），从法律角度来讲，就是犯了大错。由此可见，法律认为美德是可以学习的，这是千真万确的；我们从降生的那天起就有能力学习美德或是罪恶，因此我们通过自己的选择，做善事或是做坏事，变成了善良的人或是罪恶的人。先去实践善与恶，然后才成为好人或是坏人。而我们天生所具有的那些品质却正相反，是先有了基础，然后去实践。因为首先要具有看、听或是感知的能力，才可以看到、听见或感受到。当然，许多本领也是通过学习得到加强的。因此，好老师不仅教学生知识，还要教他们文明而正确的举止，包括用餐、饮酒、交谈、走路，等等。

“因此，无论是在技巧、技能还是美德方面，我们都非常需要一位好老师。通过他的教诲和指导，唤醒深埋在我们灵魂深处的美德的种子。好老师就像一位尽职的农夫，精心地培育美德的种子，清理欲望的荆棘和野草，以免束缚我们的思维，最终让美德的种子开花、结果，就如我们所期待的那样。这样，朱庇特给予人们的正义和自尊就会永驻每个人的心间。但是，正如再强健的身体在为目标而努力的时候也可能出现问题一样，美德的潜力虽然已经在我们的灵魂中生根，仍需要通过教育来让它发芽。因为如果要将美德的潜力付诸实践并变成真正的善行，我认为，不能仅仅依靠本性的力量，还需要不断的实践和理性的思考，从而净化和启迪人们的灵魂，揭去无知的面纱，让人们能轻易地辨明是非的能力，避免犯错。这样，美德就类似谨慎和明辨是非的能力，罪恶则类似轻率和无知。原因在于，人们不是故意地选择罪恶，只是被一些假象所迷惑。”

这时加斯帕雷阁下回答道：“现在很多人明知自己做的事情是错误的，但仍然在做；就像那些小偷和杀人犯，原因在于他们只想到当下的快感，而忘记未来可怕的惩罚。”

奥塔维亚诺先生说道：“真正的快乐与善行结伴，而真正的痛苦与邪恶为伍；当他们对虚假的快乐信以为真，却对真正的痛苦不以为然的时候，他们是在欺骗自己。所以他们虚假的快乐只能换来真正的痛苦。因此，我们要学习明辨是非的技巧，还要学习美德，让我们选择真正的善行，而非貌似如此的行为，这将令我们的人生受益无穷，因为它使我们远离了无知这个万恶之源。”

这个时候，皮埃特罗·贝博说道：“奥塔维亚诺先生，我不明白，为什么加斯帕雷阁下要将所有的罪恶之源归于无知，并相信人们犯罪的时候都几乎意识不到自己的行为，而关于什么是真正的快乐和痛苦的问题，也谈不上是在欺骗自己。并且可以肯定，即使是那些一时情绪失控的人也进行过逻辑和理性的判断，对于他们所犯的罪恶的本质也是非常清楚的。他们用自己的理性来抵制欲望，从而导致了快乐和痛苦与判断之间的矛盾。最终，欲望还是战胜了理性，就像是一艘一时抵御了风暴的船，最终还是被巨浪击垮，锚和绳索都不复存在，舵和指南针也失去了作用，任由自己在暴风雨中颠簸。所以那些情绪失控的人在犯下愚蠢的错误时也是带着一丝懊悔，几分自责的。因为如果他们不知道自己所做的事情是罪恶的，他们就不会自责了。相反，如果理性未作任何抗争，他们就将完全受欲望摆布，这样一来就不是无节制，而是纯粹的放纵了。当然，这样更糟糕。因为在无法自控的情况下，至少理性也起了一点作用，从而使得他们没有犯下更为可怕的罪恶；就像自制也只是一个不尽完美的美德，因为你毕竟还是受到了情绪的影响。因此，我认为，不能把人们无法自控而犯下的愚蠢错误与无知混为一谈，或把明知故犯叫作无心之过。”

“是啊”，奥塔维亚诺先生回答道，“你的辩论很精彩。但是我并不认为完全正确。虽然在难以自控的罪行面前，他们曾经犹豫，也确实经历过理性与欲望的斗争，知道了什么是邪恶，但是由于缺乏完备的知识，他们并没有完全理解邪恶。他们对邪恶的理解只是一个模糊的、并非确定的概念，所以他们放任了情绪而忽视了理智。如果他们拥有了真正的知识，毫无疑问他们就不会犯错误。因为无知，所以理性总是无法战胜欲望，而真正的知识永远不会输给情绪，因为情绪起源于身体而不是心灵。如果情绪受理性的合理支配和控制，它们就会成为美德，相反，就会变成邪念。然而，如果理性的本质属性没有受到无知的影响，它就会非常具有影响力，总是使人的感觉服从于它，从而通过非凡的方式和手段来达到目的。如此，虽然一个人的器官、神经和骨骼都没有理性，但是当大脑开动起来的时候，就好像思想舞动着缰绳，刺激我们的器官，使我们身体的其他部位作好了准备：作出双脚跑、双手握拳或者大脑提示的其他动作。这种事很常见，比如有人在不知情的情况下吃了味道很好，但实际上非常恶心又令人作呕的东西；当他发现了真实的情况，便会心生厌恶、不安，继而整个身体对他的判断迅速作出反应，然后他就开始呕吐。”

奥塔维亚诺先生还想继续说下去，但尊贵的朱利亚诺打断了他，插嘴说道：“如果我没有听错，你是说自制并非完美的美德，因为它受情绪的影响。然而，在我看来，当理性和欲望在思想中发生冲突的时候，那种经过与理性的斗争而最终服从于理性的美德，与那种没有跟欲望或情绪较量就胜出的美德相比，前者是更加完美的。而后者克制邪念并非是出于自身的美德，而是因为他没有这样的意愿。”

于是奥塔维亚诺说道：“你认为谁更让人敬佩：一个冒着危险和敌人正面交战，得胜而归的指挥官，还是一个运用技能和知识将敌人拖垮，不用冒险和流血的代价就取得胜利的那个？”

尊贵的朱利亚诺回答道：“如果不是因为敌人的愚蠢而导致他的必然胜利的话，当然是那个懂得避险又能取胜的指挥官更值得尊敬。”

“你说得很对，”奥塔维亚诺先生说道，“所以我想对你说，如果将自我控制能力比作是一个作战勇猛，克服了巨大的困难和危险，面对强敌仍可取胜的指挥官的话，那种节制的心态就可比作是那个没有遭遇抵抗就获胜的指挥官；因为后者就像内战时期的优秀统帅那样，他们征服而且完全扑灭了心灵的欲火，打败了内心所有蠢蠢欲动的敌人，使之彻底地回归理性。这样，这种美德在没有对心灵使用任何暴力的情况下，以巨大的说服力引导心灵走上正途，使之变得平静而安详，进而使一切都趋于和谐，得到宁静和稳定；于是，人们在一切事物中都会完全服从理性，顺从地追随理性，就像一只羊羔总是跟随在母亲的身边：母亲停下脚步，它也跟着停下脚步，母亲前进，它也跟着前进。因此，这种节制的美德才是完美的，对于统治者来说尤其重要，因为它还可以引发更多的美德。”

然后塞萨尔·贡萨加说道：“嗯，我不知道节制能为一位君王带来什么其他的美德，如果真如你所说，节制能带走人的所有情绪，我倒认为它适合一个隐士或者修道士；我想不出它适合一个君王的理由，让一个有宏图大志、不拘一格、骁勇无比等军事才能的君王，在无论什么情况下，都不能表现出愤怒、憎恨，或是仁慈、藐视、渴望等情绪。如果这样，他如何在他的人民或军队中树立权威呢？”

奥塔维亚诺先生回答道：“我并没有说节制必然完全带走或根除一个人心灵中的各种情绪，也没有说这样做会带来什么好处，因为即使在那些情绪中，还是会有一些好的方面。它所起的作用是帮助情绪中的那些不正当行为或者与正当行为背道而驰的行为和理性相呼应。所以为了避免矛盾就根除那些情绪是不正确的；这就好比通过立法禁酒的方式来控制醉酒，或者因为人们在跑步的时候偶尔会摔跤就禁止人们跑步一样。人在训练马的时候，他不会让马停止奔跑、跳跃，但在骑手的控制下，马会在合适的时间停下来。有些情绪在受到节制时会有助于美德的发展，例如愤怒会促成坚毅，对邪恶之人的憎恨会促成正义，其他情绪也会促成别的美德。假如它们一起消亡，就会使理性变得虚弱无力而失去任何效力，就好像是一个在大风过后平静下来的船长。所以，塞萨尔，如果我说平静能促成很多其他的美德，请不要那么惊讶；因为当一个人的心灵和这种和谐相一致的时候，理性就使之欣然接受真正的坚毅，而这种坚毅将使之英勇无比、战无不胜，从而远离人类的痛苦。正义也是一样的，因为它是谦逊善良的真正朋友，也是所有美德中的王者，它不仅告诉我们应该做什么，也告诉我们应该远离错误。正义是完美无缺的，其他美德都通过它得以实现，它不仅让正义的人受益，也让其他人受益。就像人们所说的那样，没有正义，朱庇特就不能很好地统治他的王国。此外还要有宽宏大量的美德，它会提升所有的美德，尽管它不能独立存在，因为缺少其他美德的人不可能是宽宏大量的。在这些好品质的指引下，人们的美德又多了一份审慎，从而使人作出正确的判断。在这条让人欣慰的美德链上还有宽容、慷慨、对荣誉的渴望、温顺、魅力、和蔼可亲和其他很多品质，由于时间的关系就不一一列举了。但是，如果我们的侍臣表现得就像我们所说的那样，他就会发现，在他辅佐的君王心中，美德变得越发枝繁叶茂，而且每天都将看到比世上任何花园里的鲜花和果实都更加让人欣喜的硕果。侍臣自己也将体验到极大的满足感，他告诉自己他给予君王的不是那些傻瓜们给予的东西，比如说金银之类的礼品、花瓶、服装（这些东西君王多的是，而送礼的人又没有多少），而是所有人类的美德中最珍贵的美德：治理国家的好方式和好方法。仅此就足以使人们幸福，使世界回到传说中撒敦[22]统治时期曾经有过的黄金时代。”

……

接着，加斯帕雷阁下说道：“我记得各位绅士在讨论一个侍臣应具有的能力的时候，其中一点是他要招人喜爱。但是，总结一下谈过的话题，我们可以得出这样的结论：一个侍臣必须通过自己的美德和威望来影响他的君王，然而有威望的人一定是位年长者，因为智慧都是随着年龄而增长的，尤其是在经验方面。所以我不明白，一个人如果年事已高是否还谈得上招人喜爱呢？就像今天晚上所说的那样，对一位长者来说，招人喜爱实在是毫无意义，因为女人喜欢的那种属于年轻人的彬彬有礼、幽默感和文雅在一位老者的身上会变得荒唐可笑，对此有些女人会心生厌恶，所有人都会去嘲弄那些沉迷于此的人。因此，如果你们所说的亚里士多德是位老臣，并且打算像年轻的爱侣们一样大谈爱情的话（就像我们亲眼看到过的那些），我恐怕他会忘记对君王的指导，毫无疑问孩子们也会在背后取笑他，而女人们除了嘲笑他之外，对他毫无兴趣。”

奥塔维亚诺回答道：“如果这位老臣身上具有所有的美德，即使他变老，我也认为他不应该被剥夺爱的权利。”

“正相反，”加斯帕雷阁下反驳道，“剥夺他的这种权利，我认为会给他带来另一种完美，使他生活得更快乐，而没有不幸和痛苦。”

于是皮埃特罗·贝博补充说道：“加斯帕雷阁下，难道你忘了前几天晚上奥塔维亚诺先生提议的那个爱情游戏了，虽然他对爱情谈不上了解，他显然很了解有些人把跟他们的女人生气、吵架和折磨都看作是快乐的这种事，还有人向他请教这种快乐的原因来着。因此，如果我们的侍臣陷入那种愉悦的爱情之中，即使年纪很大，他也不会经历任何的痛苦和烦恼。另外，我们心中的那个聪明人也不会欺骗自己，认为凡是适合年轻人做的事情都同样适合于他。即便他要去爱，也肯定会以不给他带来指责，只为他赢得赞美和幸福的方式来进行，他会远离烦恼的困扰，而这些是年轻人都很难以做到的。所以他不会忽视对君王的指导，更不会让孩子们嘲笑。”

于是公爵夫人说道：“皮埃特罗，在今天晚上的讨论中我很高兴听你也说上几句，但是现在我们更加有信心让你说话，给我们阐明这种恰到好处、又不会引发任何指责或不满的爱情；显然这是体现在侍臣身上的最有用、最重要的天赋之一。所以我请求你，告诉我们你对此所知道的一切。”

皮埃特罗笑着回答道：“夫人，我不希望我刚才支持老年人也有权利去爱的话让在座的女士们认为我自己很老，所以还是把这个任务交给别人吧。”

伯爵夫人回答道：“你还年轻，但是你不能否认你有长者的智慧。所以继续给我们讲解吧，不要制造更多的借口。”

于是皮埃特罗·贝博回答道：“说实话，夫人，如果我确实必须继续谈论这个话题，我就必须向拉维乃罗的朋友，一个隐居的修道士，寻求建议。”

听到这里，伊米莉亚夫人好像有些生气，大声说道：

“皮埃特罗，我们当中没有人像你那样不服从命令。因此，如果伯爵夫人要惩罚你也是对的。”

皮埃特罗仍然面带微笑地说道：

“夫人，行行好，不要生我的气，我说就是了。”

“好吧。”伊米莉亚回答道。

皮埃特罗·贝博沉默了一会儿后，他稍作调整，好像有什么重要的事情宣布似的，开始说了起来：

“先生们，为了说明老年人不仅能毫无顾忌地去爱而且有时还能比年轻人爱得更加幸福，我有必要先说明什么是爱，以及爱侣们经历的幸福的本质。我请求你们认真地听，因为我希望能让你们认识到每个人都有爱的权利，即使他比莫雷罗年长十五岁或二十岁。”

一阵笑声过后，他继续说道：

“古代哲学家们给爱下的定义是一种对美的渴求；既然这种渴求必须是为人们所熟知的事物，必然是先有这种事物，后有渴求，而渴求的本质就是追求美好的事物，但是由于其本身也是盲目的，所以不能认识到什么是美好的事物。因此自然本身规定每一种渴求的能力，或者说欲望，都应该同时伴有一种认知能力或者说是理解力。在人类心灵深处，有三种能力帮助我们理解和感知事物：它们是感觉、理性思维和智慧。感觉是从感官的欲求开始的，或者说是从人类与动物共通的那种欲求开始的；理智则是通过理性的选择，严格来说是人所特有的；而智慧使得人类变成完美的天使，通过单纯的意愿来表现对事物的渴求。因此，感官的欲求只渴望那些感官可以感知的东西，而人类的意愿则是在思考那些通过智慧可被理解的精神事物时才会得到满足。于是，人类天生就有理性而且被置于兽性和纯美精神这两个极端之间，可以选择追随感觉，也可以追随智慧，人的欲求在这两个方向不断作出选择。人们可以选择其中一种方式来追求美，那就是，所有的自然天成或人工创造出来的充满和谐的事物。

“但是我现在要谈的美是人身上尤其是脸部的那种美，可以激发我们热切的爱的那种美。我们要说的是，这种美是一种神圣的精华的汇集，就像是阳光普照万物，却偏偏极力展示它的美，那张面容看起来是那样的匀称，明暗色彩和谐、轮廓分明。这种美以其令人赞叹的壮丽和优雅装扮着自己，并使之熠熠发光，好像耀眼的阳光折射在镶嵌着宝石的金光闪闪的花瓶上。于是它吸引了人们的目光，一旦进入人们的视线，就会在人的心灵深处留下深刻的印象，并且不时地以其自身的魅力，伴以燃烧的激情和欲望来震撼、愉悦人们的心灵。这样，人们的思想里就有了对美的渴求，因为它认为这种美是美妙的，如果人的思想本身愿意跟随自己的感知，那么人的头脑里就形成了最严重的错误判断，即承载美的身体是美丽的主因，所以，欣赏这种美就必须尽可能地与之亲密接触。但这是错误的，任何想通过拥有身体而欣赏美的人都是在欺骗自己，因为他们不是被理性的选择而获得的真正认知所感动，而是由感官的欲望导致的错觉。因此，接下来的快乐也必定是虚假的、骗人的。所以，那些用所爱的女人来满足其不纯洁欲望的人都将遭遇两个恶果中的一个：要么在他们满足了欲望后，就开始失去兴趣甚至是开始憎恨他们的爱人，就好像是他的欲望开始悔恨自己的错误，认识到它被错误的感知判断所骗，使它相信那种邪恶是美好的；要么他们仍然困扰于相同的贪念与欲望，因为他们实际上并没有达到他们所追求的目的。不可否认，由于目光短浅，他们误以为自己正经历着快乐，就好像一个病人梦见他自己在干净的喷泉边喝水。然而，他们既没有得到片刻的安宁，也没有得到满足，这恰恰是欲望和占有的必然结果。因为他们看到相似的情况，他们不久就再一次经历了毫无羁绊的欲望，和以前一样，在相同的激情过后他们再一次发现自己对希望完全占有的东西有一种无法控制的、狂热的渴望。因此，这类恋人总是最不快乐的；他们或者由于从来没有得到他们渴望得到的东西，从而引起极大的痛苦，或者即便他们确实得到了他们所渴望得到的东西，也会发现自己并不快乐甚至是更糟。在他们的这种爱情的开始和过程中，除了给彼此带来悲伤、痛苦、难过、忧虑和付出之外别无他物；这样的爱侣必然表现出黯然沮丧、叹息不已、哭哭啼啼、哀痛悲伤、少言寡语甚至想一死了之。”

“因此我们看到感知是这种精神颓废的主要原因；这种情况多发生在人们年轻的时候，他们受到肉体欲望的诱惑，不断地削弱人类理性的力量，使灵魂轻易地受制于欲望。既然心灵已经坠落到世俗的地狱，无法进行精神的思考，那么思想本身就不能清楚地发现真相，继而无法履行操控身体的职责。所以为了明白事情的真相，思想必须借助感知来形成自己的第一概念。之后它才会相信通过感知获取的信息，然后考虑并信任这些信息，尤其是当这些信息强迫心灵接受的时候；但是感知具有欺骗性，从而使它们提供给心灵的信息充满了错误和不实。因此，年轻人总是沉迷于这种与理性完全背道而驰的感性之恋，进而导致他们不能享受爱情赐予真正的理性皈依者们的祝福和益处；他们在爱情中得到的快乐和没有理性的动物是一样的，尽管动物遭遇的痛苦比人类大得多。在我坚信如此的前提下，我相信那些年纪大而成熟的恋人的经历会恰恰相反；对他们来说，思想已经不再屈膝于肉体，因为他们天生的激情已经开始冷却。即便他们被美激起了渴望，也会受到理性的指引，那么他们就不会受骗，从而完全拥有他们深爱的美。这种拥有给他们带来的都是好的结果，因为美是善良的，对美的真正热爱也是美好的、神圣的，而且总是给那些用理性的缰绳来控制感官的罪恶的人们带来好处。这就是年长者比年轻人更能轻而易举做到的事。

“所以说老年人比年轻人更能幸福地、无可指责地去恋爱，不无道理，当然，我们所谓的老年人指的不是那些年迈的或者说身体器官已经衰退，思想已经不能通过器官来行使功能的人，而是指那些智力仍然处于盛年的人。另外我还必须加上这一点：也就是在我看来，感性之恋在每一个年龄段都是不可取的，但是对年轻人来说，是可以原谅的，甚至在某种角度上说也是允许的。虽然这种恋情就像上面提到的那样，给人们带来的是苦恼、危险、付出和不幸，但是为了赢得他们心爱的女人的爱，有些行为是高尚的；虽然这些行为带来的并不是一个很好的结果，但是它们本身是好的。他们从苦涩里挤榨出一点点甘甜，从挫折中吸取教训，知道自己爱的方式有误。所以，我认为那些克制欲望和迷恋，以理性的方式去恋爱的年轻人是真正崇高的，但我也理解那些因为人性的弱点而被感性之恋所征服的年轻人，但前提是，他们当时应该表现得有风度、有礼貌、又值得尊敬，表现出了那些绅士们所提到的其他品质，并且在他们不再年轻的时候，完全舍弃这种做法，摒除感性之欲，并视之为通向真爱的第一个台阶。但是对于那些年迈时还任由激情燃烧他们冷酷的心、令强烈的理性屈服于虚弱的感官之欲的人来说，无论怎样责备都不算过分；这些不知廉耻的家伙就像缺乏理性的动物中的一员，一个彻头彻尾的傻瓜，因为感性之恋的观念和方式与成熟的男人是完全不相称的。”

贝博停顿了一下，好像要休息的样子；正当每个人都沉默的时候，来自奥托纳的莫雷罗先生说道：

“如果一个长者比很多年轻人都强壮，精力更旺盛，而且更英俊，那么你为什么不希望他像年轻人那样去恋爱呢？”

听到这个，伯爵夫人笑着说道：

“如果恋爱对年轻人来说是一次如此不幸的经历，那么莫雷罗先生，为什么你还想要老年人也去经历同样的不幸呢？如果你也像这些先生所说的那样老了，你就不会说这么多老人们的坏话了。”

莫雷罗先生回答道：“在我看来，说老人坏话的似乎是皮埃特罗·贝博，因为他希望他们以我不能理解的方式去恋爱。同时我也认为，如此受他褒奖的美竟然不包括躯体的美，简直像是一个神话。”

“莫雷罗先生，”洛多维科伯爵问道，“你相信美像皮埃特罗·贝博说的一样好吗？”

“我当然不相信，”莫雷罗回答道，“相反，我记得我曾经见过很多邪恶、冷酷、恶毒的美女；在我看来，事情往往如此，因为美丽使她们骄傲，傲慢使她们冷酷。”

洛多维科伯爵笑着回答道：“无可置疑，你觉得她们对你冷酷是因为她们没有给予你想要的东西。还是让皮埃特罗·贝博教教你，老年人应该怎样去渴求美，他们应该从女人那里得到什么，他们应该怎样得到满足；如果你记得这些，你就会发现她们既不骄傲，也不冷酷，而且她们还会给予你想要的。”

这番话让莫雷罗很恼火，于是他反驳道：

“我不想知道和我无关之事。还是让别人告诉你，身体不如老人强壮、精力没有老人充沛的年轻人应该怎样追求这种美吧。”

于是，为了让莫雷罗先生平静下来，也为了转变一下话题，费德里科在洛多维科伯爵还没回答之前，插嘴说道：

“也许莫雷罗先生所说的‘美不总是好的’这句话并不是完全错误的，因为女人的美经常引起很多邪恶、憎恶、战争、死亡和毁灭，例如特洛伊的毁灭就清晰地证明了这一点。大多数美丽的女人不是骄傲冷酷，就是之前所说的不贞洁。但是对此，莫雷罗先生并不认为是什么过错。还有很多邪恶的男人也被赋予了英俊的外表，好像大自然如此安排就是为了让他们能更好地去行骗，或是为了让他们那令人愉悦的外貌成为隐藏鱼钩的饵。”

这时，皮埃特罗·贝博说道：“不要相信美不总是好的这种谎言。”

为了回到原来的话题，洛多维科伯爵插嘴说道：

“既然莫雷罗对和自己有很大关系的事情并不感兴趣，那就告诉我吧，向我说一说老年人怎样才可以赢得爱情的幸福；只要我可以从中受益，我并不担心自己被别人看作是个老头。”

皮埃特罗笑着说：“首先我想纠正一下这些绅士们所犯的错误，然后再满足你的要求。”

于是他继续说道：

“先生们，美是一种神圣的东西，我不希望我们中的任何人因对此口出恶言亵渎神圣而惹怒神明。作为一个给莫雷罗和费德里科先生的警告，以防他们会像那些藐视美的人们一样受到惩罚，从而像斯泰西科拉斯[23]那样双目失明，我坚持认为美来源于上帝，它就像是一个圆，圆心就是善良。正如没有圆心就没有圆一样，一个人没有善良也就没有美。所以，邪恶的灵魂依附在一个美丽的身体上是非常罕见的，而外表美也正是内心善良的一种真正表现。这种美实际上以不同的程度体现在人的身体上，是识别灵魂的一种标志，好比是树木上盛开的鲜花之美将印证收获时的水果之美一样。人类的身体也一样，对此，我们还可以从相学家们根据人的容貌来判断人的性格甚至是他的思想这件事上看得出来。甚至是在动物的身上也可以看到，它们的思想如何影响着身体并且在容貌上有所反映。我们是如何清晰地从一头狮子、一匹马或者一只鹰的面部发现它们愤怒、凶残和傲慢的本性；又如何从绵羊和鸽子那里发现纯洁和单纯，从狐狸和狼那里看到奸邪和狡诈，而且几乎所有的动物也一样，想想这些，我们就不难理解这一点。

“因此大体来说，丑陋的事物是邪恶的，美丽的事物是美好的。可以说，美就是人们渴望的、令人轻松愉快又魅力十足的美好事物的外表，而丑陋就是黑暗的、令人不快又难受的邪恶事物的外表。无论你研究什么事物，你都会发现那些美好而有益的东西总是被赋予了美。想一想万物的神奇的结构吧，它是上帝为了所有生灵的健康和生存而创造的。无尽的苍穹点缀着众多星星：而位于中心的地球被无数天体簇拥在中间；太阳照亮周围的万物，在冬天照到最低刻度后又重新升起；月球的光辉来自于太阳，随着距离太阳的远近不断变化；而其他五大星球在各自的轨道上有规律地运动着。所有这一切都按照大自然的规律和谐存在并互相影响，但是如果稍有偏离，它们就将不复存在，宇宙也因此而崩溃。此外，它们的美和魅力让人们无法想象有什么东西可以与之媲美。再来想想人体的构造，我们可称之为一个小宇宙。我们会发现人类的身体是造物主精心设计而非偶然为之的产物；我们的整体形式非常美妙，使我们很难弄清楚，到底是因为有用还是因为优美才给予了人类外貌和身体的不同部分，包括眼睛、鼻子、嘴巴、耳朵、胳膊和胸部。动物也一样。想一想鸟类的羽毛、树枝上的叶子，它们的存在都是大自然所赋予的，也都是极其精美的。除了自然界，现在我们来谈谈人类的艺术。对于一艘船来说，船头、船体、船板、船帆、船桅、船舵、船桨以及船锚和绳索，哪些是必需的？所有的这些东西都是如此动人，无论谁看见它们，都会觉得它们的存在不仅因为有用还因为好看。再如，支柱和横梁支撑着雄伟的教堂和宫殿，它们不仅赏心悦目，还是建筑不可或缺的部分。当人类最初在造房子或教堂时使用中间的屋脊并非是用来装饰建筑物，而是为了让雨水从两边顺利地流下；但是，我还得说，事物的用途和美观同样重要，所以即使在没有雨水和冰雹的地区建造教堂，屋脊的设计也是必不可少的，否则会使建筑丧失应有的庄严和美感。

“所以，一提到美丽的事物，甚至是世界本身，就意味着最高的赞美。我们提起这些就忍不住要赞美：美丽的天空、美丽的大地、美丽的海洋、美丽的河流、美丽的乡村、美丽的森林、树木、花园；或者美丽的城市、教堂、房子、军队。简而言之，这种优雅而神圣的美是万物最高超的修饰；从某种角度上，好就等同于美，尤其是人的身体。在我看来，身体美的最大成因是心灵美，因为它有一种超自然的美，使它接触到的一切事物都变得华丽而可爱，美丽心灵也一定会找一个适合她栖息的美丽身体。因此，当美以其无上的力量统治物质世界，以其绚丽的光芒驱走身体的黑暗的时候，美才是心灵的最终战利品。因此，我们一定不要说是美让女人们骄傲、冷酷，尽管莫雷罗先生可能是这样认为的；我们也不应该把那些因为男人无节制的欲望而引起的憎恶、死亡和毁灭都强加于美丽的女人。我不否认这个世界上有不贞洁的漂亮女人，但并不是她们的美使她们变成这个样子；相反，正是因为美和善之间的必然联系，她们的美才使她们远离恶行，引领其走上善行之路。但是有时候，由于外界的恶意驱使、爱人的不停挑唆、礼物、贫穷、希望、欺骗、恐惧以及数不清的其他原因，美丽善良的女人没能保持那份坚定，铸成大错；英俊的男人也是一样，因为这样或那样的原因，变得邪恶。”

塞萨尔接着评论说：“如果加斯帕雷阁下昨天的断言不假，那么毫无疑问美丽的女人比丑陋的女人更加贞洁。”

“我断言过什么啊？”加斯帕雷阁下问道。

“如果我没记错的话，”塞萨尔回答道，“你说过被追求的女人总是喜欢拒绝追求者，而没人追求的女人却会主动去追求别人。与丑女相比，美女必然有更多的追求者；这样一来，美女经常拒绝别人，而丑女却因为没有追求者而主动出击，美女就比丑女更显贞洁了。”

贝博微笑着说：“这个争论没有答案。”

然后他又补充说道：“就像其他的感官一样，我们的视觉也有受骗的时候，把一张不美丽的脸看成是美丽的，这是常有的事。比如说，有些女人不时在眼神中和表情里表现出诱惑的、挑逗式的无礼，许多人认为这些特点是令人愉悦的，视其为美，因为这让他们有机会得到他们想要的。但是，事实上这仅仅是俗艳的轻率行为，丝毫配不上如此令人尊重而神圣的称呼。”

皮埃特罗·贝博随后陷入了沉默之中，但是大家要他再多讲讲这样的爱以及欣赏美的正确方式，最终他说道：

“我想我已经说得够清楚了，年长的人比年轻人在爱中更幸福，这是我的假定。所以我不能再补充什么了。”

洛多维科伯爵回应说：“你对年轻人不幸福的论证比对年长者幸福的论证要充分，因为你没有教给年长者在爱中要循着怎样的路前进，你仅仅告诉他们要受理性的指引。许多人认为爱和理性是无法相容的。”

贝博仍然决定不再发言，但是在公爵夫人的请求下，他又接着说了起来：“如果在我们的灵魂中如此热切的渴望能这么容易就被激起，如果我们的灵魂被迫在这种和动物类似的感觉中得到滋养，而不能将这种渴望导向一种更加积极的方面，那着实是人性的悲哀。既然您希望这样，那我不会拒绝讨论这个高贵的话题。我知道我不配讲述关于爱神的神圣秘密。所以我恳求上帝能够启发我的思想和语言，使我能够教给我们优秀的侍臣如何以优于那些粗俗的众人的方式去爱。由于自幼时起我就将自己交给了上帝，希望我的话与我的意志相符，也能够为上帝赢得更多的认可。我认为，既然年轻时人的本性如此依赖于感官，当侍臣年轻时，他可以用感官的方式去爱；但是，当他更成熟时，这种情色的欲望会让他受伤，他必须小心谨慎，不要欺骗自己，不要让自己经历痛苦，那种痛苦对年轻人而言值得同情而非指责，但在年长的人则应受指责而非同情。

“因此，当他看到那些美丽而吸引人的女人时，这时的他优雅又富有魅力，已是情场高手，他可以察觉出他和她灵魂的共鸣，一旦他注意到他的目光被她的外表所吸引并把她记在心里，他的灵魂会因深深地想念她而感到愉悦，情感的洪流渐渐涌动，温暖着他的灵魂，她的眼眸里闪耀的活泼神气不断给他情感的火焰增添新的燃料，那么一开始他就应该设法寻求一种快速的自救方法，让理智提高警惕以帮助他保卫心灵的城堡，关闭通向感官和欲望的道路，使其不能强行通过或蒙混过关。若火焰被熄灭了，危险也就消失了。但是，如果它（这种情感）坚持了下来并且不断生长，那他就该知道自己被俘虏了，这时这个侍臣就应该避开庸俗激情的所有丑陋，接受理智的指引，走上圣洁的爱情之路。他应该想清楚的第一件事就是，身体是美寄居的躯壳而不是美的源泉，与此相反，美是非物质的，是如我们所说的超自然的光芒，当它与最基本和易变质的事物融合在一起时，会失去它大部分的高贵本性：因为越是完美，它所包含的物质内容越少，而当与物质完全脱离时，美才达到最完美的境界。他也必须清楚，正如人不能用味蕾来听，不能用耳朵闻一样，美以及它在我们的灵魂中激发出来的渴望绝对无法通过触觉得到满足，而只能通过真正能够将美视为客体的东西，即视觉器官来满足。因此，他应该忽略这些感官的盲目判断而是用眼睛欣赏他所爱的女人的光辉、优雅、可爱的热情、微笑、言谈举止以及其他令人愉悦的装饰。同样，他应该用听觉来欣赏她甜美的声音，优雅的言谈，如果她是一位音乐家，也要欣赏她的音乐。通过这两种不关乎肉欲却为理性服务的感官渠道，他能够用最令人愉悦的食粮滋养他的灵魂，而不会让对肉体的渴求激起任何不纯洁的欲望。另外，他应带着最高的敬意去尊重、取悦并服从他爱的女人，比珍惜自己更加珍惜他的爱人，把她的舒适和快乐放在首位，爱她躯体的美更爱她灵魂的美。因此，他必须竭尽全力使她免于走上歧途，通过他的睿智和告诫使她变得谦恭、温和，真正地拥有道德；他还必须让她的思想保持纯洁，不受任何恶念的玷污。因此通过在她那可爱灵魂的花园里播种美德，他将收获完美无瑕的举止，品尝果实甘美的味道。这将是真正的在美中创造美，在美中体现美，有人说这就是爱的目的。通过这种方式，我们的侍臣会深得爱人的欢心，她也总是会那么顺从、迷人、温柔、渴望取悦于他并得到他的爱；他们二人的渴望是非常纯洁、和谐的，因此他们也会非常幸福。”

接着莫雷罗阁下说道：“在现实生活中，这种在美中创造美一定是指让那美丽的女人生一个漂亮的孩子；在我看来，以这种方式取悦她所爱的人更能表明她对他的爱，比你提到的温柔好得多。”

贝博笑着回答说：“你不能越界，莫雷罗阁下；一个女人在把她所珍视的美给予她的爱人的时候，不仅仅是一种爱的象征，她也把通向她灵魂的途径给了他，即视觉和听觉，她的眼眸，她的面容，她的声音，她的话语无不深入她的爱人的心底，传达着她爱的证明。”

莫雷罗阁下接着说：“眼神和语言可能并且常常是虚假的证明。我认为任何不能作出更好承诺的爱都是最不确定的爱。说实话，我希望您能让您的女人比贵族阁下的女人对侍臣更加谦恭有礼、慷慨大度。然而，我认为你们双方的做法都像那些法官一样，为了显示自己的英明对自己人宣判。”

“我非常乐意，”贝博继续说道，“我说的这种女人对年长的侍臣比贵族阁下的女人对年轻的侍臣更加谦恭有礼，这是有充分理由的，因为我的侍臣只期望一切都很得体，而这些她可以很轻松地做到。然而贵族的女人，她的行为是否表现得谦恭有礼要视年轻的侍臣是否正派而定。因此，我的侍臣得到了所有他想要得到的东西，他也比另外一个更加快乐，因为另一个只满足了部分要求，其他部分却遭到了拒绝。为了使你们更好地了解理智的爱情比感性之恋更加幸福，我想说，有时候一种东西在感性之恋中应该否定，在理智的爱情中却应该给予支持。因为在前一种爱中这种东西显得不得体，而在后一种中却很合适。因此，为了取悦她那谦恭有礼的爱人，除了向他展露令人愉悦的笑容，亲密地和他说说悄悄话，自在地说说俏皮话，牵牵手，这位女士可能合情合理而又心地纯洁地吻吻她的爱人。而根据贵族阁下的规则，感性之恋是不允许这样的。原因在于，吻是身体与灵魂的结合，这里存在一种风险，即感性的爱人可能对身体的依恋大于灵魂；但是，理性的爱人却认为尽管嘴是身体的一部分，但是它也提供一种语言的渠道，而语言是对灵魂的解读，它同时也是人类呼吸和表达自己的精神的渠道。因此，理性的人吻他所爱的女人时非常愉悦，不是因为会激发任何不得体的欲望，而是因为他感觉到这种结合打开了彼此灵魂的大门，它们为共同的渴望所吸引，彼此注入对方的体内，彼此融合，每个人都拥有了两个灵魂，就仿佛由两部分组成的一个灵魂统辖着两个躯体。因此，这种吻可以被称为精神的结合而非肉体的结合，因为它对灵魂产生影响，使灵魂为它所吸引而与身体相分离。正因为如此，所有贞洁的爱人都渴望一吻，因为它代表灵魂的结合；所以在谈到爱情时，柏拉图曾经说过，接吻时，灵魂来到唇边，为的是离开身体。由于灵魂和感官所感知的事物是相互分离的，它与精神层面的完全结合可以用一个吻来表示。在他那借助灵感而创作的《雅歌》中，所罗门说：‘愿他用他的吻来吻我，’表达的愿望就是，让这种圣洁之爱把他的灵魂带向对圣洁之美的关注，通过与这种圣洁之美的亲密融合使自己的灵魂可以远离躯体。”

所有人都凝神倾听贝博的话，他停了一会儿接着说：

“既然你们让我告诉已经不再年轻的侍臣什么是真正幸福的爱情，我想引导他更进一步。因为停留在这一点是很危险的。原因在于，就像我们已经说过很多次的那样，灵魂强烈地倾向于感觉；尽管理智在选择的过程中很正确，并且意识到美并非源于肉体，还会制约不纯洁的欲望，但是，一直关注躯体的美会妨碍真正的判断。这样尽管不会导致什么罪恶，却会使分离的爱人十分痛苦。这是因为，如果躯体之美是存在的，它会给爱人的精神带来强烈的愉悦感，通过温暖他的内心，激起并且融化一些隐藏着的凝结的力量，这些力量被爱的温暖所滋养，因爱的温暖而流淌，充溢着他的内心，通过他的眼睛传达出那些精神，或那种最为微妙的气息（包含着血液中最为纯洁、最为明亮的部分），一起来迎接她的美，并且为她的美装点上各式各样的装饰。结果，灵魂中充满了想象与愉悦；它既害怕又高兴；在体验快乐的同时也体验着神圣的事物所激发的那种敬畏和崇敬，灵魂似乎有些迷乱，它相信自己来到了天堂。

“因此，只关注躯体之美的人，一旦他所爱的女人离开，他的眼前一旦没有了那美的光辉，就会失去所有的美好和幸福，结果，他的灵魂也枯萎了。因为她的美的远离，往日她在时的那种柔情不再涌来温暖他的心。而他身体的各个感觉器官开始变得干涸；然而对于她美的记忆仍然能在他的灵魂中激起一点力量，使它们能够试图将这些精神发泄出来。尽管它们的路途被阻塞，没有任何出口，但还是努力着去挣脱，它们被痛苦包围着，于是就开始戳刺灵魂使它痛苦万分，这就像孩子们的牙齿开始从柔软的牙龈中生长出来的感觉一样。它会让爱人们流泪、叹息、痛苦、烦忧，因为他们的灵魂一直处于痛苦和混乱中，它愤怒、生气直到它所珍视的美再一次出现在眼前，才突然冷静下来，又开始呼吸，它深深沉醉，从眼前的美食中汲取力量，并希望永远不要再离开这个令人着迷的景象。因此，为摆脱由于分离而造成的痛苦，享受美而不受苦，侍臣应该借助理智将他的欲望完全从躯体转向美本身。他应该在能力所及的范围内尽力思考美本身的简单与纯洁，在自己的想象中创造出一种有别于任何物质形态的抽象美，使它为自己的灵魂所喜爱和珍视，永远在灵魂中享受着它，日日夜夜，不论何时何地，不需害怕失去它；而他也会记得，躯体与美是完全不同的，而且躯体只会削减而非提升美。通过这种方式，我们那年长的侍臣将会使自己远离痛苦和忧伤，不会再经历年轻的侍臣们经历过的嫉妒、怀疑、不屑、生气、绝望和暴怒，最后一种情绪有时会把他们引上歧途，有些人不仅伤害了他们爱的女人，甚至还赔上了自己的性命。而年长的侍臣则不会伤害自己所爱的女人的丈夫、父亲、兄弟或她的家庭，他不会令她蒙羞，也不会时常被迫转移目光，谨言慎行，害怕暴露自己的渴望，或者在离开她时遭受痛苦。因为他会永远把这种珍贵的情感藏在心中，而且通过想象的力量，使她的美比在现实中的更加可爱。

“然而，如果他决定把这份爱当作阶梯，借此走向一个更伟大的境界，那么在众多的益处中他将会发现一个更加美妙的益处；这是完全有可能的，因为如果他不断地反思自己，就会发现把自己的思想局限在一个躯体上是多么狭隘。为了脱离这种思想的局限，他会逐渐地为头脑中的美增加很多装饰，通过把他头脑中想到的所有美的形式都连接在一起，并将各种形式统一起来，简化成一种单一的美，这种统一笼罩着人类本性的整体。因此，他不会再考虑某一个女人的美，而是会考虑那种装点了所有人的共同之美。这种美的光辉更加耀眼，让他惊叹不已，因此，他不再重视某个女人的美；在这种更纯净的火焰中，往日他视若珍宝的东西，变得毫无价值。现在，处于这种境界的爱，尽管高尚，很少有人能达到，但仍然不能称为完美的爱。因为人类的想象力来自于身体的感官，只能通过感官输送的数据来获取信息，所以它也不能完全清除物质中有害的一面。所以，尽管它对人类共同之美能通过抽象和简化的方法进行加工，但其结果却很模糊，不确定，因为它的形成与身体还是有着密切的关系；因此，达到这种爱的境界的人就仿佛刚刚长出羽毛的雏鸟，用柔弱的翅膀可以支撑着飞行一段路，但不敢远离鸟巢，也不敢勇敢地迎着风，飞向广阔的天空。

“因此，当我们的侍臣达到了这种爱的境界时，尽管可以说与那些仍然沉浸在感性之恋的痛苦中的人相比，他大多时候是幸福的，但我希望他不要满足，而要在爱的宏伟道路上继续勇往直前，朝着真正的幸福迈进。因此，与其将他的思想集中于外部世界，就像那些关注躯体之美的人，不如让他关注自己的内心，思索他心灵看到的一切，从而看透因注重躯体美而被忽略的内在美。因此去除所有的邪恶，通过学习真正的哲学，朝着高尚的精神世界，在智慧的不断磨砺下，灵魂开始转向对自身的思考，仿佛从沉睡中醒来，张开了眼睛，这样的眼睛原本是人人都有的，但很少有人通过它看到向它传递的那束光——天使之美的真正面目，而反过来它又将一个模糊的印象反映在躯体上。因此，当心灵对世俗的一切视而不见的时候，就对来自天堂的一切张开了眼睛；有时当身体的感官完全陷入这种冥思苦想，或进入梦乡的时候，在没有任何干扰的情况下，心灵才真正品味到天使之美的味道，心灵因那束美妙的光线而欣喜若狂，开始燃烧，开始追逐，它如此地热切、迷醉、忘我，时刻想要与那种美融为一体。因为那时心灵相信它发现了上帝的踪迹，思考它的过程就是对终极的宁静和快乐追寻的过程。因此，在这种最令人愉悦的火焰中，它升华到了最高贵的部分，即智慧层面；在那里，它不再被俗世的黑夜所笼罩，它领悟到了圣洁之美。尽管这样，它也并非完美无瑕地享受着这种境界，因为它仅仅以自己的智慧在思考，而它的智慧还不足以完全领悟那无限的济世之美。因此，爱不仅仅给人带来很多益处，它还会给心灵带来更大的幸福。因为正如它引导心灵从个体的躯体之美转向济世之美，它还将指导心灵从个体的智慧走向普世的智慧，从而到达完美的最高境界。从那里，心灵燃烧着真爱的圣火，飞翔起来与天使的本性融合在一起，它不仅抛弃了感官，甚至连理智本身也不需要了。因为，已经化身为天使的它，了解所有智慧层面的东西，眼前不再有迷雾，不再有乌云，可以凝视广阔的圣洁之美的海洋，享受着感官无法体会的至高的幸福。

“我们每天都用那被乌云遮蔽的眼睛看到存在于堕落躯壳中的美（即使是这样也仅仅是梦幻和模糊的影子），觉得它们是那么可爱，那么优雅，它们常常在我们的内心深处燃起最为热烈的火焰，带来如此的愉悦，从而觉得没有什么能与被自己深爱的女人看上一眼带来的幸福相提并论。所以可想而知，当我们看到那种圣洁之美时会怎样的快乐无比，心中一定会充满了神圣的敬仰！多么可爱的火焰，多么令人沉醉的火焰，我们相信它必然是源自于最崇高、最真实的美，这种美是其他所有美的源泉，恒久不变，永远美丽，最为质朴，毫无瑕疵；仿佛仅仅展现自我，仅仅奉献自我；然而，它是如此美丽，以至于所有其他的美好事物都从它那里汲取美丽。这就是与至善密不可分的美，它的光辉呼唤着、吸引着周围的一切，它不仅把智慧、理智、感觉和对生命的渴望赐予配得上这些能力的人，还将坚定和其他特有的品质赐予岩石和植物，给它们也打上美的印记。因此，这种爱，与其他的相比更伟大、更幸福，因为产生它的源泉更伟大。所以，正如物质的火焰能够炼出金子，这最圣洁的火焰毁掉我们灵魂中一切世俗的东西，而滋养和美化原来被感官埋没的超凡脱俗的部分。这就是诗人笔下俄塔山顶上烧死大力神赫拉克勒斯[24]的火焰，经过火的洗礼，重生的他成为永生的神灵；这就是摩西[25]手中那燃烧的荆棘，是分开的火舌，是以利亚[26]那燃烧的战车，当它离开大地飞向天空之际，那些有幸看到它高贵灵魂的人感到无比的荣耀和幸福。让我们把灵魂中所有的思想，所有的力量都引向这最为圣洁的光芒，指引我们通向天堂的路途。跟随着它，抛弃那些虚假的激情，让我们顺着阶梯攀爬，那最低的一级承载的是感官之美，最终通向那容纳着超凡脱俗，令人钦羡的真正的美的宫殿，它藏身在万能的上帝的幽居之地，凡夫俗子的眼睛是看不到的。在这里，我们能为欲望找到一个真正幸福的结局，能真正结束劳累得到安歇，为悲伤找到慰藉，为疾病找到灵药，为这动荡的一生找到躲避暴风雨的港湾。

“噢，最圣洁的爱，什么样的言语才能把你赞美？您充满了美、善良和智慧，你的源泉在于美、善良和神圣智慧的结合，你居于斯，又永久地回归它的怀抱。你优雅地把整个宇宙连接起来，就在圣洁和凡尘之间，你善意地安排上天，让它给凡尘以指引，让人们的思想回归本源，从而将他们连接在一起。你把这些因素和谐地融为一体，激发大自然去孕育生命并把所有的生命推向永恒。你把分离的东西合并在一起，把不完美变得完美，把不同变成相似，把对手化为朋友，给大地带来果实，给大海带来平和，给天空带来赐予生命的光芒。你是真正的快乐、福祉、和平、温柔和善良之父；你是粗野和卑劣的仇敌；你是所有美好的起点和终结；由于你喜欢栖息在美丽的躯体和灵魂的深处，而且有时候愿意向那些你喜爱的人展示自己，我相信，此时此刻你就居于我们之中。噢，上帝啊，请倾听我们的祈祷，把您的光辉注入我们的内心，用您那最圣洁的火焰的光芒为我们驱散黑暗，就像一位可信的向导，为我们指明走出迷宫的路。更正我们的感官错误，在我们长时间的妄想迷乱后，让我们知道什么才是真正的美。给我们的智慧增添灵性的香气，让我们与圣洁协调一致，再没有空间容纳激情的纷争。使我们的灵魂沉醉于永不干涸的满足之泉，让它永远愉悦，永远满足，谁喝了它那清澈的活水谁就能品尝到真正祝福的味道。您的光辉驱散了蒙住我们双眼的无知的迷瘴，因此它们不再赞誉世俗的美，它们也认识到第一眼看到的不是真实，相反，没有看到的才是真实。请接受我们灵魂的奉献，让它们在烧毁一切尘世渣滓的火焰中燃烧，浴火重生并与超凡脱俗之美永久地结合，而我们，从自我奴役中解放出来的我们，就像真正的爱侣能被转变成为我们爱的客体，飞向天空，参加天使的盛宴，那里有仙肴和琼浆玉液，这样，我们就可以幸福终老，就像先祖一样，通过思想的伟大力量，他们的灵魂与肉体分开，最终与上帝融为一体。”

贝博以这种激动的语气谈了这么多，仿佛出离了自己本身，而后他变得沉静缄默，仰望着天空，仿佛有些茫然了。艾米莉亚夫人和其他人全神贯注地倾听了他所有的谈话，然后，她拉了拉他长袍的褶边，说道：

“小心啊，皮埃特罗，虽然你有这种想法，但可别让你的灵魂出了窍啊。”

“夫人，”皮埃特罗回答说，“这可不是爱在我身上发生的第一个奇迹。”

随后伯爵夫人和其他所有人都再一次坚持让贝博继续说下去；几乎每一个人都感觉到了激发贝博思想的那个神圣之爱的火花。他们都急切地想听到更多，但他说道：

“先生们，我已经把有关圣洁之爱这个话题所激发出来的想法都说完了。现在这种灵感好像消逝了，我不知道该说什么；我想关于爱这个话题我不能再深入下去了，侍臣们听我说了这么多，也许他们有补充；因此，可能我的话就到此为止吧。”

“确实是，”伯爵夫人说道，“年长的侍臣如若能够遵循你刚才向他展示的光明大道，他确实会为自己莫大的幸福感到满足而不会嫉妒年轻人。”

然后塞萨尔·贡萨加评论说：“在我看来，通向幸福的路途太过陡峭，我认为没什么人能够通过。”

其后，加斯帕雷阁下评论道：“我认为这条道路对男人来说很难，对女人来说是不可能的。”

艾米莉亚夫人笑了，她说道：

“加斯帕雷阁下，如果你再这样冒犯我们，我保证不再原谅你。”

加斯帕雷阁下回答说：“说女人的灵魂不像男人那样被激情所涤荡，或不像男人那样善于思考，就像皮埃特罗所说的，如果要品味圣洁之爱就必须这样，这可不是对女人的冒犯。因此，我们从没在哪本书上读到女人获得过这种恩赐，但我们却听说许多男人有，比如，柏拉图、苏格拉底、柏罗丁[27]以及其他许多人；同样的，我们的先祖中也有许多这样的人，比如说圣弗朗西斯，他身上有爱的信使为他印上的五个最神圣的印记。还有，爱的力量让圣徒保罗说出无人敢讲的秘密，并为圣徒史蒂芬指明天路的出口。”

随后，尊贵的朱利亚诺回答说：

“在这一点上，女人丝毫不比男人逊色：因为苏格拉底自己承认他所知道的爱的所有秘密都是一个女人向他揭示的，那就是著名的狄奥提玛[28]，用爱的火焰戳刺圣弗朗西斯的天使也让我们这个时代的几个女人拥有同样的印记。你们也应该记得，由于爱，抹大拉的马利亚[29]的许多罪孽都得到了原谅，与圣保罗相比可能她的优雅并不逊色，由于天使之爱，她多次被带到耶和华的居所。你们也应该记得其他许多人，比如我昨天谈了很久的那些人，为了上帝的爱的名义，不顾自己的生命，他们不惧怕酷刑，或任何形式的死亡，不管那有多么可怕，多么残酷。她们不像皮埃特罗期望的侍臣那么年迈，只是娇弱的女子，并且正处在容易让男人想入非非的芳龄。”

加斯帕雷阁下正准备回答，但是伯爵夫人说道：

“让皮埃特罗·贝博来做裁判，让我们都遵照他的意见来判断女人是否和男人一样能够拥有圣洁之爱。但是，你们的辩论可能会持续很长时间，我们还是推迟到明天再谈吧。”

“应该说是今天晚上吧。”塞萨尔·贡萨加说道。

“为什么是今天晚上呢？”伯爵夫人问道。

塞萨尔回答说：“因为天已经亮了。”他向她指了指从窗缝里漏进来的阳光。随后他们都站起身，十分吃惊，因为没有感觉到讨论的时间比平时更长，但是由于他们开始的比平时晚了很多，而且谈得更有兴致，这些先生们是如此全神贯注，谁也没注意到时间的流逝，也没有人感觉到疲倦：在平时该睡觉的时间还醒着通常会有这种感觉。所以当宫殿里正对着卡瑞亚山那高耸山巅的一侧的窗子被打开时，他们看到，黎明已经降临东方，天空晕染得像一朵娇艳的玫瑰，所有的星星都隐遁了，只剩下那天空的女主人，金星维纳斯，守卫着日和夜的边界。从那里，好像吹起一阵微风，空气随之充满了刺骨严寒，四周的小山上，树林婆娑低语，鸟儿从睡梦中被唤醒，开始愉快地歌唱。随后，所有的人都恭敬地向伯爵夫人告别，准备回自己的房间去了，谁也没用火把，因为天光已经足够明亮；而在他们就要走出房门时，行政官转过身对伯爵夫人说道：

“夫人，为了解决加斯帕雷阁下和贵族先生之间的争论，今晚我们和裁判来得会比昨天早啊。”

艾米莉亚夫人回答说：“如果加斯帕雷阁下想批评女性，或像往常一样诋毁她们，他就该遭到审判，因为我要控告他是有失公正的人。”

[1]费德里科公爵：即费德里科二世，于1444年接手管理乌尔比诺公国，1474年正式成为乌尔比诺大公，一直执政到1482年。——译者注

[2]萨卢斯特（Sallst）：古罗马历史学家和政治家。——译者注

[3]恺撒（Caesar）：古罗马的将军、政治家。——译者注

[4]瓦罗（Varre）：古罗马政治家、学者。——译者注

[5]埃斯基涅斯（Aeschines）：古希腊演说家。——译者注

[6]狄摩西尼（Demosthenes）：古希腊雄辩家。——译者注

[7]洛多维科伯爵提到的四个意大利语单词的意思分别是：满意的、正直的、事业、人民。

[8]卡图卢斯（Catullus）：古罗马诗人。——译者注

[9]伊格内修（Egnatius）：卡图卢斯诗中的一个人物。——译者注

[10]亚西比德（Alcibiades）：古希腊雅典政客和将领。——译者注

[11]西庇阿·阿非利加努斯（Scipio Africanus，公元前237—前183）：古罗马统帅。——译者注

[12]色诺芬（Xenophon，公元前431—前355？）：古希腊将领、历史学家，苏格拉底的学生，率一万希腊雇佣军参加波斯王子小塞勒斯反对其兄阿塔泽克西兹二世的战争，远征到达黑海，著有《远征记》《希腊史》《回忆苏格拉底》等。——译者注

[13]卢库勒斯（Luculus，公元前117—前56）：罗马将军和执政官。——译者注

[14]苏拉（Sulla，公元前138—前78）：古罗马统帅、独裁者。早年参加对努米底亚国古朱古达和对北方日耳曼人的战争，并任大法官。——译者注

[15]庞培（Pompey，公元前106—前48）：罗马共和国的政治家和将领之一。——译者注

[16]布鲁特斯（Brutus，85？—42）：古罗马政治家和将军，图谋暗杀恺撒。——译者注

[17]赛壬（Sirens）：海妖，以美丽的歌声迷惑海上船员的妖怪。——译者注

[18]厄毗米修斯（Epimetheus）：普罗米修斯的兄弟，被称为“后知者”。——译者注

[19]弥涅耳瓦（Minerva）：古罗马神话中智慧和技术及工艺之神。——译者注

[20]伏尔坎（Vulcan）：天神朱庇特之子，灵魂和才智十分卓越。——译者注

[21]墨丘利（Mercury）：罗马神话中朱庇特与女神迈亚所生的儿子，担任诸神的使者和传译。——译者注

[22]撒敦（Saturn）：罗马神话中的农业之神。——译者注

[23]斯泰西科拉斯（Stesichorus）：公元前六世纪希腊抒情诗人。传说因为他用情不专，背叛了山林女神娜伊爱斯（Naias），爱上了西西里国王的女儿，眼睛被山林女神弄瞎。——译者注

[24]赫拉克勒斯（Hercules）：罗马神话中的大力神。——译者注

[25]摩西（Moses）：犹太教、基督教故事中古以色列人首领，曾率领古以色列人出埃及。——译者注

[26]以利亚（Elias）：公元前九世纪以色列的先知，见《圣经·列王记》。——译者注

[27]柏罗丁（Plotinus）：古罗马哲学家，新柏拉图学派主要代表，亚历山大里亚-罗马新柏拉图学派创始人，提出“流溢说”，著有《九章集》。——译者注

[28]狄奥提玛（Diotima）：女祭司，她教导了苏格拉底有关爱的知识。——译者注

[29]抹大拉的马利亚（Mary Magdalene）：耶稣最著名的门徒之一，耶稣曾从其身上逐出七个恶鬼，一直以被耶稣拯救的妓女形象出现在基督教的传说中。——译者注

The First Book of the Courtier

I have spent a long time wondering, my dear Alfonso, which of two things was the more difficult for me: either to refuse what you have asked me so often and so insistently, or to do it. On the one hand, it seemed to me to be very hard to refuse anything, and especially something praiseworthy, to one whom I love dearly and by whom I feel I am very dearly loved; yet on the other hand, to embark on a project which I was uncertain of being able to finish seemed wrong to one who respects adverse criticism as much as it ought to be respected. Eventually, after a great deal of thought, I have made up my mind to find out how diligent I can be when helped by affection and the anxiety to please, which usually act as a sharp spur to all kinds of activity.

Now your request is that I should describe what, in my view, is the form of courtiership most appropriate for a gentleman living at the Courts of princes, by which he will have the knowledge and the ability to serve them in every reasonable thing, winning their favour and the praise of others. In short, you want to know what kind of man must be one who deserves the name of a perfect courtier and has no shortcomings whatsoever. Considering this request, I must say that, if I did not think it a greater fault to be judged wanting in love by you than wanting in prudence by others, I would have rejected the task, for fear of being accused of rashness by all those who know how difficult an undertaking it is to select from all the many and various customs followed at the Courts of Christendom the most perfect model and, as it were, the very flower of courtiership. For familiarity often causes the same things to be liked and disliked: and thus it sometimes happens that the customs, behaviour, ceremonies and ways of life approved of at one period of time grow to be looked down on, and those which were once looked down on come to be approved. So we can see clearly enough that usage is more effective than reason in introducing new things among us and in wiping out the old. And anyone who tries to judge what is perfect in these matters often deceives himself. Being well aware of this, therefore, and of the many other problems connected with the subject proposed to me, I am compelled to say something by way of excuse and to testify that what I am doing wrong (if it can be called so) you are responsible for as well, and that if I am to be blamed for it you must share the blame. After all, you must be judged to be as much at fault in imposing on me a task greater than my resources as I am in having accepted it.

But let us now begin to discuss the subject we have chosen and, if it is possible, create a courtier so perfect that the prince who is worthy of his service, even though his dominion is small, can count himself a truly great ruler. In these books we shall not follow any strict order or list a series of precepts, as is the normal practice in teaching. Instead, following many writers of the ancient world, and reviving a pleasant memory, we shall recount some discussions which once took place among men who were singularly qualified in these matters. Even though I did not take part in them in person (being in England when they were held), they were faithfully reported to me soon after my return by someone who was present, and I shall endeavour to reproduce them as accurately as my memory allows so that you may discover what was held and thought on the subject by eminent men whose judgement can always be trusted completely. Nor will it be beside the purpose, in order to continue the story in logical order, to describe the occasion of the discussions that took place.

On the slopes of the Apennines, almost in the centre of Italy towards the Adriatic, is situated, as everyone knows, the little city of Urbino. Although it is surrounded by hills which are perhaps not as agreeable as those found in many other places, none the less it has been favoured by Nature with a very rich and fertile countryside, so that as well as a salubrious atmosphere it enjoys an abundance of all the necessities of life. Among the blessings and advantages that can be claimed for it, I believe the greatest is that for a long time now it has been governed by outstanding rulers, even though in the turmoils into which Italy was plunged by war it was for a time deprived of them. Without looking any further, we can find a splendid example in Duke Federico of glorious memory, who in his day was the light of Italy. Nor are there lacking today any number of reliable witnesses to his prudence, humanity, justice, generosity and unconquerable spirit, and to his military skill, which was brilliantly attested by his many victories, his ability to capture impregnable places, his swift and decisive expeditions, his having routed many times with few troops great and formidable armies, and his never having lost a single battle. So we can fairly compare him with many famous men of the ancient world. Among his other commendable enterprises, Duke Federico built on the rugged site of Urbino a palace which many believe to be the most beautiful in all Italy; and he furnished it so well and appropriately that it seemed more like a city than a mere palace. For he adorned it not only with the usual objects, such as silver vases, wall-hangings of the richest cloth of gold, silk and other similar material, but also with countless antique statues of marble and bronze, with rare pictures, and with every kind of musical instrument; nor would he tolerate anything that was not most rare and outstanding. Then, at great cost, he collected a large number of the finest and rarest books, in Greek, Latin and Hebrew, all of which he adorned with gold and silver, believing that they were the crowning glory of his great palace.

Following, therefore, the course of Nature, and being already sixty-five years old, Duke Federico died as gloriously as he had lived, leaving as his heir his only son, a little, motherless boy of ten named Guidobaldo. And Guidobaldo seemed to inherit not only his father's state but all his virtues as well, immediately showing in his marvellous disposition the promise of more than can be expected from a mortal man. In consequence, it was widely said that of all the wonderful things that Duke Federico had done, the greatest was to have fathered such a son. But envious of his great qualities, Fortune set herself with all her might to frustrate what had begun so nobly, with the result that before he was yet twenty years old Duke Guido fell sick with the gout which, inflicting terrible pain, grew steadily worse and within a short space of time crippled him so badly that he could neither stand nor walk. Thus one of the best and most handsome men in the whole world was deformed and ruined while still of tender age. Not satisfied even with this, Fortune so opposed him in all his projects that he rarely succeeded in what he undertook and although he was a man of mature deliberation and unconquerable spirit, everything he set his hand to, whether in arms or anything else, great or small, always ended unhappily, as we can see from the many diverse calamities which befell him, and which he always bore with such fortitude that his will was never crushed by fate. On the contrary, with great resilience and spirit, he despised the blows of Fortune, living the life of a healthy and happy man, despite sickness and adversity, and achieving true dignity and universal renown. Thus even though he was infirm, he campaigned with a most honourable rank in the service of their Serene Highnesses Kings Alfonso and Ferdinand the Younger of Naples, and subsequently with Pope Alexander VI as well as the Signories of Venice and Florence. Then, after the accession of Pope Julius II, he was made Captain of the Church; and during this time, following his customary style of life, he saw to it that his household was filled with very noble and worthy gentlemen, with whom he lived on the most familiar terms, delighting in their company. In this the pleasure he caused others was no less than what he received, for he was very well versed in both Latin and Greek, and possessed as well as an affable and charming nature, an infinite range of knowledge. Moreover, his indomitable spirit so spurred him on that, even though he himself was unable to take part in chivalrous activities, as he once used to, he loved to see them pursued by others, and he would show his fine judgement when commenting on what they did, correcting or praising each one according to his merits. So in jousts and tournaments, in riding, in handling every kind of weapon, as well as in the festivities, games and musical performances, in short, in all the activities appropriate to a well-born gentleman, everyone at his Court strove to behave in such a way as to deserve to be judged worthy of the Duke's noble company.

So all day and every day at the Court of Urbino was spent on honourable and pleasing activities both of the body and the mind. But since the Duke always retired to his bedroom soon after supper, because of his infirmity, as a rule at that hour everyone went to join the Duchess, Elisabetta Gonzaga, with whom was always to be found signora Emilia Pia, a lady gifted with such a lively wit and judgement, as you know, that she seemed to be in command of all and to endow everyone else with her own discernment and goodness. In their company polite conversations and innocent pleasantries were heard, and everyone's face was so full of laughter and gaiety that the house could truly be called the very inn of happiness. And I am sure that the delight and enjoyment to be had from loving and devoted companionship were never experienced elsewhere as they once were in Urbino. For, apart from the honour it was for each of us to be in the service of a ruler such as I described above, we all felt supremely happy whenever we came into the presence of the Duchess; and this sense of contentment formed between us a bond of affection so strong that even between brothers there could never have been such harmonious agreement and heartfelt love as there was among us all. It was the same with the ladies, whose company we all enjoyed very freely and innocently, since everyone was allowed to talk and sit, make jokes and laugh with whom he pleased, though such was the respect we had for the wishes of the Duchess that the liberty we enjoyed was accompanied by the most careful restraint. And without exception everyone considered that the most pleasurable thing possible was to please her and the most displeasing thing in the world was to earn her displeasure. So for these reasons in her company the most decorous behaviour proved compatible with the greatest freedom, and in her presence our games and laughter were seasoned both with the sharpest witticisms and with a gracious and sober dignity. For the modesty and nobility which informed every act, word and gesture of the Duchess, in jest and laughter, caused even those seeing her for the first time to recognize that she was a very great lady. It seemed, from the way in which she influenced those around her, that she tempered us all to her own character and quality, so that everyone endeavoured to imitate her personal way of behaviour, deriving as it were a model of fine manners from the presence of so great and talented a woman, whose high qualities I do not intend to describe now, since this is not to my purpose and they are well known to all the world, apart from being beyond the reach of whatever I could say or write. But I must add that those qualities in the Duchess which might have remained somewhat hidden, Fortune, as if admiring such rare virtues, chose to reveal through many adversities and harsh blows, in order to demonstrate that in the tender soul of a woman, and accompanied by singular beauty, there may also dwell prudence and a courageous spirit and all those virtues very rarely found even in the staunchest of men.

To continue, let me say that it was the custom for all the gentlemen of the house to go, immediately after supper, to the rooms of the Duchess; and there, along with pleasant recreations and enjoyments of various kinds, including constant music and dancing, sometimes intriguing questions were asked, and sometimes ingenious games played (now on the suggestion of one person and now of another) in which, using various ways of concealment, those present revealed their thoughts in allegories to this person or that. And occasionally, there would be discussions on various subjects, or there would be a sharp exchange of spontaneous witticisms; and often 'emblems', as we call them nowadays, were devised for the occasion. And everyone enjoyed these exchanges immensely, since, as I have said, the house was full of very noble and talented persons.

[ . . .]

The rule was that as soon as anyone came into the presence of the Duchess he would take his place in a circle, sitting down wherever he wished or wherever he happened to find himself; the group was arranged alternately one man and one woman, as long as there were women, for invariably they were outnumbered by the men. Then the company was governed according to the wishes of the Duchess, who usually left this task to signora Emilia. So the day after the Pope's departure, they all assembled in the customary place at the usual time, and after many pleasant discussions, the Duchess decided that signora Emilia should begin the games.

[ . . . ]

Everyone was waiting for signora Emilia when without saying a word to Bembo she turned to Federico Fregoso and indicated that he should say what game he would suggest; and he immediately began as follows:

'Madam, [ . . . ] To teach a lesson to the many fools who in their presumption and absurdity think they are entitled to be called good courtiers, I would like our game this evening to be this: that one of us should be chosen and given the task of depicting in words a perfect courtier, explaining the character and the particular qualities needed by anyone who deserves such a title. And, just as in philosophical disputations, if anything is said which does not seem appropriate, each of us may be allowed to contradict.'

Federico was continuing to speak, when signora Emilia interrupted him to say:'If the Duchess wishes, this will be our game for this evening.'

And the Duchess answered:'Yes, that is my wish.'

Then almost without exception all those who were present began to say among themselves and to the Duchess that this was the best game of all; and hardly waiting to hear each other talk, they all urged signora Emilia to decide who should make a start. So, turning to the Duchess, she said:

'Decide, madam, who it is you wish to undertake this task; for I don't want in choosing one rather than another to appear to be judging whom I think the most capable, and so give offence.'

The Duchess answered:'No, you must make the choice yourself; and take care lest by disobeying me you set a bad example to the others to do the same.'

Then, with a smile, signora Emilia said to Count Lodovico da Canossa:

'Well, then, so that we won't lose any more time, you will be the one to undertake the task as described by Federico. Not, let me say, that we believe you are such a fine courtier that you know what befits one, but because if you say everything contrariwise, as we hope you will, then the game will be still better since everyone will have a reason for challenging you, whereas if the task were given to someone knowing more than you do, no one could contradict anything he said, since it would be the truth, and so the game would prove very dull.'

The Count immediately retorted:

'But, madam, since you are present we need have no fear that the truth would go unchallenged.

[ . . . ]

'Let me start by saying that to recognize true perfection in anything is so difficult as to be scarcely possible; and this because of the way opinions vary. Thus there are many who like to hear someone talking a great deal and who will call him an agreeable companion. Some will prefer reticence; others an active and restless man; others one who always acts with calmness and deliberation; and so everyone praises or condemns according to his own opinion, always camouflaging a vice under the name of the corresponding virtue, or a virtue under the name of the corresponding vice. For example, a presumptuous man will be called frank, a modest man, dull; a simple-minded man, good; a rascal, shrewd; and so on and so forth. Still, I do think there is a perfection for everything, even though it may be concealed, and I also think that this perfection can be determined through informed and reasoned argument. And since, as I have said, the truth is often concealed and I do not claim to be informed, I can only praise courtiers of the kind I esteem myself and approve what seems to my limited judgement to be nearest to what is correct; and you can follow my judgement if it seems good, or keep to your own if it differs. Nor shall I argue that mine is better than yours, for not only can you think one thing and I another but I myself can think one thing at one time and something else another time.'

＊

The Count then continued:'so, for myself, I would have our courtier of noble birth and good family, since it matters far less to a common man if he fails to perform virtuously and well than to a nobleman. For if a gentleman strays from the path of his forbears, he dishonours his family name and not only fails to achieve anything but loses what has already been achieved. Noble birth is like a bright lamp that makes dear and visible both good deeds and bad, and inspires and incites to high performance as much as fear of dishonour or hope of praise; and since their deeds do not possess such noble brilliance, ordinary people lack both this stimulus and the fear of dishonour; nor do they believe that they are bound to surpass what was achieved by their forbears. Whereas to people of noble birth it seems reprehensible not to attain at least the standard set them by their ancestors. Thus as a general rule, both in arms and in other worthy activities, those who are most distinguished are of noble birth, because Nature has implanted in everything a hidden seed which has a certain way of influencing and passing on its own essential characteristics to all that grows from it, making it similar to itself. We see this not only in breeds of horses and other animals but also in trees, whose off shoots nearly always resemble the trunk; and if they sometimes degenerate, the fault lies with the man who tends them. So it happens with men, who, if they are well tended and properly brought up, nearly always resemble those from whom they spring, and are often even better; but if they have no one to give them proper attention, they grow wild and never reach maturity. It is true that, through the favour of the stars or of Nature, certain people come into the world endowed with such gifts that they seem not to have been born but to have been formed by some god with his own hands and blessed with every possible advantage of mind and body. Similarly, there are many to be found so uncouth and absurd that it can be believed simply that Nature was motivated by spite or mockery in bringing them into the world at all. Just as even with unceasing diligence and careful training the latter cannot usually be made to bear fruit, so with only the slightest effort the former reach the summit of excellence. And to give you an example, look at Don Ippolito d'Este, Cardinal of Ferrara, whose fortunate birth has influenced his person, his appearance, his words and all his actions. Because of this favour, despite his youth, even among the most venerable cardinals he carries such weighty authority that he seems more suited to teach than to be taught. Similarly, when conversing with men and women of every sort, when playing or laughing or joking, he has such charming ways and such a gracious manner that anyone who speaks to, or merely sets eyes on the Cardinal feels a lasting affection for him. However, to return to the subject, I say that between such supreme grace and such absurd folly can be found a middle way, and that those who are not perfectly endowed by Nature can, through care and effort, polish and to a great extent correct their natural defects. So in addition to noble birth, I would have the courtier favoured in this respect, too, and receive from Nature not only talent and beauty of countenance and person but also that certain air and grace that makes him immediately pleasing and attractive to all who meet him; and this grace should be an adornment informing and accompanying all his actions, so that he appears clearly worthy of the companionship and favour of the great.'

Then, refusing to wait any longer, signor Gaspare Pallavicino remarked:

'So that our game may proceed as it is meant to, and to show that we are not forgetting our privilege of contradicting, let me say that I do not believe that nobility of birth is necessary for the courtier. And if I thought I was saying something new to us, I would cite many people who, though of the most noble blood, have been wicked in the extreme, and, on the other hand, many of humble birth who, through their virtues, have won glory for their descendants. And if what you have just said is true, namely, that concealed in everything is the influence of its first seed, we should all be of the same character, since we all had the same beginning; nor would anyone be more noble than another. In fact, I hold that the various gradations of elevation and lowliness that exist among us have many other causes. The first and foremost is Fortune, who rules everything that happens in this world, and often appears to amuse herself by exalting whomever she pleases, regardless of merit, or hurling down those worthiest of being raised up. I fully concur with what you said about the happiness of those endowed at birth with all the perfections of mind and body; but this is seen among those of humble origins as well as those of noble birth, since Nature has no regard for these fine distinctions. On the contrary, as I have said, the finest gifts of Nature are often found in persons of very humble family. Therefore, since this nobility of birth is acquired neither through talent nor through force or skill, and is a matter for congratulating one's ancestors rather than oneself, it seems very odd to insist that, if the courtier's parents are of low birth, all his good qualities are spoilt and the other qualities you have mentioned are insufficient to bring him to the height of perfection: these being talent, good looks and disposition, and the grace which makes a person always pleasing at first sight.'

Count Lodovico answered:'I do not deny that the same virtues can exist in men of low birth as in those of noble family. However, not to repeat what we have said already, let me give one more reason among many for praising nobility of birth, which, since it stands to reason that good should beget good, everyone always respects; and it is that (since we are to create a courtier without any defects, and endowed with every kind of merit) he must be a nobleman if only because of the immediate impression this makes on all concerned. For given two gentlemen of the Court, neither of whom as yet has shown what he is like by his actions, either good or bad, as soon as it is discovered that one of them was well born and the other not, the latter will be respected far less than the former, and only after a great deal of time and effort will he win the good opinion that the other acquires instantly, merely because of his nobility. It is well understood how important these impressions are, for, speaking of ourselves, we have seen men coming to this house who, although very stupid and dull, have been regarded throughout Italy as very great courtiers; and even though they were eventually found out, they still fooled us for a long time and sustained in our minds the opinion of themselves already formed before they arrived, despite the fact that their behaviour was in keeping with their lack of merit. We have seen others, who were regarded with very little favour to begin with, eventually meet with great success. Now there are various reasons for these mistakes, including the obstinacy of princes who, in the hope of achieving a miraculous transformation, sometimes deliberately favour someone who they know does not deserve it. Then again, sometimes they are themselves deceived; but, since princes always have countless imitators, their favour confers considerable fame which in turn influences the rest of us. And if people discover something that seems to contradict the prevailing opinion, they accept that they are mistaken and they always wait for some revelation. This is because it seems that what is universally believed must be based on true and reasonable grounds. Moreover, we are always most anxious to take sides either passionately for or against, as can be seen in public combats or games or any kind of contest, where the onlookers often for no clear reason favour one or other of the participants, desperately anxious that he should win and his opponent lose. Then as regards men's characters, their good or bad reputation, as soon as we hear of it, arouses in us either love or hatred, so that for the most part we judge on the basis of one of these emotions. So you see how important are first impressions, and how hard a man must strive to give a good impression at the beginning if he is ambitious to win the rank and name of a good courtier.

'But to come to specific details, I judge that the first and true profession of the courtier must be that of arms; and this above everything else I wish him to pursue vigorously. Let him also stand out from the rest as enterprising, bold, and loyal to whomever he serves. And he will win a good reputation by demonstrating these qualities whenever and wherever possible, since failure to do so always incurs the gravest censure. Just as once a woman's reputation for purity has been sullied it can never be restored, so once the reputation of a gentleman-at-arms has been stained through cowardice or some other reproachful behaviour, even if only once, it always remains defiled in the eyes of the world and covered with ignominy. The more our courtier excels in this art, therefore, the more praise he will deserve, although I do not think he needs to have the professional knowledge of such things and the other qualities appropriate to a military commander. However, since the subject of what constitutes a great captain takes us into very deep waters, we shall be content, as we said, for the courtier to show complete loyalty and an undaunted spirit, and for these to be always in evidence. For men demonstrate their courage far more often in little things than in great. Very often in the face of appalling danger but where there are numerous witnesses one will find those who, though ready to drop dead with fear, driven on by shame or the presence of others, will press forward, with their eyes closed, and do their duty; and only God knows how. But in things of trifling importance, when they believe they can avoid danger without its being noticed, they are only too willing to play for safety. As for those who, even when they are sure they are not being observed or seen or recognized by anyone, are full of ardour and avoid doing anything, no matter how trivial, for which they would incur reproach, they possess the temper and quality we are looking for in our courtier. All the same, we do not wish the courtier to make a show of being so fierce that he is always blustering and bragging, declaring that he is married to his cuirass, and glowering with the haughty looks that we know only too well in Berto. To these may very fairly be said what a worthy lady once remarked jokingly, in polite company, to a certain man (I don't want just now to mention him by name) whom she had honoured by asking him to dance and who not only refused but would not listen to music or take part in the many other entertainments offered, protesting all the while that such frivolities were not his business. And when at length the lady asked what his business was, he answered with a scowl:"Fighting . . ."

' "Well then," the lady retorted, "I should think that since you aren't at war at the moment and you are not engaged in fighting, it would be a good thing if you were to have yourself well greased and stowed away in a cupboard with all your fighting equipment, so that you avoid getting rustier than you are already."'

'And of course everyone burst out laughing at the way she showed her contempt for his stupid presumption.

'Therefore,' Count Lodovico went on, 'the man we are seeking should be fierce, rough and always to the fore, in the presence of the enemy; but anywhere else he should be kind, modest, reticent and anxious above all to avoid ostentation or the kind of outrageous selfglorification by which a man always arouses loathing and disgust among those who have to listen to him.'

'As for me,' signor Gaspare replied, 'I have very seldom known men who are any good at anything who do not praise themselves. It seems to me that it is only right to allow them to do so, since, when a man who knows he is of some worth sees what he does being ignored, he grows angry at the way his qualities are hidden from sight and is forced to reveal them in some way lest he be cheated of the honour which is the rightful prize for virtuous endeavour. Thus, among the writers of the ancient world, rarely does anyone of any worth refrain from praising himself. Those who praise themselves even though they lack merit are certainly intolerable; but then we assume that our courtier will not be one of them.'

At this, the Count said:

'If you were listening, what I did was to censure those who praise themselves extravagantly and brashly. But I certainly agree that it would be wrong to take exception when a worthy man indulges in some modest self-praise; indeed it is then more convincing than if it comes from someone else. What I am saying is that a man who praises himself in the right way, and does not cause envy or annoyance in doing so, is well within the bounds of discretion; and he deserves the praise of others as well as what he allows himself, because he is achieving something very difficult.'

'You must teach us how to do it,' remarked signor Gaspare.

'Well,' the Count replied, 'there are those who taught this among the writers of the ancient world. However, in my opinion it all depends on saying things in such a way that they do not seem to be spoken with that end in view, but are so very much to the purpose that one cannot refrain from saying them; and also on giving the impression of avoiding self-praise, while indulging in it: but not in the style of those braggarts who open their mouths and let the words pour out heedlessly. As one of our own did the other day, who, after he had had his thigh run through by a spear at Pisa, said he thought a fly had stung him; and another who said he didn't keep a looking-glass in his room because when he lost his temper his expression was so terrible that if he saw it he would frighten himself to death.'

Everyone laughed at this, but Cesare Gonzaga added:

'What are you laughing at? Don't you know that after Alexander the Great had heard that in the opinion of a certain philosopher there were countless other worlds, he began to weep, and when asked why he did so, he replied: "Because I haven't yet conquered a single one" – as if he had it in him to conquer them all? Doesn't this seem to you to be more boastful than that remark about the fly?'

Then the Count remarked:

'And Alexander was a greater man than the one who mentioned the fly. But surely we must forgive outstanding men when they presume too much of themselves? After all, a man who has to achieve great things must have the courage to do them and must have confidence in himself. He should not be cowardly or abject, though he should be modest in his words, presuming less of himself than he achieves and being careful, too, that his presumption does not turn to rashness.'

After the Count had fallen silent for a moment, Bernardo Bibbiena said, with a smile:

'I remember your saying earlier that this courtier of ours should be naturally endowed with beauty of countenance and person and with an attractive grace. Well, I feel sure that I possess both grace and beauty of countenance, and that's why so many women, as you know, are madly in love with me. But when it comes to the beauty of my person, I am rather doubtful, and especially as regards these legs of mine which do not seem to me to be as good as I would wish; still, as to my chest and so on, I am quite satisfied. So please explain in more detail about what shape of body one should have, so that I can extricate myself from doubt and put my mind at rest.'

After everyone had laughed at this for a moment, the Count said:

'Certainly it's no lie to say that you possess the grace of countenance that I mentioned, and I have no need of any other example to illustrate it; for undoubtedly we can see that your appearance is very agreeable and pleasing to all, even if your features are not very delicate, though then again you manage to appear both manly and graceful. This is a quality found in many different kinds of faces. And I would like our courtier to have the same aspect. I don't want him to appear soft and feminine as so many try to do, when they not only cuff their hair and pluck their eyebrows but also preen themselves like the most wanton and dissolute creatures imaginable. Indeed, they appear so effeminate and languid in the way they walk, or stand, or do anything at all, that their limbs look as if they are about to fall apart; and they pronounce their words in such a drawling way that it seems as if they are about to expire on the spot. And the more they find themselves in the company of men of rank, the more they carry on like that. Since Nature has not in fact made them the ladies they want to seem and be, they should be treated not as honest women but as common whores and be driven out from all gentlemanly society, let alone the Courts of great lords.

'Then, as for the physical appearance of the courtier, I would say that all that is necessary is that he should be neither too small nor too big, since either of these two conditions causes a certain contemptuous wonder and men built in this way are stared at as if they were monsters. However, if one is forced to choose between the two evils, then it is better to be on the small side than unduly large; for men who are so huge are often found to be rather thick-headed, and moreover, they are also unsuited for sport and recreation, which I think most important for the courtier. So I wish our courtier to be well built, with finely proportioned members, and I would have him demonstrate strength and lightness and suppleness and be good at all the physical exercises befitting a warrior. Here, I believe, his first duty is to know how to handle expertly every kind of weapon, either on foot or mounted, to understand all their finer points, and to be especially well informed about all those weapons commonly used among gentlemen. For apart from their use in war, when perhaps the finer points may be neglected, often differences arise between one gentleman and another and lead to duels, and very often the weapons used are those that come immediately to hand. So, for safety's sake, it is important to know about them. And I am not one of those who assert that all skill is forgotten in a fight; because anyone who loses his skill at such a time shows that he has allowed his fear to rob him of his courage and his wits.

'I also believe that it is of the highest importance to know how to wrestle, since this often accompanies combat on foot. Next, both for his own sake and for his friends, the courtier should understand about seeking restitution and the conduct of disputes, and he should be skilled in seizing the advantage, and in all this he must show both courage and prudence. Nor should he be too anxious for these engagements, save when his honour demands it; for, as well as the considerable danger that an uncertain outcome brings with it, whoever rushes into these things precipitately and without urgent cause deserves to be gravely censured, even if he is successful. However, when a man has committed himself so far that he cannot withdraw without reproach then both in the preliminaries and in the duel itself he should be very deliberate. He should always show readiness and courage; and he should not behave like those who are always quibbling and arguing over points of honour, and when they have the choice of weapons, select those which can neither cut nor prick, arm themselves as if they had to face a cannonade, and thinking it enough if they are not defeated, retreat all the time and keep on the defensive, giving proof of utter cowardice, and in this way making themselves the sport of children, like those two men from Ancona who fought at Perugia a little while ago, and made everyone who saw them burst out laughing.'

'And who were they?' asked Gaspare Pallavicino.

'Two cousins,' answered Cesare.

'And in their fighting, more like two dear brothers,'said the Count. Then he continued:

'Weapons are also often used in various sports during peacetime, and gentlemen often perform in public spectacles before the people and before ladies and great lords. So I wish our courtier to be an accomplished and versatile horseman and, as well as having a knowledge of horses and all the matters to do with riding, he should put every effort and diligence into surpassing the rest just a little in everything, so that he may always be recognized as superior. And as we read of Alcibiades, that he surpassed all those peoples among whom he lived, and each time in regard to what they daimed to be best at, so this courtier of ours should outstrip all others, and in regard to the things they know well. Thus it is the peculiar excellence of the Italians to ride well with the rein, to handle spirited horses very skilfully, and to tilt and joust; so in all this the courtier should compare with the best of them. In tourneys, in holding his ground, in forcing his way forward, he should compare with the best of the French; in volleying, in running bulls, in casting spears and darts, he should be outstanding among the Spaniards. But, above all, he should accompany his every act with a certain grace and fine judgement if he wishes to earn that universal regard which everyone covets.

'There are also many other sports which, although they do not directly require the use of weapons, are closely related to arms and demand a great deal of manly exertion. Among these it seems to me that hunting is the most important, since in many ways it resembles warfare; moreover, it is the true pastime of great lords, it is a suitable pursuit for a courtier, and we know that it was very popular in the ancient world. It is also fitting that the courtier should know how to swim, jump, run and cast the stone for, apart from the usefulness of these accomplishments in war, one is often required to display one's skill and such sports can help to build up a good reputation, especially with the crowd which the courtier always has to humour. Another noble sport which is very suitable for the courtier to play is tennis, for this shows how well he is built physically, how quick and agile he is in every member, and whether he has all the qualities demonstrated in most other games. I think no less highly of performing on horseback, which is certainly very exhausting and difficult but more than anything else serves to make a man wonderfully agile and dextrous; and apart from its usefulness, if agility on horseback is accompanied by gracefulness, in my opinion it makes a finer spectade than any other sport. Then if our courtier possesses more than average skill in all these sports, I think he should ignore the others, such as turning cartwheels, tight-rope walking and that kind of thing, since these are more like acrobatics and hardly suitable for a gentleman. Then again, since one cannot always be taking part in such strenuous exercises (besides which constant repetition causes satiety and destroys the regard we have for rare things) one must always be sure to give variety to the way one lives by doing different things. So I would like the courtier sometimes to descend to calmer and more restful games, and to escape envy and enter pleasantly into the company of all the others by doing everything they do; although he should never fail to behave in a commendable manner and should rule all his actions with that good judgement which will not allow him to take part in any foolishness. Let him laugh, jest, banter, romp and dance, though in a fashion that always reflects good sense and discretion, and let him say and do everything with grace.'

Then Cesare Gonzaga said:'It is certainly too soon to interrupt this discussion, but if I stay silent I shall not be taking advantage of my privilege of speaking and I shall fail to learn something more. And I hope I may be forgiven if I ask a question instead of contradicting. I believe this may be allowed me, following the example set by our Bernardo who, through his excessive desire to be thought handsome, has already violated the laws of our game by doing the same.'

'You see,' the Duchess commented, 'how a single transgression leads to any number of others. So the one who sins and gives a bad example, as Bemardo has done, deserves to be punished not only for his wrongdoing but also for that of the others.'

Then Cesare remarked:'In that case, madam, I will be exempt from any penalty, since Bernardo is to be punished both for his own transgression and for mine.'

'On the contrary,' said the Duchess, 'you must both of you be punished twice: he for his own wrongdoing and for having persuaded you to err, and you for your own mistake and for having imitated the criminal.'

'Madam,' answered Cesare, 'I've done nothing crimi nal so far; so in order to let Bernardo have all the punishment to himself I'll keep quiet.'

He had already stopped talking when signora Emilia said with a laugh:

'Say whatever you please, because, if the Duchess allows, I shall forgive both the one who has transgressed and the one who is going to do something nearly as bad.'

Said the Duchess:'Very well, then. But take care you do not deceive yourself and perhaps think that you deserve more praise for being dement than for being just. For if one is too forgiving with a transgressor, one injures the innocent. However, I don't want my sternness in reproaching your indulgence to mean that we fail to hear what Cesare has to ask.'

So then, at a sign from the Duchess and from signora Emilia, he at once began:

'If I remember rightly, my dear Count, it seems to me that you have repeated several times this evening that the courtier has to imbue with grace his movements, his gestures, his way of doing things and in short, his every action. And it appears to me that you require this in everything as the seasoning without which all other attributes and good qualities would be almost worthless. Now I admit that everyone should easily be persuaded of this, seeing that, by the very meaning of the word, it can be said that a man who behaves with grace finds it with others. You have said that this is very often a natural, God-given gift, and that even if it is not quite perfect it can be greatly enhanced by application and effort. It seems to me that those who are born as fortunate and as rich in such treasures as some we know have little need of any further instruction, since the gracious favour they have received from heaven raises them, almost despite themselves, higher than they might have desired, and makes everyone both like and admire them. I do not argue about this, since it is not in our power to acquire it of ourselves. But regarding those who receive from Nature only so much as to make it possible for them to acquire grace through enterprise, application and effort, I should like to know by what art, teaching and method they can gain this grace, both in sport and recreation which you believe are so important, and in everything else they say or do. Now since by praising this quality so highly you have, I believe, aroused in all of us a strong desire to obtain it, because of the task given you by signora Emilia, you are also obliged to satisfy us by teaching the way to do so. '

'I am not obliged, ' said the Count, 'to teach you how to acquire grace, or indeed anything else, but only to show you what a perfect courtier should be. And I would not undertake the task of teaching you how to acquire this quality, especially as a little while ago I said that the courtier ought to know how to wrestle, and vault and so many other things which, never having learned them myself, I'm sure you know full well how I could teach them. Let it be enough that just as a good soldier knows how to tell the smith what style and shape and quality his armour should be, and yet cannot teach him how to hammer or temper it, so perhaps I shall know how to tell you what a perfect courtier should be, but not be able to teach you what you have to do to become one. However, although it is almost proverbial that grace cannot be learned, to satisfy your request as far as I can, I say that if anyone is to acquire grace as a sportsman or athlete (first assuming that he is not disqualified by Nature) he should start young and learn the principles from the best teachers. How important this seemed to King Philip of Macedon, for instance, can be seen from the fact that he wanted it to be Aristotle, the eminent philosopher, and perhaps the greatest ever, who should teach the elements of letters to his son Alexander. Then, coming to our own contemporaries, consider the physical grace and agility of Signor Galleazzo Sanseverino, Grand Equerry of France, who performs so well in this respect because in addition to his natural aptitude he has made every endeavour to learn from good teachers and to keep company with outstanding men, taking from each of them the best he can give. Thus just as for wrestling, vaulting and the handling of various kinds of weapons he has taken as his guide our Pietro Monte, who as you know is the sole and unchallenged master in regard to every kind of trained strength and agility, so for riding, jousting and so forth he has always taken as his models those who have won recognition for such skills.

'Therefore anyone who wants to be a good pupil must not only do things well but must also make a constant effort to imitate and, if possible, exactly reproduce his master. And when he feels he has made some progress it is very profitable for him to observe different kinds of courtiers and, ruled by the good judgement that must always be his guide, take various qualities now from one man and now from another. Just as in the summer fields the bees wing their way among the plants from one flower to the next, so the courtier must acquire this grace from those who appear to possess it and take from each one the quality that seems most commendable. And he should certainly not act like a friend of ours, whom you all know, who thought that he greatly resembled King Ferdinand the Younger of Aragon, but had not tried to imitate him except in the way he raised his head and twisted a corner of his mouth, a habit which the King had acquired through illness. There are many like this, who think they are marvellous if they can simply resemble a great man in some one thing; and often they seize on the only defect he has. However, having already thought a great deal about how this grace is acquired, and leaving aside those who are endowed with it by their stars, I have discovered a universal rule which seems to apply more than any other in all human actions or words: namely, to steer away from affectation at all costs, as if it were a rough and dangerous reef, and (to use perhaps a novel word for it) to practise in all things a certain nonchalance which conceals all artistry and makes whatever one says or does seem uncontrived and effortless. I am sure that grace springs especially from this, since everyone knows how difficult it is to accomplish some unusual feat perfectly, and so facility in such things excites the greatest wonder; whereas, in contrast, to labour at what one is doing and, as we say, to make bones over it, shows an extreme lack of grace and causes everything whatever its worth, to be discounted. So we can truthfully say that true art is what does not seem to be art; and the most important thing is to conceal it, because if it is revealed this discredits a man completely and ruins his reputation. I remember once having read of certain outstanding orators of the ancient world who, among the other things they did, tried hard to make everyone believe that they were ignorant of letters; and, dissembling their knowledge, they made their speeches appear to have been composed very simply and according to the promptings of Nature and truth rather than effort and artifice. For if the people had known of their skills, they would have been frightened of being deceived. So you see that to reveal intense application and skill robs everything of grace. Who is there among you who doesn't laugh when our Pierpaolo dances in that way of his, with those little jumps and with his legs stretched on tiptoe, keeping his head motionless, as if he were made of wood, and all so laboured that he seems to be counting every step? Who is so blind that he doesn't see in this the dumsiness of affectation? And in contrast we see in many of the men and women who are with us now, that graceful and nonchalant spontaneity (as it is often called) because of which they seem to be paying little, if any, attention to the way they speak or laugh or hold themselves, so that those who are watching them imagine that they couldn't and wouldn't ever know how to make a mistake.'

[ . . . ]

At this point, signora Emilia interrupted:'It seems to me that this argument of yours has grown too protracted and tedious. So it would be as well to postpone it to another time.'

Federico started to answer all the same, but signora Emilia refused to let him; and eventually the Count remarked:

'There are many who want to judge style and discuss the rhythms of language and the question of imitation, yet cannot explain to me what style and rhythm are, or how to define imitation, or why things taken from Homer or someone else read so well in Virgil that they seem improved rather than plagiarized. Perhaps the reason for this is that I am not capable of understanding them. But since it is a convincing proof of whether a man understands something that he has the ability to teach it, I fear that they understand it very little themselves, and that they praise both Virgil and Cicero because they are aware that many others praise them and not because they recognize the difference between them and the rest. For certainly the difference does not consist in their preserving a few words or so in a usage different from that of the others. In Sallust, in Caesar, in Varro and in other good writers we find several terms used differently from the way Cicero employs them; yet both ways are perfectly acceptable, since the strength and genius of a language does not consist in such trifles: as Demosthenes rightly said to Aeschines, who asked him sarcastically whether some of the words he had used, which were not Attic, were monsters or portents; and Demosthenes simply laughed at this and replied that the fortunes of Greece hardly depended on that. So what cause should I have to worry if some Tuscan or other reproved me for saying satisfatto rather than sodisfatto, onorevole rather than orrevole, causa rather than cagione, populo rather than popolo and so forth?'[＊]

At this Federico stood up and exclaimed:'Now I beg you, listen to me for a moment.'

But signora Emilia said with a laugh:'No, I shall be most displeased with any one of you who continues with this subject at the moment, for I wish the discussion to be postponed until another evening. But you, my dear Count, please continue with your discussion of the courtier, and show us what a good memory you have, because I think that if you can begin where you left off it will be quite a feat.'

'I fear,' answered the Count, 'that I have lost the thread. However, unless I am mistaken, we were saying that the taint of affectation always robs everything of grace and that the highest degree of grace is conferred by simplicity and nonchalance, in praise of which, and in condemnation of affectation, much more could be said. However, I want to add just one more thing and that is all. Now, every woman is extremely anxious to be beautiful or at least, failing that, to appear so. So when Nature has fallen short in some way, she endeavours to remedy the failure by artificial means. That is why we have women beautifying their faces so carefully and sometimes painfully, plucking their eyebrows and forehead, and using all those tricks and suffering all those little agonies which you ladies imagine men know nothing about but which they know only too well. '

Here, madonna Costanza Fregoso laughed and said:'It would be far more courteous of you to continue with your discussion and to say what is the source of grace and speak of courtiership, rather than seek to expose the faults of women to no purpose. '

'On the contrary, it is very much to the purpose,'answered the Count, 'because these faults of yours that I mention rob you of grace, seeing that they spring only from affectation, through which you make it clear to everyone that you are excessively anxious to be beautiful. Surely you realize how much more graceful a woman is who, if indeed she wishes to do so, paints herself so sparingly and so little that whoever looks at her is unsure whether she is made-up or not, in comparison with one whose face is so encrusted that she seems to be wearing a mask and who dare not laugh for fear of causing it to crack, and who changes colour only when she dresses in the morning, after which she stays stock-still all the rest of the day, like a wooden statue, letting herself be seen only by torchlight, in the way a wily merchant shows his cloth in a dark corner. How much more attractive than all the others is a pretty woman who is quite dearly wearing no make-up on her face, which is neither too pallid nor too red, and whose own colouring is natural and somewhat pale (but who occasionally blushes openly from embarrassment or for some other reason), who lets her unadorned hair fall casually and unarranged, and whose gestures are simple and natural, betraying no effort or anxiety to be beautiful. Such is the uncontrived simplicity which is most attractive to the eyes and minds of men, who are always afraid of being tricked by art. In a woman, lovely teeth are always very pleasing, for since they are hidden from view most of the time, unlike the rest of the face, it can be believed that less effort has been spent on making them look beautiful; and yet those who laugh to no purpose and merely to display their teeth, betray their artificiality, and however goodlooking they may be would seem to everyone most ungraceful, like Catullus' Egnatius. The same is true of the hands which, if they are delicate and fine, and are uncovered at the right time, when there is need to use and not just to display their beauty, leave one with a great desire to see more of them, especially after they have been covered again with gloves. For it appears that the person who covers them hardly cares or worries whether they are seen or not, and has beautiful hands more by Nature than through any effort or design. Surely, too, you have sometimes noticed when a woman, passing along the street on her way perhaps to church, happens, in play or for some other reason, to raise just enough of her skirts to reveal her foot and often a little of her leg as well. Does it not strike you as a truly graceful sight if she is seen just at that moment, delightfully feminine, showing her velvet ribbons and pretty stockings? Certainly I find it very agreeable, as I'm sure you all do, because everyone assumes that elegance in a place where it is generally hidden from view must be uncontrived and natural rather than carefully calculated, and that it cannot be intended to win admiration.

'In this way affectation is avoided or hidden; and now you can see how incompatible it is with gracefulness and how it robs of charm every movement of the body or of the soul, about which, admittedly, we have so far said very little. However, we should not neglect it; for, as the soul is far more worthy than the body, it deserves to be all the more cultivated and adorned. As for what our courtier ought to do in this respect, we shall leave aside the precepts of all the many wise philosophers who have written on the subject, defining the virtues of the soul and discussing their worth with such subtlety; instead, keeping to our purpose, we shall state very simply that it is enough if he is, as we say, a man of honour and integrity. For this includes prudence, goodness, fortitude and temperance of soul, and all the other qualities proper to so honourable a name. And I believe that he alone is a true moral philosopher who wishes to be good; and for this he needs few precepts other than the ambition itself. Therefore Socrates was perfectly right in affirming that in his opinion his teaching bore good fruit when it encouraged someone to strive to know and understand virtue; for those who have reached the stage where they desire nothing more eagerly than to be good have no trouble in learning all that is necessary. So I shall say no more about this.

However, in addition to goodness, I believe that for all of us the true and principal adornment of the mind is letters; although the French, I know, recognize only the nobility of arms and think nothing of all the rest; and so they not only do not appreciate learning but detest it, regarding men of letters as basely inferior and thinking it a great insult to call anyone a scholar. '

Then the Magnifico Giuliano remarked:

'You are right in saying that this error has prevailed among the French for a long time now; but if good fortune has it that Monseigneur d'Angoulême, as it is hoped, succeeds to the throne, then I believe that just as the glory of arms flourishes and shines in France, so also with the greatest brilliance must that of letters. For, when I was at that Court not so long ago, I set eyes on this prince, and it seemed to me that, besides his hand some looks, there was such an air of greatness about him, accompanied, however, by a certain gracious humanity, that the kingdom of France on its own must always seem too limited for him. And subsequently from many gentlemen, both French and Italian, I heard a great deal in praise of his noble courtesy, his magnanimity, his valour and his generous spirit; and among other things I was told that he greatly loved and esteemed learning and respected all men of letters, and that he condemned the French themselves for being so hostile to this profession, especially as they have in their midst as magnificent a university as Paris, where people flock from all over the world.'

Then the Count added:'It is a marvellous thing that at such a tender age, guided solely by his natural instincts and departing from the usual attitudes of his countrymen, he should of himself have chosen so commendable a path. And since subjects always imitate the behaviour of their rulers, it could well be, as you say, that the French may yet come to value learning at its true worth. They could easily be persuaded to if they would listen to reason, since nothing is more naturally desired by men or more proper to them than knowledge, and it is the height of folly to say or believe that it is not always a good thing.

'If I could speak with them or with others whose opinion does not agree with mine I would endeavour to show them how useful and necessary letters are to human dignity and life. For they were surely given by God as his supreme gift to mankind. And I should not lack examples from among those many great commanders of the ancient world, in all of whom prowess at arms was accompanied by the glory of learning. For, as you know, Alexander revered Homer so highly that he always kept the Iliad at his bedside. And he gave the greatest attention not only to these studies but also to philosophical speculations, under the guidance of Aristotle. Taught by Socrates, Alcibiades used letters to increase and enhance his good qualifies. The attention which Caesar gave to study is attested by his own inspired writings. It is said that Scipio Africanus constantly had by him the works of Xenophon, in which, under the name of Cyrus, is drawn the portrait of a perfect king. I could cite Lucullus, Sulla, Pompey, Brutus and many other Romans and Greeks; but I shall just remind you that so excellent a commander as Hannibal, though naturally fierce and a stranger to humanity, treacherous and contemptuous both of men and the gods, none the less was something of a scholar and understood the Greek language. And if I am not mistaken I once read that he even left a book written by himself in Greek. But there is no call to tell you this, since I well know that you all realize how wrong the French are in thinking that letters are detrimental to arms. You know that in war what really spurs men on to bold deeds is the desire for glory, whereas anyone who acts for gain or from any other motive not only fails to accomplish anything worth while but deserves to be called a miserable merchant rather than a gentleman. And it is true glory that is entrusted to the sacred treasury of letters, as everyone knows except those who are so unfortunate as not to have made their acquaintance. When he reads about the great deeds of Caesar, Alexander, Scipio, Hannibal and all the others, who is so cringing, timorous and abject that he does not burn with the ambition to emulate them and is not ready to relinquish his all too brief natural life in favour of an almost eternal fame, which makes him live on more splendidly after death? But those who do not appreciate the pleasures of learning cannot realize how great is the glory that they preserve for so long, and measure it only by the life of one or two men, since their own memories are limited. The kind of glory of which they have experience is nothing in comparison with the almost everlasting glory about which, unfortunately, they know nothing; and since, therefore, glory means so little to them, we may reasonably believe that, unlike those who understand its nature, they will run few risks in pursuing it. Now someone may object to what I am saying and attempt to disprove it by various examples: citing, for instance, the knowledge of letters shown by the Italians compared with their lack of valour on the battlefield during recent years. This is only too true; but surely it may be said that here the weakness of a few has inflicted grave misfortune along with lasting infamy on the many, and they are responsible for our ruin and the way our spirit has been weakened if not crushed. Yet it would be more shameful for us to make this known to the world than it is for the French to be ignorant of letters; so it is better to pass over in silence what we cannot recall without sorrow, and leaving this subject (which I took up unwillingly) to return to our courtier.

'I should like our courtier to be a more than average scholar, at least in those studies which we call the humanities; and he should have a knowledge of Greek as well as Latin, because of the many different things that are so beautifully written in that language. He should be very well acquainted with the poets, and no less with the orators and historians, and also skilled at writing both verse and prose, especially in our own language; for in addition to the satisfaction this will give him personally, it will enable him to provide constant entertainment for the ladies, who are usually very fond of such things. But if because of his other activities or through lack of study he fails to achieve a commendable standard in his writing, then he should take pains to suppress his work, to avoid ridicule, and he should show it only to a friend he can trust. And the exercise of writing will be profitable for him at least to the extent that it will teach him how to judge the work of others. For it is very unusual for someone who is not a practised writer, however erudite he may be, to understand completely the demanding work done by writers, or appreciate their stylistic accomplishments and triumphs and those subtle details characteristic of the writers of the ancient world. Moreover, these studies will make our courtier well informed and eloquent and(as Aristippus said to the tyrant) self-confident and assured no matter whom he is talking to. However, I should like our courtier to keep one precept firmly in mind: namely, that in what I have just discussed and in everything else he should always be diffident and reserved rather than forward, and he should be on his guard against assuming that he knows what he does not know. For we are instinctively all too greedy for praise, and there is no sound or song that comes sweeter to our ears; praise, like Sirens' voices, is the kind of music that causes shipwreck to the man who does not stop his ears to its deceptive harmony. Recognizing this danger, some of the philosophers of the ancient world wrote books giving advice on how a man can tell the difference between a true friend and a flatterer. Even so, we may well ask what use is this, seeing that there are so many who realize perfectly well that they are listening to flattery, and yet love the flatterer and detest the one who tells them the truth. Indeed, very often, deciding that the one who praises them is not being fulsome enough, they lend him a hand themselves and say such things that even the most outrageous flatterer feels ashamed. Let us leave these blind fools to their errors and decide that our courtier should possess such good judgement that he will not be told that black is white or presume anything of himself unless he is certain that it is true, and especially in regard to those flaws which, if you remember, when he was suggesting his game for the evening Cesare recalled we had often used to demonstrate the particular folly of this person or another. To make no mistake at all, the courtier should, on the contrary, when he knows the praises he receives are deserved, not assent to them too openly nor let them pass without some protest. Rather he should tend to disclaim them modestly, always giving the impression that arms are, as indeed they should be, his chief profession, and that all his other fine accomplishments serve merely as adornments; and this should especially be his attitude when he is in the company of soldiers, lest he behave like those who in the world of scholarship want to be taken for warriors and among warriors want to seem men of letters. In this way, as we have said, he will avoid affectation, and even his modest achievements will appear great.'

[ . . . ]

注释

＊ The Italian words cited by Count Lodovico mean: satisfied, honourable, cause and people.

The Second Book of the Courtier

'To continue the arguments of these gentlemen, which I wholly confirm and approve, I maintain that among the things we call good there are some that are always good simply in themselves, such as temperance, fortitude, health and all the virtues that foster peace of mind; and there are others that are good in various respects and depending on the end to which they are directed, such as laws, liberality, riches and so forth. I consider, therefore, that the perfect courtier, as Count Lodovico and Federico have described him, can indeed be good and praiseworthy, not, however, simply in himself but in regard to the end to which he is directed. For, to be sure, if the only fruit produced by the courtier's noble birth, gracefulness, charm and skills were just himself, I should not consider it right for a man to put into acquiring the perfection of courtiership all the study and effort that are certainly necessary. On the contrary, I should claim that many of the skills that have been attributed to him, such as dancing, entertaining, singing and playing games, were vain and frivolous, and in a man of rank deserving of censure rather than praise. For these elegances of dress, devices, mottoes and other such things that belong to the world of women and romance often, despite what many may think, serve simply to make men effeminate, to corrupt the young and to lead them into dissolute ways. And the consequences are that the name of Italy is brought into disgrace and there are few who have the courage I shall not say to die, but even to take a risk. And certainly there are countless other things which would be of far greater benefit in both peace and war, given the same amount of study and effort, than this kind of sterile courtiership. But if the activities of the courtier are directed as they should be to the virtuous end I have in mind, then I for one am quite convinced not only that they are neither harmful nor vain but that they are most advantageous and deserving of infinite praise.

'In my opinion, therefore, the end of the perfect courtier (which we have so far left untouched) is, by means of the accomplishments attributed to him by these gentle men, so to win for himself the mind and favour of the prince he serves that he can and always will tell him the truth about all he needs to know, without fear or risk of displeasing him. And, if he knows that his prince is of a mind to do something unworthy, he should be in a position to dare to oppose him, and make courteous use of the favour his good qualities have won to remove every evil intention and persuade him to return to the path of virtue. Thus if the courtier is endowed with the goodness these gentle-men have attributed to him, as well as being quick-witted and charming, prudent and scholarly and so forth, he will always have the skill to make his prince realize the honour and advantages that accrue to him and his family from justice, liberality, magnanimity, gentleness and all the other virtues befitting a ruler, and on the other hand, the infamy and loss that result from practising the vices opposed to these virtues. Therefore I consider that just as music, festivities, games and other agreeable accomplishments are, so to speak, the flower of courtiership, so its real fruit is to encourage and help his prince to be virtuous and to deter him from evil. Then we must consider that the merit of good deeds consists in two principal things: to choose a truly virtuous end for our intentions, and to know how to find convenient and suitable means for its attainment. And so it necessarily follows that a man who strives to ensure that his prince is not deceived by anyone, does not listen to flatterers or slanderers or liars, and distinguishes between good and evil, loving the one and detesting the other, aims at the best end of all.

'It seems to me also that the accomplishments these gentlemen have attributed to the courtier can be a good means of attaining the end I have in mind; and this is because of the many faults we see in our present-day rulers the greatest are ignorance and conceit. And the root of these two evils is nothing other than falsehood, which is a vice rightly detestable to God and man and more harmful to princes than any other. For princes lack most of all what they must have in the fullest measure, namely, someone to tell them the truth and remind them of what is right. For those who are hostile to the prince are not prompted by affection to perform these offices; on the contrary, they prefer to have him live wickedly and never correct his faults. And then again, they dare not criticize the prince openly for fear of being punished. Meanwhile, among the prince's friends there are few who have free access to him, and these few are wary of reproaching him for his faults as freely as they reproach ordinary people, and often in order to win grace and favour they think only of suggesting things that are agreeable and diverting, even though they may be dishonourable and wicked. In this way, from being friends they become flatterers, and to benefit from their intimacy they always speak and act in order to gratify, and they mostly proceed by telling lies that foster ignorance in the prince's mind not only of the world around but of himself. And this can be said to be the greatest and most disastrous falsehood of all, for an ignorant mind deceives itself and lies to itself.

'The result of this is that apart from never hearing the truth of anything, princes become drunk with the power they wield, and abandoned to pleasure-seeking and amusements they become so corrupted in mind that (seeing themselves always obeyed and almost adored, with so much reverence and praise and never a hint of censure or contradiction) they pass from ignorance to extreme conceit. In consequence, they never accept anyone else's advice or opinion; and, believing that it is very easy to know how to rule and that successful government requires no art or training other than brute force, they devote all their mind and attention to maintaining the power they have and they believe that true happiness consists in being able to do what one wants. Therefore there are some princes who hate reason and justice because they think these would act as a bridle to their desires, reduce them to servitude, and if followed, rob them of the pleasures and satisfactions of their rule; and they suppose that their power would be neither perfect nor complete if they were constrained to obey the call of duty and honour, since they believe that no one who obeys is a true ruler. Therefore following on these beginnings, and letting themselves be carried away by self-conceit, they grow arrogant, and with imperious countenance and stern ways, with sumptuous dress, gold and gems, and rarely letting themselves be seen in public, they think to gain authority among men and to be regarded as gods. But these princes, to my mind, are like the giant figures that were made in Rome last year on the day of the festival in Piazza d'Agone and which outwardly looked like great men and horses in a triumph but inside were stuffed with rags and straw. However, princes of this sort are worse still. For the giant figures were held upright by their own great weight, whereas, since they are badly balanced within and out of proportion in relation to their base, the downfall of these rulers is caused by their own weight, and from one error they fall into countless others. For their ignorance and their false belief that they can do no wrong, and that their power springs from their own wisdom, prompt them to use all and every means, just or not, to usurp states whenever they have the chance.

'But if they decided to know and follow, what they ought to do, then they would strive to rule in quite other ways than they do now; for they would realize how outrageous and pernicious it is when subjects, who must be governed, are wiser than the rulers who must govern them. You will agree that there is no harm in not knowing how to play music, or dance, or ride; nevertheless, a man who is not a musician is ashamed and does not dare to sing in the presence of others, or dance if he doesn't know how, or ride if he cannot sit his horse well. Yet ignorance of how to govern peoples gives rise to so many evils, so much death, destruction, burning and ruination, that it may be said to be the deadliest plague of all; and despite that some rulers who know absolutely nothing about government are not ashamed to set about the task of governing before the eyes not of a small group of men but rather of the entire world, seeing that they are so exalted in rank that all eyes are turned towards them and hence not only their great but even their slightest defects are always observed.

[ . . . ]

'I maintain, therefore, that since nowadays rulers are so corrupted by evil living, by ignorance and by false conceit, and it is so difficult to give them an insight into the truth and lead them to virtue, and since men seek to win their favour through lies and flattery and other wicked means, the courtier easily can and should seek to gain the goodwill of his prince by means of the noble qualities given to him by Count Lodovico and Federico. Through these, he should so win over the mind of his prince that he may go to him freely whenever he wishes to discuss any subject without hindrance. And, if he is as has been described, he will succeed in this purpose without great effort and thus he will always be able to reveal the true facts on any subject very promptly. Moreover, he will gradually be able to instil virtue into his mind, to teach him continence, fortitude, justice and temperance, and enable him to relish the sweet fruit which lies under the slight bitterness first tasted by one who is struggling against his vices, which are always as harmful, offensive and notorious as the virtues are beneficial, agreeable and universally praised. And he will be able to incite his prince to virtue by the example of those famous captains and other outstanding men of whom it was customary in the ancient world to make statues of bronze and marble, and sometimes of gold, and to erect them in public places, both to honour the great and to inspire others to work to achieve the same glory through worthy emulation.

'In this way, the courtier will be able to lead his prince along the stem path of virtue, adorning it, however, with shady fronds and strewing it with gay flowers to lessen the tedium of an arduous journey for one whose endurance is slight; and so now with music, now with arms and horses, at other times with verse or with conversations about love, and with all the means these gentlemen have suggested, he will be able to keep the prince continually absorbed in innocent pleasures, while also, as I have said, always accompanying these beguilements with emphasis on some virtuous habit, and in that way practising a healthy deception like a shrewd doctor who often spreads some sweet liquid on the rim of a cup when he wants a frail and sickly child to take a bitter medicine. Thus, under the cloak of pleasure, no matter what the time, or place, or pursuit, the courtier will always achieve his objective, and for this he will deserve far greater praise and reward than for any other good work he could possibly do. For there is nothing so advantageous to mankind as a good prince, and nothing so harmful as an evil one; and it follows that no matter how cruel and atrocious, no punishment can be enough for those courtiers who turn gentle and charming manners and noble qualities to evil ends, and by these means seek to ingratiate themselves with their prince in order to corrupt him and make him stray from the path of virtue into vice. For of these it can be said that they contaminate with deadly poison not a single cup used by one person but the public fountain at which everyone must drink.'

Signor Ottaviano fell silent, as if he were unwilling to add to what he had said. But then signor Gaspare remarked:

'It does not seem to me, signor Ottaviano, that this goodness of mind and the continence and other virtues in which you wish the courtier to instruct his lord can be learned; rather, I think that the men who possess them have been given them by Nature and by God. This must be so, since you will find that there is no one in the world so wicked and ill-disposed, or so intemperate and unjust, as to confess that he is such when he is asked; on the contrary, everyone, no matter how evil, likes to be thought just, continent and good; and this would not be the case if these virtues could be learned, for it is no disgrace not to know what one hasn't studied but certainly shameful to lack what Nature should have bestowed. Thus everyone tries hard to conceal his natural defects of mind or body, as we see in the case of the blind, the lame, the crippled and all those who are maimed or ugly. For although these defects can be imputed to Nature, yet no one likes to think he has them, since then it seems that Nature herself has caused them deliberately as a seal and token of wickedness. My opinion in this is also confirmed by the story told of Epimetheus, who knew so little how to distribute the gifts of Nature among men that he left them far less well endowed than all other creatures; and so Prometheus stole from Minerva and Vulcan the ingenuity and knowledge by which men gain their livelihood. But they still lacked knowledge of the civic virtues and the moral law, because this was guarded in Jove's fortress of Olympus by most alert guardians, by whom Prometheus was so greatly intimidated that he dared not go near them. So Jove, taking pity on the wretchedness of mankind (which because of its lack of civic virtue was defenceless against the attacks of wild beasts) sent Mercury down to earth bearing justice and self-respect to adorn their cities and unite the citizens. And he decided that these should not be distributed in the same way as the other gifts of mankind, where only one man among many needs to be skilled (as in the case of medicine) but should be instilled into every single person. And under the law he ordained all those who were unjust and shameless should be exterminated and put to death as public menaces. So you see then, signor Ottaviano, that these virtues are granted to men by God, and cannot be learned since they come from Nature.'

Then signor Ottaviano replied with a smile:

'So you would have it, signor Gaspare, that men are so unhappy and perverse in their judgement that they have applied themselves to discovering ways in which to tame the natures of wild beasts, bears, wolves and lions, and by the same skills can teach a pretty bird to fly where they choose it to go and return of its own will from the woods and its natural freedom to cages and captivity, and yet no matter how hard they apply themselves they cannot and will not discover ways by which to benefit themselves and improve their minds by diligence and study? In my opinion this would be as if our doctors were to study with all diligence to acquire solely the skill to heal sore nails and baby-rash and neglect treating fevers, pleurisy and other serious diseases; and as we all realize that would be quite preposterous. I consider, therefore, that the moral virtues do not come to us entirely from Nature, because nothing can ever grow accustomed to what is naturally its opposite, as we see in the case of a stone which, if it were thrown up in the air ten thousand times would still never grow accustomed to flying upwards of itself. So if the virtues were as natural to us as weight is to a stone, we would never become accustomed to vice. Nor are the vices natural to us in this way, for then we could never be virtuous; and it would be too wicked and foolish to punish men for defects that proceed from Nature through no fault of our own. This would be an error on the part of the laws, which do not inflict punishment on wrongdoers for what they have done in the past (for what is done cannot be undone) but have regard for the future, so that the one who has erred may err no more, nor cause others to do so through his bad example. So we see that the laws accept that the virtues can be learned, and this is certainly true; for we are born capable of acquiring virtues, and similarly vices, and therefore we become habituated to the one or the other through the behaviour we adopt, first of all practising the virtues or the vices, and then becoming virtuous or vicious. But the opposite is the case with qualities that are given us by Nature, which we first of all have the potentiality to practise, and then we actually practise, as in the case of the senses. For first we have the capacity to see and hear and touch and then we do see and hear and touch; although many of these faculties too are enhanced by education. For this reason, good masters not only teach children their letters but also polite manners and correct bearing in eating, drinking, speaking and walking.

Therefore, as with other arts and skills so also with the virtues, it is necessary to have a master who by his teaching and precepts stirs and awakens the moral virtues whose seed is enclosed and buried in our souls and who, like a good farmer, cultivates and dears the way for them by removing the thorns and tares of our appetites which often so darken and choke our minds as not to let them flower or produce those splendid fruits which alone we should wish to see born in the human heart. Thus in this way justice and self-respect, which you say Jove sent on earth to all men, are natural in each one of us. But just as however robust it is a man's body may fail when seeking to accomplish some task, so, although the potentiality for these virtues is rooted within our souls, it often fails to develop unless helped by education. For if it is to pass to actuality and to its full realization, it cannot, as I said, rely on Nature alone but needs the assistance of skilful practice and reason to purify and enlighten the soul by removing from it the dark veil of ignorance, which is the cause of most human errors, since if good and evil were easily recognized and understood everyone would always choose good and eschew evil. Thus virtue may be defined more or less as prudence and the knowledge of how to choose what is good, and vice as a kind of imprudence and ignorance, which leads us into making false judgements. This is because men never choose evil deliberately but are deceived by a certain semblance of good.'

Then signor Gaspare replied:'Yet there are many who fully understand that they are doing evil, and still do it; and this is because, like thieves and murderers, they are more conscious of the pleasures of the moment than of the punishment they fear in the future. '

Signor Ottaviano remarked:'True pleasure is always good, and true suffering always evil; therefore these men deceive themselves when they take false pleasures for true and true suffering for false. And so their false pleasures often earn them genuine pain. It follows that the art that teaches us to distinguish the true from the false can certainly be learned; and the virtue which enables us to choose what is genuinely good and not what wrongly appears to be so may be called true knowledge, which is more advantageous in life than any other kind, because it rids us of the ignorance which, as I said, is the cause of all the evils there are.'

At this, Pietro Bembo said:'I do not understand, signor Ottaviano, why signor Gaspare should have to concede that all evils spring from ignorance and that there are few who realize what they are doing when they sin and do not at all deceive themselves regarding true pleasure or suffering. It is certain that even men who are incontinent form their judgement reasonably and logically, and are fully aware of the evil and sinful nature of what they desire. So they use their reason to oppose and resist their desires, and this causes the battle of pleasure and pain against judgement. Then eventually the desires prove too strong for reason, which abandons the struggle, like a ship which for a time resists the storm but finally, battered by the overwhelming fury of the winds, with anchor and rigging smashed, lets herself be driven by the tempest, unresponsive either to helm or compass. So the incontinent commit their follies with a certain hesitant remorse, as if despite themselves. And this they would not do if they did not know that what they were doing was evil; on the contrary, without any resistance from reason they would abandon themselves utterly to their desires, and in this case would not be incontinent but simply intemperate. And this is far worse, since reason plays a part in incontinence, which is therefore a less serious vice; just as continence is an imperfect virtue, since it is influenced by the emotions. In consequence, it seems to me that one cannot ascribe the follies of the incontinent to ignorance or say that they are merely deceiving themselves without sinning, when they know full well what they are doing.'

'Well,' answered signor Ottaviano, 'your argument sounds very fine. Nevertheless, I don't think that it is really valid. For although the incontinent sin in that hesitant manner, and their reason does struggle with their desires, and they realize what evil is, yet they lack flail knowledge and do not understand evil as well as they need to. Possessing only a vague notion rather than any certain knowledge of evil, they allow their reason to be overcome by emotion. But if they enjoyed true knowledge there is no doubt that they would not fall into error. For reason is always overcome by desire because of ignorance, and true knowledge can never be defeated by the emotions, which originate in the body rather than the soul. And if the emotions are properly governed and controlled by reason, then they become virtuous, and if otherwise, then vicious. However, reason is so potent that it always makes the senses obey it, insinuating itself by marvellous ways and means, provided what it ought to possess is not seized by ignorance. In this manner, though a man's faculties, nerves and bones do not possess reason, when the mind begins to stir within us it is as if thought were shaking the bridle and spurring our faculties on, so that all the parts of the body prepare themselves: the feet to run, the hands to grasp or to do what the mind suggests. This is shown by what often happens when someone unknowingly eats food that tastes delicious but is really foul and disgusting; for when he finds out what it was, his mind is revolted and dismayed, and then the body responds so quickly to his judgement that he has to vomit.'

Signor Ottaviano was going on to say more, but he was then interrupted by the Magnifico Giuliano who remarked:

'If I have heard aright, you said that continence is not a perfect virtue because it is influenced by the emotions. Yet it seems to me that when there is conflict in our minds between reason and desire, the virtue which fights and gives the victory to reason ought to be considered more perfect than that which conquers when no lust or emotion opposes it. For in the latter case the person concerned does not refrain from evil out of virtue but because he has no wish to do it.'

Then signor Ottaviano said:'Who would you think the more admirable: a commander who runs the risk of open confrontation with the enemy, and yet conquers him, or one who uses his skill and knowledge to sap the enemy's strength and render him powerless and so conquers without risk or bloodshed?'

The Magnifico replied:'The one who conquers by less dangerous means is certainly the more praiseworthy, provided that his inevitable victory is not brought about by the enemy's ineptitude.'

'You have judged aright,' said signor Ottaviano. 'And so I tell you that continence can be compared to a commander who fights manfully and who, when the enemy is strong and powerful, conquers all the same, though not without great difficulty and risk. But unruffled temperance is like the commander who conquers and rules without opposition; and when it has not only subdued but totally extinguished the fires of lust in the mind which possesses it, like a good ruler in time of civil war, temperance destroys all seditious enemies within and hands over to reason the sceptre of absolute power. Thus this virtue does no violence to the soul, but gently infuses it with a powerful persuasion that turns it to honest ways, renders it calm and full of repose, in all things even and well-tempered, and informed in all respects with a certain harmony that adorns it with serene and unshakeable tranquillity; and so in all things it is ready to respond completely to reason and to follow wherever reason may lead with the utmost docility, like a young lamb that runs and walks alongside its mother, stops when she does, and moves only in response to her. This virtue of temperance, therefore, is wholly perfect and especially appropriate for men who rule, for it gives rise to many other virtues.'

Then Cesare Gonzaga remarked:'Well, I don't know what virtues appropriate for a ruler can spring from temperance, if temperance, as you say, removes all the emotions from one's mind. This might be fitting in a hermit or a monk; but I can hardly think that it is becoming for a prince, who is magnanimous, liberal and valiant in arms, whatever the provocation, never to display anger or hatred or indeed kindliness or scorn or lust or any emotion at all. For how could he otherwise exert any authority either over his people or his troops?'

Signor Ottaviano replied:'I did not say that temperance completely removes and uproots the emotions from a man's soul, nor would it be well for it to do so, since there are good elements even in the emotions. But what it does do is to make what is perverse and opposed to right conduct in the emotions responsive to reason. So it is not right, in order to remove conflicts, to extirpate the emotions altogether; for this would be like trying to suppress drunkenness by legislating against the use of wine, or forbidding anyone to run since when they do so men sometimes fall over. You are well aware that when someone is breaking in a horse he does not stop it from running or jumping but ensures that it does so at the right time and at the command of the rider. So when they are moderated by temperance the emotions are conducive to virtue, just as wrath strengthens fortitude, hatred against wicked men strengthens justice, and the other emotions strengthen other kinds of virtue. And if they were killed altogether, this would leave the reason weak and languid, so that it would be ineffectual, like the captain of a ship that is becalmed after the winds have dropped. So do not be so surprised, Cesare, if I said that temperance is the cause of many other virtues; for when a man's soul is attuned to this harmony, reason makes it readily receptive to true fortitude, which in turn makes it intrepid and unassailable, and immune to human suffering. And this is just as true of justice, the pure friend of modesty and goodness, and the queen of all the virtues, because justice teaches us to do what should be done and to eschew what is wrong. Thus justice is wholly perfect, since the other virtues perform their work through her, and she benefits both the just man and others as well. And without justice, as it is said, Jove himself could not govern his kingdom well. These virtues are also followed by magnanimity, which enhances them all, though it cannot exist alone since anyone lacking other virtues cannot be magnanimous. And then for their guide, the virtues have prudence, which consists in a certain quality of judgement in making the right decisions. The other links in this happy chain of virtues are liberality, munificence, the desire for honour, gentleness, charm, affability and many other qualities there is not the time to name. But flour courtier behaves as we have suggested he will discover these flourishing in the soul of his prince, and every day will see blossoming there more delightful flowers and fruits than there are in all the lovely gardens on earth. He himself will know great contentment, when he reminds himself that he gave his prince not what fools give, namely, gifts such as gold and silver, vases and garments (of which the prince has too many already and the giver only too few) but what is doubtless the greatest and rarest of all human virtues: the manner and method of good government. This alone would be enough to make men happy and restore to earth the golden age which is said to have existed once, when Saturn ruled.'

[ . . . ]

Then signor Gaspare said:'I remember that when these gentlemen were discussing the accomplishments of the courtier they wished him to be in love. However, when we sum up what has been said so far we could come to the conclusion that the courtier who must introduce the prince to virtue through his own merits and authority must of necessity be an elderly man, for only rarely does wisdom not wait upon age, and especially as regards what we learn from experience. So I do not see how if he is advanced in years it is fitting for the courtier to be in love, seeing that, as has already been said this evening, in old men love is futile and what women take for agreeable courtesies, pleasantries and elegance in the young are in the old inept and ridiculous follies which will cause some women to detest and everyone to deride whoever indulges in them. So if this Aristotle of yours, as an elderly courtier, were to be in love and to do the things that young lovers do(like some we have seen in our own times) I fear he would forget to instruct his prince and doubtless the children would make fun of him behind his back and the ladies would hardly derive any pleasure from him other than to mock him.'

Then signor Ottaviano answered:'As all the other qualities attributed to the courtier are suitable to him, even when he is old, I don't think it right to deprive him of the happiness of being in love.'

'On the contrary,' retorted signor Gaspare, 'to deprive him of it adds another perfection to him and enables him to live happily, free of all calamity and misery.'

Then Pietro Bembo added:'Do you not remember, signor Gaspare, that although he is untutored in love in the game he suggested the other evening signor Ottaviano evidently knew that there are some lovers who regard as pleasurable all the storms of indignation, the outbursts of temper, the wars and the torments that they experience with their ladies? And he asked to be taught the cause of this pleasure. Therefore if our courtier were to be inflamed with the kind of love that is agreeable and without bitterness, even if elderly he would not experience any misery or suffering. And then again as a wise man, which we suppose him to be, he would not deceive himself in thinking that everything suitable for a young man to do was likewise suitable in his case. If in love, he would doubtless love in a way that would not only bring him no blame but earn him great praise and complete happiness, free of all vexation, which rarely if ever happens with younger men. And so he would not neglect to instruct his prince nor would he do anything to cause children to make fun of him.'

Then the Duchess remarked:'I am glad, Pietro, that you have had to make little effort in our discussion this evening, because now we can have all the more confidence in giving you the task of speaking, and of teaching us about this kind of love which is so felicitous that it brings with it neither blame nor displeasure; for doubtless it would be one of the most useful and important of the endowments yet attributed to the courtier. So please, I beg you, tell us all you know about it.'

Pietro smiled and replied:'Madam, I wouldn't wish my having said that it is permissible for old men to love to cause these ladies to suppose that I am old myself. So please give this task to someone else.'

The Duchess replied:'You should not run away from being reputed old in wisdom, even if you are young in years. So please go on, and don't make any more excuses.'

Then Pietro Bembo answered:'truly, madam, if I do have to talk on this subject I shall have to go for advice to my Lavinello's friend, the hermit. '

At this, as if annoyed, signora Emilia exclaimed:

'Pietro, no one among us is more disobedient than you. So it would be only right if the Duchess were to punish you.'

Pietro, who was still smiling, answered:

'Don't be annoyed with me, madam, for pity's sake. For I shall tell you what you want.'

'Then please do so,' replied signora Emilia.

Thereupon, Pietro Bembo remained quiet for a little while. Then, having composed himself for a moment as if to speak of important things, he began as follows:

'Gentlemen, to show that old men can love not only blamelessly but sometimes more happily than the young, it will be necessary for me to enter upon a little discourse in order to make it clear what love is and what is the nature of the happiness that lovers experience. So I beg you to listen attentively, because I hope to make you realize that there is no man to whom it is unbecoming to be in love, even though he should be fifteen or twenty years older than signor Morello.'

After there was some laughter at this, Pietro Bembo continued:

'I say, therefore, that as defined by the philosophers of the ancient world Love is simply a certain longing to possess beauty; and since this longing can only be for things that are known already, knowledge must always of necessity precede desire, which by its nature wishes for what is good, but of itself is blind and so cannot perceive what is good. So Nature has ruled that every appetitive faculty, or desire, be accompanied by a cognitive faculty or power of understanding. Now in the human soul there are three faculties by which we understand or perceive things: namely, the senses, rational thought and intellect. Thus the senses desire things through sensual appetite or the kind of appetite which we share with the animals; reason desires things through rational choice, which is, strictly speaking, proper to man; and intellect, which links man to the angels, desires things through pure will. It follows that the sensual appetite desires only those things that are perceptible by the senses, whereas man's will finds its satisfaction in the contemplation of spiritual things that can be apprehended by intellect. And then man, who is rational by his very nature and is placed between the two extremes of brute matter and pure spirit, can choose to follow the senses or to aspire to the intellect, and so can direct his appetites or desires now in the one direction, now in the other. In either of these two ways, therefore, he can long for beauty, which is the quality possessed by all natural or artificial things that are composed in the good proportion and due measure that befit their nature.

'However, I shall speak of the kind of beauty I now have in mind, which is that seen in the human body and especially the face and which prompts the ardent desire we call love; and we shall argue that this beauty is an influx of the divine goodness which, like the light of the sun, is shed over all created things but especially displays itself in all its beauty when it discovers and informs a countenance which is well proportioned and composed of a certain joyous harmony of various colours enhanced by light and shadow and by symmetry and dear definition. This goodness adorns and illumines with wonderful splendour and grace the object in which it shines, like a sunbeam striking a lovely vase of polished gold set with precious gems. And thus it attracts to itself the gaze of others, and entering through their eyes it impresses itself upon the human soul, which it stirs and delights with its charm, inflaming it with passion and desire. Thus the mind is seized by desire for the beauty which it recognizes as good, and, if it allows itself to be guided by what its senses tell it, it falls into the gravest errors and judges that the body is the chief cause of the beauty which it enshrines, and so to enjoy that beauty it must necessarily achieve with it as intimate a union as possible. But this is untrue; and anyone who thinks to enjoy that beauty by possessing the body is deceiving himself and is moved not by true knowledge, arrived at by rational choice, but by a false opinion derived from the desire of the senses. So the pleasure that follows is also necessarily false and deceptive. Consequently, all those lovers who satisfy their impure desires with the women they love meet with one of two evils: either as soon as they achieve the end they desire they experience satiety and distaste and even begin to hate what they love, as if their desire repented of its error and recognized the way it had been deceived by the false judgement of the senses, which had made it believe that evil was good; or else they are still troubled by the same avidity and desire, since they have not in fact attained the end they were seeking. Admittedly, confused by their short-sighted view of things, they imagine that they are experiencing pleasure, just as sometimes a sick man dreams that he is drinking from a dear fountain. Nevertheless, they enjoy neither rest nor satisfaction, and these are precisely what they would enjoy as the natural consequences of desiring and then possessing what is good. On the contrary, deceived by the resemblance they see, they soon experience unbridled desire once more and in the same agitation as before they again find themselves with a raging and unquenchable thirst for what they hope to possess utterly. Lovers of this kind, therefore, are always most unhappy; for either they never attain their desires, and this causes them great misery, or if they do attain them they find themselves in terrible distress, and their wretchedness is even greater. For both at the beginning and during the course of this love of theirs they never know other than anguish, torment, sorrow, exertion and distress; and so lovers, it is supposed, must always be characterized by paleness and dejection, continuous sighings and weepings, mournfulness and lamentations, silences and the desire for death.

'We see, therefore, that the senses are the chief cause of this desolation of the spirit; and they are at their full strength in youth, when they are stimulated by the urges of the flesh which sap a man's powers of reason in exact proportion to their own vigour and so easily persuade the soul to yield to desire. For since it is sunk in an earthly prison and deprived of spiritual contemplation, the soul cannot of itself dearly perceive the truth when it is carrying out its duties of governing the body. So in order to understand things properly it must appeal to the senses for its first notions. In consequence it believes whatever they tell it and respects and trusts them, especially when they are so vigorous that they almost compel it; and because the senses are deceptive they fill the soul with errors and mistaken ideas. As a result, young men are invariably absorbed by this sensual kind of love and wholly rebellious against reason, and so they make themselves unworthy of enjoying the blessings and advantages that love gives to its true devotees; and the only pleasures they experience in love are the same as those enjoyed by unreasoning animals, though the distress they suffer is far more terrible than theirs. Therefore on this premise, which I insist is the absolute truth, I argue that lovers who are more mature in age experience the contrary; for in their case the soul is no longer so weighed down by the body and their natural ardour has begun to cool, and so if they are inflamed by beauty and their desire for it is guided by rational choice, they are not deceived and they possess completely the beauty they love. Consequently its possession brings them nothing but good, since beauty is goodness and so the true love of beauty is good and holy and always benefits those in whose souls the bridle of reason restrains the iniquity of the senses; and this is something the old can do far more easily than the young.

*

'So it is not unreasonable to argue also that the old can love blamelessly and more happily than the young, accepting that by old we do not mean those who are senile or whose bodily organs have grown so feeble that the soul cannot perform its operations through them, but men whose intellectual powers are still in their prime. I must also add this: namely, that in my opinion although sensual love is bad at every age, yet in the young it may be excused and perhaps in some sense even permitted. For although it brings them afflictions, dangers, exertions and all the unhappiness we have mentioned, yet there are many who perform worthy acts in order to win the favour of the women whom they love, and though these acts are not directed to a good end they are good in themselves. And so from all that bitterness they extract a little sweetness, and the adversities they endure finally teach them the error of their ways. So just as I think those young people who subdue their desires and love in a rational manner are truly heroic, I excuse those who allow themselves to be overcome by the sensual love to which human weakness inclines them, provided that they then display gentleness, courtesy, worthiness and all the other qualities these gentlemen mentioned, and that when they are no longer young they abandon it completely and leave sensual desire behind them, as the lowest rung of the ladder by which we can ascend to true love. But no blame is too severe for those who when they are old still allow the fires of passion to burn in their cold hearts and make strong reason obey their feeble senses; for they deserve the endless shame of being numbered like idiots among the animals which lack reason, because the thoughts and ways of sensual love are wholly unbecoming to men of mature years.'

Bembo then paused for a moment, as if to rest; and as everyone remained silent, signor Morello da Ortona said:

'But if there were to be found an old man more able-bodied, more vigorous and more handsome than many youths, why would you not wish that he should be allowed to love in their way?'

The Duchess laughed at this and remarked:

'If love is such an unhappy experience for the young, why, signor Morello, do you want old men as well to suffer the same unhappiness? But if you were old, as these gentlemen say, you would not plot such evil against old men.'

Signor Morello replied:'It seems to me that the one who is plotting evil against old men is Pietro Bembo, because he wishes them to love in a way that I, for one, cannot understand. And I also think that to possess the beauty he praises so much without the body is a fantasy.'

'Do you believe, signor Morello,' asked Count Lodo vico, 'that beauty is always as good as Pietro Bembo says?'

'I certainly do not,' answered signor Morello. 'On the contrary, I remember having seen many beautiful women who were evil, cruel and spiteful; and this seems to me to be nearly always the case, since beauty makes them proud, and pride makes them cruel.'

Count Lodovico replied with a smile:'Doubtless they seem cruel to you because they do not grant you what you want. But let Pietro Bembo teach you how old men ought to desire beauty, and what they should seek from women, and with what they ought to be satisfied; and provided you keep within these limits you will discover that they are neither proud nor cruel, and they will also grant you what you want.'

Signor Morello showed his irritation at this, and he retorted:

'I don't want to learn what doesn't concern me. Let someone teach you the way in which this beauty ought to be desired by young men who are not so ablebodied or vigorous as the old.'

Then Federico, in order to calm signor Morello and to change the subject, interrupted before Count Lodovico could reply and said:

'Perhaps signor Morello is not altogether wrong in saying that beauty is not always good, for often woman's beauty causes the world endless evil, enmity, war, death and destruction, as was shown very clearly, for example, by the downfall of Troy. And for the most part beautiful women are either proud and cruel or else, as has been said, unchaste; though this last signor Morello would not consider a fault. There are also many wicked men who are endowed with good looks, and it seems that Nature has made them so in order that they may be better able to deceive, and that their agreeable appearance is the bait concealing the hook.'

Then Pietro Bembo stated:'Do not believe that beauty is not always good.'

Here, in order to return to the original subject, Count Lodovico broke in and remarked:

'Since signor Morello is not interested in learning what concerns him so deeply, teach it to me, and show me how old men may win the happiness of love; for I shall not worry if I cause myself to be considered old, provided I profit by it.'

Pietro Bembo said with a smile:'First I wish to correct the error made by these gentlemen, and then I shall satisfy you as well.'

Then he continued as follows:

'Gentlemen, beauty is a sacred thing, and I should not wish any of us to act like profane and sacrilegious men in speaking ill of it and thereby incurring the wrath of God. So as a warning for signor Morello and Federico, lest they are punished in the way most suitable for those who despise beauty, and lose their sight like Stesichorus, I say that beauty springs from God and is like a circle, the centre of which is goodness. And so just as one cannot have a circle without a centre, so one cannot have beauty without goodness. In consequence, only rarely does an evil soul dwell in a beautiful body, and so outward beauty is a true sign of inner goodness. This loveliness, indeed, is impressed upon the body in varying degrees as a token by which the soul can be recognized for what it is, just as with trees the beauty of the blossom testifies to the goodness of the fruit. The same is true of the human body, as we know from the way physiognomists often establish a man's character and sometimes even his thoughts from his countenance. Moreover, even in animals the qualities of the soul as far as possible impress themselves upon the body and can be perceived from their physical appearance. Consider how clearly we can perceive anger, ferocity and pride in the face of the lion, the horse and the eagle; and a pure and simple innocence in lambs and doves; evil guile in foxes and wolves, and so with nearly all the animals.

'Therefore for the most part the ugly are also evil, and the beautiful good. And it can be said that beauty is the pleasant, gay, charming and desirable face of the good, and that ugliness is the dark, disagreeable, unpleasant and sorry face of evil. And no matter what things you study, you will always find that those which are good and useful are also graced with beauty. Consider the structure of this great fabric of the universe, which was created by God for the health and preservation of all His creatures. The bowl of heaven, adorned with so many celestial lamps, and the earth in the centre, surrounded by the elements and sustained by its own weight; the sun, illuminating all things as it revolves, in winter approaching the lowest sign, and then by degrees ascending to the other side; the moon, which derives its light from the sun, in accord with whether the sun is approaching or drawing away; and the five other stars which separately travel the same course: these all influence each other so profoundly through the coherence of the natural order that if they changed in the slightest they could no longer exist together and the universe would crumble. Moreover, they have such beauty and loveliness that the human mind cannot conceive anything more graceful. Consider next the structure of man, who may be called a little universe in himself. We see that every part of his body is in the natural order of things made by design and not by chance and that his form as a whole is so beautiful that it is difficult to decide whether it is utility or grace that is given more to the human face and body by its various parts, such as the eyes, nose, mouth, ears, aims and breast. The same can be said of all the animals. Consider the feathers of birds and the leaves and branches of trees, which are given by Nature to preserve their being, and yet which are also of the greatest loveliness. Now let us leave Nature and come to human art. What is so necessary for a ship as the prow, the sides, the mainyards, the mast, the sails, the helm, the oars, the anchor and the rigging? Yet all these things are so attractive that anyone looking at them must conclude they exist as much for pleasure as for use. Columns and architraves support lofty galleries and palaces, but they are no less pleasing to the eye than they are useful to the building. When men first began to build they included the middle ridge in their churches and houses not to embellish their buildings but to allow the water to flow off without trouble on either side; nevertheless, attractiveness of appearance soon became as important as usefulness, so that if a church were to be built in a land which never knew rain or hail, it would seem to lack both dignity and beauty if left without the ridge of a roof.

'Thus to call anything beautiful, even the world itself, constitutes the highest praise. It is praised when we say such things as: beautiful sky, beautiful earth, beautiful sea, beautiful rivers, beautiful countryside, beautiful woods, trees and gardens; or beautiful cities, churches, houses and armies. In short, this gracious and sacred beauty is the supreme adornment of everything; and it can be said that in some manner the good and the beautiful are identical, especially in the human body. And the proximate cause of physical beauty is, in my opinion, the beauty of the soul which since it shares in true supernatural beauty makes whatever it touches resplendent and lovely, especially if the body it inhabits is not of such base material that the soul cannot impress on it its own quality. Therefore beauty is the true trophy of the soul's victory, when with her heavenly power she rules over material nature and with her light dispels the darkness of the body. We must not say, therefore, that beauty makes women proud or cruel, though this may seem to be the case to signor Morello; neither should we impute to beautiful women those enmities, deaths and destructions which are caused by the unrestrained desires of men. To be sure, I shall not deny that we can also find in the world beautiful women who are unchaste. But it is all the same not their beauty which makes them so; on the contrary, because of the bond between beauty and goodness, their beauty turns them away from impurity and leads them to the path of virtuous conduct. But sometimes evil training, the continual urgings of their lovers, gifts, poverty, hope, deceits, fear and a thousand other causes can defeat the steadfastness even of good and beautiful women; and for this and other reasons handsome men can also become wicked.'

Then Cesare remarked:'If what signor Gaspare alleged yesterday is true, then there is no doubt that women who are beautiful are more chaste than those who are ugly. '

'And what did I allege?' asked signor Gaspare.

'If I remember correctly,' replied Cesare, 'you said that women who are wooed always refuse to satisfy their suitor, and that those who are not, do the wooing themselves. And it is certain that the beautiful are always more wooed and pursued in love than the ugly; therefore the beautiful always refuse, and so they are more chaste than those ugly women who, as they have no suitors, do the wooing themselves.'

Bembo smiled and said:'there can be no answer to this argument.'

Then he added:'It also often happens that, like the other senses, our sight can be deceived and can judge to be beautiful a face that is not so at all. For example some women occasionally display in their eyes and looks a certain enticing and suggestive immodesty which is called beauty by many who find these traits pleasing because they promise them the chance of gaining what they desire. But in truth this is simply meretricious impudence, and unworthy of so honoured and sacred a name.'

Pietro Bembo then fell silent, but he was urged to say more about this kind of love and about the true way in which beauty should be enjoyed; and at length he said:

'I think I have shown clearly enough that old men can be happier in love than the young; and this was my premise. So it is not for me to add any more.'

Count Lodovico replied:'You have demonstrated the unhappiness of the young better than the happiness of the old, whom you have not yet taught what path to follow in love but merely instructed to let themselves be guided by reason. And many people consider that it is impossible to reconcile love with reason.'

Bembo was still determined to say no more, but the Duchess begged that he should do so, and therefore he continued:

'It would be too unfortunate for humanity if our soul, in which such ardent desire can so easily arise, were forced to find nourishment only in what it has in common with the animals and could not direct its desire to its nobler element. So, as this is your wish, I will not refuse to discuss this noble theme. And since I know that I am unworthy to speak of Love's sacred mysteries, I pray him so to inspire my thoughts and words that I can teach this excellent courtier of ours how to love in a manner beyond the capacity of the vulgar crowd. And because I have since boyhood dedicated my life to him, may my words now conform to this intention and redound to his credit. I maintain, then, that since in youth human nature is so inclined to the senses, while the courtier is young he may be allowed to love in a sensual manner; but if in more mature years he should be inflamed with this amorous desire, he must proceed with circumspection and take care not to deceive himself or let himself experience the distress which in young men deserves compassion rather than blame but in old men blame rather than compassion.

'Therefore when he sets eyes on some beautiful and attractive woman, with charming ways and gentle manner, and being skilled in love recognizes that his spirit responds to hers, as soon as he notices that his eyes fasten on her image and carry it to his heart and his soul begins to take pleasure in contemplating her and feels an influx that gradually arouses and warms it, and those vivacious spirits shining from her eyes constantly add fresh fuel to the fire, then he should at the very beginning procure a swift remedy and alert his reason in order to defend with its help the fortress of his heart, and so close the passes to the senses and to desire that they cannot enter either by force or deception. If the flame is extinguished, so is the danger. But if it perseveres or grows, then in the knowledge that he has been captured the courtier should determine to eschew all the ugliness of vulgar passion and guided by reason set forth on the path of divine love. Then first he must reflect that the body in which beauty shines is not the source from which it springs, and on the contrary that beauty, being incorporeal and, as we have said, a ray of the supernatural, loses much of its nobility when fused with base and corruptible matter: for the more perfect it is, the less matter it contains, and it is most perfect when completely separated from matter. He must also reflect that just as a man cannot hear with his palate or smell with his ears, beauty can in no way be enjoyed nor can the desire it arouses in our souls be satisfied through the sense of touch but solely through what has beauty for its true object, namely, the faculty of sight. So he should ignore the blind judgement of these senses and enjoy with his eyes the radiance, the grace, the loving ardour, the smiles, the mannerisms and all the other agreeable adornments of the woman he loves. Similarly, let him use his hearing to enjoy the sweetness of her voice, the modulation of her words and, if she is a musician, the music she plays. In this way, through the channels of these two faculties, which have little to do with corporeal things and are servants of reason, he will nourish his soul on the most delightful food and will not allow desire for the body to arouse in him any appetite that is at all impure. Next, with the greatest reverence the lover should honour, please and obey his lady, cherish her even more than himself, put her convenience and pleasure before his own, and love the beauty of her soul no less than that of her body. He should, therefore, be at pains to keep her from going astray and by his wise precepts and admonishments always seek to make her modest, temperate and truly chaste; and he must ensure that her thoughts are always pure and unsullied by any trace of evil. And thus, by sowing virtue in the garden of her lovely soul, he will gather the fruits of faultless behaviour and experience exquisite pleasure from their taste. And this will be the true engendering and expression of beauty in beauty, which some say is the purpose of love. In this manner, our courtier will be most pleasing to his lady, and she will always be submissive, charming and affable and as anxious to please him as she is to be loved by him; and the desires of both will be very pure and harmonious, and consequently they will be perfectly happy.'

Then signor Morello remarked:'In reality, this engendering of beauty in beauty must mean the begetting of a beautiful child in a beautiful woman; and it would seem to me a far clearer sign that she loved her lover if she pleased him in this than if she treated him merely with the affability you mention.'

Bembo laughed and replied:'You mustn't go beyond the bounds, signor Morello; nor indeed does a woman grant just a token of affection when she gives her lover her beauty, which is precious to her, and along the paths into her soul, namely, sight and hearing, sends the glances of her eyes, the image of her face, her voice and her words, which penetrate her lover's heart and convey the proof of her love.'

Signor Morello then said:'Glances and words can be false witnesses, and often are. So anyone who has no better pledge of love is in my opinion most uncertain; and truly I was expecting you to make this lady of yours a little more courteous and generous towards the courtier than the Magnifico made his. However, I think both of you are acting in the same way as those judges who pronounce sentence against their own people in order to seem wise.'

'I am perfectly willing,' Bembo continued, 'for this lady to be far more courteous to my elderly courtier than signor Magnifico's lady is to the young courtier. And this is with good reason, for my courtier will wish only for seemly things, all of which she may therefore concede to him quite innocently. But the Magnifico's lady, who is not so certain of the young courtier's modesty, should concede him only what is seemly and deny him what is not. Therefore my courtier, who obtains all he asks for, is happier than the other, who is granted some of his requests but refused others. And to help you understand even better that rational love is happier than sensual love, I say that sometimes the same things should be denied in sensual love and granted in rational love, because in the former context they are unseemly, and in the latter, seemly. Thus to please her gracious lover, besides granting him pleasant smiles, intimate and secret conversations, and the liberty to joke and jest and touch hands, the lady may very reasonably and innocently go so far as to grant a kiss, which in sensual love, according to the Magnifico's rules, is not permitted. For as a kiss is a union of body and soul, there is a risk that the sensual lover may incline more to the body than the soul; but the rational lover knows that although the mouth is part of the body nevertheless it provides a channel for words, which are the interpreters of the soul, and for the human breath or spirit. Consequently, the rational lover delights when he joins his mouth to that of the lady he loves in a kiss, not in order to arouse in himself any unseemly desire but because he feels that this bond opens the way for their souls which, attracted by their mutual desire, each pour themselves into the other's body in turn and so mingle that each of them possesses two souls, and it is as if a single spirit composed of the two governs their two bodies. So the kiss may be called a spiritual rather than physical union because it exerts such power over the soul that it draws it to itself and separates it from the body. For this reason, all chaste lovers desire a kiss as a union of souls; and thus when inspired to love Plato said that in kissing the soul comes to the lips in order to leave the body. And because the separation of the soul from things that are perceptible to the senses and its complete union with spiritual things can be signified by the kiss, in his inspired book of the Song of Songs Solomon says: "let him kiss me with the kiss of his mouth", in order to express the wish that his soul be transported by divine love to the contemplation of celestial beauty and by its intimate union with this beauty might forsake the body.'

All were listening very attentively to what Bembo was saying; and then, after a moment's pause, he added:

'Since you have made me begin to teach the courtier who is no longer young about love that is truly happy, I want to lead him a little further still. For to stop at this point is very dangerous, because, as we have said several times already, the soul is strongly inclined towards the senses; and although reason may choose well in its operation and recognize that beauty does not arise from the body, and therefore act as a check to impure desires, yet the constant contemplation of physical beauty often perverts true judgement. And even if no other evil resulted from this, absence from the person one loves causes much suffering. This is because when beauty is physically present, its influx into the lover's soul brings him intense pleasure, and by warming his heart it arouses and melts certain hidden and congealed powers which the warmth of love nourishes and causes to flow and well up round his heart and send through his eyes those spirits or most subtle vapours, composed of the purest and brightest part of the blood, to receive the image of her beauty and embellish it with a thousand varied adornments. In consequence, the soul is filled with wonder and delight; it is frightened and yet it rejoices; as if dazed, it experiences along with its pleasure the fear and reverence invariably inspired by sacred things, and it believes it has entered into its Paradise.

'Therefore the lover who is intent only on physical beauty loses all this good and happiness as soon as the woman he loves by her absence leaves his eyes deprived of their splendour and, consequently, his soul widowed of its good. For, since her beauty is far away, there is no influx of affection to warm his heart as it did when she was there, and so the openings of his body become arid and dry; yet the memory of her beauty still stirs the powers of his soul a little, so that they seek to pour those spirits forth. Although their paths are blocked and there is no exit for them, they still strive to depart, and thus tormented and enclosed they begin to prick the soul and cause it to suffer bitterly, as children do when the teeth begin to grow through their tender gums. This causes the tears, the sighs, the anguish and the torments of lovers, because the soul is in constant pain and turmoil and almost raging in fury until its cherished beauty appears once more; and then suddenly it is calmed and breathes again, and wholly absorbed it draws strength from the delicious food before it and wishes never to part from such a ravishing vision. Therefore, to escape the torment caused by absence and to enjoy beauty without suffering, with the help of reason the courtier should turn his desire completely away from the body to beauty alone. He should contemplate beauty as far as he is able in its own simplicity and purity, create it in his imagination as an abstraction distinct from any material form, and thus make it lovely and dear to his soul, and enjoy it there always, day and night and in every time and place, without fear of ever losing it; and he will always remember that the body is something altogether distinct from beauty, whose perfection it diminishes rather than enhances. In this way the courtier of ours who is no longer young will put himself out of reach of the anguish and distress invariably experienced by the young in the form of jealousy, suspicion, disdain, anger, despair and a certain tempestuous fury that occasionally leads them so much astray that some not only beat the women they love but take their own lives. He will do no injury to the husband, father, brothers or family of the lady he loves; he will cause her no shame; he will not be forced sometimes to drag his eyes away and curb his tongue for fear of revealing his desires to others; or to endure suffering when they part or during her absence. For he will always carry the treasure that is so precious to him safe in his heart; and by the power of his imagination he will also make her beauty far more lovely than it is in reality.

'However, among all these blessings the lover will find one that is far greater still, if he will determine to make use of this love as a step by which to climb to another that is far more sublime; and this will be possible if he continually reflects how narrowly he is confined by always limiting himself to the contemplation of a single body. And so in order to escape from this coninement, he will gradually add so many adornments to his idea of beauty that, by uniting all possible forms of beauty in his mind, he will form a universal concept and so reduce all the many varieties to the unity of that single beauty which sheds itself over human nature as a whole. And thus he will come to contemplate not the particular beauty of a single woman but the universal beauty which adorns all human bodies: and then, dazzled by this greater light, he will not concern himself with the lesser; burning with a more perfect flame, he will feel little esteem for what he formerly prized so greatly. Now this stage of love, although so noble that few attain it, still cannot be called perfect. For the human imagination is a corporeal faculty and acquires knowledge only through the data supplied to it by the senses, and so it is not wholly purged of the darkness of material things. Thus although it may consider this universal beauty in the abstract and simply in itself, yet it perceives it not at all clearly nor within a certain ambiguity because of the affinities that the images it forms have with the body itself; and so those who reach this stage of love are like fledglings which on their feeble wings can lift themselves a little in flight but dare not stray far from the nest or trust themselves to the winds and the open sky.

'Therefore when our courtier has arrived at this stage, even though he can be called most happy in comparison with those lovers who are still sunk in the miseries of sensual love, I wish him not to be satisfied but to move boldly onwards along the sublime path of love and follow his guide towards the goal of true happiness. So instead of directing his thoughts to the outward world, as those must do who wish to consider bodily beauty, let him turn within himself to contemplate what he sees with the eyes of the mind, which begin to be penetrating and clear-sighted once those of the body have lost the flower of their delight; and in this manner, having shed all evil, purged by the study of true philosophy, directed towards the life of the spirit, and practised in the things of the intellect, the soul turns to contemplate its own substance, and as if awakened from deepest sleep it opens the eyes which all men possess but few use and perceives in itself a ray of that light which is the true image of the angelic beauty that has been transmitted to it, and of which in turn it transmits a faint impression to the body. Thus, when it has become blind to earthly things, the soul opens its eyes wide to those of heaven; and sometimes when the faculties of the body are totally absorbed by assiduous contemplation, or bound to sleep, no longer hindered by their influence the soul tastes a certain hidden savour of the true angelic beauty, and ravished by the loveliness of that light it begins to bum and to pursue the beauty it sees so avidly that it seems almost drunk and beside itself in its desire to unite with it. For the soul then believes that it has discovered the traces of God, in the contemplation of which it seeks its final repose and bliss. And so, consumed in this most joyous flame, it ascends to its noblest part, which is the intellect; and there, no more overshadowed by the dark night of earthly things, it glimpses the divine beauty itself. Even so, it does not yet enjoy this perfectly, since it contemplates it only in its own particular intellect, which cannot comprehend universal beauty in all its immensity. And so, not even satisfied with bestowing this blessing, love gives the soul greater happiness still. For just as from the particular beauty of a single body it guides the soul to the universal beauty of all bodies, so, in the last stage of perfection, it guides the soul from the particular intellect to the universal intellect. And from there, aflame with the sacred fire of true divine love, the soul flies to unite itself with the angelic nature, and it not only abandons the senses but no longer has need of reason itself. For, transformed into an angel, it understands all intelligible things and without any veil or cloud it gazes on the wide sea of pure divine beauty, which it receives into itself to enjoy the supreme happiness the senses cannot comprehend.

'The kinds of beauty which every day we see in corruptible bodies with these clouded eyes of ours (and which even so are only dreams and faint shadows) appear to be so lovely and graceful that they often kindle in us a most ardent fire and cause such delight that we count no happiness the equal of what we sometimes feel because of a single glance we may receive from the eyes of the woman we love, so what happy wonder, what blessed awe must we think is that which possesses the soul when it attains the vision of divine beauty! What sweet flame, what ravishing fire must we believe that to be which springs from the source of supreme and true beauty, the fountain of all other beauty which never increases or diminishes! Always beautiful; most simple of itself and equally in all its parts; like only to itself and sharing in nothing other than itself; it is yet so beautiful that all other beautiful things derive their beauty from it. And this is the beauty indistinguishable from the highest good, which by its light calls and draws all things to it and which not only gives intellect to intellectual beings, reason to rational beings and the senses and the desire for life to sensual beings, but also transmits to the very plants and rocks, as an imprint of itself, motion and the instinct of their own particular nature. This love, therefore, is as greater and happier than the others as the cause that produces it is greater. And thus, just as material fire refines gold, so this most sacred fire consumes and destroys everything that is mortal in our souls and quickens and beautifies the celestial part which previously, because of the senses, was dead and buried. This is the pyre on which the poets write that Hercules was burned on the summit of Mount Oeta and through whose fire he became divine and immortal after death; this is the burning bush of Moses, the parted tongues of fire, the fiery chariot of Elias, which doubles the grace and happiness of those souls worthy to see it, when it leaves the earth below and flies towards heaven. So let us direct all the thoughts and powers of our soul towards this most sacred light which shows us the path that leads to heaven; and following after it and divesting ourselves of the human passions in which we were clothed when we fell, let us ascend by the ladder whose lowest rung bears the image of sensual beauty to the sublime mansion where dwells the celestial, adorable and true beauty which lies hidden in the secret recesses of the Almighty where profane eyes may not see it. And here we shall find a most happy end to our desires, true rest from our labours, a sure remedy for our miseries, a wholesome medicine for our infirmities, a most safe harbour from the raging storms of the tempestuous sea of this life.

'O most sacred Love, what tongue is there that can praise you worthily? Full of beauty, goodness and wisdom, you flow from the union of beauty, goodness and divine wisdom, there you dwell, and through it you return to it perpetually. Graciously binding the universe together, midway between celestial and earthly things, by your benign disposition you direct the heavenly powers in their government of the lower, and turning the minds of men to their source, you unite them with it. You unite the elements in harmony, inspire nature to produce, and move all that is born to the perpetuation of life. You join together the things that are separate, give perfection to the imperfect, likeness to the unlike, friendship to the hostile, fruit to the earth, tranquillity to the sea, its life-giving light to the sky. You are the father of true pleasures, of all blessings, of peace, of gentleness and of good will; the enemy of rough savagery and vileness; the beginning and the end of every good. And since you delight to inhabit the flower of beautiful bodies and beautiful souls, and there sometimes consent to reveal a little of yourself to those worthy to see you, I believe that you now dwell here among us. Consent then, O Lord, to hear our prayers, pour yourself into our hearts, and with the radiance of your most sacred fire illumine our darkness and like a trusted guide show us the right path through this blind maze. Correct the falsity of our senses, and after our long delirium give us the true substance of goodness. Quicken our intellects with the incense of spirituality and make us so attuned to the celestial harmony that there is no longer room within us for any discord of passion. Inebriate our souls at the inexhaustible fountain of contentment that always delights and never satiates and that gives a taste of true blessedness to whoever drinks from its living and limpid waters. With the rays of your light cleanse our eyes of their misty ignorance, so that they may no longer prize mortal beauty but know that the things which they first thought to see are not, and that those they did not see truly are. Accept the sacrifice of our souls; and burn them in the living flame that consumes all earthly dross, so that wholly freed from the body they may unite with divine beauty in a sweet and perpetual bond and that we, liberated from our own selves, like true lovers can be transformed into the object of our love and soar above the earth to join the feast of the angels, where, with ambrosia and immortal nectar for our food, we may at last die a most happy death in life, as did those ancient fathers whose souls, by the searing power of contemplation, you ravished from their bodies to unite with God.'

Having spoken in that way with such vehemence that he seemed transported out of himself, Bembo then remained silent and still, looking towards heaven, as if dazed. And then signora Emilia, who together with all the others had listened to all he had to say with the utmost attention, plucked the hem of his robe and said:

'Take care, Pietro, that with these thoughts of yours you too do not cause your soul to leave your body.'

'Madam,' answered Pietro, 'that would not be the first miracle that love has worked in me.'

Then the Duchess and all the others began once again to insist that Bembo should continue his discourse; and everyone almost seemed to feel in his mind a spark of the divine love that had inspired Bembo himself. They were all anxious to hear more, but he then added:

'Gentlemen, I have said all that was dictated to me on the spur of the moment by the holy frenzy of love. And now that its inspiration seems to have failed, I would not know what to say; and I think that love does not wish its secrets to be revealed any further, or that the courtier should pass beyond the stage I have been graciously permitted to show him; and so perhaps I may speak no further about this subject.'

'Truly,' said the Duchess, 'if the courtier who is no longer young is such that he is able to follow the path you have shown him he should rightly be content with such great happiness and feel no envy of the young.'

Then Cesare Gonzaga remarked:'The road that leads to happiness seems to me so steep that I hardly think anyone can travel it.'

And then signor Gaspare added:'I think to travel this road would be difficult for men, but impossible for women.'

Signora Emilia laughed and said:

'Signor Gaspare, if you return to giving us so many insults, I promise you will not be forgiven again.'

Signor Gaspare replied:'It is no insult to you to say that the souls of women are not as purged of the passions as those of men or as versed in contemplation as Pietro has said those which are to taste divine love must be. Thus do we not read that any woman has ever received this grace, but we do read of many men who have, such as Plato, Socrates, Plotinus and many others; and similarly many of our holy Fathers, such as St Francis, upon whom an ardent messenger of love impressed the most holy seal of the five wounds. And only the power of love could transport the Apostle St Paul to the vision of those secrets of which no man is allowed to speak, or show St Stephen the heavens opening.'

Then the Magnifico Giuliano replied:

'But women would not be surpassed by men in the slightest as far as this is concerned: for Socrates himself confessed that all the mysteries of love that he knew had been revealed to him by a woman, the famous Diotima, and the angel who pierced St Francis with the fire of love has also made several women of our own time worthy of the same seal. You should also remember that many sins were forgiven St Mary Magdalene because she loved much and that she, perhaps in no less a state of grace than St Paul, was many times rapt to the third heaven by angelic love, and remember many others who, as I told at greater length yesterday, for the love of Christ's name have cared nothing for their own life, nor have they feared tortures or any manner of death, however horrible and cruel. And these were not old, as pietro wishes his courtier to be, but tender and delicate girls, of the age at which he says sensual love should be allowed to men.'

＊

Signor Gaspare was preparing to reply; but then the Duchess said:

'Let Pietro Bembo be the judge of this, and let us abide by his decision as to whether or not women are as capable of divine love as men. But, as the argument between you could last too long, it would be as well to postpone it until tomorrow.'

'Rather, fill this evening,' said Cesare Gonzaga.

'Why this evening?' asked the Duchess.

Cesare replied:'Because it is already day'; and he showed her the light that was beginning to come in through the clefts of the windows. Then they all rose to their feet, greatly astonished, because it did not seem that the discussion had lasted longer than usual, but as they had started far later and taken greater pleasure in it, those gentlemen had been so absorbed that they had not noticed the way time was passing; nor did anyone feel at all fired: and this often happens when the accustomed time of sleep is spent in wakefulness. So when the windows on the side of the palace that faces the lofty peak of Mount Catria had been opened, they saw that dawn had already come to the east, with the beauty and colour of a rose, and all the stars had been scattered, save only the lovely mistress of heaven, Venus, who guards the confines of night and day. From there, there seemed to come a delicate breeze, filling the air with biting cold, and among the murmuring woods on nearby hills wakening the birds into joyous song. Then all, having taken their respectful leave of the Duchess, went to their rooms, without torches, for the light of day was sufficient; and, as they were about to leave the room, the Prefect turned to the Duchess and said:

'Madam, to settle the argument between signor Gaspare and the Magnifico, we shall come with our judge this evening earlier than we did yesterday.'

Signora Emilia replied:'On condition that if signor Gaspare should want to criticize women and slander them in his usual manner he shall give his bond to stand trial, for I arraign him as a fugitive from justice.'

译者导读

“人法地，地法天，天法道，道法自然”

——《老子》

本书的书名虽取自《老子》，但内容全部摘选自《庄子》，并进行了重新编排。这大概也可反映出庄子与老子的关系。庄子是老子的后学，极致推崇老子，虽然其学说思想与老子不尽相同，但有关“道、德”的根本观念则基本相同，皆为当时一切传统思想之反对派，故经常被人并称为“老庄哲学”。

有关庄子其人，我们知之甚少。《史记》曰：“庄子者，蒙人也，名周。周尝为蒙漆园吏，与梁惠王、齐宣王同时。”《庄子》一书之中也多次提及庄子与惠施往来，且死于惠施之后。但庄子一生的其他事迹，并无更多记载。至于其生卒年月，根据马叙伦《庄子年表》，庄子大约生活于公元前370年至公元前298年。

庄子的学说，胡适认为“只是一个‘出世主义’”，其中《天下篇》最能表现其思想，庄子虽生于世俗，却“独与天地精神往来，……上与造物者游，而下与外死生无终始者为友”。胡适还说“中国古代的出世派哲学至庄子始完全成立”。虽然《史记》中对庄子的评价并不高，说他“著书十余万言，大抵率寓言也”，“皆空语，无事实”。但后世仍有很多人推崇庄学，认为其“文体思想，皆极超旷”，表达了那种“忘我，顺其自然，入世而超世”的深刻体验。其“‘道’‘天’一也”的思想背后，也传达出了“道可道，非常道”之“道不可知”的理念。

本书分为十四部分。第一部分“齐物论”阐明“万物皆为一”，是庄子哲学的中坚思想，也是整个庄子思想的辩证法基础；第二部分“完美契合”藉多个故事传达“顺天而为”的思想，其中就有著名的“庖丁解牛”的故事；第三部分“何为真人？”和第四部分“命而已！”继而探讨了“顺天而为”思想下应具有的人生观和价值观；第五部分是关于“惠子”（即惠施）的，辩论中阐明庄子思想的同时，他们之间的友情也跃然纸上；第六部分“马蹄”则由“马与粘土之遭遇”引出庄子的政治观，就是要“任天顺性”；第七部分“博学何用？”透露出庄子对于知识和幸福的态度，主张“无为而为”；第八部分“无为而为是谓天”继续展开对“无为而为”的讨论，直指“天”与“性”；第九部分“天在动吗？”则深入追问何为“天”之“道”，又回到“无为而为”；第十部分藉另一组故事探讨“真实与幸福”，答案仍是“任天顺性”、“无为而为”；第十一部分“把握生命的目的”阐发“无为而为”的人生观；第十二部分“勿要问道”比苏格拉底“我知道我什么都不知道”走得更远，“道”非但是“不知道”更是“顺性无为”；第十三部分“何为本真？”中的两个故事皆关政治，一“文”一“武”，欲强问道，唯有道法自然；最后，第十四部分则关于庄子在自己生活中如何践行自己的思想。不论是从多方面展开论证，还是从理论到实践，这样的组织安排使得《庄子》有了一个系统的脉络，为理解庄子的思想贡献了一个可供参考的架构。

最后，谈一谈本书的翻译。其实，越来越多的中国古典哲学在西方有了译本，特别是当下中国的影响力日盛。或许有人会问，为何需要将译本再转译成中文呢？当然，曾经有很多人在翻译原是中文的内容时闹出过不少笑话。这自有译者疏忽之故，个中原因我们在此无法深究。但是无论如何，对西方译本的回译，特别是古代文本，有助于我们了解和参照西方学界所进行的解读，毕竟我们对古文的解读也并非总是意见一致。有些译本更是对原文本进行了重新编排，这也有助于我们寻找古代文本内部的系统结构。译者并非庄学专家，知识能力有限，若有不妥之处，还请大家多多指正。

参考书目：

陈柱，《诸子概论》，广西师范大学出版社，2010.

冯友兰，《中国哲学史》，重庆出版社，2009.

胡适，《中国哲学史大纲》，商务印书馆，2011.

第一部分　齐物论

现在，我有话要说。我所说的跟别人所说的是不是属于同一范畴呢？我不知道。在某个层面上，我所说的是不同的。但在另一个层面上，肯定又是相同的，即我所说的和别人所说的没有什么不同。不管是哪种情形，容我尽量把我的意思说给你听。

有开始，就有开始尚未开始之时，就有开始尚未开始之时尚未开始之时。有有，就有无，而且很难说无是否无，或者有是否有。

我刚说了一番话，但是我并不知道在我所说的话里我要说的是否是真的，或者是否真的说了？

天下没有比毛发的末端更大的东西了，泰山相比都算为小；没有比夭折的婴儿更长寿的了，彭祖相比都算短命。

天地与我同时出生，而且万物与我为一。

既然万物皆为一，还有需要进行言说吗？可是我刚刚说了万物皆为一，我就已经进行言说了，不是吗？一加一等于二，二加一等于三。由此推算下去，即便是业务娴熟的会计也可能会弄不明白，何况是一般人呢。如果从“无”到“有”我们得到三，想想如果是从“有”到“有”呢，我们得要走多远！

还是不要开始，让我们呆在原地。

伟大的道没有开始，言说自打开始就已经改变了意义。但是出于“有此”的想法，界限还是出现了。我想说一说这些界限。左与右，相互关系及其影响，区分与异议，效仿与争辩，这些就是所谓的八德。

圣人不会谈论宇宙界限之外的事物——虽然他也不会加以否认。宇宙之内的事物，他虽进行谈论却不会断言。对于《春秋》中所记载的先王的事迹，圣人讨论但不评判。如果有事物被区分，就有事物未被区分；如果有异议存在，就有没有争议的事物存在。

你问，这是什么意思？圣人包容万物，而一般人却只是就事物起争执。这就是为什么我说争执意味着你根本不理解。

伟大的道路没有名字，

伟大的争辩没有言说，

伟大的善行不是行善，

伟大的虚心不是谦虚，

伟大的勇气不是残暴。

清晰明确的道不是道，

起争论的言语无价值，

行善只看眼前终无果，

虚心若被无视即失败，

残暴的勇气没有意义。

……

啮缺问王倪：“老师，你知道万物相一致的是什么吗？”

王倪说：“我怎么可能知道？”

“老师，那你知道什么你不知道吗？”

他回答说：“我怎么能知道？”

“那万物都是无知的吗？”

王倪说：“这我怎么可能知道？话虽如此，我还是想试着说点什么。我怎么知道我说我知道的东西不是我不知道的呢？同样地，我怎么知道我认为我不知道的就不是我知道的呢？我想问你几个问题：

‘如果有人睡在一个潮湿的地方，他会浑身疼痛甚至会半身不遂，可是鳗鱼会如此吗？如果有人爬上一棵树，他会害怕发抖，可是猴子会这样吗？这三者之中，谁的居所是最明智的呢？

‘人吃肉，鹿吃草，蜈蚣吃蛇，而猫头鹰和乌鸦吃老鼠。这四者之中，谁的口味是最好的呢？

‘猴子相互结伴，鹿彼此结群。人们说毛嫱和丽姬是世界上最漂亮的女人，可是鱼看见她们会潜水而逃，鸟会飞向天空，鹿也会逃跑。这四者之中，到底是谁知道真正的美呢？依我看，善和义，是非之途，根本就是相互交织的。我想我不可能知道它们之间的区别！’”

啮缺说：“老师，如果你不知道善和恶之间的区别，是不是说完美之人也没有这样的知识呢？”

王倪回答说：“完美之人是纯精神的，他感受不到滚烫沙漠的热度，也感受不到浩瀚水域的冰冷。能劈开高山的闪电和能搅动海水的风暴都不能让他惊恐。这样的人乘着云彩登上日月，遨游于四海内外。死生都不能影响他，他也不关心善恶！”

瞿鹊子问长梧子：

我听老师说：圣人

不劳作，也不寻利，

不行善，也不为害，

而且他也不追求道；

不说话却可以达意，

说话时却无所传达，

超越了尘世的界限。

“老师把所有这些看作是一连串无尽的词语，可在我看来它们就像是有关神秘之道的言论。老师，您认为如何？”

长梧子说：“这样的说法甚至会让黄帝感到困惑，那么孔子怎么可能明白呢！而且，你过于超前了，蛋还未孵化就想计算鸡的数量，看到碗就想到烤好的禽肉。我尽量跟你随便一说，你也随便一听。智者如何能够坐在日月之旁而包容整个宇宙？因为他让万物归于和谐，所以他拒绝差异和混乱，并且无视地位和权力。当一般人匆忙地四处闯荡，圣人却显得愚蠢无知，而且在他看来万物是合而为一的。万物只是顺其自然，万物在他看来都是在做它们应该做的。

“我怎么知道对生的爱不是虚幻呢？或者对死的恐惧不正像一个离家出走的年轻人找不到回家的路？丽姬小姐是边疆守卫艾的女儿。当她被晋国俘获时，她哭得眼泪都把捆绑她的绳子浸湿了；随后她来到了晋王的宫殿，睡在晋王的床上，享用晋王的食物，就后悔之前流眼泪了。我怎么知道人死后不会为他们之前贪生而后悔呢？

“清晨来临，那些梦到在宴会上喝醉的人可能会哭泣呻吟；那些在梦中哭泣呻吟的人待清晨醒来就外出打猎去了。当他们做梦时，他们并不知道是在做梦。确实，在梦中他们可能认为他们在解梦，只有当他们醒来才知道这不过是一场梦。思考和清醒之日终将到来，到那时我们就会知道一切都是一场大梦。只有愚蠢之人才认为他们现在是清醒的，好像他们真得知道发生了什么，谁演王子，谁演仆人。真是愚蠢啊！老师和你都活在梦里。当我说这是梦时，我也在做梦。就这句话也是骗人的。如果万年之后我们能有一次机会见到一位明白这个道理的真正伟大的圣人，这就好像只过去了一上午似的。

“假如你和我进行辩论，你胜过了我，而不是我胜过了你，这难道就意味着你就当然是对的而我就当然是错的吗？如果我胜过了你，是否就能得出我就当然是对的而你因此就是错的呢？我们之中真的有一个是对的而另一个是错的吗或者是否我们都是对的或者都是错的呢？你和我终究都不知道，而其他人就更不清楚了。如此，我们让谁来给我们正确答案呢？你能问那认为你对的人吗？可是这样的人怎么能够给出一个公正的答案呢？我们能问那认为我对的人吗？可是如果他同意我的意见，他又怎么能够作出公正的评判呢？那么，同样地，我们能问对你我的意见都赞同的人吗？同样地，如果他对你我都赞成，他怎么能给出一个真正的判断呢？那我们能问对你我都持异议的人吗？还是一样，如果他对你我都反对，他怎么能进行真诚的评判呢？很明显，不论你我还是其他任何人相互间都不能作出如此决定。那么，我们是否还应当等待另外有人出现呢？

“等待一个声音来统合一切跟不等待任何人一样没有意义。把所有事物一块儿置于天的平等之下，让它们变化的过程持续无阻，并且学会如何成长到老。把所有事物一块儿置于天的平等之下是什么意思呢？至于何为是非，我要说非亦是，是亦非。但是让我们不要纠缠于此讨论。忘记生，忘记担心是非。投入到那未知的无穷之中，找到属于你的位置！”

罔两问景：“你先是在动，然后又站着不动；你坐下，然后又站起来。你为什么不能自己作决定呢？”

景答道：“我要依赖其他东西来成为我自己吗？难道这个其他的东西自己不也得依赖另外的其他东西吗？我必须得依赖蛇的鳞片或蝉的双翼吗？我怎么能够分辨事物是怎样的呢？我怎么知道事物不是怎样的呢？”

从前，我庄周梦到过自己是一只蝴蝶，飞来飞去，十分开心。我忘记了自己是庄周。然后突然我醒了，又变回庄周了。但是我不能分辨，到底我是庄周梦见自己是一只蝴蝶，还是我是一只蝴蝶梦见自己现在成了庄周呢？无论如何，庄周和蝴蝶之间肯定是有某种区别的！我们可以称之为事物的转化。

第二部分　完美契合

庖丁为文惠君宰杀一头牛。他手上的每一个动作、肩膀的每一次耸动、双脚的每一次迈步、膝盖的每一次推抵、肉撕裂时发出的每一声，以及下刀时所发出的嗖嗖之声，都是那么地完美契合，就好比《桑林》的舞蹈或《经首》的旋律。

“啊，太棒了！”文惠君说道，“你的技艺为何如此高超呢？”

庖丁放下他的刀然后说道：“属下最爱的是道，它优于任何技艺。当我最开始宰牛的时候，我看到的只是一整头牛。三年后，我就学会了不把牛看成一个整体。现在我是借着我的心智来行动，而不是用我的双眼。我不去管那感觉，而是追随着我的灵魂。我看到了那自然的线条，我的刀子划过那大的空隙、顺着那大的腔孔，这是将已存在的为我所用。因此，我避开了那些大的肌肉，更别说那大的骨头了。一个好的厨师一年换一把刀，因为他用刀切。一个普通的厨师却不得不一个月换一把刀，因为他用刀砍。现在我这把刀已经用了十九年了，用它宰杀了几千头牛。但是，它的刀刃仍像刚开过光一样锋利。两个关节之间是空隙，而刀刃却没有什么厚度。如果你把没有厚度的刀刃切进这样的空隙之中，是有足够空间的，当然足以让刀划过。不过，当我碰到比较困难的部分，我能够看出它不好处理，我就会小心谨慎。我仔细观察，谨慎移动。然后，轻轻地，我滑动刀子，直到肉都分开，像一块土掉到地上一样散开。我手持刀站在那里，环顾四周，然后心满意足地把刀擦干净收起来。”

文惠君说：“妙极了！我听了庖丁说的话，从他的话里我学到了尽享此生的方法。”

公文轩看到右师时，十分惊讶，说道：“此人是谁？为何他只有一只脚？这是天生的还是人为的？”

右师说道：“天生的，不是人为的。天赋予我生命，同时它只给了我一只脚。人的相貌是天生的，因此我知道我这是天生的，不是人为的。沼泽里的野鸡每走十步啄食一次，每走百步喝水一次，但它可不想被养在笼子里。即便你待它如国王，它的灵魂也是不开心的。”

老子死后，秦失前来为他哀悼。他叫喊了三声后就离开了。

老子的一个弟子说道：“难道老师不是你的朋友吗？”

他回答说：“没错。”

“那么你真的以为这样的哀悼方式是最好的吗？”

“是的。起先我以为这些人是真正的人，但是现在我不这么确定了。我进来哀悼的时候，有老人在哭泣，就好像他们失去了自己的孩子一样；有年轻人在痛哭，如同自己的母亲去世了一般。这样的一群人聚在一起，不停地瞎聊，但是老子可没让他们来这儿聊天；而且还哭哭啼啼，虽然老子并不想要别人为他流眼泪。这是违背天意，沉浸在情绪之中，忽视了天的赋予。古人称之为违背天理的后果。你老师来到这个世界，是因为他应当出生。现在他死，也是完全自然的。如果你准备接受并顺其自然，悲伤和喜悦都不能触碰到你。古人将其视为神的工作，让我们脱离束缚。

“我们可以指着那燃尽的木材，但是其上烧过的火，我们却不知道它去到何方。”

……

颜阖即将成为卫灵公长子的老师，所以他前去拜访蘧伯玉说：“有一个人，天性没有道德。如果我让他只是顺其自然，国家将岌岌可危；如果我尽力让他回归有节制的生活，那么我的生命将有危险。他只能认识到他人的过分举动，却不能看到自己的。在这种情况下，我该怎么办呢？”

蘧伯玉说：“问得好！要警惕，要小心，保证你自己是正确的。外表上要表示赞同，心里要保持满足和谐。但是，这些策略都有风险。不要让你的外在态度影响你的内在自我，也不要让你的内在自我表现于外。如果你使自己陷入了他做事的方式之中，你会被推翻、毁灭、摧毁，并最终溃败。如果你内心的和谐表现于外，你将会获得声名，然而你会被称为恶人。如果他做事像个孩子，那么跟他在一起时就表现得像个孩子；如果他不允许有任何限制，那就按他说的做。如果他跨越栅栏，就跟着他！只有理解他，然后才能巧妙地引领他改过。

“你难道不知道螳螂的故事吗？愤怒之中，它挥舞着它的手臂阻挡快速行进的马车，却不知道它无力阻止，还对它自己的力量信心满满哩！要警惕，要小心！如果你如此盲目自信，你将遭遇同样的危险。

“难道你不知道驯虎师的做法吗？他不会给老虎活的动物做食物，害怕过度刺激它们会让它们爱上杀戮。他甚至都不给它们整个的动物尸体，害怕激起它们撕碎动物的怒气。他观察它们的食欲，意识到它们的凶猛。老虎和人不同，但是如果你懂得如何去适应它们，你可以训练它们听从训练师的指令。那些违逆老虎天性的人不会活得很久。

“爱马的人用精美的篮子和瓶子收集马粪和马尿。可是，当一只蚊子或牛虻落在马身上，马夫突然地将其轰走时，马会挣脱马嚼子、损坏马具并伤到前胸。马夫是出于爱马尽量去做那有益的事情，可是最终结果却适得其反。因此我们更应行事谨慎啊！”

在去齐国的路上，木匠石来到一个叫曲辕的地方。他在那里看到一棵橡树，被当作土地神明的庙宇敬拜。这棵树那样地大，足以遮蔽一千头牛。它有一百抱那么粗，高耸超过山顶足有八十英尺处才开始发枝。可以被开凿成整艘船的树枝就有十根。大量的人前来参观，使这个地方有了节日的气氛，但是木匠石都没环视一圈就继续赶路了。他的助手仔细观察过这棵树后，紧追上他的老师说：“自从我首次拿起斧头追随您以来，还没见过这样的树木呢。先生，您为什么都不停下来看一眼就继续赶路呢？”

他说：“安静，啥也别说了！这棵树没啥用。用它做船会沉，做棺木会很快腐烂，做家具会散成碎片，做门会到处渗出树液，做梁柱会生蛀虫。这棵树没用，什么也做不了。因此它才能活这么长。”

石师傅返程的时候，这棵树在梦中向他显灵，说：“你到底要把我比作什么？用于观赏的果树吗？山楂树、梨树、柑橘树、葫芦或其他果树之类的树吗？他们的果实成熟时会被打掉，树木因此而遭罪。大的树枝会遭到破坏，小的树枝会被折断。因为它们有用，它们就遭罪，所以不能尽享天所赋予的寿命。对于人们所进行的此类破坏，它们只能怪罪自己有用。万物皆如此。我花费了很长时间学会变得无用，尽管有那么几次我差点就被摧毁。不过，现在我已经完善了无用之术，对我来说，这很有用！如果我以前有用，我能长这么大吗？再说，你我皆是物。一物怎能对他物加以评判呢？你这个终将死去的无用之人又怎能了解一棵无用之树呢？”

木匠石醒来之后就把他所做的梦告诉他的学徒。学徒说：“如果它想变得无用，为什么还被用作土地神明的庙宇呢？”

石说：“嘘！别说了！这棵树正好在此，因此变成了祭坛。这样它才能保护自己，免受那些尚未意识到它无用之人的伤害。如果它不是祭坛，就有被砍伐掉的危险。另外，这棵树不是一般的树，所以用一般的言语来谈论它可就是不得要领了。”

南伯子綦在商地的山丘之间漫游，碰到一棵巨大而不寻常的树，树下可以为一千辆马车提供荫蔽，全部都能被遮挡住。子綦说：“这是怎样的树啊？它肯定是世上最棒的木材！”但是，当他抬头看时，看到小一点的树枝是那样的弯曲变形、长满树瘤，根本就不能用作房梁；往下看，看到树干也是弯曲变形的，不能用作好的棺木。他舔了一片叶子，感觉嘴唇被擦伤了，很疼。他又闻了闻，这一下差点发疯，就跟大醉了三天似的。

子綦说：“这棵树肯定毫无用处，因此它才能长这么大。啊哈！这就是圣人赖以生存的那种无用啊。

“在宋国有一个区域为荆氏之地，特别适合种植梓树、柏树和桑树。不过，那些有一握多粗的树，被要为他们的猴子做木桩的人砍了；那些有三四指距宽的树，被要给大房子做梁木的人砍了；那些有七八指距宽的树，被想要他们的棺木每一面都是整个厚板的君主和富人砍了。因此，这些树都不能活过天赋予它们的寿命，反而在它们生命的黄金时期被人用斧子砍掉。这都是有用的后果啊！献祭时，把有白色额头的牛、鼻孔上翻的猪以及患有痔疮的人作为祭品献给河神是没有用的。僧人知道这些，因此他们视这些生物为不祥的。但是，圣人却因相同的原因而对它们高度评价。

“支离疏身体残疾，下巴陷进了他的肚脐，肩膀高过了头顶，发髻指着天，五脏都被挤压到了身体的顶部，两条大腿紧紧顶着肋骨。他靠磨针和洗衣服挣的钱足以糊口。他给人去糠筛米挣的钱能养活十个人。官员来征兵时，他大摇大摆地闲逛，不必躲藏；官员想要组织大批人员服劳役时，因为他身体畸形，也没人去找他。反过来，当官员向体弱之人分发粮食时，他却可领到三大份，还有十捆柴。如果像他这样身体畸形的人都能够养活自己并尽享天赋的寿命，又何况那仅在道德层面上畸形的人呢！”

……

在鲁国有一个身残之人名叫叔山无趾。他拖着残肢来见孔子。孔子说：“你以前不谨慎所以才遭此厄运。现在才来见我为时已晚。”

无趾说：“因为我的无知和对身体照顾不周，我失去了一只脚。现在我来找您是因为我还有比脚更重要的东西想要保全。没有什么东西是苍天不能覆盖的，也没有什么东西是大地不能承载的。我本希望先生您可以做我的天地，没有想到您会这样待我。”

孔子说：“我真是愚蠢。先生是善人，请不要走，我想要跟您分享我所学到的。”

可是，无趾还是走了，孔子说：“要注意啦，学生们！无趾，伟大啊，虽然失去了一只脚却仍然想通过学习来弥补他的过错。你们个个身体健全，岂不更应该要学习！”

无趾把他的故事讲给老子听，说：“孔子肯定尚未成为完美之人，不是吗？他好像还是沉溺于追求名誉声望而不能自拔，好像并未懂得完美之人将名声视同枷锁。”

老子说：“为什么不帮他认识到死生是一回事，是非也是一回事，好让他自枷锁中解脱呢？”

无趾反问：“如果是天在惩罚他，他又如何能摆脱呢？”

鲁哀公问孔子说：“卫国有一人，相貌丑陋，叫哀骀它。但是在他身边的那些人都敬佩他，若女人看到他，便跑到他们的父母跟前说：‘我宁愿做这位君子的小妾也不愿做别人的妻子。’这样的事情发生过不止十次。从未有人听说他引领过任何东西，倒是经常附随别人。他不强大，不能救别人于危亡之中；他也不富有，不能充实别人的肚皮。况且，他是那样的丑陋，足以吓到全世界的人。他从不带头干什么，只是附和别人的提议，对于自己家四面墙以外的世界一无所知。但是人们成群结队地来找他。很明显，他和普通人不一样，因此我召他前来见我。他确实丑陋，足以让全世界的人都害怕他。可是他跟我在一起还不到一个月，我就开始欣赏他了。不到一年，我就完全信赖他了。因为国家尚未有主政的大臣，所以我请他担任此职。对于我的请求，他的反应是那么地难过，那么地羞怯，如同要拒绝一般。我为自己感到羞愧，但最终还是把国家交给了他。不久后，他便起身离开了。我很难过，我觉得这是重大的损失，因为没有人可以与我分担治国的重担了。你说，这是什么样的人呢？”

孔子说：“我曾经出使楚国，看到一些小猪仔正奋力在它们死去的母亲身上吸奶。可不一会儿它们就全都站起来离开了。因为母亲似乎不再注意它们，所以它们也不再感到与母亲间的亲密了。它们爱母亲不是爱她的躯体，而是那给予躯体生命的东西。如果一个人在战场上被杀，葬礼上授予他的战争荣誉对他来说没有什么用处。失去双脚的人不会喜爱鞋子。因为在这两种情况下，他们失去了那让这些东西有价值的理由。没错，天子的妻室不用修剪她们的指甲也不用穿耳洞；一个新近结婚的君子会远离宫廷，免于那繁重的义务。照料身体要花费如此多的精力，想想要保存道德需要怎样的照料吧！虽然哀骀它什么都不说，人们却信任他。他什么都不做，人们却爱戴他。他能够使别人情愿把国家政权交给他，还唯恐他不接受。他必定是一个具有完美品格和无形道德之人。”

“你说的‘完美品格’是什么意思？”哀公问。

孔子回答道：“死亡、出生、存在和烦恼、吉兆和凶兆、财富、贫穷、有用和无用、荣誉和责备、饥饿和口渴、寒冷和炎热——所有这些都是世界运行的方式、命运的结果。日夜交替，但是我们却无法知道它们来自何处。不要让这样的事扰乱你内在的平衡，也不要让这样的事使你心生烦恼。如果你能平衡且享受日夜，掌控它们并为之陶醉，而且能够夜以继日地始终如此并统和万物，就能够造就一颗应变的心，这就是完美品格。”

“那‘无形道德’又是什么意思？”

“静止的水，可以在其中发现完美的平衡。这样的水就是我们所有人的榜样。保持内心和谐，不让任何外在之事影响它。道德，即是真正平衡的结果。道德没有任何形状或形式，但任何事情都不能没有它。”孔子说。

第三部分　何谓真人？

一个人若既懂得天道又通晓人道便达到完美了。懂得天，他便和天一同成长。懂得人性，用他的明智所知道的，来培养他的明智所不知道的，因此能获得善终而不是英年早逝。这便是完美。

虽然如此，但事实上问题仍然存在。真正的理解必然有所适用，可适用的对象本身却是不确定的。我怎么知道我称为天的不是人，或者我称为人的不是天呢？

只有真人才能理解。那么何谓真人？古时真人不与贫穷相抗争，也不在财富之中寻求圆满——因为他没有什么宏伟蓝图。因此，他从不为任何失败而懊悔，也不为任何成功而狂喜。他测量高度时毫无畏惧，探测深度时毫无困难，穿过火焰时毫无疼痛。就是这种人，他的理解已经将其提升到接近道了。

古时的真人睡时无梦，醒时无忧。他吃饭而非品尝，深呼吸，非常之深。真人从双脚往上全身呼吸，而普通人仅从喉咙呼吸。蹩脚之人说话如同呕吐一般。为贪婪和欲望所吞噬，在天道面前他们只是浅薄。

古时真人并不恋生，亦不畏死。他来时，无所期望；他去时，毫无抗拒。他静静地去，他静静地来，就是这样。他并不打算忘记他的起源，也没兴趣知道以后的遭遇。他不仅乐意接受任何事物，并且会忘记他之前已接受的事物并将其赠送。他并不偏爱心而是偏爱道，并将天道置于人道之上。这就是真人。

像这样，他内心健忘，

面容平静，额头舒展；

凄冷似秋，温暖似春。

高兴愤怒如四季变化。

面对万物，行为得当，

却没人知道最后结局。

故圣人即便召集军队，

征战列国，让其臣服，

也不会失去人民爱戴。

他本性宽宏造福万代，

但他却并不热爱世人。

圣人不追求有福同享。

仁人不流露自身情感。

智者不等待自然天性。

学者平衡利好与破坏。

君子不为求名而迷失。

迷失真我和道路的人，

就没有能力指挥别人。

……

古时的真人显得出世，

也就没有失败的危险。

看似匮乏却毫不拿取。

随心所欲却不好批评。

明显虚空却毫无炫耀。

开心地笑，似很满足。

反应快速，似无选择。

悲伤时，他表现出来。

满意时，他道德从容。

安静时，他天人合一。

骄傲时，他放荡不羁。

他的天性好像不可知。

从不在乎，忘其欲言。

他视法律为政府外形。

将仪式礼仪视为翅膀，

将知识视为符合时宜。

他还将道德视为得当。

因视法律为政府外形，

故他可灵活处理死刑。

因他将仪式视为翅膀，

他可与社会和谐相处。

因视知识为符合时宜，

他理解万事自然之道。

因他将道德视为得当，

才能跟领袖人物同行。

所以他自发采取行动，

别人还以为代价很高。

因此他所追求的是一。

而他所否认的也是一。

一是一，不一也是一。

一是说，他与天合一。

不一是说，与人合一。

当天与人没有争执时，

我们就能说是真人了。

死亡和出生是有定数的。就像黑夜过后必有黎明一样确定无疑，死生乃天命注定。这超出了人的掌控能力，事情就是这样的。一些人将天视为他们的父亲并一直爱他。对于那更伟大的，他们又该献上多少虔诚呢！一些人视他们的君主胜过他们自己，愿意为他献出生命。对于那比他们的君主更真的，他们又该献上多少生命呢！

当泉水干涸的时候，人们发现鱼都搁浅在地上。它们用自身的水分来保持彼此潮湿，用它们的粘液来让彼此湿润。就算它们在河流和湖泊里只能彼此相忘，也岂不是更好。人们赞美尧而批判桀，但是如果人们把他俩都忘掉而只是顺从道，岂不是更好。宇宙给予了我这躯体的负担，使生命变成挣扎，让我到老年时休息，死后才获得安宁。因此，那让生活美好的，同样也让死亡美好。

一条船可以藏于峡谷之中，一张渔网可以藏于池塘之中，这样你可能认为它们因此就安全了。但是，夜半之时会有壮汉前来将它们拿走。眼光狭小之人只是不明白将小东西藏于大东西之中并不意味着它们就不会被偷走。如果你将取自天下之物藏于天下，它就没有地方可以遗失了！这就是万物的真理。拥有人形是一件高兴的事，但是在宇宙可能的形式中，其他形式也同样好。存在着无数的可能性难道不是一件幸事吗？圣人要去那无物逃离他的地方，安心地在那里与万物共存。无论英年早逝还是年华老去，不论是开始还是结束，他都欣然接受，将它们看作是同样好——他应该成为别人的榜样。如果是这样，那么那维系生命万物、作为一切变化起源的又该是我们怎样的榜样呢！

伟大的道既有内在真实又有外在表现，但它是无为、无形的。

它可以被传递，但不能被接收。

它可以被获得，但不能被看见。

它根植于自身，在开天辟地前，

它就已存在，并将永远地存在。

它赋予神灵以神性，开天辟地。

它先于元气存在却不能说崇高；

它处宇宙四方之下却不能说深。

它先于天地而生却不能说是老。

它远比古代更为古老却并不老。

……

子祀、子舆、子犁和子来在一起交谈，说道：“如果有谁能如此想象：‘无’是他的头，‘生’是他的背，而‘死’是他的尾，并且知道死生存亡都是一样的、相同的——这样的人就应该是我们的朋友。”四个人都笑了，心生默契，于是成为朋友。

不久，子舆生病了。子祀前去探望，子舆说：“造物主真是伟大啊！他让我身体畸形。我的背就如同那驼背之人，我所有的脏器都跑到上方，而且下巴也陷进了肚脐中，肩膀升到了脑袋以上，发髻都指着天了！”他已阴阳失调。可是他却心中平静，毫无忧虑。他蹒跚到井边，往井里看他的倒影，然后说，“我的天啊！造物主已经让我变得完全畸形了！”

子祀问道：“你讨厌这个样子吗？”

“不，我为什么要讨厌呢？比方说，我的左臂可能会变成一只小公鸡，那样的话我就能够在晚上报时了。或许，最后我的右臂会变成一把十字弓，那样的话我就能猎杀一只鸟来吃。我的屁股也可能会变成车轮，我的灵魂变成一匹马，那我就会骑上马出去兜一圈。毕竟，到那时我就再也不需要其他车辆了。我得生是因为时机到了，同样时机到了我也会死去。那些顺从自然的进程而默默前行的人不会为喜乐或悲伤而担忧。这样的人在以前被认为是实现自由、摆脱束缚了。那些不能实现自我解脱的人被外物所束缚。即便如此，也没有什么可以胜过天——事实一直如此。这么说来我又为什么要讨厌现在的样子呢？”

后来子来生病了。喘喘嘘嘘地快要死了。他的妻子和儿女都在他身旁哀伤。子犁前来看望他，子来却说：“闭嘴，出去！你想要扰乱变化的进程吗？”

子犁倚在门口评论道：

“造物主何其伟大！

要把你变成什么？

要派你去向何方？

重生为老鼠肝脏？

还是变成虫的臂？”

子来说：

“当父母让子女到某地的时候，

不论东南西北，子女皆听从。

阴阳二气是我们人类的父母。

它们让我死，如果我不遵从，

这也只能算是我的刚愎任性。

我的死亡根本不是它们的错！

宇宙赋予我形体，使我出生，

引领我步入暮年，安于死亡。

若喜悦生命，也须喜悦死亡。

一个好的匠人，打铁的时候，

会不高兴，如果铁跳出来说：

‘一定要把我做成镆铘一样。’

我既已足够大胆，呈现人形，

若我说：‘我要做人，要做人。’

造物主定会有些怀疑地看我！

若天地是熔炉，自然是工匠，

它会派我去不适宜的地方吗？

让我们平静死去，安静醒来。”

第四部分　命而已！

子舆和子桑是朋友。刚好下了十天的雨，子舆就说：“子桑可能有麻烦了。”于是他包好一些食物带给他。来到子桑的家门口，他听到奇怪的声音，有人正一边弹琵琶一边唱：

“父啊！母啊！天啊！人啊！”

歌者的声音听上去好像即将要消逝了，却努力要唱完那诗文。子舆进门后就问：“子桑，你为何如此歌唱？”

他答道：“我正努力弄明白是什么让我衰败至此？我的父母肯定不想让我这么穷吧？天待万物都是一样的。地承载万物也是一样的。天地也不想我贫穷，不是吗？我想弄明白是谁如此安排，但是我找不到答案。如果你非要下个结论，这不过是命而已。”

……

天根在去殷山南面旅行的路上。他抵达蓼水，在那里碰到了无名人，就问他：“我想问问你如何治理天下万物？”

无名人答道：“走开，你这愚蠢的笨蛋！多么让人讨厌的问题啊！我正和造物主一起遨游。要是太累了，我便乘着自在虚无之鸟，去那世界四方之外，遨游于无处之所、无有之地。你为什么要打断我并用如何治理天下万物这样的问题来扰乱我的心？”

天根又问了同样的问题。无名人答道：

“让你的心在质朴之中旅行。

与那无法定义的合为一体。

让万物都保持自然的样子。

而不要怀有你个人的观点。

这就是治理天下万物之法。”

阳子居前去拜访老子，他说：“有这么一个人，他热情且谨慎，有清晰的见解和智慧，并且从不间断地学习道。这样的人肯定是有大智慧的君王了吧？”

老子说：“和圣人比，这样的人只是一个谦卑的仆人，被他的工作所束缚，疲惫不堪、心中苦恼。据说，人们猎杀老虎和猎豹是因为它们的皮毛美丽。猴子和狗也因为它们的技能而被人套上绳索。它们怎么能够和有大智慧的君王比呢？”

阳子居吃惊地说：“恕我大胆问问有大智慧的君王是如何治理的？”

老子说：

“这就是大智慧君王的治理之道！

他的工作影响天下万物，却好像什么都没做。

他的权威延伸到所有生灵，但没有人依赖他。

他虽没有名望或荣光，然而万物都达成完满。

他于神秘之处立足，并且于虚无之境中遨游。”

郑国有一个鬼神巫师叫季咸。他能够预知人的生死；他知道天降的好运和灾祸；他知道幸福和痛苦、人生和寿命，能具体到年、月、周和日，好像他自己就是神一样。郑国的人一旦看到他走过来，就会逃走。列子前去看他，却被迷住了。他回去就告诉壶子：“先生，我原以为你的道是完美，但是现在我找到更好的了。”

壶子说：“我以前向你展示的只是我讲道的外在文本，不是它的内核。你怎么能认为已掌握了我的道呢？如果你有母鸡却没有公鸡，你怎么能够获得鸡蛋呢？你在世界面前炫耀你的道。这个人因此才可以算出你的运数。你把这个巫师带来我们见见面。”

第二天列子就把这个巫师带来见壶子。当他和列子一同离开壶子的家时，巫师说：“天啊！你的老师要死了。实际没几天可活了——他可能最多活七天。我看到了一个奇怪的景象——如同打湿的灰烬一般。”

列子回到屋内，哭得那样厉害，泪水都浸湿了大衣，并把他听到的告诉了壶子。壶子说：“我让自己看起来如同大地。我就像山一样坚固，什么都没向他显露。他可能把我看成了一本合上的书，看上去没有德行。如果可以，你再把他带来。”

第二天，列子又和那个巫师一起来见壶子。当他们出去后，巫师对列子说：“你的老师碰到我多走运啊！他好多了。没错，他确实有活力了。生命又重新流动起来了。”

列子回到屋内，将巫师的话告诉给壶子。壶子说：“我让自己看起来好比是天，名声和财富都不存于心。我的自然之状在我身上自然流露。他在我身上看到了生命全部的和自然的运行。如果可以，你再把他带来。”

第二天，他们又一起来见壶子。出门后，巫师对列子说：“你的老师每次都不一样。我在他的脸上捕捉不到运数。如果他能回归到某种一致性上，我再来看他。”

列子回到屋内向壶子转告了此事。壶子说：“我向他展示自己，就像那伟大的虚无，其中万物皆平等。他几乎必然在我身上看到了我内心力量之间的和谐。当水流动的时候，会有旋涡；水域平静的地方，会有旋涡；水域聚集的地方，也会有旋涡。一共有九种类型的旋涡，我只向他展示了三种。如果可以，你再把他带来。”

第二天他们两个又来见他。可是，都还没有坐定，巫师就慌慌张张地跑掉了。壶子说：“去追他！”

列子在后面追他。但是追不上他。回来后他对壶子说：“他跑了，我没追上。我追不上他。”

壶子说：“我只是向他展示迄今尚未揭示的潜能。我所展示的自己不知道谁是谁，也不知道何物是何物。我达到随心所欲地流转和变化。因此他才逃离。”

由此，列子意识到迄今为止真正的道他什么都没学到，所以他就回家了。三年期间他从不出门。他为妻子做饭，像待人一样养猪。对于学业他毫无兴趣。他排除自己的欲望，追求真理。他的身体如同变成了土地一般。万物之中，他一直与一相合，终身如此。

不要渴求名望。

不要谋划打算。

不要尽力作为。

不要努力求知。

保持自然，但不要将其视为任何。

配合天赋予的一切，但不求拥有。

只是保持虚无。

完美之人心如明镜。

它不探求事物。

它不寻找事物。

它不寻求知识，只作回应。

故能应对一切，不受伤害。

……

踏上真理之路的人不会丢失内在天性。

对于这样的人，那联合的没有问题；

那分开的没有关系；

那长的不会太长；

那短的不会太短。

比方说，鸭子的腿短，

但要拉长会造成痛苦。

鹤的腿长，

但要缩短会导致忧伤。

天生为长的我们不应削减，

天生为短的我们不应拉长。

因为那是无济于事的。

或许，可以说，仁和义不是人性所固有的？看看那些想要表现友善的人所忍受的焦虑有多少吧。

第五部分　惠子

惠子对庄子说：“魏王给了我一颗大葫芦的种子，我种了，长出的果实很大，足以盛五斗多的任何东西。于是我就用它盛水，结果装满后太沉了都提不起来。我就把它切成两半来做瓢，但是又太笨拙了，根本没法用。不是说它们不够大，我只是发现我不会使用它们，所以我就把它们毁掉了。”

庄子说：“惠子啊，问题当然是你不知道如何使用大东西了。宋国有一个人，他能制作一种乳膏，保护双手不龟裂，于是他的家人就一代一代地以漂洗丝绸为生。一位行人听说之后便提出用一百黄金购买这个秘方。所有的家庭成员聚到一起商量如何回复，说：‘我们一代一代地漂洗丝绸，可是赚的钱不足数金；现在一个早上我们就可以赚得一百金！卖了吧。’于是这位行人得到了秘方就前去见吴王。吴王正与越国进行争战。吴王授权行人指挥军队，冬天最寒冷的时候他们在水上与越人作战，对越人施以了毁灭性打击，行人则获赠了他所征服区域中的一大块土地作为奖赏。同样防止双手龟裂的乳膏却导致两种情形：一人获得了封地，而其他人却止步于一直漂洗丝绸，因为他们使用这个秘方的方法如此不同。那，先生，你有一个大葫芦，足以盛五斗，可是你为何不用它来做大瓶子，这样你就可以借此在河湖上漂流了，而不是把它们看作无用之物处理掉呢？惠子啊，是因为你脑子长草了啊！”

惠子对庄子说：“我有一棵大树，人们都说没用。它的树干到处是结，没有木匠愿意加工它，而且它的树枝是那样弯弯曲曲，没法用直尺和圆规丈量。所以，尽管它长在路旁，所有木匠都不屑一顾。先生，您所发表的言论，浮夸而无用，因此所有人都不屑一顾。”

庄子说：“先生，你难道没有见过野猫和黄鼠狼吗？它趴在那，弯曲着身子等待；它东蹦西跳，也不管高低；直到落入陷阱，死在网罗之中。还有牦牛，它就像天空中的云那么庞大。它是大，但是不能凭此事实就可捉老鼠。现在，先生你，有一棵大树却不知怎么用。那你为何不把它种在旷野之中，然后你就可以去漫游或在树荫下休憩呢？天下没有斧头会攻击它，不会缩短它的寿命，因为事物若无用便再也不会感到不安了。”

……

惠子问庄子：“一个人有没有可能没有任何情绪？”

庄子说：“当然。”

惠子问：“一个人没有情绪了——你还可以称他为人吗？”

庄子答道：“道赋予他面容，天提供给他形体，怎么能得出结论说他不能被称为人呢？”

“如果他已被称为人，怎么能得出他没有情绪呢？”

庄子说：“我所说的情绪不是这个意思。当我说一个人没有情绪，我是说一个人不让善恶影响他。他万事顺其自然，让生命以它自己的方式延续。”

惠子说：“若他不干预生命，那他又如何照看自己呢？”

“道赋予他面容，天提供给他形体。他不让善恶影响自己。可是你现在呢，你把灵魂穿在衣袖上，竭尽气力撑着自己站在树上喃喃而语，或者，趴在桌子上睡觉。天赋予你形体，你却在无意义的争辩之中将其耗尽。”

……

惠子被任命为梁国的宰相，庄子前去见他。有人告诉惠子说：“庄子要来了，因为他要取代你的位置。”这让惠子很惊恐，他花了三天三夜搜遍了全国，想要找出这个陌生人。

庄子去见他时说：“南方有一种鸟叫作雏凤，先生，你知道吗？这种鸟，它从南海升起，飞向北海。它只在海棠树上休憩，只吃楝树的果实，只喝甘泉中的水。曾经有一只猫头鹰，爪子上紧抓着一只快要腐烂的老鼠的尸体，抬头瞥见它就说：‘嘘！’我说你啊，先生，你主政梁国，你就觉得有必要把我吓唬走吗？”

庄子和惠子一同在濠水的堰堤上散步，庄子就说：“你看到鱼儿是怎样跃出水面、随心所欲地游来游去了吗？这就是鱼真正的快乐。”

惠子说：“你又不是鱼，你如何知道鱼喜欢什么？”

庄子说：“你又不是我，你怎么知道我不知道鱼喜欢什么。”

惠子说：“我不是你，所以我肯定不知道你到底知道什么。不过，很显然你也不是鱼，你必然也不知道鱼真正喜欢什么。”

庄子说：“哎，如果你不介意，还是让我们回到你最开始的问题吧。你问我如何知道鱼真正的快乐到底是什么。因此，你问这个问题的时候，你已经知道我是知道的。而且我也是因为站在濠水的堰堤上才知道的。”

……

庄子的妻子死了，惠子前来安慰他，可这时庄子正坐着，两腿交叉，一边猛敲一个毁坏的浴盆，一边唱歌。

惠子说：“你们作为夫妻一起生活，她养育了你的子女。她死了，你不哭也就罢了，却大声敲着浴盆唱歌，这怎么可以！”

庄子说：“当然不可以了。她刚去世时，我跟所有人一样，很是忧伤。可是，我随后想到了她的出生，她生命最初的情形，还想到她出生之前。实际上，不仅是她出生之前，还有她的形体被创造之前。不仅是她的形体被创造之前，还有她生命的气息最初开始之前。从这一切之中，通过奇妙的神秘变化她被赋予了生命的气息。她的生命气息发生转化，她便具有了形体。她的形体再发生转化，她便出生了。现在转化又要发生了，她便死去。她就如同一年四季一样，春夏秋冬交替更迭。她现在躺在坟墓中安息了，如果我还要呜咽哭泣，必然显得我不明白命运的道理。所以我才停止哭泣。”

……

庄子说：“一个弓箭手，都懒得瞄准，全然凭借运气射中了靶心。我们可以称他为好射手，可是如果那样的话，那么天下所有人都可以称作神射手羿了，这样可以吗？”

惠子说：“可以。”

庄子说：“对于什么事情在他们心中才是正确的，人们意见迥异，但是每个人都知道他认为正确的事情。因此世界上每个人都可以被称作尧，是这样的吗？”

惠子说：“可以。”

庄子说：“那么，有四个学派——儒家、墨家、杨朱和公孙龙——再算上先生你自己，一共五派。那么哪一派是正确的呢？或者更像是鲁遽那样呢？他的一个弟子曾说：‘我已经掌握了你的道，先生，我冬天可以为壶加热，夏天可以让水结冰。’鲁遽说：‘这只是用阳气于阳气，用阴气于阴气，不是我所说的道。让我来向你展示我的道。’他给两把琵琶调好音，一把放在大厅，一把放在内室。在一把琵琶上弹奏宫音，另一把琵琶上也会响起宫音。角音也是一样，因为乐器之间是协调一致的。然后他对其中一把琵琶进行了重新调音，使它与五个主音完全不合。当这把琵琶演奏时，另一琵琶琴弦的二十五个音响起，与这把琵琶琴弦的音完全一致且均跟随这把琵琶的音而起。那么，如果你坚持你是正确的，那不正是如此吗？”

惠子说：“孔子、墨子、杨朱和公孙龙的弟子想要跟我辩论，每个人都想击败其他人，每个人都想用各种辩论的声音猛烈地压倒我——但是他们都没能成功。这个你怎么看？”

庄子说：“齐国有人将儿子卖到宋国做看门人，从不担心儿子有任何差池。但也正是此人却竭尽全力去保护他的钟铃。但是他不会跨过他自己国家的边界去寻找他的儿子，这就是他所理解的有价值的事。或者，那个著名的人物，身体残废作看门人的楚国人，要是他半夜在另一个国家想要跟一个船夫打架会怎样呢？结果是他绝对过不了河，只能惹得船夫生气。”

……

惠子和庄子辩论，说：“你说的话没用！”

庄子说：“你只有明白了何为无用，才能讨论何为有用。天地是大，可是人类也只能使用他们行走于其上的那宇宙的一小部分。即便如此，若是你在自己脚下深挖不止，直到黄泉，谁又能从中受用呢？”

惠子说：“没用。”

庄子说：“因此，的确如此，没用的显然是有用的。”

庄子继续说：“如果有人渴望去旅行，什么才能阻止他呢？要是有人不愿去旅行，那么什么才能鼓动他呢？不论是在随波逐流中隐藏自己，还是远离人群以寻求遗忘，都不能通达得道。他们踉跄跌倒，却无法恢复从前。他们走向毁灭，如火焰一般，从不回头。即便他们是君主与群臣的关系，也会成为过去。这些头衔随时代变化，便无贵贱之分了。人都说完美之人行动从不留痕。

“尊古蔑今，学者皆如此。即便狶韦氏的弟子，就算他们以同样的方式看待当下，也会被不分好歹地清除。唯有完美之人能够处世而不偏颇，追随他人而不迷失自我。他不吸取他们的说教，他只是听了且懂了，不作任何承诺。

眼睛锐利才能看得清楚；

耳朵敏锐才能听得清楚；

鼻子灵敏才能辨别味道；

嘴巴敏锐才能享受美味；

内心感受深刻方有智慧；

智慧深入骨髓便是道德。

“万有之中，道不会被阻塞，因为若受阻，便透不过气；若透不过气，便产生混乱。混乱则毁灭万物的生命。凡活着的都要呼吸。可是，若无法呼吸，也不能怪天。天日夜不停地寻求气息在身体中运行：是人在妨碍气息运行。子宫要有它的空间，心要有属天的旅程。要是房间不够大，婆媳之间将起争执。要是心不能在天际遨游，感觉的六种开端会彼此竞争。大森林、丘陵和山脉在精神上都胜过人类，因为它们是不可战胜的。

“道德满溢，会造就名声；追求名声的欲望过度，就只是过度。有危机，才有谋划；有争论，才有知识。顽疾让人痛下决心，正式的行动产生于万物的欲望。春天到了，雨水会伴着阳光而来，草木蓬勃生长，人们又一次准备好收割的工具。曾经倒下的，又有一半开始发芽，没有人知道到底是为什么。

安静对于病人有疗效；

按摩对老人是有益的；

静静的沉思能让忧伤之人平静。

确实，只有不安之人需要这些。

不受困扰的自在之人却不需要。

圣人革新天下万物，可神人从不询问其方法。

贤人改善他的时代，可圣人从不询问其方法。

君主治理他的国家，可贤人从不询问其方法。

小人总是将就应付，可君主从不询问其方法。

“演门的看门人父亲过世，他因施加于自身的极度苦行而受到赞扬，被授予模范官员的称号。这个地方的其他一些人也采取了类似极端的行为，结果死了一半的人。尧要将国家让给许由，许由就逃跑了。汤要将他的王国让给务光，务光大发脾气。纪他听说此事，便和他的弟子隐退到窾水边，三年里当地的诸侯都来表示对他的同情。也因同样的原因，申徒狄纵身跳入黄河。渔网用于捕鱼，可是得了鱼之后渔网就被忘记了。兔网用来捕兔，可是捕得了兔子之后兔网就被忽略了。言词用来表达概念，可是一旦你掌握了概念就把言词遗忘了。我想找那忘记言词之人，这样我就可以和此人辩论了。”

……

庄子参加一个葬礼时路过惠子的坟墓。他环顾了一下跟随他的人们，说：“郢地有一个人将泥点弄在鼻尖上，那泥点如同苍蝇的翅膀一样小。他让人请来匠人石将其削去。石挥动斧子将其削去，斧子砍过去时造成一阵风，恰好将郢人鼻子上泥土的痕迹消除掉，郢人站着不动，心中毫不担心。宋元君听说此事便召匠人石来见他。

“他说：‘你能行好给我演示一次吗？’

“匠人石回答说：‘我确实曾成功过一次，不过可以让我施展的那个人早就已经死了。

“‘自从先生去世以后，我就没有合适之人来施展了。我再也没有可以谈话的对象了。’”

第六部分　马蹄

马有蹄，故四脚可以稳立于霜雪；马有毛，因此才能抵御风寒。它们吃草喝水，高跃飞奔，因为这是马的天性。即便给它们高塔大殿，它们也不会感兴趣的。可是，当伯乐问世后，就说：“我知道如何训练马。”他为它们做标记、剪毛、削蹄，在头上套上缰绳，给它们戴上笼头，使它们步履蹒跚，并将它们关在马厩里。如此，十匹马中至少有两到三匹会死掉。然后他让它们挨饿、口渴，让它们飞驰奔跑，教练它们步伐整齐。前怕嚼子和缰绳，后怕鞭子和鞭条；马因为这个已经死了一大半了。

陶工说：“我知道如何使用粘土，塑成圆形好似圆规，塑成方形就如同用了矩尺一样。”木工说：“我知道如何使用木材，要弯的，我就用模具；要直的，我就用准绳。”可是，粘土和木材的天性真的是要用圆规和矩尺、模具和准绳来塑造吗？但无论如何，一代又一代的人都说：“伯乐擅长控制马，陶工和木工擅长使用粘土和木材。”这倒是真的。而且那些治理世界的人们滔滔不绝地重复着同样的无稽之谈。

我认为真正懂得治理世界的人不是这样的。百姓有自然的天性，他们织布做衣服，耕作以生产食物。这是他们的基本道德。禀赋纯一，而不偏私，这叫作天然的放任。因而，在完美道德的时代，百姓行动稳重，眼神专注。这样的时代，山上没有道路也没有隧道，湖上没有船只也没有桥梁；万物同类而居，共处而生。鸟群和兽群不断增加，草木长高。在这样的时代，事实上鸟兽不用绳索便可让人带领着一起遨游，鸟巢也可让人自在地去观看。

在完美道德的时代，百姓与鸟兽共处，和万物共同分享这个世界。没有人会区分贵族和农民！完全无知但拥有永不消逝的道德；完全没有欲望，人们纯素朴实。纯素朴实，这就能保住人们的本性。可随后完美的圣人出现了，无休止地传布仁慈，努力施行公义，于是突然间所有人都开始疑惑了。他们开始过度关心音乐，对礼仪修修补补，因此整个世界都不安起来。如果纯正的本质没有如此被约束，他们怎么会最后反而要使用祭祀的碗呢？如果原始的玉石没有被碎开，怎么可能会被制成权利的标志呢？如果道和德——方式和道德——没有被忽视，仁慈和公义又怎么会被推崇呢？如果天性没有被遗忘，又怎么会发明礼仪和音乐呢？如果五色没有被混淆，又怎么会出现格式和设计呢？如果五音没有被混淆，它们怎么可能会被六律所取代呢？滥用真正的元素去制作人工制品是匠人的罪过。滥用道和德——方式和道德——来树立仁慈和公义，这是圣人的过错。

马在野外生存的时候，吃草喝水；高兴时，它们交颈摩擦。生气时，它们背对彼此互相踢踏。这就是马所知道的一切。如果套上马具被强制列队，它们学会了看向旁边、弯曲颈部、四处猛冲、努力吐出马嚼子、摆脱缰绳。马因此学到的知识和种种恶行事实上都是伯乐的过错啊。

第七部分　博学何用？

制作弓箭、十字弓、网罗等需要丰富的知识，可结果是鸟儿在困境中越飞越高。制作鱼线、圈套、鱼饵和鱼钩需要丰富的知识，可结果是鱼儿面对危险在水中四散而逃。制作陷阱、圈套和网罗需要丰富的知识，可结果是动物被惊扰，纷纷躲藏入沼泽地中。同样地，花言巧语、密谋策划、散播谣言、强词夺理、发起争论和表面妥协都需要众多才艺，可结果只能是人们变得困惑了。因此，天下万物之所以处于不安之中就是因为对于知识的追求。世上万物皆知如何寻求他们尚未掌握的知识，却不知如何寻找他们已经知道的。世上万物皆知非难他们所不喜欢的，却不知道非难他们所已经喜好的。这就是造成天下大乱的原因。这就像是：在上，日月的光明被遮蔽；在下，山川丧失了它们的力量；四时的天然运行遭到破坏。微小的昆虫，甚至是植物，无不丧失了它们的天性。这就是世界追求知识的后果。自三代至今，一直如此。善良诚实的人被忽视，懦弱奉承的人却受到推崇。无为而为的平静被弃绝，争吵辩论却备受追捧。正是这种无稽之谈让天下万物如此困惑起来。

……

人们太快乐了吗？若是事实，就会伤及阳气。人们复仇之心太重了吗？假若如此，就会伤及阴气。若阴阳二气都受损，四时更替会被打乱，寒暑平衡会被打破，终将危及人的身体！人们将不能在快乐和忧愁之间掌握平衡。这会让人们永不停息，东奔西跑，无目的地谋划，无理由或徒劳地旅行。结果是整个世界开始关注宏大的目的计划、野心和仇恨，随后就会产生盗跖、曾参和史䲡之徒。总之，虽然世界可能想要奖赏善人，却没有足够多的奖赏；世界也不能惩罚所有的恶人，因为没有足够多的惩罚。

……

因此，君子若发现治理世界必须按照某种方法，便会意识到无为而为就是最好的方法。做到无为，他便可以安身于自然和天命的真实本质之中。如果他像珍重自己的身体一样治理世界，那么世界便可由他来治理。如果他像爱自己的身体一样爱世界，便可将世界交付给他。如果君子能够使其五官免遭毁坏，当然还有他的视野和听觉；如果他可以像死尸一般静处，而开发他的龙之力量；如果他能如此保持平静，他的话语将如雷鸣，他的行动将被视为天之灵在行动，是受天的指引。如果他从容自在、无为而为，他那温和的灵魂会将万物引向他，如尘云一般。如此之人怎么还会有时间来治理世界呢？

……

云将乘着旋风之翼，到东方游历。突然他碰到鸿蒙，鸿蒙正跳来跳去，拍着大腿像鸟儿一样跳跃。云将看到此景，停了下来。静静地站着，心怀敬意，他问：“老人家，您是何人？在做什么呢？”

鸿蒙继续拍着大腿像鸟儿一样跳跃，答道：“正玩得高兴呢！”

云将说：“我想请教一个问题。”

鸿蒙看着云将说：“不知羞耻！”

云将说：“天的气息不再和谐，地的气息也落入圈套，六气不再混合，四时不再更替。现在我想聚合六气而赋予万物生气。我该怎么办呢？”

鸿蒙拍着大腿，四处跳跃，说道：“我不知道，我不知道！”

这个问题云将无法继续问了。可是三年后，东游时，他路过宋国的郊野，再次碰到了鸿蒙。云将非常高兴，快步走向前去，站在他面前说：“天哪，您还记得我吗？天哪，您还记得我吗？”他两次叩首，请求鸿蒙为他指点。

鸿蒙说：“四处遨游，却不知道为什么。鲁莽冲动，却不知道到哪里去。我就是这样古怪地四处遨游，我明白万物产生皆有因。我又知道些什么呢？”

云将说：“我也是鲁莽冲动的，可是我到哪儿人们就跟到哪儿。现在，因为他们都跟随我，我就想得到您的指教。”

鸿蒙说：“破坏天道扰乱了万物的真正存在，妨碍了天之奥秘的圆满。这导致了动物四散，鸟儿整夜鸣唱，庄稼和树木遭殃，连昆虫都受灾毁灭了。唉，所有这些都是由于人们错误地认为他们懂得治理之道而引起的呀！”

云将说：“那我该做什么呢？”

鸿蒙说：“哦，就让他们痛苦吧！就像鬼魂，我要像鬼魂一样跳着舞离开了。”

云将说：“我很难见您一面，哦，天哪，就再给我些指点吧。”

鸿蒙说：“咳！要强大你的心。确保无为而为，万物自然就会化生。丢下你的躯体，放弃你的视力和听力，忘记你是谁，与那浩瀚和虚无合而为一。放松内心，解放心灵，如同没有灵魂一般平静。所有生灵会返回它们的本元，不知所以地返回它们的本元。一直处于黑暗之中，一直处于黑暗之中，在它们整个存在期间，永远不能摆脱。如果你努力去理解，它们就会摆脱。不要问其名，不要寻其形。如此万物自然而生。”

云将答道：“天哪，您以此品德让我受宠，以此神秘让我受教；我一生所求，现在终于得到了。”他两次叩首后起身，告辞而去了。

第八部分　无为之为是谓天

是故圣人冥思于天却并不辅助天。

关心如何完善道德又不为其拖累。

他们依道而行而不谋划。

他们行仁慈却不依赖它。

他们广施公义却不欲加积累。

他们遵守礼仪却不借此厚积。

他们为不得不为之事，并且绝对不会逃避责任。

他们尽力适用他们的法律但并不认为它们有效。

他们重视百姓，不会随便使用他们。

他们利用万物，不会轻易拒绝它们。

没错，万物虽无用但必须加以利用。

谁不明白天，谁就无法在道德上保持纯粹。

谁不理解道，谁就不能理解任何其他方法。

那些不明道的人，可悲啊！

可是这里的道又是什么呢？

有天之道；

有人之道。

无为而让人尊敬：是天之道。

反过来积极有为：是人之道。

天之道才是君主；

人之道只是仆人。

二者间相差犹如两极。

不能不对此深思熟虑。

……

天与地虽然都广阔无垠，

其多样性却只源于一处。

尽管生命形式成千上万，

它们的秩序却是一致的。

我们人类虽然数量众多，

却只受一个君主的统治。

他根于道德，完美于天。

人们说在很久很久以前，

天下万物的君主统治靠：

无为、天道，别无他物。

……

通过无为而有所作为是谓天。

有关于无为的言论是谓道德。

爱众人并助其成功是谓仁慈。

联合那尚未联合的是谓伟大。

超越各种障碍边界是谓宽容。

拥有大量丰富之物是谓富有。

拥有并能坚守道德是谓纲领。

成长直至道德成熟是谓坚定。

与道始终保持一致是谓完满。

拒绝让外物困扰你是谓完美。

君子如果清楚地明白这十个道理，他的事业也将是高尚的，他的行为终将造福万物。

这样的人会让金子留在山中，

还会让珍珠继续待在深渊里。

他不视金钱物品为真正的利，

也不会为名望和财富所诱惑，

不会以长寿为乐，夭亡为悲；

他不重视财富，以财富为福，

也不会因为贫穷而感到羞耻。

他不求将天下财富占为己有，

也不愿统治世界而据为私有。

他的荣耀在于明了万物一体，

死亡和出生也是相互统一的。

圣者大师说：

“道，多么深奥，多么安静；

多么明白，又多么纯净啊！

没有它，金石都无法共鸣。

虽然金石自身都可以发声，

但如果不敲击，就没有声。

万物皆有无法计量的维度。”

……

谆芒说：“什么是圣人治理之道？只委任那些与职位相适宜的人；只根据被任命之人的价值来任命；只在充分了解情形之后再采取行动。如果行为和言语相一致，整个世界都被改变。结果是，只要手一挥或者一个眼神，全世界的百姓都会奔向你。这就是圣人治理之道。”

“我能请教什么是有德之人吗？”

“有德之人安静无思：

行动之时没有谋划；

不测算是非与善恶。

有德之人与四海内

所有人分享其所得，

并能从中获得乐趣。

他们分享所拥有的，

并且因此感到满足。

悲伤时，他们就像

是失去母亲的孩子。

疑惑时，他们就像

是迷了路的旅行者。

虽大量财富与安逸

被降福到他们身上，

他不知其从何而来；

虽吃喝充足而有余，

他不知其从何而来。

此有德之人的风格。”

“那么神人又当如何？”谆芒说：

“灵魂上升至最强之光

而他们的身体消失了。

他们荣耀般欣喜若狂。

他们活出自己的命运，

始终追求真正的自己，

处在天地的快乐之中，

而种种忧虑都消逝了。

万物复归其真正天性。

这被人称为最初奥秘。”

……

运行时毫不积聚，这就是天之道，

因此一切生命形式都能实现完美。

运行时毫不积聚，也是帝王之道，

所以全世界都将臣服于他的脚下。

运行时毫不积聚，还是圣人之道，

因此四海之内的一切都尊敬他们。

明了天，理解圣人，遨游于宇宙，

遵守帝王君主道德的同时做自己：

这就是那些能够了悟的人的天性，

看似毫无所知却是处于静止而已。

圣人是不活动的，不是因为不活动有什么价值，他们只是静止不动而已。即便众人也不能使他烦恼，因此他们是平静的。水面静止时，能够将你的眉毛胡须都映照出来。水面完全水平，都可以作为木匠的水平仪。如果静止的水面能够如此清明，想象一下纯净的灵魂可以提供什么吧！圣人的心是静止的！天地可以映在其中，好比万物之镜。虚空、静止、平静、朴素、寂静、安静、无为，这是天地道德的核心。帝王、君主和圣人皆止息于此。止息，他们才虚空；虚空，他们才能充实；充实才能圆满。虚空才有清定；在清定中他们可以旅行；在旅行中他们到达。静定，就能够无为；无为，任事者就各有专责了。通过无为之为，他们高兴，很是高兴；高兴到不受任何担心忧虑的影响，完全没有它们的一席之地，因此他们的寿命持续很久。虚空、静止、平静、朴素、寂静、安静，无为之为是万物的根本。如果你明白此理而去南面临朝，便是尧一般的君上；如果你明白此理而去北面朝君，便是舜一般的臣下。

……

庄子说：

我的老师啊！我的老师啊！

他评判万物却不感觉到自己爱批评；

他的慷慨及于万世却不以此为仁慈；

他比最古老的还长寿却不自视年长；

他覆天载地创造众生却不自认灵巧。

这就是所谓属天的幸福。

“有一种说法：‘如果你知道天的幸福，那么你就明白生命自天来，死亡只是万物的变化。静止时，他们是阴，而运行时，他们是阳。’知晓属天的幸福意味着你不得扰乱天，也不得与他人作对。你不为外物所累，也不受鬼神责谴。还有一种说法：‘他随天而动，与地同憩，他的心为一，他是全世界的王；鬼神不能使他担忧，他的灵魂不知疲乏，他的心与所有生灵为一。’意思是说他的虚空和静止进入到天地万物之中，与万物一同运行。这就是属天的幸福。属天的幸福是圣人的心；这就是他们照看天下万物的方法。”

帝王君主之德以天地为父母，以道德为师，以无为作为核心。通过无为之为，他们能让全世界随其所愿而不知疲倦。通过作为，他们甚至无法开始满足世界的需要。因此古人重视无为之为。

……

因此，世上古代的君主虽对天地了如指掌，却从不谋划；即便他们了解生命的全部，他们也从不说出来；尽管他们的能力比四海所环绕的土地上任何一个人都大，他们却什么都不做。

天什么都不生产，

可万物都在变化；

地什么都不维持，

可万物都被供养；

帝王和君主无为，

却能治理全世界。

有一种说法就说：

没有比天更崇高，

没有比地更富足，

没有比帝王更加伟大的了。

……

因此，是古人清晰地掌握了伟大的道，率先追寻天的意义，然后又寻求它的道和德的意义。

当他们清楚明了道和德时，

他们就懂得了仁慈和公义。

当他们清楚掌握仁与义时，

他们能明白如何履行义务。

当他们知道如何尽义务时，

他们就懂得了形式与名声。

当他们理解形式与名声时，

他们就有能力任命职位了。

当他们有能力进行任命时，

他们进而监督人们的工作。

当他们监督人们的工作时，

他就要对善与恶进行评判。

当他们作出了善恶评判时，

他们就要进行惩罚和奖励。

……

从前，舜对尧说：“作为天子，你如何用心？”

尧说：“我不会怠慢那毫无抵抗之人，也不会忽视那贫穷之人。我为那死者哀伤，并照看孤儿寡母。这就是我的用心之道。”

舜评论说：“好倒是好，但还不够开朗。”

尧说：“那我该怎么做呢？”

“天德发现之时，山峦为之高兴，日月为之闪耀，四季交替运行。日夜交替的常规模式随即产生，雨云也应时而动。”

尧说：“那么我一直以来所做的一切只是徒增烦扰啊！你寻求顺从于天，而我却一直寻求符合于人。”

……

孔子向西而行，打算将其图书藏于周的档案室里。子路建议道：“我听说掌管皇家档案室的官员是老子。但是他已经辞职回家了。先生，如果你想把你的书放在那里，就去见见他，请求他帮帮忙。”

孔子说：“好。”于是他就去见老子，但是老子拒绝帮忙。于是他就拿出他的十二经，开始说教。

当他说到一半时，老子说：“说得也太多了。简要一点。”

孔子说：“从根本上说，就是仁义。”

老子说：“我可否问你，仁义不正是人的本性吗？”

孔子说：“当然。如果君子没有仁，他就没有目的；如果没有义，他就没有生命。仁义，的确是人的天性。不然还能是什么呢？”

“我可否问你，什么是仁义？”

孔子答道：“万物一体，内心平和，兼爱万物，毫无私心，这就是仁义。”

老子说：“其实，你所说的本身就让人误解。‘兼爱万物’，这么说既含糊不清又夸大其词！‘毫无私心’，这难道不是已经有私心了吗？先生，如果你想让百姓保持淳朴，你难道不应当依靠天地之道吗？

天与地各自都有其永恒不变的区域；

太阳和月亮在它们的轨道上发着光；

星辰在其秩序允许的范围之内运行；

鸟与动物在鸟群和兽群中找到归属。

想想那井然有序各自站立的树木吧！

“因此，先生，遵循德行走，按照道前行，你就会抵达完美的终点。又何必靠着所有这些仁义，一路昂首阔步，就像敲着鼓去寻找一个丢失的孩子？先生，你只是扰乱了人们的天性而已！”

……

老子说：

“道不会在大事物前踌躇，

也不会丢弃那小的事物。

故万物因道而焕发生气。

它那样巨大，那样浩瀚，

没有什么是它不包容的；

它那么高深，那么叵测，

超出了可以思考的边界。

道德形式寓于仁义之中，

尽管只是其精神的一瞥。

除了完美之人谁能理解？

完美之人掌控他的时代，

有点令人畏惧的任务啊！

但这不会愚弄或困住他。

他拥有掌控世界的权力，

但这对他来说无足轻重。

他所有的谬误皆可洞悉，

却从来不计算个人得失。

他直达问题的核心并且

懂得如何保护真理之本。

因此，天地皆在他之外，

他遗忘万物，精神抖擞。

他与道同行，与德相合，

与仁义告别，遗忘礼乐，

因为完美之人早将自己

的心安放在了真理之上。”

这一代人认为在书本中能发现道的价值。但是书本只是语言，语言有了意义才有价值。意义就是不停地寻求表达语言无法传达的意义。这一代人看重语言并将其载入书中，但是他们所看重的可能只是误解，因为他们所看重的不一定全都是那么有价值的。所以，我们用眼看事物，看到了，但也只是外在的形式和颜色，我们所听的也只是名称和声音。这一代人还想象着形式、颜色、名称和声音就足以认识事物的根本，多么可悲啊！形式、颜色、名称和声音绝不足以把握或揭示真理，这就是为什么说知者不言、言者不知。可是，这一代人如何才能明白这个道理呢？

第九部分　天在动吗？

天在动吗？地静止不动吗？

日月会争执该去往何处吗？

谁又是所有这一切的主宰？

是谁在约束和控制着它呢？

谁会无所事事造就这一切？

是否存在某个隐藏的原因

让万物如此，不管其意愿？

或者是不是只是别无选择

万物才不得不运动和改变？

云为雨生还是雨使云聚呢？

是什么使它们存在？是谁

无为却能造就这快乐满溢？

风从北面吹来，西奔东跑，

旋转而上，不知去向何方？

它们是谁的气息呢？是谁

无为却能创造这一切活动？

……

桓公正坐在堂上读书，车匠扁在堂下制作车轮。他放下自己的凿子和锤子，来到堂上问桓公：“我可否问您，先生，您读的是什么言论呢？”

桓公答道：“圣人之言。”

“这些圣人都还活着吗？”

桓公说：“他们都死了很久了。”

“那么，先生，您读的不过是这些古人留下的糟粕罢了！”

桓公怒斥：“你一个车匠，怎敢对我读的书评头论足！要是你能说出理由便罢，要不然你就得死！”

车匠扁就回答说：“陛下，小人我是从自己工作的角度来看的。当我做轮子的时候，如果我用力过于柔和，尽管这样会很舒适，但是不会作出好轮子。如果我用力过猛，我就会疲倦，作出来的也不会成功！所以，不能太柔和，也不能太用力，我在手上把握，在心里把持。我嘴里说不出来，但我就是知道。这个我无法教给我儿子，我儿子也不能从我这里学会。因此，七十年来我一直沿着这条路前行，现在我还在做轮子。古人死时便跟他想说的话一同离开了。这就是我为什么说陛下您在读的仅仅是这些古人留下的糟粕而已！”

……

孔子虚度了五十一年，从未听任何人说起过道，直到他南下来到沛地，前去拜见了老子。

老子说：“你来了啊，先生？我听说过你，说你是北方的智者。先生，你理解了道了吗？”

孔子答道：“我还没有理解呢。”

“好吧，先生，你于何处求道的呢？”

“我是在那可以被衡量和规定的内容之中寻求的，可是虽然花了五年时间，我还是没能够找到。”

“那么，先生，你接下来怎么做的呢？”

“我又于阴阳之中寻找，但是十年、十二年过去了，我仍然不能有所发现。”

老子说：“当然了！如果道可以被进献的话，人人都会向其君上进献了。如果道可以被进奉的话，没有不向其父母进奉的。如果道可以被言说，没有人会不告知其兄弟姐妹。如果道可以被传递，没有人会不传给他的后人。可是，道显然不是这样的，理由就是：

如果心中没有一个真正的中心

来接受它，那么道不可能停留；

如果心外没有一个真正的方向

来引导它，那么道不可能传达。

如果心中那真正的中心不能够

向外发散，就无法在外有所得。

可即便圣人也无法将它引出来。

如果那从外面进入内心的事物

在真正的中心不被欢迎，那么

就算圣人也不能就放手不管了。”

……

孔子去拜见老子，跟他谈论仁义。老子说：“如果你簸扬糠皮时眼睛里进去了沙砾，天地和四方都要变得混乱了。蚊虻叮咬会让你整晚无法入睡。仁义呢，如果强加给我们，会扰乱我们的内心，造成极大的不安。先生，你如果想让天下万物免于丧失其最初的质朴，你必须随风而行，坚定地立于道德之上。你为何如此用力，如同敲着大鼓去寻找丢失的孩子？那雪白色的鹅无须天天洗澡去保持洁白，那乌鸦也不必天天染色来保持乌黑。黑与白源自天然的质朴，而不是靠争辩。名声和财富，即便得到了，也不能让人们更伟大。当水域干涸时，鱼儿搁浅在陆地上，它们挤在一起，尽量通过吐沫打湿彼此来保持湿润。但是，如果它们能安全地待在江湖之中而忘记彼此，这样岂不是更好吗？”

拜见完老子后，孔子回到家中，整整三天一句话不说。他的弟子问他：“先生，您见过老子了，请问您如何看待他呢？”

孔子说：“我终于见到了龙！龙盘绕以现形，伸展以展示力量。它驾着云气，在阴阳之中滋养。我只有张大了嘴不能合拢。关于老子我又能说什么呢？”

……

古人虽然谈论得志，但他们并不是指官家马车和职位徽章。他们仅仅是指幸福是如此完满，无须增加任何东西。今天所谓得志是指拥有官家马车和职位徽章。马车和徽章作用于身体，它们不能碰触到内在的天性。这样的好事可能会不时地出现。当它们发生时，你无力阻拦，就像你也不能制止它们会再次离开一样。所以，拥有马车和徽章，我们也没有理由骄傲自大，同样，痛苦和穷困也不是我们沦于世俗的理由。将这两种情形看作是一样的，那么你就能够免于焦虑、顺其自然了。因此，如果那给你带来幸福的事物在消逝时给你带来烦恼，现在你就能明白这样的幸福是毫无价值的。所以说，那些在物质的欲望中迷失自己的人也会因为世俗而丧失内在的天性。他们被称为本末倒置之人。

第十部分　真实与幸福

秋日洪水的时节到了，一百条河流涌入黄河。河水翻腾，水面如此宽阔，从河岸望向对面，连牛马都不能分辨得出。此时，黄河之神毫无疑问很高兴，认为世界上最美的东西是属于他的。他顺流而下，向东而行，最终到达了北海。在这里他朝东望去，水域一眼望不到边。他这个黄河之神只得摇摇头，向外望去时刚好看到海神若，于是边叹气边说：

“俗话说：‘一个人自以为听了一百次道后，其他人就都比不上他了。’这说的就是我呀。我听说过人们嘲笑儒家的学识，轻视伯夷的公义，但是我不相信。现在我见识到了你无穷的广阔。要是我没有来到你的门前，我可能就危险了，会被那些懂得伟大方法之人嘲笑的。”

北海的若答道：“井底之蛙不能谈论大海，因为它被井的空间所限制。夏日的昆虫不能谈论冰，因为它只知道自己所属的季节。视野狭窄的学者不能谈论道，因为他被他的学说所限制。现在你已经走出了你的河岸并看到了大海。你现在知道自己的浅陋了，所以现在和你谈论大的道理也是可能的了。天下没有比海更广阔的水域了。千万条河流注入它，到目前所知从未终止过，可是它绝不会满溢。它向尾闾的里面注泄，但是海从未干涸。春天和秋天不会有任何变化。它从不关注洪水或干旱。它比长江和黄河的水加起来还多得多，根本无法估量。可是我从未因此而自以为了不起。我只是把自己跟天地相比较，我生命的气息自阴阳之中获得。与天地相比，我仅仅是大山上的小块石头或一棵小树。当我看到了我自己的浅陋，怎么可能还会骄傲呢？

“四海所充满的空间与天地之间的广阔比起来，不是像沼泽旁边的一堆石头吗？将中国与四海之内的大陆相比，不是像谷仓之中的一粒粮食吗？说到所有生灵，我们可以数出成千上万种，人类只不过是其中之一。人们居于九州之内，不论舟船可以通到哪里，人类也只是谷物所供养的所有生灵中的一部分。人类与众多生命形式相比，不就像马身上的一根毛吗？”

……

黄河之神说：“这个时代的议论者说：‘最精微的东西没有形体，最广大的东西无法限定。’这些话是真的吗？”

北海的若答道：“从最精微者的角度来看，我们看到那浩瀚广大的，不能够理解它。从最广大者的角度来看，我们要看那最精微的，就不可能看清楚。最精微的是那小的之中最小的，最广大的是那大的之中最大的；我们必须加以区分，即便这只能视情况而定。不过，那粗糙的和那精微的都有形体。没有形体，就不可能去计算它们。可以言说的是事物粗糙的一面，能够用意念捕捉的是事物精微的一面。但是那言语无法描述、意念也无法捕捉的，就与粗糙和精微毫不相关了。

“因此，伟大的人，在他的行动之中，不会去伤害别人，也不会宣扬仁义；他不会为了利益而行动，也不看轻门前的仆人；他不会争夺财产和财富，也不会过多表示礼让；他不请求别人的帮助，不夸耀他的自力更生，也不鄙视贪婪和吝啬之人；他不随波逐流，也不标榜特立独行；他追随众人，但不看重那靠谄媚获得成功的人。世间的头衔和荣耀，他不感兴趣，他也不在乎惩罚的羞辱。他知道，是与非、伟大与渺小都没有分别。我听有人说：‘得道之人没有名声，完美之德没有所得，伟大之人忘记自我。’多么完美，这就是他所遵循的道路。”

黄河之神问道：“不论是内在的还是外在的，我们怎么就有贵贱这样的区分？我们为什么要区分渺小和伟大？”

北海的若说：“从道的角度来看，事物既不高尚也不低劣。从事物的角度来看，万物皆视自己为高尚而视他物为低劣。从日常观念的角度来看，高尚和低劣都不是从个体事物的角度被理解的。考虑到不同的观点，某物如果因为它大的方面而被视为大，就意味着：众多事物中没有一个不能被视为是大的。同样，如果某物因为它小的方面就被视为小，那么万物都能被视为小。若我们知道天地就像一粒米那样小，或者发尖如同山脉绵延那样广大，那我们就明白了我们对大小的理解是相对的。从每个事物的功用角度来看，我们将某物视为有用是因为它有用，就意味着，在所有的为数众多的事物之中，每个事物都可以被视为是有用的。同样的，如果某物被视为无用只是因为它看似无用，那么万物均可被视为无用。如果我们知道东和西是相反的方向，而且还彼此需要，那么我们就能明白相互交流和相互作用是如何起作用的了。从选择的角度来看，如果某物被看作是好的是因为它毫无疑问是好的，那么在所有的为数众多的生命之中，没有什么是不好的。同样，如果某物被视为是错的是因为它毫无疑问是错的，那么没有哪个生命形式不能被视为是错的。”

……

“安静，安静，黄河之神！你如何能知道通往高贵或者卑贱的途径抑或伟大或渺小所在之处？”

黄河之神说：“好吧。那我能做什么，不能做什么呢？我怎么才能判断什么该保留、什么该拒绝或者什么该向往、什么该离弃呢？”

北海的若说：“从道的角度来看，何谓高贵、何谓卑贱，都只是永不停歇的变化。不要执著于你的想法，因为这是跟道的伟大相背离的。什么是少、什么是多，这些说法的用处是有限的。不要试图只是成为哪一个，这只能是凸显你偏离道有多远。要像毫不偏私的一国君主那样严肃端正。要高尚，像当地社神一样，人们供奉他，他赐福毫不偏私。要像天空一样开放，四方光亮而没有边界。你若慈爱照料万物，又怎么能偏爱哪个呢？这称之为不偏不倚。若视万物为一体，你又怎么能论及长短呢？道无始无终，但所有生灵皆有出生和死亡，所以你不能确信什么。这一刻它们是空的，下一刻就满了。它们是不能依靠的。时光不能倒流，也不能停止。衰退、成熟、充实和空虚，当它们结束后，又会重新开始。所以，我们可以谈论伟大的义，讨论万物的根本原则。生命力急速向前飞驰，不停地加速，每一刻都在改变，每一分都在变迁。至于说，我们应该做什么和不应该做什么？只有紧跟这变化的过程。”

黄河之神说：“如果是这样，那么道又有什么重要的呢？”

北海的若答道：“理解道就理解了原理。如果你理解了原理，当事情发生时你就知道该如何处理。知道了这个，你就能保证不会发生伤害自己的事了。如果有人具备完美之德，火不能伤害他，水也无法溺死他，寒冷酷热都不能影响他，鸟兽也不能伤害他。既然我说他避开了所有这些事情，只是说他能够分辨哪里是安全的、哪里是危险的。他自在应对祸与福，妥善处理要接近或避开什么，因此没有东西能伤害他。所以说，天是内在的，人是外在的，而德来自属天的。了解了天和人的行动，将自己根植于天之中，依德行事。然后你就能弯曲、伸展、前冲或后退，因为你总能回归根本，人们会说你已经达到至高了。”

“那你说什么是属天的？什么又是属人的呢？”

北海的若说：“牛有四脚：这就是我所说的属天的。如果马被戴上笼头，牛鼻被穿孔，我称此为人道。所以说，‘不要让那属人的取代那属天的。’不要让你的意图抵消天命。要小心，保护好它，不要丧失了，这就是我所谓的回归本真。”

一条腿的动物嫉妒千足虫；千足虫嫉妒蛇；蛇嫉妒风；风嫉妒眼睛；而眼睛嫉妒心。

一条腿的动物对千足虫说：“我有一只脚，虽然可以跳跃但几乎哪也去不了。可是先生你却有这么多的脚。你是如何做到的呢？”

千足虫说：“那可不一定。你难道没见过有人吐痰吗？吐出来一大团，紧跟着一堆唾沫星子，像小雨一样落下来，数都数不清。现在我只是发动那属天的机能，至于其他的——我没啥头绪！”

千足虫对蛇说：“我用所有这些脚随处走动，可是我却不能追上你，而先生你却一只脚都没有。为什么会这样？”

蛇说：“我是按照天的设计移动的，这我怎么控制得了呢？我能用脚来干什么呢！”

蛇对风说：“通过活动脊椎和肋骨，我才能前行，可至少我还有些可见的形体。可是先生你呢，从北海飞驰而来，向南海消逝而去，没有任何可见的形体。怎么会这样？”

风说：“没错，我从北海飞驰而来，向南海消逝而去。可是，事实上，若你用手指挥我，你就比我厉害，或者你用脚践踏我，你也能赢我。不过，我能刮倒大树，刮塌大屋，倒也是事实；而且只有我能做到。因此，谁若能战胜所有小问题实际上就是大胜者。做到大胜的，只有圣人才能够啊。”

……

公孙龙问魏牟：“我年轻的时候，学习先王之道，并且随着我不断成长，我清楚地明白仁义的重要性。我将同异合而为一，区分坚硬和白色、确定和不确定、可能和不可能。我努力理解百家哲学，驳倒他们的学说。我以为我已经明白了一切。可是，现在我听了庄子的言论，令我感到惊讶的是这些话让我感到不安起来。是我的知识不如他吗？或者是我的智慧不及他？我发现我都不能张口了，所以我想请教我该做什么。”

公子牟向前微倾，深深地叹了口气，然后仰天而望，笑着说：“先生啊，你难道没听说过破败老井中青蛙的故事吗？它对东海的乌龟说：‘我好高兴啊！我可以跳到井的壁沿之上，或者一路踏着破砖块跳入井中。当我跳入水中，我漂浮着，水托着我的下巴、两腿；在泥上，我可以把双脚深深地插入其中。我看着周围那些幼虫、螃蟹和蝌蚪，没有一个能比得上我的。能够完全控制一洼水，一点都不想动，只是享受这口老井，这太棒了！先生，你为什么不找个时间下来看看我呢？’

“东海的乌龟尝试了一下，但是它还没把左脚放入井中，它的右膝就被卡住了。这时候它停下来，曳脚后退出来，然后开始谈论大海：‘一千公里这样的距离不足以描述大海的长度，一千里格深也不足以表达其深度。在禹的时代，十年中有九年闹洪水，可是这也没能让海水升高一寸。在汤的时代，八年之中有七年闹旱灾，可是这也没能让海水降低一寸。没有什么能改变这些水域，不论从长远来看还是从短期来看；它们不会减退也不会升高，不会变大也不会变小。这就是东海的大快乐。’破败老井里的青蛙听了之后，非常惊奇；它彻底震惊，目瞪口呆，怅然若失。

“如果一个人的理解力尚不能应对这样的知识和是非之争，他若坚持想看清楚庄子的言论，就如同那想要背起一座大山的蚊子或者那想跑得跟黄河水一样快的虫子，明显是不可能的。如果一个人的理解力尚不能应对这样的知识和如此微妙的言论，他所能做的也只能是获得一些短期的回报。他就像那破败老井里的青蛙，难道不是吗？但是庄子没有扎根在地下黄泉，也没有跳跃登上苍天。没有南、北之分：他自在分散于四方，消失于深处。没有东、西之分：从最黑暗的深处出发，他重返伟大的道路之上。那么，先生你感到震惊，就想要精选他的一些观点加以批判或者通盘查阅以便进行辩论。何苦呢，这就像是通过一根很细的管子来观察天或者用一只猫头鹰来探索整个大地。这样的工具太小了，不是吗？先生，你还是走吧！或者，可能的话，你难道没听说过寿陵的少年以及他们在邯郸发生的故事吗？没有学会那个国家的人们想要教给他们的东西，他们把在家里学到的东西也忘了，最后只得爬着回家了。因此，先生，如果你现在还不离开，就会忘记你早已知道的东西，在事业上就只有失败了！”

公孙龙张大了嘴，不能合拢，舌头顶在上颚动不了，根本放不下来，然后他就退出去，逃走了。

庄子有一天在濮河上钓鱼，楚王派了两个高级官员来拜访他，并带来了一条口信。口信说：“我想烦请你来治理我的国家。”

庄子一直紧握着鱼竿，说：“我听说楚国有一个神龟，已经死了三千年了。国王将其包裹密封起来，藏在了他的祖庙里。你说，这只龟是情愿死了龟壳被人们供奉起来呢？还是宁愿活着继续在泥中爬行呢？”

两位高官说：“它宁愿活着继续在泥中爬行。”

庄子说：“那么，回去吧！我愿意继续在泥中爬行！”

……

庄子和惠子一同在濠水的堰堤上散步，庄子就说：“你看到鱼儿是怎样跃出水面、随心所欲地游来游去了吗？这就是鱼真正的快乐。”

惠子说：“你又不是鱼，你如何知道鱼喜欢什么？”

庄子说：“你又不是我，你怎么知道我不知道鱼喜欢什么。”

惠子说：“我不是你，所以我肯定不知道你到底知道什么。不过，很显然你也不是鱼，你必然也不知道鱼真正喜欢什么。”

庄子说：“哎，如果你不介意，还是让我们回到你最开始的问题吧。你问我如何知道鱼真正的快乐到底是什么。因此，你问这个问题的时候，你已经知道我是知道的。而且我也是因为站在濠水的堰堤上才知道的。”

……

在这广阔的全世界，有没有可能在某处能拥有完美的幸福？有没有一种方法能够让自己保持活力？现在，能做什么，又能相信什么呢？应该避免什么，又应该坚持什么呢？应该追求什么，又应该放弃什么呢？幸福在哪里，罪恶又在哪里呢？

在这广阔的全世界，人们看重的是财富、职位、长寿和名声。

能够带来幸福的是美好时光、精美食物、华美服饰、漂亮景色和美妙音乐。

那受人鄙视的是贫穷、吝啬、夭亡和污名。

那被认作痛苦的是生活方式不能让自己得到休息、嘴巴从未品尝过美食、身上没有华美服饰、眼睛看不到美好景色、耳朵听不到美妙音乐。

那些富人疲于奔命地工作，获得的财富越来越多，超出了他们所需要的。故而身体只是被视作外物。

那些位高权重的人没日没夜地谋划思索下一步的行动。漫不经心地对待自己的身体。在生活之中不断地被焦虑所困扰。如果他们能活得长寿，到最后老态龙钟，忧心忡忡，精疲力竭：多么悲惨的命运啊！身体受到了残酷的对待。天下所有人都将勇敢的人视作值得尊敬的，可是这并不能使他们免于死亡。这是否是明智的，我怀疑我是不是知道。可能是吧，但这丝毫不能拯救他们。也可能不是，但这却能拯救别人。人们说：“如果一个朋友不听你给他提的意见，那就放弃，不要争辩。”毕竟，子胥因争辩而丢了性命。他如果没有争辩的话，也就不会出名。可能真有善吗，或者根本不可能？

现在，当普通百姓意欲寻找幸福时，我不确定他们找到的幸福到底是不是幸福。我研究了普通百姓为了寻找幸福而做的事情和他们所奋力追求的东西，他们四处奔波，显然无法自拔。他们说他们幸福，而我并不幸福，但也没有不幸福。终究，他们拥有幸福了吗？我认为无为而为值得被称作幸福，尽管普通百姓视之为大的负担。所以说：“完美幸福不是幸福，完美荣耀不是荣耀。”

全世界的人都不能评判孰是孰非。但可以肯定的是无为而为能判定是非。完美幸福是保持活力，而只有无为而为能有这个效果。因此我要说：

天凭其纯净无为而为，

地靠其平静无为而为。

因此，天地将其无为之为相结合，万物都发生改变，因此重新焕发生命！比奇妙还奇妙的是，它们凭空产生！所有生命都是神奇的，都产生于无为之为。有一种说法，就是天地无为而为，却没有什么是未完成的。人们之中，有谁能理解这样的无为而为呢？

……

支离叔和滑介叔在冥伯山一带和昆仑地区游览，黄帝也曾在这里停留。突然滑介叔的左肘上毫无征兆地快速长出了如柳条般的东西。他自然无比惊讶，而且还有点恼怒。

支离叔说：“先生，你厌恶它吗？”

滑介叔说：“没有，我又该厌恶什么呢？生命通过乞讨索取而存在；若生命靠乞讨索取而生，那么生命就像是一个垃圾场。死亡和出生就像早晨和夜晚。先生，让你我来观察这转变的方式吧，现在我就在转变。所以，我怎么能够厌恶呢？”

庄子去楚地看一个古代的干枯头骨，他用马鞭戳了戳，说：“先生，你是因为走上一条不幸的道路，让你的父母和家庭蒙羞，结果才变成这样的吗？先生，或许是寒冷和饥饿让你变成这样子的？先生，又或许只是春秋的不断交替使你变成这样的？”

如此说着，他便把头骨拉过来当枕头，躺下睡着了。夜半时分，他在梦中看到那个头骨，对他说：“先生，你说话喋喋不休，就像一个公众演说家。你说的每一个字都表明先生你是一个为生活所困之人。可生活与我们死人毫不相干了。你想听听一些关于死的言论吗，先生？”

庄子说：“当然。”

头骨告诉他说：“死人，在上没有君主，在下没有侍从。没有什么工作与四时相关，所以我们存在着，我们的春秋如同天地一样，永无止境。毫无疑问，这是南面称王的快乐都不能比的。”

庄子不相信，说：“如果我叫司命官让先生你起死回生，有身体，有血肉，还有同伴，这样你会不喜欢吗？”

头骨皱起眉头，面带忧容，说：“我为什么要放弃连做君王的快乐都比不过的幸福，重新变回负担累累的人类呢？”

……

孔子说：“你以前没听说过这个故事吗？很久以前，一只海鸟降落在鲁国的都城。鲁侯列队将它带至太庙，在那里为它演奏《九韶》的音乐，还提供献祭的供品。但是，这只可怜的鸟儿看上去只有困惑和迷失，一片肉都没吃，也不喝一杯酒，没过三天就死了。问题是人们用他们自己吃的东西而不是鸟儿吃的东西来喂养一只鸟。

“养一只鸟要让它活，就叫它生活在树林之中，在河岸和水湾中跳跃，在河湖之中浮游，吃泥鳅和小鱼，成群结队地飞翔或休憩，自由自在地生活。鸟儿不喜欢听见人声，更不用说其他一切噪音和烦恼了。如果你想取悦鸟儿而在它们栖息的湖周围演奏《九韶》的音乐，鸟儿一听到音乐就会飞走。如果动物听到了，它们也会跑开躲起来；要是鱼儿听到了，也会潜入水底以逃脱。也只有人，听到之后会聚集起来倾听。

“鱼生活在水中感到很满足，可是若要让人试一试，他们会淹死，因为不同的物种需要不同的、刚好适合它的环境。因此古代的圣人从未期待其他生物能给他哪怕是一次回应，也从未试图让它们与人类保持一致。名称不能过度延伸来囊括现实，观念也只应当在合适的时候应用，因为这样不仅是合乎情理的，也会带来好运。”

……

祭祖的祭祀看了看猪圈说：“死有什么不好的呢？我花三个月时间把你们养肥，然后我要经过十天的精神戒律，三天的斋戒，铺好白色的芦苇，把你们肩部和臀部的肉切成块，然后放在献祭的地方。你们对此肯定没有意见，是吧？”

可是，事实上从猪的角度来看，吃燕麦和麸皮，然后待在猪圈里，这样的安排会更好。从我的角度来看，活着的时候成为一名重要的官员受人尊敬，死后用马拉的灵车埋葬，躺在羽毛的床上。我会接受这样的安排！而猪才不屑于这样的生活呢，但我却会很满足，尽管我不知道为什么我观察事物会跟一头猪相差这么多？

第十一部分　把握生命的目的

如果你已经把握了生命的目的，试图把生命变成不是它原来的样子或者它不可能成为的样子是没有意义的。

如果你已经把握了命运的目的，试图通过知识改变命运是没有意义的。

如果你想照料好你的身体，首先要解决好物质资料，可是即便你拥有了你想要的一切事物，身体仍可能照料不好。

你有生命之后，你必须首先保证生命不会抛弃身体。但是，也有可能身体仍保持活力，可生命却不能维持。出生不能逃避，死亡又不能避免。多荒唐啊！看到世间的人们相信只要照料身体就能保全生命。可是，如果照料身体不足以保全生命，为什么全世界的人仍继续如此呢？照料身体可能是没有意义的，但至少也不能忽视，所以就不可避免了。

如果有人不想再做任何事情来维持身体，人们便建议他们摆脱这个世界，因为摆脱之后他们就能免于承担任何义务了。不用承担义务之后，他们便能变得正直平静了。变得正直平静之后，他们便能向其他人一样获得新生。获得新生之后，他们就接近道了。为什么摆脱世间的烦恼、忘记生命的目的是一个好主意呢？如果你摆脱了生存的困扰，你的身体就不会疲倦；如果你遗忘了生命，你的精神就不会受损。因此，若你的身体和精神和谐了，你就达到天人合一了。天地是万物的父母。天地合则创造形体，天地分则创造开始。身体和精神没有缺陷的，人们就说是有适应能力。加强了再加强，就可以返还本始去辅助天。

列子问看门人尹说：“唯有完美之人可以在水下行走而不被淹死，在火里行走而不被灼伤，在众生万物间行走而不恐惧。我想问，完美之人是如何做到的？”

看门人尹答道：“因为他保全了元气，而与知识、工作、坚持或勇敢没有关系。坐下来，我把一切都讲给你听。

“万物都有面貌、形体、声音和颜色：这些只是外表。这一点和那一点怎么就能彼此分离呢？甚至，为什么它们就应当被看作是万物之中最先存在的呢？它们只是形体和颜色而已。然而，万物都开始于那无形的，最后落入那无所变化的。

“如果你能把握并懂得这个道理，并能一以贯之，什么都不能阻挡你！也意味着你能居于没有限制的界限之内，退隐于没有开端的范围之中，漫游到那万物开始和结束的地方；整合本性，滋养元气，协调德行，沿着这条路径与万物的起源相通。这样的人坚守着天人合一的状态，他的精神没有缺陷，因此，什么都不能进入他的内心去攻击他！

“如果一个醉汉从他的马车上摔下来，就算是马车正跑得飞快，他也不会摔死。他与其他人没什么两样，都有骨头和关节，但他却不会受伤，这是因为他的精神是统一的。因为他没有意识到他在出行，也完全不知道自己摔了出去，所以生、死、惊恐和害怕都不能影响他，他只是突然遭遇了一些状况，没有焦虑或受伤。

“如果通过饮酒喝醉就能够保持精神统一，那么想象一下如果天人合一的话一个人能够怎样的精神统一啊！圣人退回到天的宁静之中，因此没有什么能够伤害他。即便是在外复仇之人，都不会折断敌人的剑。不论人们多么心烦，也不会对正好掉在他们身上的瓦片发脾气。我们反倒应当认识到天下万物都是统一的。因此，我们就有可能摆脱混乱、暴力和战争，还有严酷的惩罚和死刑，因为这就是道。

“不要在人之中去倾听那属天的，而要在天之中倾听那属天的，因为看重天德能够获得生命，而注重人性却会毁坏生命。不要丢弃那属天的，但也不要轻视人的方面：这样人们就能接近实现真理了。”

……

孔子在吕梁观光，在那里瀑布有近五十余米高，河水竞流一路长达六十余千米，水流得太快了，不论是鱼还是其他任何生物都无法在水里游泳。他看到一个人跳入水中，他以为这个人也许出于某种忧虑想要寻死，所以他安排他的弟子一路沿着河岸准备将他拉上岸。可是，那个游泳的人游了一百码后上岸了，若无其事地沿着河岸走，口里唱着歌，身上滴着水。

孔子追上他说：“我还以为你是个鬼呢，可是现在我看清楚了，先生你确实是一个人。我想问一下，你有水下游泳之道吗？”

他说：“没有，我没有道。我从我本来就已知道的出发，培养我的内在天性，剩下的就交给命运了。我随着水流进入水中，又随着浪花浮出水面，只是顺从水的道，并不自作主张。这就是我能在水里行动的方法。”

孔子说：“你说你从本来就已知道的出发，培养你的内在天性，剩下的就交给命运，这是什么意思？”

他说：“我出生在陆地上，在地上我感到满足，也明白我所知道的。我受到水的滋养，在水里感到安全，这就反映了我的内在天性。我不确定我为何要这么做，但是我肯定这是命运的安排。”

一个名叫庆的雕木工正在雕刻一块木头，要制成挂钟的支架，看过这个支架的人非常惊讶，因为它简直是鬼斧神工。鲁侯见了便问：“你的技艺是从何处学来的呢？”

庆答道：“我只是一个雕木工，哪有什么‘技艺’？但是，有一点我是确定的，在制作这个挂钟的支架时，我不让它损耗我的元气，所以我注意保持内心平静。斋戒三日之后，我就再也不想什么赞扬、奖赏、头衔或收入了。斋戒五日之后，我就再也不想什么光荣或责备、技巧或愚蠢了。等斋戒满七天，我就变得那样平静，连自己是否还有四肢和躯体都遗忘了。到那时，君上和他的朝廷在我的意识中就不存在了。我所有的精神都集中在一起，丝毫没有外在的担忧。随后，我就出发前往山中森林，探索树木属天的内在本性；一旦我发现了形状完美的木材，切实地看出它被制成挂钟的支架的潜力，然后就放手投入工作；要是看不到这种潜力，我就罢手不管它。如此，我就让那属天的与天相协调，或许因此人们才认为我的雕工如有神助吧！”

……

工匠倕能画得像用了直尺一般直，或者像用了圆规一般曲，因为他的手指能够顺应变化，他的心没有妨碍。因此，他的内心专一而没有阻碍。当你穿着舒服的鞋子走路的时候，你会忘记双脚。当你的腰带舒服合身的时候，你会把腰都忘了。当你的心满意前行的时候，智慧可以忘记是非。如果你对发生的一切心满意足，内心就不会有任何改变，也就没有什么会由外而生。从舒适满足出发，不经历什么烦心的事，就有可能知道什么是忘掉舒适的舒适了。

……

庄子步行穿越群山深处时看到一棵巨大、翠绿的树。一个伐木工在树边停下，但是没有砍伐这棵树。当被问及原因时，他说：“这棵树没啥用。”庄子说：“因为这棵树被认为是无用的，它才能享尽天所赋予它的寿命。”

庄子从山中出来后在一个朋友家里过夜。这位朋友很高兴，让他的儿子去杀一只鹅做菜。他儿子回应说：“一只鹅会叫，一只鹅不会叫，你说该杀哪一只呢？”父亲答道：“杀那只不会叫的。”

第二天，庄子的弟子就问他：“昨天，山中有一棵树因为没用才能享尽天所赋予的寿命。现在，在你朋友家里，一只鹅因为没用而被杀了。老师，这事你怎么看？”

庄子笑着说：“就我个人而言，我会在有用和没用之间找准一个位置。这个处于有用和没用之间的位置看似很好，但是我要告诉你们并非如此，因为麻烦还会找上你。而且，如果你想要登上道德之巅，就不是这样了。

没有确信，没有指引，

没有赞美，没有责备，

可以成龙，可以成蛇，

应时而动，只要得当。

时而向上，时而向下，

唯以和谐，做你向导，

遨游何处，万物源头。

“让万物顺其自然，但不可让万物只是把你当成一个物体，这样你就不会再陷入困境了！这也是神农和黄帝所选择的道路。不过，现在，由于物种数量众多种类丰富，再加上人类的道德规范，万物早已不是它们原来的样子！

联合只为了分离；

完成只为了崩塌；

锋利的刀刃变钝；

受提拔的被打倒；

雄心壮志被挫败；

智者被阴谋陷害；

愚蠢之人被欺骗。

“因此，能相信什么呢？我的弟子，只有道和德！”

……

孔子被困在陈国和蔡国之间，七天没有吃上热饭了。太公任前来慰问孔子，说：“先生，你认为你会死吗？”

孔子说：“当然。”

“先生，那你怕死吗？”

“当然。”

太公任说：“我想告诉你永生之道。在东海居住着一种鸟叫作意怠。这只鸟之所以意怠是因为心烦意乱又移动缓慢，心烦意乱又移动缓慢就跟没有力气一样，只有在别的鸟儿的帮助下才可以飞，而且总争着先回到巢里去。它们谁也不喜欢处在最前或待在最后，吃东西也不敢先尝。因此，这种鸟从来不单独飞，而鸟群之外没有谁能伤害它，也包括人类，这样它就可以避免灾祸了。

“挺直的树最先被砍倒；甘甜的井水最早干涸。先生，你意图展示你的知识好让那无知者感到震惊，并通过你自身的进步来表明他人的粗俗。你闪耀着，积极地发着光，就好像你将日月都带在身边似的。而所有这一切都是你无法避免灾祸的原因。

“我听大成之人说过：‘傲慢之人没做什么值得夸耀的事，而那些有所成就的人却愿意看着他们取得的成就日渐消亡，名声很快消逝。’没几个人能够忘记成功和声望，重新再做回普通人！道运行一切，但是完美之人并不立于它的光芒之下；他的道德运行一切，可是他并不追逐名望。他虚空而质朴，看似疯狂。他隐匿姓名，放弃权力，对成就和名望毫无兴趣。因此，他不批评他人，他人也不批评他。完美之人从不为人所知，因此，先生你又为何想要如此呢？”

孔子说：“太好了！”然后就向他的朋友们告别，离开他的弟子退隐到大沼泽之中，穿着兽皮和粗糙的衣服，并以橡子和栗子为食。他走入兽群之中，动物们不会害怕；走入鸟群之中，鸟儿也不会飞走。如果鸟儿和动物都不会惊慌，那么人也不必惊慌了！

孔子问桑雽：“在鲁国我曾两次被驱逐出境，在宋国差点被一棵推倒的树砸到，在卫国有关我的所有记录都被消除，在商地我贫困潦倒，在陈国和蔡国之间又受到围困。我忍受了那么多的困扰。我的朋友和我认识的人都离我而去，我的弟子也开始离弃我。可是，为什么会这样呢？”

桑雽说：“难道你没听说过那个逃亡的殷国人的故事吗？有个叫林回的，将价值千金的璧玉扔在一旁，把儿子捆在背上匆忙逃走了。有人问：‘是因为这个孩子更值钱吗？一个孩子肯定值不了那么多。是因为携带璧玉需要付出更多气力吗？显然一个孩子要更麻烦些。那么你为什么丢弃价值千金的璧玉，而背起你年幼的孩子匆忙逃跑呢？’林回对他们说：‘将我与翡翠徽章连在一起的是贪婪，而儿子与我之间的联系却是天性所牵连的。’

“如果人们之间的纽带是建立于利益之上，那么当灾祸降临时，人们很容易分离。如果人们之间的关系是天性所牵连的，那么当有麻烦时，他们会团结在一起。团结还是分离，这可是完全不同的两种结果。与君子交往可能像水一样平淡无味，而与内心卑鄙的小人交往却像酒一样甜腻。君子的平淡能发展出感情，而小人的甜蜜却会让人厌恶。毫无理由聚在一起的人，也必然会毫无理由地分离。”

……

庄子穿着一件破旧的、打着补丁的粗布长袍，用绳子拢住鞋子，就这样前去拜见魏王。魏王说：“先生，你怎么成这样子了？”

庄子答道：“我这是贫穷，而不是颓废。如果学者拥有道德却不能运用，那才是颓废呢。如果他的衣服破旧，鞋子靠绳子拢着，那是贫穷，而不是颓废。这是叫作生不逢时啊。陛下，你难道没有见过爬树的猴子吗？当它们处在悬铃木、栎树和樟脑树之中时，它们可以自如地攀着树枝，即便是后羿和蓬蒙这样的神射手都不能瞄准它们。可是，当它们来到带刺的桑树、多刺的枣树或其他有刺的灌木丛中，它们小心谨慎地移动，左顾右盼，害怕地发抖。这并不是因为它们的筋骨变得僵硬或者不能弯曲了，而是因为猴子们没有处在它们所适应的环境之中，因此不能施展它们的本领。既然我发现自己生活的时代居上者是愚昧的君主和反叛的臣子，我又如何能不颓废呢？”

……

庄子正在雕陵的一处公园里闲逛，突然看到一只奇怪的寒鸦从南方飞来。它的翼展超过两米，眼睛大大的，直径足有两厘米半。它经过时紧贴着庄子的额头掠过，然后飞到栗子林中停了下来。庄子说：“这是什么鸟啊，翅膀如此大却飞不了多远，眼睛如此大可却看不清楚？”他拉起长袍，拿着十字弓快步朝它走去，以便能够近距离向它射击。这时他看到一只蝉，正沉浸在一处极好的树荫里，忘记了自身的安全。突然，一只螳螂伸出了触角，准备袭击蝉，它如此投入到捕食之中竟也忘记了自身的安全。这只奇怪的寒鸦向下飞过，把它们两个都抓住了，不过同样地，在为战利品而兴奋的同时，它也忘记了自身的安全。庄子同情地叹了口气说：“唉！这就是一物给另一物带来灾祸的同时，也给自己带来灾祸啊。”他将十字弓扔在一旁刚要离开，守林人便来追赶他，骂他是个偷猎者。

庄子回到家后沮丧了三个月。蔺且当时正和他在一起，就问：“老师，你为何如此沮丧？”

庄子说：“我太在意我的躯体而忘记自我了。就好比看着浑浊的水，却想着它真清澈啊。而且，我以前听我老师说过：‘与当地人交往，就要像当地人一样行事。’因此我就出门到雕陵的一处公园散步，可我却忘记了自我。一只奇怪的寒鸦掠过我的额头，然后在栗树林中停下了，在那里它也忘记了自己真正的存在。守林人以为我应当受到责备。我因此感到很沮丧。”

……

孔子去见老子，发现他正在洗头。他把头发披散在肩膀上等着晾干。他一动不动站在那里，就像世界上没有其他人存在一样。孔子静静地站着，然后过了一会儿，静静地走到他的面前，说：“刚才是我眼花了吗，真的是你？刚才，先生你的身体就像是古老的朽木一样静止不动。你看上去心无所想，就好像是处在另外一个世界，完全孤立地站着。”

老子说：“我让我的心遨游于万物的元始境界了。”

孔子说：“这是什么意思呢？”

“我心里想要把它推理出来，但困困顿顿地不能理解；我的嘴一直张着，却不能够说出。不过，我还是要尽量给你描述一下。至阴严厉而冷酷，至阳美好而热烈。严厉和冷酷源自地，美好和热烈源自天。二者混合相通，彼此联合而产生了万物。或许有一个人控制并确保这一切，但是即便如此，也没人见到过任何形体或形状。衰退和成长，圆满和虚空，时而黑暗时而明亮，太阳的变化和月亮的圆缺，这些都日复一日地出现，可是没人见过是什么引发这一切的。生命有它的起源，死亡也有它的归宿。开始和结束无情地循环交替，没有人知道这一切的终点。如果不是这样，谁又是那起点和指引呢？”

孔子说：“我想问一下，这样的遨游是怎样的呢？”

老子说：“能够进行这样的遨游，是极致的美好，也是完美的幸福；能够得到极致的美好，并漫游在完美的幸福之中，就是完美之人了。”

孔子说：“我想听听怎么才能够做到呢？”

老子答道：“食草的动物不会因为草场的变更而死亡。生于水中的动物也不会因为水的更换而死亡。它们能够忍受细小的变化，但是不能忍受最根本的东西发生变化。快乐、愤怒、悲伤和高兴不会进入它们的心中。普天之下，一切生灵汇聚成一个整体。了解这个整体就能与其合而为一，而且你的四肢和百节都将只是尘灰。因为死亡与出生，结束与开始就像昼夜更替。这样你心满意足的状态就不会被得失、祸福之类的小事所扰乱了！那些轻视权力地位的人，弃之如泥土一般，因为他们知道他们真正的自我比任何头衔都重要。你对自我的珍视存于内心，不受外在发生之事的影响。万物的不断变化就像是没有结束的开始。这其中有什么能够扰乱你的心呢？那些理解道的人摆脱了所有这一切。”

孔子说：“先生，你的德行如同天地一般，可即便是你也不得不求助这些完美之辞来引导你。古代的伟人之中，又有谁能实现它呢？”

老子答道：“我自然是没有。流水什么都不做，但它遵循了它的天性。完美之人在德行方面也是如此。他不去培养它，可是所有人都受到它的存在影响。他就像天的自然高，地的自然厚，日月的自然亮。哪有必要去培养呢！”

……

庄子去拜见鲁哀公。哀公说：“鲁国有很多儒者，但是他们之中很少有人研究你的著作，先生。”

庄子说：“鲁国儒者很少。”

哀公说：“鲁国上下都是穿着儒者衣服的人。你怎么能说很少呢？”

庄子说：“我听说，那些儒者中头戴圆帽的，懂得天时；脚踏方鞋的，懂得地势；腰带上挂着半圆形玉玦的，对眼前发生的一切应对自如。不过，能理解道的君子，未必穿那种服装；当然，他也可能穿上那种服装，却根本不懂得道！如果陛下对此仍有疑问，不妨下一道命令，说：‘任何不能行道而着儒服者，杀！’”

哀公就照此行了，五天后整个鲁国没有一个儒者敢穿儒服了！只有一个老者穿着儒服站在哀公门外。哀公即刻召见他，与他讨论国家事务。虽然他们讨论了上千事宜，中间有成千上万次离题，可是老者应答如流。

庄子说：“因此，整个鲁国只有这一个人是儒者。你怎么能说有很多呢？”

第十二部分　勿要问道

知向北漫游，直至玄水的岸边，登上隐弅山丘后，恰好碰到无为谓。知对无为谓说：“我想问你点事。要想懂得道需要怎样的思考和反应呢？我们应当在何处、以何种方式保证能够安心于道呢？要获得道我们需要通过何种途径、采取何种计划呢？”他问了无为谓三个问题，可是对方没有回答。他并非知而不答，而是根本不知道如何回答。

知没有得到任何答案，所以他继续向白水的南方前行，爬上了狐阕山顶，在那里看到了狂屈。知向狂屈提出了同样的问题。狂屈说：“啊哈！我知道，让我来告诉你。”可他说到一半时，却忘了要说什么！

知又没有得到任何答案，所以他就返回到王宫去拜见黄帝并向他请教。黄帝说：“试着不要思考、不要反应，这样你就会懂得道了。只有当你无处可寻、无路可走的时候，你才能在道中得到心安。没有途径、没有计划，这样你才能获得道。”

知对黄帝说：“你我都懂得了这个道理，可是其他人都不懂，那么我们到底谁是对的呢？”

黄帝说：“无为谓才是真正对的。狂屈看似是对的。你我终究还是差得太远啊。

懂得道的人，什么都不说。

说道的人，其实并不懂得。

所以圣人遵循无言的教诲。

道不能催生，德不能求取。

不过，仁却可以为人所施，

义能够争取，礼可以遵守。

可以说：道失去了德出现；

德如果也失去了，仁出现；

仁如果再失去了，义出现；

义如果还是丢失，才有礼。

礼只是道褶边上一个装饰，

即将发生混乱的一个标志。

“可以说：‘遵循道的人每天做的越来越少。随着他做的越来越少，他最终会实现无为而为。实现无为而为后，就没有什么是没有完成的了。’既然我们已然积极作为，如果我们想要返回原初的状态，会发现这是多么的难啊！除了伟人，谁又能改变这种情形呢？

生向着死前行，死是生的先驱。

谁又能知道它们运行的方式呢？

人的生命最初以元气作为开端；

气聚时方有生，气散时便有死。”

……

孔子对老子说：“今天，您好像很轻松，因此我想请教什么是完美的道？”

老子说：“你应当通过斋戒和苦行来清洁和净化你的心，洁净你的灵魂，抑制你的知识。道是深奥难言的啊！我愿意尽量说说对它的一些理解：

“那光明闪耀的生于幽深黑暗之中；

井然有序之物源于那没有定型的；

那属精神的是从道之中生出来的；

身体的根源来自于精液中的精华；

万物皆通过出生而赋予彼此形体。

拥有九窍的动物皆腹中怀胎而生，

而那拥有八窍的动物都是卵生的。

道来时没有踪迹，去时也无迹象，

既不进门也不居留，通达于四方。

那些与道同行的人将会身体强壮，

他们的思想真诚的同时不失深奥，

耳聪目明，即使用心也不知疲倦，

对万物作出回应时没有丝毫偏见。

正因如此，天是高的而地是广的，

日月运行，万物繁荣。这便是道！

“即便最广博的知识也不能理解它。

理性不代表智慧，故圣人皆弃之。

有一种东西是完整的，无须增加；

而且无论你拿走什么都不会减少。

这就是圣人始终保持不变的东西。

它渊深得如同大海，

它峻峭得如同高山，

结束也是开始，承载万物而不缺。

君子之道只是外观，这才是真道！”

……

泰清请教无穷说：“先生，你懂得道吗？”

无穷说：“我不懂。”

接着他又问无为，无为说：“我懂得道。”

泰清就问：“先生，你所理解的道，有什么特别的提示吗？”

“有。”

“是什么？”

无为说：“就我所知，道可以提高也可以降低，可以聚结也可以分散。要懂得道，这些就是我所能给你的提示。”

带着不同的答案，泰清去找无始，说：“无穷说他不懂得，而无为说他懂得，我想知道这二人之中谁是对的，谁又是错的。”

无始说：“说不懂得是深奥的，而说懂得是浅薄的。说不懂得是向内寻求，说懂得是向外求索。”

随后泰清仰望天空，叹道：“说不懂得是懂得，说懂得是不懂得啊！谁能懂得说不懂得才是懂得啊？”无始说：

“道不能被听见，能听见的就不是道。

道不能被看见，能看见的就不是道。

道不能被言说，能言说的就不是道。

你知道谁赋形给无形吗？道没有名。”

无始继续说：

“有人向你问道你就回答，说明你不懂得道。

“问道之人对道什么都不懂。

“勿要问道，因为问道是不合适的，这个问题也无法得到回答，因为这就像是问那些处于悲惨窘境的人。回答不能回答的问题，表明内心尚未理解。当一个内心尚未理解的人等着那些处于悲惨窘境的人回答的时候，就表明他们对外没有把握他们所处的世界，对内没有理解那伟大的开始。所以他们既不能跨越昆仑山，也不能遨游于大虚空。”

……

南荣趎准备好吃的喝的之后就出发了，过了七天七夜，他来到了老子家中。

老子说：“你是从庚桑楚那里来的吗？”

南荣趎答道：“是的。”

“那么，先生，你怎么带着这么一大群人跟着你呢？”

南荣趎转过身去，很吃惊地看着身后。

老子说：“先生，你难道不明白我的意思吗？”

南荣趎羞愧地低下头，然后抬起头来，叹息说：“现在我记不得我所要回答的话了，因此也就忘了我要问什么了。”

老子说：“你在说什么？”

南荣趎说：“我对事物有任何了解吗？人们说我愚蠢。我懂吗？这只能让我烦恼。如果我不是仁慈的，那么我会让他人痛苦。如果我是仁慈的，那么我自己又会痛苦。如果我不是公义的，那么我会伤害他人。如果我是公义的，那么我自己又会烦恼。我怎样才能摆脱这一切呢？这三个问题困扰着我，所以我听从了庚桑楚的意见，来向您请教这些问题。”

老子答道：“刚才，我深入观察了你的眼睛，我能看出你是怎样的一个人。你刚才所说的话证实了我是对的。你不知所措、困惑迷乱，就好像是失去了父母，而要用一根竿子伸到海底去寻找他们。你迷失了，感到害怕。你想重新发现你的自我和内在天性，可是你不知道要怎样去做。你的处境真是可怜啊！”

南荣趎请求回到他的房间。他努力求取好的东西，让自己摆脱坏的东西。愁苦了十天之后，他出来了，再次去见老子。

老子说：“我能够看出你一直在认真仔细地洗涤心灵、净化自我，不过你仍然是不纯洁的，尽管外在很干净。在你的内心有东西在搅动，心里仍然有一些腐朽的东西。外在的影响会压在你的身上，你会发现不能控制它们。向它们关闭你内在自我的门户是比较明智的。同样地，如果是内在的影响扰乱你，而且你发现不可能控制它们，那么也要关闭你内在自我的门户，好把它们关在里面。要同时抵抗外在的和内在的影响，就算是这对于一个懂得道与德的人来说，都已经超出了他的控制，何况是一个在道的方向刚刚起步的人呢！”

南荣趎说：“一个村民生病了，邻居询问他的病情。他能描述他的病，虽然这种病他以前从来没得过。当我向你请教大道时，就像是喝了让我病情加重的药。我就想了解保护生命的一般方法就可以了。”

“保护生命的基本方法——你能抱一吗？”老子说。“你能守终吗？你能不用龟壳或蓍草占卜而知祸福吗？你知道何时收手，何时终止吗？你能忘记他人而专心于内在自我吗？你能躲避诱惑吗？你能真诚待人吗？你能成为小婴儿吗？婴儿整日哭泣，喉咙却不会嘶哑：真是完美的和谐。婴儿整日紧握拳头，两手却从不痉挛，因为他持守天道。婴儿整日盯着看，外面的世界却不能影响他。他行动却不知去向何方，他坐着却不知坐在何处，他安静平和，随遇而安。这就是保护生命之法。”

南荣趎接着问：“难道这就是成为完美之人所要做的一切吗？”

“当然不是。这是所谓的冰消冻解。你能做到吗？完美之人就如同跟他人是一体的，共同从大地寻找食物，向上天寻找快乐。但是，他从不考虑从他人处获利或有所得，不把自己拖入图谋策划之中，也不卷入不切实际的事业。他去时，机警灵活、永不停歇；他来时，天真率直、毫无矫饰。这才可以被称为保护生命的方法。”

“那么，这个就是他的完美状态吗？”

老子答道：“还不算。刚才我问你：‘你能成为幼小的婴儿吗？’婴儿行动时却不知道为了什么，行动时却不知道要去哪里。他的身体就像日渐腐朽的树枝，他的心就像已然冷却的灰烬。就这样，祸不会影响他，福也不会降临。既无祸福，他就不会被那降临到大多数人身上的不幸所影响了。”

……

可以说：

“完美的行为不分别众人；

完美的公义不计较外物；

完美的知识不需要谋划；

完美的仁慈不表露情感；

完美的信仰不誓言真诚。”

压制意志的冲动，

解开心中的误解。

除去德行的症结，

开启大道的运行。

荣誉和财富，

显赫和权威，

名声和利禄，

此六者为意志幻觉所形成。

外表和风格，

美好和理性，

盛气和回忆，

此六者都是心的缺陷。

厌恶和喜欢，

喜悦和愤怒，

悲伤和幸福，

此六者是德行的症结。

拒绝和接受，

给予和获取，

知识和能力，

此六者是大道运行的阻碍。

当这四组各六项不再折磨

心绪时，你就处于中心了。

处于中心，你就能够平静。

能够平静，就能得到启蒙。

得到启蒙，你就能够虚空。

虚空之后，便是无为而为。

无为而为，便能成就一切。

道是献身德行的核心部分。

生命呢，则是德行的光亮。

内在的天性是生命的动力。

……

庄子家境贫寒，因此他前去向监河侯借点米。监河侯说：“可以啊。我就要收到百姓缴纳的赋税了，到时候给你三百金，够吗？”

庄子气得脸都紫了，说：“昨天在我来的路上，我听到有个声音在叫我。我环顾一周，在马车留的车辙之中看到一条大鱼。我说：‘鱼啊！你在这里做什么？’它说：‘我是东海掌管波浪的大臣。阁下，不知您是否可以给我一些水？’我说：‘好的。我要到南方去游历吴国和越国，随后我会改变西河水流的方向，那样水就会流到你这了。这样可以吗？’大鱼气得脸都紫了，说：‘我离开了我所必需的东西，没有地方可去了。只要给我一点水我就能活下去。可是，你这样来答复我，那你以后就只有到干鱼摊上来找我了！”

……

伟大的合一懂得道，

伟大的神秘显露道，

伟大的阴气观察道，

伟大的眼睛看见道，

伟大的平等是开始，

伟大的技能产生道，

伟大的信任触碰道，

伟大的法官持守道。

天道存在于万物之中：追随光明，躲入阴暗，开始存在于万物之中。这样做，你的理解就好像是不理解，你的智慧就好像是不明智。正因为不明智，随后你才能变得明智。当你问问题时，不要设定界限，即便它们不可能是没有界限的。尽管事物好像有时上升，有时下落，有时溜走，但无论如何有一个自古至今一成不变的事实。它不会改变，因为什么都不能影响它。难道我们不能说它就是唯一伟大的和谐吗？那么我们为什么不应当探究它，我们又为什么如此困惑呢？如果我们用不让人困惑的东西来理解那确实让人困惑的东西，那么我们就能够回归到那不让人困惑的东西上来了。这将是人之大不惑。

……

四季各有原初的生命，

而上天没有任何偏私，

故四季循环得以实现。

政府五部门职能不同，

而君主没有任何偏私，

因此国家得以治理好。

战争与和平二者之中，

伟人不偏好任何一个，

因而他道德才能完美。

万物都是各不相同的，

然而道不会区别对待，

因此道是没有名称的。

没有名称，无为而为，

尽管如此，万物并生。

四季循环，世代更替。

祸福会降临到你身上，

有的时候它不受欢迎，

也有时候你乐于接受。

习惯接受自己的看法，

然后与别人进行争辩，

有时也要谴责正直的，

然后谴责那些使坏的。

你应当像那大沼泽地，

能够容下上百种树木。

或者应当像一座大山，

草木共存能安处一地。

这便是所谓丘里之言。

第十三部分　何为本真？

从前，赵文王喜爱刀剑。各路行家里手都来到他门前，足有三千多人，都是剑术方面的专业人士。他们做他的宾客。他们没日没夜地在他面前比武，每年死伤的人数超过一百。可是国王从未停止对比武观赏的喜爱。这样持续了三年，随后国家开始分裂，其他诸侯也开始谋划将其推翻。

太子悝为此心烦意乱，便向他左右的人说明此情形。

他说：“如果有人能够劝说国王远离这些剑客，我就给他一千黄金。”

左右的人说：“庄子能做到。”

太子派了一名使者带着一千黄金去见庄子。庄子拒绝接受黄金，但还是跟着使者一同返回。他进来拜见太子，说：“太子啊，你有什么事情指教我，要送给我一千黄金？”

太子说：“我听说先生是有名的智者。这一千黄金的赏赐是犒劳你的随从的。可是，你拒绝接受，我又怎么敢再多说什么呢？”

庄子说：“我听说太子想要用我来帮助国王戒除他长久以来的爱好。如果我在试图说服国王时让他感到心烦，没能完成你交托的事，那么我可能会被处死。到时候黄金对我又有何用呢？或者，如果我能够说服国王，完成了你的心愿，整个赵国又有什么是我不能求取的呢？”

太子说：“没错。可是国王只召见剑客。”

庄子说：“没关系。我对剑术也很在行。”

太子说：“太好了。不过国王召见的剑客都是头发蓬乱，胡子拉碴，戴着用简单粗糙的带子系着的宽大帽子，而且穿着后面被剪短的袍子。他们怒目环视，只谈论他们的剑术。国王就喜欢这样的。现在，如果你穿着儒服觐见，那么你第一步就完全走错了。”

庄子说：“请允许我去准备剑客的全套装备。”

他三天之内就全都准备好了，然后回去见太子。太子带着他去觐见国王，国王已拔出剑，坐在那等着他了。庄子缓慢地穿过大门走进大堂。当他见到国王时，并不行礼。

国王问道：“你对我有何指教，竟然让太子给你带路？”

“我听说大王喜欢刀剑，所以我把我的剑带来让大王看看。”

“你的剑在战斗中有何用？”

“我的剑十步之内可杀一人，而且行走千里它的威力也不会减弱。”

国王很高兴，说：“那天下就没有人能比得过你了。”

庄子答道：“一个好的剑客开始先佯攻，然后佯败引诱对方，跟着就是一击，后于对方发出，先于对方到达。我想向您展示一下我的技巧。”

国王说：“先生，到你的房中先休息片刻，听候我的命令。我会安排比赛然后再叫你。”

国王接下来一连七天测试他的剑客。死亡或严重受伤的超过六十人，只剩下五六个人被选出来，受命来到大堂。然后国王叫来庄子，说：“现在，就在今天，我让你跟这些人比试，展示一下你的剑术。”

庄子说：“我一直等待这样一个机会。”

国王问道：“先生，你想选什么样的剑，长的还是短的？”

庄子说：“什么样的都行，不过我有三把剑，只要国王同意，我用哪一把都可以。不过，首先我想对它们做个介绍，然后再用。”

国王说：“我愿意听你说说这三把剑。”

庄子说：“我有天子之剑、诸侯之剑和百姓之剑。”

“天子之剑是什么样的？”

“天子之剑以燕为剑尖，以长城、齐国和泰山为剑刃。晋国和卫国是剑背，周朝和宋国是剑柄，而韩国和魏国是剑鞘。它的四面由蛮夷包围，被四季裹藏。渤海环绕着它，永恒的常山缠束着它。五行制衡着它，刑罚和道德缠裹着它。它遵循着阴阳而出现，在春夏之中保持警觉，并于秋冬之中采取行动。向前刺去，它前面就不剩什么了；向上举起，它上面就不剩什么了；向下按低，它下面就不剩什么了；左右挥动，它四周就不剩什么了。若举得高高的，它能将天劈开；若按得低低的，它能将地脉切断。用这把剑只需一次，便可以让天下诸侯归顺、万民臣服。这就是天子之剑。”

文王大为惊讶，好像已经忘记了别的一切。

他问：“诸侯之剑是什么样的？”

庄子说：“诸侯之剑的剑尖是睿智勇敢之人；剑刃是正直诚实之人；剑背是高尚善良之人；剑柄是诚信明智之人；剑鞘是勇敢杰出之人。这把剑若向前刺去，没有什么能够抵抗；若挥向高处，没有什么能在它之上；若挥向低处，没有什么能在它之下；若四处旋转，没有什么能够靠近它。在上，它效法天道，能与三大光明一同前行。在下，它效法方静的地道，能与四季的运行同时进行。在中原之地它能恢复百姓的和谐，与四方保持平衡。这把剑一使用，就好似响起雷声隆隆。四方疆界之内，人人守法，并且所有人都遵守诸侯的命令。这就是诸侯之剑。”

“百姓之剑又是什么样的？”

“百姓之剑是由那些头发蓬乱、胡子拉碴，戴着用简单粗糙的带子系着的宽大帽子，而且穿着后面被剪短的袍子的人所使用的。他们怒目环视，只谈论他们的剑术，同时会在国王面前比武。举起剑来，能够砍断脖子；向下挥动，能划开肝肺。使用百姓之剑的人跟随时可能丧命的斗鸡没什么两样。现在呢，噢，大王，您拥有天子的地位，却因为喜爱百姓之剑，让自己变得毫无价值。这就是我斗胆之言。”

国王将庄子带到他的大殿，膳食官奉上食物，国王围着房间大踏步绕了三圈。

“大王，坐下来平静一下，有关剑要说的我都已经说了。”

这之后，文王三个月没有外出，他的所有剑客都在自己房中自杀而死。

……

孔子在缁帷之林中漫步，在杏坛边上坐了下来。他的弟子开始读书，孔子在弹琴唱歌。他的歌唱了还不到一半时，一位渔夫下船并朝他的方向走来。渔夫的胡须眉毛都是白的，头发很乱，袖子耷拉在身体两侧。他走上斜坡，来到干燥一点的地面上就停下了，左手放在膝盖上，右手托着下巴，一直聆听直到曲终。随后，他就招呼子贡和子路，他们俩就去见他。

他指着孔子说：“那是谁啊？”

子路说：“他是鲁国来的君子。”

渔夫随后问起孔子的家庭。子路说：“孔氏一家。”

“这位孔氏后人靠什么为生呢？”

子路正在想说什么，子贡回答说：“这位孔氏后人，在内在天性上，他持守忠诚；在行动上，他表现仁义；他修饰礼乐，协调人际关系。在上，尊重君上；在下，努力教化百姓，想要以此造福整个世界。这就是这位孔氏后人所做的事情。”

渔夫进而又问：“他拥有要他治理的土地吗？”

子贡说：“没有。”

“他是哪个国王的辅佐大臣吗？”

“不是。”

陌生人笑着转身离开，说：“那么，仁倒是仁，可是他免不了要伤害自身了。内心疲惫、身体匮乏会伤及他真正的天性。可惜啊，我想他已离道太远了。”

子贡回去将此事告诉孔子。孔子将琴放到一旁，站起来说：“或许他是个圣人。”随后他便走下斜坡去找渔夫了。他来到水边时，渔夫正要用篙撑船离开。看到孔子，他又把船撑回来见他。孔子赶紧向后退了几步，两次行礼后再走向前。

陌生人说：“先生，你想干什么？”

孔子说：“先生，刚才您说了一些话，但是没有说完。我没有才学，理解不了。所以我想找您，哪怕只是听听您说话的声音，希望能够对我有所启发。”

“噢，你真是好学啊，先生！”

孔子两次行礼后站起来，说：“从很小的时候，我就开始追求学问，现在我都六十九岁了，可是我从未听到过完美的讲道，所以除了时刻保持虚心之外我又能做什么呢？”

陌生人说：“物以类聚，每个音符也只是自我回应。这是天所设立的界限。我不会讨论与我相关的事，而只关注你需要了解的东西。先生，你埋头所做的都是人事。天子、诸侯、大臣和百姓，如果这四种人都做正确的事，就能实现美好团结了。如果这四种人分崩离析，那么就会造成可怕的大混乱。如果臣子尽自己的本分，百姓也关心自己的事情，那么人们就不会彼此侵犯。

“田地荒芜，屋顶漏雨，衣食不足，赋税不公正，妻妾不睦，长幼失序，这些都是百姓的烦恼。

“工作能力不足，工作感到无聊，行为不轨，手下粗心懒散，工作没业绩，职位不稳固，这些都是大臣的烦恼。

“没有忠心的臣子，国家陷于内战，工匠技艺不精，贡品毫无价值，春秋集会布置简陋，天子忧虑不安，这些都是诸侯的烦恼。

“阴阳失调，寒暑波动毁坏万物，诸侯的压迫和叛乱，引发暴动，荼毒百姓，礼仪施行不善，国库亏空，社会关系混乱，百姓淫乱，这些都是天子和他的子民的烦恼。

“现在，先生，在这个序列较高的一端，你不是统治者，也不是诸侯，甚至都不是宫廷中的司官，而在另一端，你也没有大臣的职位以及大臣的所有职责。尽管如此，你却决定要修饰礼乐，协调人际关系，并借此教化普通百姓。难道你这不是做得太过了吗？

“另外，有八种毛病是人很容易犯的，还有四种罪恶会影响他们的处事，这些都不能被忽视：

‘不是自己的事情却要参与，是专横。

‘没人理你的时候偏要让人注意，是冒昧。

‘用专门讨好的话来拍别人马屁，是谄媚。

‘对于别人说的话不辨是非，是阿谀。

‘好谈论别人的过失，是谗毁。

‘挑拨朋友和家庭关系，是恶毒。

‘为了伤害别人而虚假称赞，是邪恶。

‘不辨是非，而且为了摸清他人底细两面三刀，是奸诈。

‘这八种毛病不仅给别人造成混乱，而且对实施者自身也会造成伤害。君子不与有这八种毛病的人交朋友，明君也不会任命这样的人做臣子。

‘至于我之前所说的四种罪恶，它们是：

‘野心——喜欢承担大的事业，改变老的传统，希望能够以此提高自己的名声和地位。

‘贪婪——自以为无所不知，试图让所有事情都按照自己的方式来做，把别人做的事情说成是自己做的。

‘顽固——看到自己的错误后不肯改正，坚持按照错误的方式行事。

‘偏狭——别人赞同你时，你笑脸相迎；别人不赞同你了，就绝交并鄙视他们。’

‘这就是那四种罪恶。如果你能消除八种毛病，避免四种罪恶，那么你就达到可以受教的程度了。”

孔子神情哀伤，叹了口气，两次行礼后站起来说：“鲁国两次将我驱逐出境，我从卫国逃离，在宋国他们砍倒了一棵树差点砸到我，而且在陈国、蔡国之间又遭受围困。我不知道我做了什么让人们这样误解我。为什么我要遭受这四种灾祸呢？”

陌生人面露忧容，接着他的脸色就变了，说：“先生，要让你弄明白太难了！曾经有一个人，他害怕自己的影子和脚印，所以他想要逃跑来躲避它们。可是，他每次抬脚放下都会产生更多的脚印，而且不管他跑得有多快，他的影子始终跟着他。他认为自己跑得太慢，就加快速度跑，这样一直不停，直到最后筋疲力尽、倒地而亡。他不知道，只要找个树荫坐下，他就能摆脱他的影子；也不知道，只要静止不动，他就会停止产生脚印。他真是一个大傻瓜啊！

“先生，你想要区分仁义的范围，探求异同的边界，研究静止和运动之间的变化，就给予和接受发表意见，要求人们喜欢什么不喜欢什么，统一喜悦和愤怒的限度，但是你几乎一直没有摆脱过灾祸。要是以前你能严格修身，小心谨慎保全本真，并且愿意让其他的人和物也回归他们本来的样子，那么你本可以避免这些麻烦的。可是，看你现在，自己不能修身却决定要教化别人。难道你不是过于执著于外在事物了吗？”

孔子很沮丧，说：“我能向你请教何为本真吗？”

陌生人答道：“真正的本真是简单纯粹的极致状态。没有纯粹、没有真诚就意味着你不能感动别人。因此，如果你假装哀伤哭泣，那么不论你如何投入，也不是真正的悲伤。如果你强使自己表现愤怒，即便你听上去非常凶猛，也不会让人畏惧。如果你强使自己表现热情，不管你怎样笑，你也不能营造和谐。真正的悲伤可以无声但真是哀痛；真正的愤怒，即便不显露出来，也让人畏惧；真正的感情甚至没有微笑都能营造和谐。如果一个人内心拥有本真，会影响他的外在精神，因此本真非常重要。”

第十四部分　后记

庄子说：“理解道容易，不说它很难。理解却不说，是为了追求属天的。理解并说出，是受制于人的因素。以前人们关注的是属天的，而不是属人的。”

……

宋国有一个人，名叫曹商，宋王派他作为大使出使秦国。在他离开宋国时，只给了他几辆马车。可是，秦王与他相处得很愉快，就给了他一百多辆。返回宋国的路上，他遇到庄子，说：“生活于贫穷村落的简陋街巷中，靠制作草鞋为生，还得忍饥挨饿，弄得颈项干瘪、面容憔悴，这样的日子我无法忍受！但是，得到拥有万辆马车的君王的信任，就可以被赏赐其中的一百辆，这样的日子我喜欢，而且我也擅长于此。”

庄子说：“嗯。秦王生病的时候，他召见医生，谁能切开溃疡挤出脓水就能得到一辆马车作为赏赐。而把药物塞到他直肠之中的医生能得到五辆马车。所医治的病越卑下，赏赐的马车就越多。那么，先生，我想你定是一直为他舔舐痔疮才能得到这么多马车吧？请走开吧，先生！”

……

有人请庄子到朝中做官。庄子答复来使说：“先生，你见过献祭的牛吗？人们用精美的服饰装扮它，用青草和大豆喂养它。可是，当它被牵到太庙之中时，就算它最热切期盼的是单纯地做一头牛犊，又怎么可能呢！”

庄子就要死了，他的弟子想要为他举行隆重的葬礼。庄子说：“我把天地作我的寿衣和棺木，让日月作我的双璧，让群星作我的珠宝，让万物作我的送葬人。我的葬礼一切具备，还缺什么吗？我还需要什么呢？”

他的弟子说：“先生，我们担心乌鸦和老鹰会把您吃掉。”

庄子说：“在地上，我被乌鸦和老鹰吃掉；在地下，还不是被蠕虫和蚂蚁吃掉。夺了这个的给那个，你们这不就是偏袒吗？

“试图用不平等的东西去创造平等，只能是平等地不平等。试图用不确定的东西去证明某事，必然只会让事情不确定。一个人如果视力清晰就以为自己明白，那他只是为视力，而一个人在精神引导之下才能洞见真实。我们用眼睛所看到的东西与我们通过精神所懂得的东西是不同的，这个智慧之见由来已久了。可是愚蠢的人依赖他们的眼睛，陷入只是属人的东西之中而丢失了自我，他所做的一切都只是假象——多可悲啊！”

……

“茫然呆滞的没有形体；

改变和变化永不停歇；

什么是生？什么是死？

什么又是以天地为伴？

清明的精神去向何方？

若被遗忘，又将如何？”

我们被万物环绕，可是没有哪个是我们的归宿。从前人们以为这就是道的方法。庄子听说了这些看法，很高兴。他就用奇怪神秘的说法、荒唐离奇的短语、语意模糊的术语来教授它们。他教授的是他所相信的，可是却从来不偏执，也不会只是从一个角度看待事物。在他眼里，整个世界陷入愚蠢之中，因此已无法理解任何合乎情理之事。

PART 1
Working Everything
Out Evenly

Now, I have something to say. Do I know whether this is in the same sort of category as what is said by others? I don't know. At one level, what I say is not the same. At another level, it most definitely is, and there is no difference between what I say and what others say. Whatever the case, let me try and tell you what I mean.

There is the beginning; there is not as yet any beginning of the beginning; there is not as yet beginning not to be a beginning of the beginning. There is what is, and there is what is not, and it is not easy to say whether what is not, is not; or whether what is, is.

I have just made a statement, yet I do not know whether what I said has been real in what I said or not really said.

Under Heaven there is nothing greater than the tip of a hair, but Mount Tai is smaller; there is no one older than a dead child, yet Peng Tsu died young.

Heaven and Earth and I were born at the same time, and all life and I are one.

As all life is one, what need is there for words? Yet I have just said all life is one, so I have already spoken, haven't I? One plus one equals two, two plus one equals three. To go on from here would take us beyond the understanding of even a skilled accountant, let alone the ordinary people. If going from 'no-thing' to 'some-thing' we get to three, just think how much further we would have to go if we went from 'some-thing' to something!

Don't even start, let's just stay put.

The great Tao has no beginning, and words have changed their meaning from the beginning, but because of the idea of a 'this is' there came to be limitations. I want to say something about these limitations. There is right and left, relationships and their consequences, divisions and disagreements, emulations and contentions. These are known as the eight Virtues.

The sage will not speak of what is beyond the boundaries of the universe-though he will not deny it either. What is within the universe, he says something about but does not pronounce upon. Concerning the record of the past actions of the kings in the Spring and Autumn Annals, the sage discusses but does not judge. When something is divided, something is not divided; when there is disagreement there are things not disagreed about.

You ask, what does this mean? The sage encompasses everything, while ordinary people just argue about things. This is why I say that disagreement means you do not understand at all.

The great Way is not named,

the great disagreement is unspoken,

great benevolence is not benevolent,

great modesty is not humble,

great courage is not violent.

The Tao that is clear is not the Tao,

speech which enables argument is not worthy,

benevolence which is ever present does not achieve its goal,

modesty if flouted, fails,

courage that is violent is pointless.

[...]

Yeh Chueh said to Wang Ni, 'Do you know, Master, what everything agrees upon?'

'How can I possibly know?' said Wang Ni.

'Do you know, Master, what you do not know?'

'How can I know?' he replied.

'Then does nothing know anything?'

'How could I know that?' said Wang Ni. 'Nevertheless, I want to try and say something. How can I know that what I say I know is not actually what I don't know? Likewise, how can I know that what I think I don't know is not really what I do know? I want to put some questions to you:

'If someone sleeps in a damp place, he will ache all over and he will be half paralysed, but is it the same for an eel? If someone climbs a tree, he will be frightened and shaking, but is it so for a monkey? Out of these three, which is wisest about where to live?

'Humans eat meat, deer consume grass, centipedes devour snakes and owls and crows enjoy mice. Of these four, which has the best taste?

'Monkeys mate with each other, deer go with deer. People said that Mao Chiang and Li Chi were the most beautiful women in the world, but fish seeing them dived away, birds took off into the air and deer ran off. Of these four, who really knows true beauty? As I see it, benevolence and righteousness, also the ways of right and wrong, are completely interwoven. I do not think I can know the difference between them!'

Yeh Chueh said: 'Master, if you do not know the difference between that which is good and that which is harmful, does this mean the perfect man is also without such knowledge?'

'The perfect man is pure spirit,' replied Wang Ni. 'He does not feel the heat of the burning deserts nor the cold of the vast waters. He is not frightened by the lightning which can split open mountains, or by the storms that can whip up the seas. Such a person rides the clouds and mounts upon the sun and moon, and wanders across and beyond the four seas. Neither death nor life concern him, nor is he interested in what is good or bad!'

Chu Chiao Tzu asked Chang Wu Tzu,

'I have heard from the Master

that the sage does not labour at anything,

does not look for advantage,

does not act benevolently,

does not harm,

does not pursue the Tao;

He speaks without speaking,

and does not speak when he speaks,

and looks beyond the confines of this dusty world.

'The Master sees all this as an endless stream of words, but to me they are like the words of the mysterious Tao. Master, what do you think?'

Chang Wu Tzu said, 'Such a saying as this would have confused even the Yellow Emperor, so how could Confucius be able to understand them! However, you are getting ahead of yourself, counting your chickens before your eggs are hatched and looking at the bowl, imagining the roasted fowl. I will try to speak to you in a random way, so you listen to me likewise. How can the wise one sit beside the sun and moon and embrace the universe? Because he brings all things together in harmony, he rejects difference and confusion and ignores status and power. While ordinary people rush busily around, the sage seems stupid and ignorant, but to him all life is one and united. All life is simply what it is and all appear to him to be doing what they rightly should.

'How do I know that the love of life is not a delusion? Or that the fear of death is not like a young person running away from home and unable to find his way back? The Lady Li Chi was the daughter of a border warden, Ai. When the state of Chin captured her, she wept until she had drenched her robes; then she came to the King's palace, shared the King's bed, ate his food, and repented of her tears. How do I know whether the dead now repent for their former clinging to life?

'Come the morning, those who dream of the drunken feast may weep and moan; when the morning comes, those who dream of weeping and moaning go hunting in the fields. When they dream, they don't know it is a dream. Indeed, in their dreams they may think they are interpreting dreams, only when they awake do they know it was a dream. Eventually there comes the day of reckoning and awakening, and then we shall know that it was all a great dream. Only fools think that they are now awake and that they really know what is going on, playing the prince and then playing the servant. What fools! The Master and you are both living in a dream. When I say a dream, I am also dreaming. This very saying is a deception. If after ten thousand years we could once meet a truly great sage, one who understands, it would seem as if it had only been a morning.

'Imagine that you and I have a disagreement, and you get the better of me, rather than me getting the better of you, does this mean that you are automatically right and I am automatically wrong? Suppose I get the better of you, does it follow that I am automatically right and you are therefore wrong? Is it really that one of us is right and the other wrong? Or are we both right and both wrong? Neither you nor I can really know and other people are even more in the dark. So who can we ask to give us the right answer? Should you ask someone who thinks you are right? But how then can that person give a fair answer? Should we ask someone who thinks I am right? But then if he agrees with me, how can he make a fair judgement? Then again, should we ask someone who agrees with both of us? But again, if he agrees with both of us, how can he make a true judgement? Should we ask someone who disagrees with both of us? But here again, if he disagrees with both of us, how can he make an honest judgement? It is clear that neither you, I nor anyone else can make decisions like this amongst ourselves. So should we wait for someone else to turn up?

'To wait for one voice to bring it all together is as pointless as waiting for no one. Bring all things together under the Equality of Heaven, allow their process of change to go on unimpeded, and learn to grow old. What do I mean by bringing everything together under the Equality of Heaven? With regard to what is right and wrong, I say not being is being and being is not being. But let us not get caught up in discussing this. Forget about life, forget about worrying about right and wrong. Plunge into the unknown and the endless and find your place there!'

The Outline said to the Shadow, 'First you are on the move, then you are standing still; you sit down and then you stand up. Why can't you make up your mind?'

Shadow replied, 'Do I have to look to something else to be what I am? Does this something else itself not have to rely upon yet another something? Do I have to depend upon the scales of a snake or the wings of a cicada? How can I tell how things are? How can I tell how things are not?'

Once upon a time, I, Chuang Tzu, dreamt that I was a butterfly, flitting around and enjoying myself. I had no idea I was Chuang Tzu. Then suddenly I woke up and was Chuang Tzu again. But I could not tell, had I been Chuang Tzu dreaming I was a butterfly, or a butterfly dreaming I was now Chuang Tzu? However, there must be some sort of difference between Chuang Tzu and a butterfly! We call this the transformation of things.

PART 2
Perfect Accord

Cook Ting was butchering an ox for Lord Wen Hui. Every movement of his hand, every shrug of his shoulder, every step of his feet, every thrust of his knee, every sound of the sundering flesh and the swoosh of the descending knife, were all in perfect accord, like the Mulberry Grove Dance or the rhythm of the Ching-shou.

'Ah, how excellent!' said Lord Wen Hui. 'How has your skill become so superb?'

Cook Ting put down his knife and said, 'What your servant loves best is the Tao, which is better than any art. When I started to cut up oxen, what I saw was just a complex ox. After three years, I had learnt not to see the ox as whole. Now I practise with my mind, not with my eyes. I ignore my sense and follow my spirit. I see the natural lines and my knife slides through the great hollows, follows the great cavities, using that which is already there to my advantage. Thus, I miss the great sinews and even more so, the great bones. A good cook changes his knife annually, because he slices. An ordinary cook has to change his knife every month, because he hacks. Now this knife of mine I have been using for nineteen years, and it has cut thousands of oxen. However, its blade is as sharp as if it had just been sharpened. Between the joints there are spaces, and the blade of a knife has no real thickness. If you put what has no thickness into spaces such as these, there is plenty of room, certainly enough for the knife to work through. However, when I come to a difficult part and can see that it will be difficult, I take care and pay due regard. I look carefully and I move with caution. Then, very gently, I move the knife until there is a parting and the flesh falls apart like a lump of earth falling to the ground. I stand with the knife in my hand looking around and then, with an air of satisfaction, I wipe the knife and put it away.'

'Splendid!' said Lord Wen Hui. 'I have heard what cook Ting has to say and from his words I have learned how to live life fully.'

When Kung Wen Hsien saw the Commander of the Right he was surprised and said, 'Who is this man? Why has he only got one foot? Is this from Heaven or from man?'

'From Heaven, not from man,' said the Commander. 'My life came from Heaven, which also gave me just one foot. The human appearance is a gift, which is why I know that this is from Heaven, not from man. The marsh pheasant manages one peck every ten paces, and one drink every hundred steps, but it does not wish to be kept in a cage. Even if you treated it like a king, its spirit would not be happy.'

When Lao Tzu died, Chin Shih came to mourn for him. He uttered three shouts and then left.

A follower of the Master said, 'Wasn't the Master a friend of yours?'

'Certainly,' he replied.

'Then do you really think this way of mourning is best?'

'Certainly. To begin with I thought these were real men, but now I am not so sure. When I came in to mourn, there were old folk weeping as though they had lost a child; there were young people wailing as if for the loss of a mother. Such a gathering of everyone, all talking away though he didn't ask them to talk and weeping even though he didn't ask for tears! This is to turn from Heaven and to indulge in emotions, ignoring what is given. The ancient ones called this the result of violating the principles of Heaven. When the Master came, it was because he was due to be born. When he died, it was entirely natural. If you are prepared to accept this and flow with it, then sorrow and joy cannot touch you. The ancient ones considered this the work of the gods who free us from bondage.

'We can point to the wood that has been burned, but when the fire has passed on, we cannot know where it has gone.'

[...]

Yen Ho was about to start as tutor to the eldest son of Duke Ling of the state of Wei, so he went to visit Chu Po Yu and said, 'Here is a man whom Heaven has given a nature devoid of all virtue. If I simply allow him to go on in this way, the state is at risk; if I try to bring him back to a principled life, then my life is at risk. He can just about recognize the excesses of others, but not his own excesses. In a case like this, what can I do?'

'This is a good question!' said Chu Po Yu. 'Be on guard, be careful, make sure you yourself are right. Let your appearance be in agreement, let your heart be content and harmonious. However, both these strategies have their dangers. Do not let your outward stance affect your inner self, nor allow your inner self to be drawn out. If you allow yourself to be sucked into his way of things, you will be thrown down, ruined, demolished, and will fall. If your inner harmony becomes drawn out, then you will have fame and a name, you will be called an evil creature. If he acts like a child, then be a child with him; if he permits no restraints, do the same. If he goes beyond the pale, follow him! Understand him, and then guide him back subtly.

'Don't you know the story of the praying mantis? In its anger it waved its arms in front of a speeding carriage, having no understanding that it could not stop it, but having full confidence in its own powers! Be on guard, be careful! If you are over-confident in this way, you will be in the same danger.

'Don't you know what a tiger trainer does? He does not give them living animals for food, in case it over-excites them and breeds a love of killing. He does not even give them whole carcasses, for fear of exciting the rage of tearing the animals apart. He observes their appetite and appreciates their ferocity. Tigers are a different creature from humans, but you can train them to obey their trainer if you understand how to adapt to them. People who go against the nature of the tiger don't last long.

'People who love horses collect their manure and urine in fine baskets and bottles. However, if a mosquito or gadfly lands on the horse, and the groom suddenly swipes it away, the horse breaks its bit, damages its harness and hurts its chest. The groom, out of affection, tried to do what was good, but the end result is the reverse of that. Thus should we exercise caution!'

Carpenter Shih was on his way to Chi, when he came to the place called Chu Yuan, where he saw an oak tree which was venerated as the home of the spirits of the land. The tree was so vast that a thousand oxen could hide behind it. It was a hundred spans round and it soared above the hill to eighty feet before it even began to put out branches. There were ten such branches, from any one of which an entire boat could be carved. Masses of people came to see it, giving the place a carnival atmosphere, but carpenter Shih didn't even look round, just went on his way. His assistant looked at it with great intensity, and then chased after his master and said, 'Since I first took up my axe and followed you, I have never seen wood such as this. Sir, why did you not even glance at it nor stop, but just kept going?'

He said, 'Silence, not another word! The tree is useless. Make a boat from it and it would sink; make a coffin and it would rot quickly; make some furniture and it would fall to pieces; make a door and it would be covered in seeping sap; make a pillar and it would be worm-eaten. This wood is useless and good for nothing. This is why it has lived so long.'

When Master Shih was returning, the tree appeared to him in a dream, saying, 'What exactly are you comparing me with? With ornamental fruit trees? Trees such as the hawthorn, pear trees, orange trees, citrus trees, gourds and other such fruit trees? Their fruits are knocked down when they are ripe and the trees suffer. The big branches are damaged and the small ones are broken off. Because they are useful, they suffer, and they are unable to live out the years Heaven has given them. They have only their usefulness to blame for this destruction wrought by the people. It is the same with all things. I have spent a long time studying to be useless, though on a couple of occasions I was nearly destroyed. However, now I have perfected the art of uselessness, and this is very useful, to me! If I had been of use, could I have grown so vast? Furthermore, you and I are both things. How can one thing make such statements about another? How can you, a useless man about to die, know anything about a useless tree?'

When carpenter Shih awoke, he told his apprentice what he had dreamt. The apprentice said, 'If it wants to be useless, why is it used as the shrine for the spirits of the land?'

'Hush! Don't say another word!' said Shih. 'The tree happens to be here so it is an altar. By this it protects itself from harm from those who do not realize it is useless, for were it not an altar, it would run the risk of being chopped down. Furthermore, this tree is no ordinary one, so to speak of it in normal terms is to miss the point.'

Nan Po Tzu Chi, wandering amongst the mountains of Shang, came upon a great and unusual tree, under which could shelter a thousand chariots, and they would all be covered. Tzu Chi said, 'What kind of a tree is this? It is surely a most wondrous piece of timber!' However, when he looked up, he could see that the smaller branches were so twisted and gnarled that they could not be made into rafters and beams; and looking down at the trunk he saw it was warped and distorted and would not make good coffins. He licked one of its leaves and his mouth felt scraped and sore. He sniffed it and it nearly drove him mad, as if he had been drunk for three days.

'This tree is certainly good for nothing,' said Tzu Chi. 'This is why it has grown so large. Ah-ha! This is the sort of uselessness that sages live by.

'In the state of Sung there is the district of Ching Shih, which is excellent for growing catalpas, cypresses and mulberry trees. However, those which are more than a handspan or so around are cut down by people who want to make posts for their monkeys; those which are three or four spans around are cut down to make beams for great houses; those of seven to eight spans are cut down by lords and the wealthy who want single planks to form the side of their coffins. As a result, the trees do not live out the years Heaven has allotted them, but instead are cut down by the axe in the prime of their life. This is all the result of being useful! At the sacrifice, oxen marked by the white forehead, pigs that have turned-up noses and men suffering from piles are useless as offerings to the River Ho. Shamans know this and as a result they consider such creatures as being inauspicious. However, the sage, for exactly this same reason, values them highly.

'Crippled Shu, now, is a man with his chin lost in his navel, his shoulders higher than the top of his head and his topknot pointing to Heaven, his five vital organs all crushed into the top of his body and his two thighs pressing into his ribs. By sharpening needles and washing clothes he earns enough to eat. By winnowing rice and cleaning it he was able to feed ten people. When the officials called up the militia, he walked about freely, with no need to hide; when they are trying to raise a large work gang, because of his deformities, no one bothers him. Yet when the officials were handing out grain to the infirm, he received three great portions and ten bundles of firewood. If a man like this, deformed in body, can make a living and live out the years Heaven sends him, how much more should a man who is only deformed in terms of his Virtue!'

[...]

In the state of Lu there was a mutilated man called Shu Shan the Toeless. He came upon his stumps to see Confucius. Confucius said, 'You were not careful and therefore suffered this fate. It is too late to come and see me now.'

'Because of my lack of knowledge and through lack of care for my body, I lost my feet,' said Toeless. 'Now I have come to you because I still have that which is of greater value than my foot and I wish to save it. There is nothing that great Heaven does not cover, nor anything that the Earth does not sustain. I had hoped you, Sir, would be as Heaven and Earth to me, and I did not expect you to receive me like this!'

'I am being stupid!' said Confucius. 'Good Sir, please do not go away and I will try to share with you what I have learnt!'

However, Toeless left and Confucius said, 'Be watchful, my followers! Great Toeless has lost his feet but still he wants to learn in order to recompense for his evil deeds. How much more so should you who are ablebodied want to learn!'

Toeless told his story to Lao Tzu, saying, 'Confucius has definitely not become a perfect man yet, has he? So why does he try to study with you? He seems to be caught up with the search for honour and reputation, without appearing to understand that the perfect man sees these as chains and irons.'

Lao Tzu said, 'Why not help him to see that death and birth are one thing and that right and wrong are one thing, and so free him from the chains and irons?'

'Given that Heaven punishes him, how can he be set free?' asked Toeless.

Duke Ai of Lu said to Confucius, 'In Wei there was a man with a terrible appearance called Ai Tai To. But those around him thought the world of him and when women saw him they ran to their mothers and fathers saying, "I would rather be the concubine of this gentleman than anyone else's wife." This has happened more than ten times. He was never heard to take the lead in anything, but was always in accord with others. He was not powerful and thus able to save people from death, nor was he wealthy and able to feed people. Furthermore, he was so hideous he could scare the whole world. He never took the lead, just agreed with whatever was suggested, and he knew little about the world beyond his own four walls. But people came flocking to him. It is clear he is different from ordinary people, so I asked him to come and see me. He certainly was ugly enough to frighten the whole world. Yet he had only been with me for less than a month when I began to appreciate him. Within a year I had full trust in him. In my country there was no prime minister, so I offered him the post. His response to my request was to look most sorrowful and diffident as if he was going to turn it down. I was ashamed of myself but in the end simply handed over the country to him. Very soon after, he upped and left. I was distressed and felt this a great loss, for I had no one with whom to share the cares of the state. Now, what sort of man is this?'

Confucius said, 'I was once in the state of Chu on a commission, and I saw some piglets trying to suckle from their dead mother. After a while they started up and left her. She did not seem to notice them and so they no longer felt any affinity with her. What they loved about their mother was not her body but what gave life to the body. When a man is killed in battle, at his burial his battle honours are of little use to him. A man without feet has little love for shoes. In both cases they lack that which makes these of any significance. Indeed, the consorts of the Son of Heaven do not cut their own nails or pierce their ears; a newly wed gentleman stays outside the court and is freed from onerous duties. With so much attention being paid to caring for the body, imagine what care should be given to preserving Virtue! Now Ai Tai To speaks not a word, yet he is believed. He does nothing and is loved. People offer him their kingdoms, and their only fear is that he will refuse. He must indeed be a man of perfect character, whose Virtue is without shape!'

'What do you mean by "perfect character"?' asked Duke Ai.

Confucius replied, 'Death, birth, existence and trouble, auspicious and inauspicious signs, wealth, poverty, value and worthlessness, glory and blame, hunger and thirst, cold and hot-all these are the way the world goes and the result of destiny. Day and night follow each other, but there is no way of knowing where they come from. Don't allow this to disrupt your innate balance, don't allow this to perturb your mind. If you can balance and enjoy them, have mastery over them and revel in this, if you can do this day in and day out without a break and bring all things together, then this brings forth a heart prepared for changes and this is perfect character.'

'But what do you mean when you say his Virtue is without shape?'

'Perfect balance is found in still waters. Such water should be an example to us all. Inner harmony is protected and nothing external affects it. Virtue is the result of true balance. Virtue has no shape or form yet nothing can be without it,' said Confucius.

PART 3
So What is a True Man?

The one who understands Heaven and understands the ways of humanity has perfection. Understanding Heaven, he grows with Heaven. Understanding humanity, he takes the understanding of what he understands to help him understand what he doesn't understand, and so fulfils the years Heaven decrees without being cut off in his prime. This is known as perfection.

However, it is true that there are problems. Real understanding has to have something to which it is applied and this something is itself uncertain. So how can I know that what I term Heaven is not human? Or that what I call human is not Heaven?

Only the true man has understanding. So what is a true man? The true man of old did not fight against poverty, nor did he look for fulfilment through riches-for he had no grand plans. Therefore, he never regretted any failure, nor exulted in success. He could scale the heights without fear, plumb the depths without difficulties and go through fire without pain. This is the kind of person whose understanding has lifted him up towards the Tao.

The true man of old slept without dreaming and awoke without anxiety. He ate without tasting, breathing deeply, incredibly deeply. The true man breathes from his feet up, while ordinary people just breathe from the throat. The words of broken people come forth like vomit. Wallowing in lust and desire, they are but shallow in the ways of Heaven.

The true man of old did not hold on to life, nor did he fear death. He arrived without expectation and left without resistance. He went calmly, he came calmly and that was that. He did not set out to forget his origin, nor was he interested in what would become of him. He loved to receive anything but also forgot what he had received and gave it away. He did not give precedence to the heart but to the Tao, nor did he prefer the ways of humanity to those of Heaven. This is what is known as a true man.

Being like this, his heart forgets,

his appearance is calm,

his forehead is plain;

He is as chilly as autumn and as warming as spring.

His joy and anger arise like the four seasons.

He acts properly towards all things

and none know where this will lead.

So if the sage summons the army and conquers states,

he does not lose the affections of the people.

His magnanimous nature enriches ten thousand generations,

yet he has no affection for the people.

One who seeks to share his happiness with others is not a sage.

One who displays his feelings is not benevolent.

One who waits for Heaven is not a wise man.

The noble who cannot harmonize the good and the destructive is not a scholar.

One who seeks for fame and thereby loses his real self is no gentleman.

One who loses his true self and his path is unable to command others.

[...]

The true man of old appeared aloof but was in no danger of falling.

He appears deficient, yet takes nothing.

He does what he wills but is not judgemental.

His emptiness was clear, but there was no showing off.

Cheerfully smiling, he seemed to be content.

He responded immediately as if there was no choice.

If upset, he showed it.

If content, he was at ease with Virtue.

When calm, he appeared to be one with the world.

When superior, the world had no control over him.

His inner nature seemed unknowable.

Never being really aware, he forgot what to say.

He saw the law as the external form of government.

The rituals he saw as the wings,

knowledge as being the same as what is appropriate at the time.

Virtue he saw as what is proper.

Viewing law as the external form of government,

he was flexible in imposing the death sentence.

Viewing the rituals as the wings,

he got on well with society.

Viewing knowledge as being that which is appropriate,

he followed the natural course of events.

Viewing virtue as that which is proper,

he walked along with others who were capable of leading.

So he acted spontaneously,

but others thought it was at great cost.

Thus all that he sought was one.

What he disowned was also but one.

What is one is one, and what is not one is also one.

In the one, he was with Heaven.

In the not-one, he was one with humanity.

When heaven and humanity are not in dispute,

then we can say this is really the true man.

Death and birth are fixed. They are as certain as the dawn that comes after the night, established by the decree of Heaven. This is beyond the control of humanity, this is just how things are. Some view Heaven as their father and continue to love it. How much more should they show devotion for that which is even greater! Some people consider their lord as being better than themselves and would willingly die for him. How much more should they do the same for one who is more true than their lord!

When the springs dry out, the fish are found stranded on the earth. They keep each other damp with their own moisture, and wet each other with their slime. But it would be better if they could just forget about each other in rivers and lakes. People sing the praises of Yao and condemn Chieh, but it would be better if they could forget both of them and just follow the Tao. The cosmos gives me the burden of a physical form, makes life a struggle, gives me rest in old age and peace in death. What makes life good, therefore, also makes death good.

A boat can be hidden in a gorge, and a fishing net in a pool, and you may think they are therefore safe. However, in the middle of the night a strong man comes and carries them off. Small-minded people just cannot see that hiding smaller things in larger things does not mean they will not be stolen. If you take everything under Heaven and try to store it under Heaven, there is no space left for it to be lost in! This is the real truth about things. To have a human form is a joyful thing. But in the universe of possible forms, there are others just as good. Isn't it a blessing to have these uncountable possibilities! The sage goes where nothing escapes him, and rests contented there with them. He takes pleasure in an early death, in old age, in the origin and in the end and sees them all as equally good-he should be an example to others. If this is so, then how much more should our example be that which holds together the whole of life and which is the origin of all that changes!

The great Tao has both reality and expression, but it does nothing and has no form.

It can be passed on, but not received.

It can be obtained, but not seen.

It is rooted in its own self, existing before Heaven and Earth were born, indeed for eternity.

It gives divinity to the spirits and to the gods.

It brought to life Heaven and Earth.

It was before the primal air, yet it cannot be called lofty;

it was below all space and direction, yet it cannot be called deep.

It comes before either Heaven or Earth, yet it cannot be called old.

It is far more ancient than antiquity, yet it is not old.

[...]

The Masters, Ssu, Yu, Li and Lai, said one to another, 'Anyone who can conceive of nothingness as his head, life as his back and death as his tail and who knows that death and birth, being and no-being, are one and the same-one like this shall be our friend.' The four men smiled and agreed in their hearts and therefore became friends.

Shortly after, Master Yu fell ill. Master Ssu went to visit him and Yu said, 'How great is the Maker of All! He has made me deformed. My back is like a hunchback's, and all my organs are on top while my chin is lost in my navel and my shoulders rise up above my head and my topknot points to Heaven!' His yin and yang were in disarray. However, his heart was calm and he was not worried. He limped to a well and looked in at his reflection and said, 'Goodness me! The Maker of All has made me completely deformed!'

'Do you dislike it?' asked Master Ssu.

'Not really, why should I? For example, perhaps my left arm will become a cockerel and then I shall be able to tell the time at night. Maybe, eventually, my right arm will become a crossbow and then I can hunt a bird and eat it. Possibly my bottom will become wheels and my soul will be a horse which I shall climb upon and go for a ride. After all, I wouldn't then need any other vehicle again! I obtained life because the time was right. I will lose life because it is time. Those who go quietly with the flow of nature are not worried by either joy or sorrow. People like these were considered in the past as having achieved freedom from bondage. Those who cannot free themselves are constrained by things. However, nothing can overcome Heaven-it has always been so. So why should I dislike this?'

Later Master Lai fell ill. Gasping and heaving, he lay close to death. His wife and children were mourning around him. Master Li came to see him and Master Lai said, 'Hush, get out! Do you want to disrupt the processes of change?'

Leaning against the doorway Li commented,

'How great is the Maker of All!

What will you be made into next?

Where will you be sent?

Will you come back as a rat's liver?

Or will it be as a pest's arm?'

Master Lai said,

'When a mother and father tell a child to go somewhere,

be that east, west, south or north, the child obeys.

Yin and yang are the mother and father of humanity.

They have brought me close to death

and if I disobey this would be just perversity.

My death is not their problem!

The cosmos gives me form, brings me to birth,

guides me into old age and settles me in death.

If I think my life good, then I must think my death good.

A good craftsman, casting metal,

would not be too pleased with metal that jumped up and said,

"I must be made into a sword like Mo Yeh."

Now, given that I have been bold enough

to take on human shape already, if I then said,

"I must be a human, I must be a human!",

the Maker of All would view me somewhat askance!

If Heaven and Earth are like a furnace and Nature is the craftsman,

then is it possible he could send me anywhere that was not appropriate?

Peacefully we die, calmly we awake.'

PART 4
Simply Fate!

Masters Yu and Sang were friends. It happened to rain for ten days, and Master Yu said, 'Master Sang may be in trouble!' So he packed some food to take to him. Arriving at Master Sang's door he heard strange noises and someone playing a lute, singing,

'Oh Father! Oh Mother! Oh Heaven! Oh humanity!'

It sounded as if the singer's voice was about to break and the singer was rushing to finish the verse. Master Yu entered and said, 'Master, why are you singing like this?'

He said, 'I was trying to work out what has reduced me to this. My father and mother wouldn't want me to be so poor, surely? Heaven treats all alike. Earth supports all alike. Heaven and Earth wouldn't wish me poor, would they? I seek to know who has done this, but I can't find an answer. When you come down to it, it must be simply fate.'

[...]

Tien Ken was travelling to the south of Yin Mountain. He reached the river Liao, where he met the Man without a Name and said to him, 'I wish to ask you about governing everything under Heaven.'

The Man without a Name said, 'Get lost, you stupid lout! What an unpleasant question! I am travelling with the Maker of All. If that is too tiring, I shall ride the bird of ease and emptiness and go beyond the compass of the world and wander in the land of nowhere and the region of nothing. So why are you disturbing me and unsettling my heart with questions about how to rule all below Heaven?'

Tien Ken asked the same question again. The Man without a Name replied.

'Let your heart journey in simplicity.

Be one with that which is beyond definition.

Let things be what they are.

Have no personal views.

This is how everything under Heaven is ruled.'

Yan Tzu Chu went to visit Lao Tzu and he said, 'Here is a man who is keen and vigilant, who has clarity of vision and wisdom and who studies the Tao without ceasing. Such a person as this is surely a king of great wisdom?'

'In comparison to the sage,' said Lao Tzu, 'someone like this is just a humble servant, tied to his work, exhausting himself and distressing his heart. The tiger and the leopard, it is said, are hunted because of the beauty of their hides. The monkey and the dog end up in chains because of their skills. Can these be compared to a king of great wisdom?'

Yang Tzu Chu was startled and said, 'May I be so bold as to ask about the rule of a king who is great in wisdom?'

Lao Tzu said,

'The rule of a king who is great in wisdom!

His works affect all under Heaven, yet he seems to do nothing.

His authority reaches all life, yet no one relies upon him.

There is no fame or glory for him but everything fulfils itself.

He stands upon mystery and wanders where there is nothing.'

In Chen there was a shaman of the spirits called Chi Hsien. He could foretell when people would die and be born; he knew about good fortune and failure as granted by Heaven; he knew about happiness and distress, life and its span, knowing the year, month, week and day, as if he were a god himself. As soon as the people of Cheng saw him coming, they would run away. Lieh Tzu went to see him and was fascinated by him. Coming back to Hu Tzu, he said, 'I used to believe, Master, that your Tao was perfection. Now I have found something even better.'

Hu Tzu said, 'What I have shown you is the outward text of my teaching, but not what is central. How can you think you have grasped my Tao? If you have hens but no cockerel, how can you have eggs? You flaunt your Tao before the world. This is why this man can read your fortune. Bring this shaman to me and let us meet.'

The next day Lieh Tzu brought the shaman to visit Hu Tzu. And as he left Hu Tzu's house with Lieh Tzu, the shaman said, 'Oh dear! Your Master is dying. There's virtually no life left-he has maybe a week at most. I saw a strange sight - it was like wet ashes!'

Lieh Tzu went in again, weeping so copiously that tears soaked his coat, and told Hu Tzu what had been said. Hu Tzu said, 'I made myself appear like the earth. I was as solid as the mountain, showing nothing to him. He probably perceived me to be a closed book, apparently without virtue. Bring him again if you can.'

The next day Lieh Tzu came again with the shaman to see Hu Tzu. As they went out, the shaman said to Lieh Tzu, 'How lucky for your Master that he has met me. He is getting better. Indeed he is truly alive. Life is flowing again.'

Lieh Tzu went back in and commented on this to Hu Tzu. Hu Tzu said, 'I made myself appear to him like Heaven, without fame or fortune on my mind. What I am wells up in me naturally. He saw in me the full and natural workings of life. Bring him again if you can.'

The next day they came again to see Hu Tzu. As they went out, the shaman said to Lieh Tzu, 'Your Master is never the same. I cannot grasp the fortune shown in his face. If he returns to some constancy then I will come and see him again.'

Lieh Tzu went back in and reported this to Hu Tzu. 'I showed him myself as the great Void where all is equal,' said Hu Tzu. 'He almost certainly saw in me the harmony of my innate forces. When water moves about, there is a whirlpool; where the waters are calm, there is a whirlpool; where the waters gather, there is a whirlpool. There are nine types of whirlpool and I have shown him just three. Bring him back again if you can.'

The next day they both came again to see him. However, before he had even sat down, the shaman panicked and ran off. Hu Tzu said, 'Follow him!'

Lieh Tzu ran after him. But he could not catch up with him. Coming back to Hu Tzu, he said, 'He has gone, I've lost him. I couldn't catch him.'

Hu Tzu said, 'I just appeared to him as hitherto unrevealed potential. I presented myself as not knowing who is who, nor what is what. I came flowing and changing as I willed. That's why he bolted.'

As a result of this, Lieh Tzu realized that he had so far learnt nothing real, so he returned home. For three years he did not go out. He cooked for his wife and tended the pigs as if they were humans. He showed no interest in his studies. He cast aside his desires and sought the truth. In his body he became like the ground itself. In the midst of everything he remained enclosed with the One and that is how he remained until the end.

Do not hanker for fame.

Do not make plans.

Do not try to do things.

Do not try to master knowledge.

Hold what is but do not hold it to be anything.

Work with all that comes from Heaven, but do not seek to hold it.

Just be empty.

The perfect man's heart is like a mirror.

It does not search after things.

It does not look for things.

It does not seek knowledge, just responds.

As a result he can handle everything and is not harmed by anything.

[...]

One on the true path does not lose his innate given nature.

To such a man that which is united presents no problem;

That which is divided is all right;

What is long is not too long;

That which is short is not too short.

The duck's legs for example are short, but trying to lengthen them would cause pain.

The legs of a crane are long, but trying to shorten them would produce grief.

What nature makes long we should not cut,

nor should we try to stretch what nature makes short.

That would not solve anything.

Perhaps then, benevolence and righteousness are not an inherent part of human nature? For look how much anxiety is suffered by those who wish to be kind.

PART 5
Hui Tzu

Hui Tzu spoke to Chuang Tzu, saying, 'The King of Wei gave me the seeds of an enormous gourd, which I planted and it produced a fruit big enough to hold five bushels of anything, so I used it to hold water, but it was then too heavy to pick up. I cut it into two to make scoops, but they were too awkward to use. It was not that they weren't big, I just found I could not make use of them, so I destroyed them.'

Chuang Tzu said, 'Dear Sir, surely the problem is that you don't know how to use big things. There is a man in Sung who could make a cream which prevented the hands from getting chapped, and generation after generation of his family have made a living by bleaching silk. A pilgrim heard this and offered to buy the secret for a hundred pieces of gold. All the family came together to respond and said, "For generation after generation we have bleached silk, yet we have never made more than a few pieces of gold; now in just one morning we can earn a hundred pieces of gold! Let's do it." So the pilgrim got the secret and went to see the King of Wu. He was struggling with the state of Yueh. The King of Wu gave the pilgrim command of the army and in the depths of winter they fought the men of Yueh on the water, inflicting a crushing blow on the forces of Yueh, and the traveller was rewarded by the gift of a vast estate from the conquered territory. The cream had stopped the hands chapping in both cases: one gained an estate, but the others had never got further than bleaching silk, because they used this secret in such different ways. Now, Sir, you have a gourd big enough to hold five bushels, so why didn't you use it to make big bottles which could help you float down the rivers and lakes, instead of dismissing it as being useless? Because, dear Sir, your head is full of straw!'

Hui Tzu spoke to Chuang Tzu, saying, 'I have a big tree, which people call useless. Its trunk is so knotted, no carpenter could work on it, while its branches are too twisted to use a square or compass upon. So, although it is close to the road, no carpenter would look at it. Now, Sir, your words are like this, too big and no use, therefore everyone ignores them.'

Chuang Tzu said, 'Sir, have you never seen a wild cat or weasel? It lies there, crouching and waiting; east and west it leaps out, not afraid of going high or low; until it is caught in a trap and dies in a net. Yet again, there is the yak, vast like a cloud in heaven. It is big, but cannot use this fact to catch rats. Now you, Sir, have a large tree, and you don't know how to use it, so why not plant it in the middle of nowhere, where you can go to wander or fall asleep under its shade? No axe under Heaven will attack it, nor shorten its days, for something which is useless will never be disturbed.'

[...]

Hui Tzu asked Chuang Tzu, 'Is it possible for someone to be without emotion?'

'Certainly,' said Chuang Tzu.

'A man without emotion-can you really call him a man?' asked Hui Tzu.

Chuang Tzu replied, 'The Way gives him a face and Heaven provides a shape, so how can it follow he is not called a man?'

'But if he is already called a man, how can it follow that he has no emotion?'

'That's not what I mean by emotions,' said Chuang Tzu. 'When I say a man has no emotions, what I mean by this is someone who does not allow either the good or the bad to have any effect upon him. He lets all things be and allows life to continue in its own way.'

Hui Tzu said, 'If he doesn't interfere with life, then how does he take care of himself?'

'The Way gives him a face and Heaven provides a shape. He does not allow either the good or the bad to have any effect on him. But you now, you wear your soul on your sleeve, exhausting your energy, propping yourself up on a tree, mumbling, or bent over your desk, asleep. Heaven gives you a form and you wear it out by pointless argument!'

[...]

Hui Tzu was made Minister of State in Liang and Chuang Tzu went to see him. Someone told Hui Tzu, 'Chuang Tzu is coming, because he wants to oust you from your office.' This alarmed Hui Tzu and he scoured the kingdom for three days and nights trying to find this stranger.

Chuang Tzu went to see him and said, 'In the south there is a bird known as the Young Phoenix, do you know about this, Sir? This bird, it arises in the Southern Ocean and flies to the Northern Ocean and it never rests on anything except the begonia tree, never eats except the fruit of the melia azederach and never drinks except from springs of sweet water. There was once an owl who had clutched in his talons a rotting rat corpse. As the Young Phoenix flew overhead the owl looked up and said, "Shoo!" Now you, Sir, you have the state of Liang and you feel you have to shoo me away?'

Chuang Tzu and Hui Tzu were walking beside the weir on the River Hao, when Chuang Tzu said, 'Do you see how the fish are coming to the surface and swimming around as they please? That's what fish really enjoy.'

'You're not a fish,' replied Hui Tzu, 'so how can you say you know what fish enjoy?'

Chuang Tzu said: 'You are not me, so how can you know I don't know what fish enjoy?'

Hui Tzu said: 'I am not you, so I definitely don't know what it is you know. However, you are most definitely not a fish and that proves that you don't know what fish really enjoy.'

Chuang Tzu said: 'Ah, but let's return to the original question you raised, if you don't mind. You asked me how I could know what it is that fish really enjoy. Therefore, you already knew I knew it when you asked the question. And I know it by being here on the edge of the River Hao.'

[...]

Chuang Tzu's wife died and Hui Tzu came to console him, but Chuang Tzu was sitting, legs akimbo, bashing a battered tub and singing.

Hui Tzu said, 'You lived as man and wife, she reared your children. At her death surely the least you should be doing is to be on the verge of weeping, rather than banging the tub and singing: this is not right!'

Chuang Tzu said, 'Certainly not. When she first died, I certainly mourned just like everyone else! However, I then thought back to her birth and to the very roots of her being, before she was born. Indeed, not just before she was born but before the time when her body was created. Not just before her body was created but before the very origin of her life's breath. Out of all this, through the wonderful mystery of change she was given her life's breath. Her life's breath wrought a transformation and she had a body. Her body wrought a transformation and she was born. Now there is yet another transformation and she is dead. She is like the four seasons in the way that spring, summer, autumn and winter follow each other. She is now at peace, lying in her chamber, but if I were to sob and cry it would certainly appear that I could not comprehend the ways of destiny. This is why I stopped.'

[...]

Chuang Tzu said, 'An archer, not bothering to take aim, by sheer luck hits the centre of the target. We could call him a good archer, but in that case, everyone in the world could be called a Yi the Archer, isn't that right?'

'OK,' said Hui Tzu.

Chuang Tzu said, 'People differ over what they consider to be right, but everyone knows what they think is right. So everyone in the world could be called a Yao, isn't that right?'

'OK,' said Hui Tzu.

Chuang Tzu said, 'So, there are four schools-the Literati, Mohists, Yangists and Pingists-which along with your own, Sir, make five. So which of these is right? Perhaps it is more like the case of Lu Chu? One of his followers said, "I have taken hold of your Tao, Master, and I can heat the pot in winter and make ice in summer." Lu Chu said, "But this is surely just using yang for yang and yin for yin. This is not what I would call the Tao. I will show you my Tao." So he tuned up two lutes and put one in the hall and the other in a private apartment. On striking the note Kung on one, the Kung note vibrated on the other. Likewise with the Chueh note, for the instruments were in harmony. Then he re-tuned one so that it was not in harmony with any of the five key notes. When this was played, all twenty-five of the strings on the other one vibrated, all faithful to their own note and all set off by the one note on the other lute. So, if you insist you are right, aren't you like this?'

Hui Tzi replied, 'The followers of Confucius, Mo, Yang and Ping, like to tackle me in debate, each one trying to defeat the other, each violently trying to shout me down with their various arguments-but they haven't succeeded yet. So what about that?'

Chuang Tzu said, 'A citizen of Chi, not concerned by any mutilation, sold his son to someone in Sung, where he became a gatekeeper. Yet this same man would go to great lengths to protect any of his bells or chimes. But he would not go looking for his son beyond the borders of his own country, such was his understanding of what is worthwhile! Or what if that well-known character, the citizen of Chu who was maimed and a gatekeeper, at midnight in another country, were to pick a fight with a boatman? Then he would never get across the river and would only have provoked the boatman's anger.'

[...]

Hui Tzu argued with Chuang Tzu and said, 'What you say is useless!'

'You have to understand what is useless, then you can talk about what is useful,' said Chuang Tzu. 'Heaven and Earth are vast indeed and yet human beings only use the tiny part of the universe on which they tread. However, if you dug away beneath your feet until you came to the Yellow Springs, could anyone make use of this?'

'Useless,' said Hui Tzu.

'So indeed it is true that what is useless is clearly useful,' said Chuang Tzu.

Chuang Tzu continued, 'If someone has the itch to travel, what can stop him? But if someone does not wish to travel, then what can make him? The one who hides in conformity or the one who is distant and seeks oblivion, both fail to achieve perfect understanding and Virtue! They stumble and fall but do not recover. They crash ahead like fire and never look back. Even if they are a ruler with ministers, this too passes. These titles change with each generation and neither is better than the other. It is said that the perfect man leaves no trace of his actions.

'To respect the past and despise the present, this is what scholars do. Even the followers of Chi Hsi Wei, who view this generation in that way, are swept along without choice. Only the perfect man is able to be in the world and not become partisan, can follow others and not get lost. He does not absorb their teachings, he just listens and understands without any commitment.

'The eye that is penetrating can see clearly;

the ear that is acute hears well;

the nose that discriminates distinguishes smells;

the mouth with a keen sense of taste enjoys the flavours;

the heart that feels deeply has wisdom

and the wisdom that cuts to the quick is Virtue.

'Through all that is, the Tao will not be blocked, for if it is blocked, it gasps, and if it gasps, chaos breaks through. Chaos destroys the life in all. Everything that lives does so through breath. However, if breath will not come, this cannot be blamed on Heaven. Heaven seeks to course breath through the body day in and day out without ceasing: it is humanity which impedes this. The womb has its chambers and the heart has its Heavenly journey. However, if rooms are not large enough, then mother-in-law and wife will argue. If the heart does not wander in Heaven, then the six openings of sensation will compete with each other. The great forests, the hills and mountains surpass humanity in their spirit because they cannot be overcome.

'Virtue overflows into fame and desire for fame overflows into excess. Plans arise from a crisis and knowledge comes through argument. Obstinacy fuels resolution and official actions arise from the desires of all. When spring comes, the rains come along with the sunshine, the plants surge into life and harvesting tools are made ready again. Half of all that has fallen begins to sprout, and no one knows why for sure.

'Quietude and silence are healing for those who are ill;

massage is beneficial to the old;

peaceful contemplation can calm the distressed.

To be sure, it is only the disturbed person who needs these.

Someone who is at ease and is untroubled by such things has no need of this.

The sage reforms everything below Heaven, but the spiritual man does not enquire how.

The worthy person improves his generation, but the sage does not enquire how.

The ruler governs the country, but the worthy person does not enquire how.

The petty man makes do in these times, but the ruler does not enquire how.

'The gatekeeper of Yen Gate had a father who died and the gatekeeper was praised for the extremities of self-deprivation he inflicted on himself, and was honoured by the title of Model Officer. Some others in the area also underwent such extremities, and half of them died. Yao offered the country to Hsu Yu and Hsu Yu fled from him. Tang offered the kingdom to Wu Kuang and Wu Kuang became angry. Chi To heard this and retreated with his followers to the waters of the Kuan, where the local nobles came and commiserated with him for three years. For the same reason, Shen Tu Ti threw himself into the Yellow River. A fish trap is used to catch fish, but once the fish have been taken, the trap is forgotten. The rabbit trap is used to snare rabbits, but once the rabbit is captured, the trap is ignored. Words are used to express concepts, but once you have grasped the concepts, the words are forgotten. I would like to find someone who has forgotten the words so I could debate with such a person!'

[...]

Chuang Tzu was following a funeral when he passed by the grave of Hui Tzu. He looked round at those following him and said, 'The man of Ying had on the end of his nose a piece of mud as small as a fly's wing. He sent for the craftsman Shih to cut it off. Shih swirled his axe around and swept it down, creating such a wind as it rushed past that it removed all trace of the mud from the man of Ying, who stood firm, not at all worried. The ruler Yuan of Sung heard of this and called craftsman Shih to visit him.

"Would you be so kind as to do this for me?" he said.

'Craftsman Shih replied, "Your servant was indeed once able to work like that, but the type of material I worked upon is long since dead."

'Since the Master has died, I have not had any suitable material to work upon. I have no one I can talk with any longer.'

PART 6
Horses' Hooves

Horses have hooves so that their feet can grip on frost and snow, and hair so that they can withstand the wind and cold. They eat grass and drink water, they buck and gallop, for this is the innate nature of horses. Even if they had great towers and magnificent halls, they would not be interested in them. However, when Po Lo came on the scene, he said, 'I know how to train horses.' He branded them, cut their hair and their hooves, put halters on their heads, bridled them, hobbled them and shut them up in stables. Out of ten horses at least two or three die. Then he makes them hungry and thirsty, gallops them, races them, parades them, runs them together. He keeps before them the fear of the bit and ropes, behind them the fear of the whip and crop. Now more than half the horses are dead.

The potter said, 'I know how to use clay, how to mould it into rounds like the compass and into squares as though I had used a T-square.' The carpenter said, 'I know how to use wood: to make it bend, I use the template; to make it straight, I use the plumb line.' However, is it really the innate nature of clay and wood to be moulded by compass and T-square, template and plumb line? It is true, nevertheless, that generation after generation has said, 'Po Lo is good at controlling horses, and indeed the potter and carpenter are good with clay and wood.' And the same nonsense is spouted by those who rule the world.

I think that someone who truly knows how to rule the world would not be like this. The people have a true nature, they weave their cloth, they farm to produce food. This is their basic Virtue. They are all one in this, not separated, and it is from Heaven. Thus, in an age of perfect Virtue the people walk slowly and solemnly. They see straight and true. In times such as these the mountains have neither paths nor tunnels, on the lakes there are neither boats nor bridges; all life lives with its own kind, living close together. The birds and beasts multiply in their flocks and herds, the grass and trees grow tall. It is true that at such a time the birds and beasts can be led around without ropes, and birds' nests can be seen with ease.

In this time of perfect Virtue, people live side by side with the birds and beasts, sharing the world in common with all life. No one knows of distinctions such as nobles and the peasantry! Totally without wisdom but with virtue which does not disappear; totally without desire they are known as truly simple. If people are truly simple, they can follow their true nature. Then the perfect sage comes, going on about benevolence, straining for selfrighteousness, and suddenly everyone begins to have doubts. They start to fuss over the music, cutting and trimming the rituals, and thus the whole world is disturbed. If the pure essence had not been so cut about, how could they have otherwise ended up with sacrificial bowls? If the raw jade was not broken apart, how could the symbols of power be made? If the Tao and Te-Way and Virtue-had not been ignored, how could benevolence and righteousness have been preferred? If innate nature had not been left behind, how could rituals and music have been invented? If the five colours had not been confused, how could patterns and designs have occurred? If the five notes had not been confused, how could they have been supplanted by the six tones? The abuse of the true elements to make artefacts was the crime of the craftsman. The abuse of the Tao and TeWay and Virtue-to make benevolence and righteousness, this was the error of the sage.

Horses, when they live wild, eat grass and drink water; when they are content, they entwine their necks and rub each other. When angry, they turn their backs on each other and kick out. This is what horses know. But if harnessed together and lined up under constraints, they know to look sideways and to arch their necks, to career around and try to spit out the bit and rid themselves of the reins. The knowledge thus gained by the horse, and its wicked behaviour, is in fact the fault of Po Lo.

PART 7
What's the Point of a Great
Deal of Knowledge?

A great deal of knowledge is needed to make bows, crossbows, nets, arrows and so forth, but the result is that the birds fly higher in distress. A great deal of knowledge is needed to make fishing lines, traps, baits and hooks, but the result is that the fish disperse in distress in the water. A great deal of knowledge is needed to make traps, snares and nets, but the result is that the animals are disturbed and seek refuge in marshy lands. In the same way, the versatility needed to produce rhetoric, to plot and scheme, spread rumours and debate pointlessly, to dust off arguments and seek apparent agreement, is also considerable, but the result is that the people are confused. So everything under Heaven is in a state of distress, all because of the pursuit of knowledge. Everything in the world knows how to seek for knowledge that they do not have, but do not know how to find what they already know. Everything in the world knows how to condemn what they dislike, but do not know how to condemn what they have which is wrong. This is what causes such immense confusion. It is as if the brightness of the sun and moon had been eclipsed above, while down below the hills and streams have lost their power, as though the natural flow of the four seasons had been broken. There is no humble insect, not even any plant, that has not lost its innate nature. This is the consequence for the world of seeking after knowledge. From the Three Dynasties down to the present day it has been like this. The good and honest people are ignored, while spineless flatterers are advanced. The quiet and calm of actionless action is cast aside and pleasure is taken in argument. It is this nonsense which has caused such confusion for everything under Heaven.

[...]

Are people too cheerful? If so, they harm the yang. Are people too vengeful? If so, they harm the yin. If both yin and yang are corrupted, then the four seasons will not follow each other, the balance of hot and cold will not be kept and this results in distress to the very bodies of the people! People will be unable to control a balance between joy and anger. It makes them restless, moving here, moving there, plotting to no purpose, travelling for no good reason or result. The consequence of this is that the world becomes concerned with mighty goals and plots, ambition and hatred, which brings in its wake the likes of Robber Chih, Tseng and Shih. As a result, the world may wish to reward the good, but there are not enough rewards available; nor can it adequately punish the bad, for there are not enough punishments.

[...]

So it is that the noble master who finds he has to follow some course to govern the world will realize that actionless action is the best course. By non-action, he can rest in the real substance of his nature and destiny. If he appreciates his own body as he appreciates the world, then the world can be placed in his care. He who loves his body as he loves the world can be trusted to govern the world. If the noble master can prevent his five main organs from being destroyed, and his vision and hearing also; if he can become as lifeless as a corpse and develop his dragon powers; if he can thus still himself, his words will sound like thunder while his actions will be seen as the actions of a spirit from Heaven, who is guided by Heaven. If he is unconcerned and engaged in actionless action, his gentle spirit will draw all life to him like a dust cloud. How then would such a person have time for governing the world?

[...]

Yun Chiang was travelling east, carried along upon the wings of a whirlwind. Suddenly he met Hung Mung, who was jumping around, slapping his thighs and hopping like a bird. Yun Chiang saw this and stopped dead, standing still in respect, and said, 'Elderly man, who are you? What are you doing?'

Hung Mung continued to slap his thighs and hop like a bird, then replied, 'Enjoying myself!'

Yun Chiang said, 'I would like to ask a question.'

Hung Mung looked at Yun Chiang and said, 'That's a shame!'

Yun Chiang said, 'The very breath of Heaven is no longer in harmony. Earth's very breath is ensnared, the six breaths do not mix, the four seasons do not follow each other. Now I want to combine the six breaths in order to bring life to all things. How do I do this?'

Hung Mung slapped his thighs, hopped around and said, 'I don't know, I don't know!'

Yun Chiang could go no further with this questioning. But three years later, travelling east, he passed the wilderness of Sung and came upon Hung Mung again. Yun Chiang, very pleased, rushed towards him, stood before him and said, 'Heaven, have you forgotten me? Heaven, have you forgotten me?' Bowing his head twice, he asked for teaching from Hung Mung.

Hung Mung said, 'Wandering everywhere, without a clue why. Wildly impulsive, without a clue where. I wander around in this odd fashion, I see that nothing comes without reason. What can I know?'

Yun Chiang replied, 'I am also wildly impulsive, but the people follow me wherever I am. I cannot stop them following me. Now, because they follow me, I want to have a word of teaching from you.'

'The disruption of the ways of Heaven distresses the true being of things, halting the fulfilment of Heaven's Mysteries,' said Hung Mung. 'This causes the animals to disperse, the birds to sing throughout the night, misfortune to hit the crops and the woods, and disaster to blight the very insects themselves. Alas, all this is caused by the people's error of thinking they know how to rule!'

'What should I do then?' said Yun Chiang.

'Oh, you distress them! Like a spirit, a spirit I will dance away,' said Hung Mung.

'I have had such trouble meeting you,' said Yun Chiang. 'Oh Heaven, just give me one other word.'

'Oh ho!' said Hung Mung. 'Strengthen your heart. Remain sure in actionless action, and all things will then transform themselves. Reject your body, throw out hearing and eyesight, forget that you are anyone, become one with the Vast and the Void. Loosen the heart, free the spirit, be calm as if without a soul. All living things return to their root, return to their root, not knowing why. Constantly in darkness, constantly in darkness, and throughout their physical existence they never depart from this. If they tried to understand this, they would depart from this. Ask not for its name, seek not for its shape. So all life comes to birth through itself.'

Yun Chiang replied, 'Heaven, you have honoured me with this Virtue, taught me through Mystery; my whole life I sought it, now I have it.' He bowed his head twice and got up. He said farewell and left.

PART 8
The Action of Non-action
is Called Heaven

So the sages contemplate Heaven but do not assist it.

They are concerned to perfect their Virtue but do not allow it to encumber them.

They set forth according to the Tao but do not make plans.

They work with benevolence but put no reliance upon it.

They draw extensively upon righteousness but do not try to build it up.

They observe the rituals but do not set great store by them.

They do what they have to and never shirk their responsibilities.

They try to make their laws applicable but do not believe them effective.

They value the people and do not take them for granted.

They make use of things and do not dismiss them lightly.

True, things are worthless but they must be used.

Those who do not see Heaven clearly will not be pure in Virtue.

Those who fail to follow the Tao cannot follow any other path.

What a disaster for those who cannot follow the Tao!

What is this Tao?

There is the Tao of Heaven;

there is the Tao of humanity.

Non-action brings respect: this is Heaven's Tao.

To be active is the Tao of humanity.

It is Heaven's Tao that is the ruler;

the Tao of humanity is the servant.

The Tao of Heaven and the Tao of humanity are poles apart.

Do not fail to reflect upon this.

[...]

Heaven and Earth are vast,

and their diversity comes from one source.

Although there are ten thousand forms of life,

they are one in their order.

Human beings are multitudinous,

but they are governed by one ruler.

The ruler is rooted in Virtue and perfected by Heaven.

It is said that long ago

the rulers of everything below Heaven

ruled through actionless action,

through Heavenly Virtue and nothing else.

[...]

The action of non-action is called Heaven.

The words of non-action are called Virtue.

To love all humanity and to bring success to them is called benevolence.

To unite that which is not united is called greatness.

To go beyond harriers and boundaries is called open-handedness.

To have a vast multitude of diverse things is called wealth.

To have and to hold Virtue is called guidance.

To grow in maturity in Virtue is called stability

To be aligned with the Tao is called completion.

To refuse to allow anything external which distracts you is called perfection.

The nobleman who clearly perceives these ten things will be also magnanimous in his ventures and his actions will benefit all life.

Such a man will leave the gold in the mountain

and the pearls to lie in the deep.

He does not view money and goods as true profit,

nor is he attracted by fame and fortune,

nor by enjoyment of long life,

nor sadness at an early death;

he does not value wealth as a blessing,

nor is he ashamed by poverty.

He will not lust for the wealth of a generation to have as his own;

he has no wish to rule the whole world as his private domain.

His honour is clarity of understanding that all life is part of one treasury

and that death and birth are united.

The Sage Master said,

'The Tao, how deep and quiet it lies;

how pure is its clarity!

Without it neither gold nor stone would resonate.

The gold and stones have sounds within them

but if they are not struck, then no sound comes forth.

All the multitudinous creatures have dimensions beyond calculation!

[...]

'The way sages rule?' said Chun Mang. 'Only appoint those who are fit for the office; make appointments in accordance with the worthiness of those appointed; act only after studying the situation thoroughly. When deeds and words are in accord, the whole world is transformed. Consequently, a wave of the hand or a sharp look will bring the peoples of all the world rushing to you. This is the way sages rule.'

'Can I ask about the Virtuous ones?'

'The Virtuous one is still and without thought:

when he moves he is without design;

he keeps no tally of right and wrong, good or bad.

Virtuous ones share their gains with all within the four seas

and from this they derive pleasure.

They share what they have and are content.

Mournful, they are like a child who has lost his mother;

uncertain, they are like travellers who are lost.

Though blessed with great wealth and comforts,

they have no idea where it comes from;

they have more than enough to eat and drink,

but have no idea where it comes from.

This is the style of Virtuous ones.'

'What about the spiritual ones?'

Chun Mang said,

'Their spirits rise up to the brightest light

and their bodies disappear.

They are gloriously enraptured.

They live out their fate,

The spiritual one pursues to its end what is truly him

and dwells in the delight of Heaven and Earth

while his multitudinous cares fall away.

All things return to their true nature.

This is called Primal Mystery'

[...]

It is Heaven's Tao to journey and to gather no moss,

thus all the forms of life are brought to perfection.

It is the Emperor's Tao to journey and to gather no moss,

which is why the whole world comes to his feet.

It is the sages' Tao to journey and to gather no moss,

thus all that lies within the oceans venerates them.

To understand Heaven clearly,

to comprehend the sages,

to journey through the entire cosmos

following the Virtue of the Emperors and the kings

but also to be spontaneous themselves:

this is the nature of those who comprehend,

seeming not to know

but being centred in stillness.

The sages are quiescent, not because of any value in being quiescent, they simply are still. Not even the multitude of beings can disturb them, so they are calm. Water, when it is still, reflects back even your eyebrows and beard. It is perfectly level and from this the carpenter takes his level. If water stilled offers such clarity, imagine what pure spirit offers! The sage's heart is stilled! Heaven and Earth are reflected in it, the mirror of all life. Empty, still, calm, plain, quiet, silent, non-active, this is the centredness of Heaven and Earth and of the Tao and of Virtue. The Emperor, king, and sages rest there. Resting, they are empty; empty, they can be full; fullness is fulfilment. From the empty comes stillness; in stillness they can travel; in travelling they achieve. In stillness they take actionless action. Through actionless action they expect results from those with responsibilities. Through actionless action they are happy, very happy; being so happy they are not afflicted by cares and worries, for these have no place, and their years of life are prolonged. Empty, still, calm, plain, quiet, silent, actionless action is the foundation of all life. If you are clear on this and facing south, it means you are a noble like Yao; if you are clear on this and facing north, you will become a minister like Shun.

[...]

Chuang Tzu said,

'My Master Teacher! My Master Teacher!

He judges all life but does not feel he is being judgemental;

he is generous to multitudes of generations

but does not think this benevolent;

he is older than the oldest

but he does not think himself old;

he overarches Heaven and sustains Earth,

shaping and creating endless bodies

but he does not think himself skilful.

This is what is known as Heavenly happiness.

'There is a saying: "If you know the happiness of Heaven, then you know that life is from Heaven and death is the transformation of things. In their stillness they are yin and in their journeying they are yang." To know Heavenly happiness means that you do not upset Heaven, nor go against others. You are not reliant on material things, you are not rebuked by the ghosts. There is a saying: "He moves with Heaven and rests with Earth, his heart is one, he is the king of the whole world; the ghosts do not worry him and his soul is not wearied, his heart is one with all living beings." This means his emptiness and stillness enter all beings in Heaven and Earth, travelling alongside all beings. This is known as the Heavenly happiness. Heavenly happiness is the heart of the sage; this is how he cares for all under Heaven.'

The Virtue of emperors and kings considers Heaven and Earth as its parents, the Tao and Virtue as its master and actionless action as its core. Through actionless action they can make the whole world do as they will and yet not be wearied. Through action they cannot even begin to fulfil what the world requires. This is why the ancient ones valued actionless action.

[...]

Thus the ancient kings of the world, who knew everything about Heaven and Earth, had no designs; even though they understood the whole of life, they did not speak out; though their skills were greater than any in the lands bounded by oceans, they did nothing.

Heaven produces nothing,

yet all life is transformed;

Earth does not support,

yet all life is sustained;

the Emperor and the king take actionless action,

yet the whole world is served.

There is a saying that there is nothing as spiritual as Heaven,

nothing as rich as Earth,

nothing as great as emperors and kings.

[...]

Thus it was that the ancient ones clearly grasped the great Tao, seeking first the meaning of Heaven and then the meaning of its Tao and Virtue.

When they clearly understood the Tao and Virtue,

they then understood benevolence and righteousness.

When they clearly grasped benevolence and righteousness,

they could see how to perform their duties.

When they grasped how to perform their duties,

they came to understand form and fame.

When they comprehended form and fame,

they were able to make appointments.

When they had made appointments,

they went on to examining people and their efforts.

When they had examined people's efforts,

they moved to judgements of good or bad.

When they had made judgements of good and bad,

they went on to punishments and rewards.

[...]

In days gone by Shun spoke to Yao, saying, 'Being Heaven's king, how do you use your heart?'

'I do not abuse those who are defenceless,' said Yao, 'nor do I ignore the poor. I mourn for those who die, caring for the orphaned child and for the widow. This is how I use my heart.'

'Righteous as far as righteousness goes, but not that great,' commented Shun.

'What ought I to do, then?' said Yao.

'When Heaven's Virtue is found, the hills rejoice, the sun and moon shine and the four seasons are in line. The regular pattern of each day and night follows properly and the rain clouds are moved accordingly.'

Yao said, 'So all I've really been doing is getting worked up and bothered! You seek compliance with Heaven, whereas I have sought compliance with humanity.'

[...]

Confucius travelled west to place his books in the archives of Chou. Tzu Lu offered advice, saying, 'I have heard that the official in charge of the Royal Archives is Lao Tzu. But he has resigned and lives at home. Sir, if you want to place your books there, go and see him and ask his assistance.'

'Splendid,' said Confucius. So off he went to see Lao Tzu, but Lao Tzu refused to help. So Confucius took out his Twelve Classics, and started to preach.

When he was halfway through, Lao Tzu said, 'This is too much. Put it briefly.'

Confucius said, 'In essence, it is benevolence and righteousness.'

'May I ask,' said Lao Tzu, 'are benevolence and righteousness of the very essence of humanity?'

'Certainly,' said Confucius. 'If the nobleman is without benevolence, he has no purpose; if without righteousness, he has no life. Benevolence and righteousness, these are truly of the innate nature of humanity. How else could it be?'

'May I ask, what are benevolence and righteousness?'

'To be at one, centred in one's heart, in love with all, without selfishness, this is what benevolence and righteousness are,' replied Confucius.

'Really! Your words reveal misunderstanding,' said Lao Tzu. '"Love of all", that's both vague and an exaggeration! "Without selfishness", isn't that rather selfish? Sir, if you want people to remain simple, shouldn't you look to the ways of Heaven and Earth?

'Heaven and Earth have their boundaries which are constant;

the sun and moon hold their courses in their brightness;

the stars and planets proceed in the boundaries of their order;

the birds and creatures find their confines within their herds and flocks.

Think of the trees which stand within their own boundaries in order.

'So Sir, walk with Virtue and travel with the Tao, and you will reach the perfect end. Why bother with all this benevolence and righteousness, prancing along as if you were beating a drum and looking for a lost child? Sir, you will just confuse people's true nature!'

[...]

The Master said,

'The Tao does not hesitate before that which is vast,

nor does it abandon the small.

Thus it is that all life is enlivened by it.

So immense, so immense there is nothing which is not held by it;

so deep, so unfathomable beyond any reckoning.

The form of its Virtue is in benevolence and righteousness,

though this is a minor aspect of its spirit.

Who but the perfect man could comprehend all this?

The perfect man has charge of this age,

a somewhat daunting task!

However, this does not fool him or trap him.

He holds the reins of power over the whole world

but it is of little consequence to him.

His discernment unearths all falsehood

but he gives no thought to personal gain.

He gets to the heart of issues and knows how to protect the foundation of truth.

Thus Heaven and Earth are outside him,

he ignores all life and his spirit is never wearied.

He travels with the Tao,

is in agreement with Virtue,

bids farewell to benevolence and righteousness and ignores ritual and music,

because the perfect man has set his heart upon what is right.'

This generation believes that the value of the Tao is to be found in books. But books are nothing more than words, and words have value but only in terms of their meaning. Meaning is constantly seeking to express what cannot be said in words and thus passed on. This generation values words and puts them into books, yet what it values is perhaps mistaken, because what it values is not really all that valuable. So we look at things and see things, but it is only an outward form and colour, and what can be heard is just the name and sound. How sad that this generation imagines that the form, colour, name and sound are enough to capture the essence of something! The form, colour, name and sound are in no way sufficient to capture or convey the truth, which is why it is said that the knowledgeable do not speak and those who speak are not knowledgeable. But how can this generation understand this?

PART 9
Does Heaven Move?

Does Heaven move?

Does the Earth stand still?

Do the sun and moon argue about where to go?

Who is lord over all this?

Who binds and controls it?

Who, doing nothing, makes all of this be?

Is there some hidden cause that makes things as they are, whether they wish or not?

Or is it just that everything moves and turns because it has no choice?

Do the clouds come before the rain, or does the rain cause the clouds?

What causes them to be?

Who, doing nothing, brings all this joyful excess into being?

The winds come from the north,

going first to west then to east,

swirling up on high, to go who knows where?

Whose breath are they?

Who, doing nothing, creates all this activity?

[...]

Duke Huan was sitting up in his hall reading a book. The wheelwright Pien was down below in the courtyard making a wheel. He put down his chisel and hammer, went up to the hall and asked Duke Huan, 'May I ask you, Sir, what words you are reading?'

Duke Huan replied, 'The words of the sages.'

'Are these sages still living?'

'They are long dead,' said Duke Huan.

'Then, Sir, what you are reading is nothing but rubbish left over from these ancient men!'

'How dare you, a wheelwright, comment on what I read! If you can explain this, fine, if not you shall die!' thundered Duke Huan.

The wheelwright Pien replied, 'Your Lordship's servant looks at it from the perspective of his own work. When I work on a wheel, if I hit too softly, pleasant as this is, it doesn't make for a good wheel. If I hit furiously, I get tired and the thing doesn't work! So, not too soft, not too vigorous, I grasp it in my hand and hold it in my heart. I cannot express this by word of mouth, I just know it. I cannot teach this to my son, nor can my son learn it from me. So for seventy years I have gone along this path and here I am still making wheels. The ancient ones, when they died, took their words with them. Which is why I can state that what Your Lordship is reading is nothing more than rubbish left over from these ancient ones!'

[...]

Confucius had pottered along for fifty-one years and had never heard anyone speak of the Tao until he went south to Pei and went to see Lao Tzu.

Lao Tzu said, 'So you've come then, Sir? I have heard of you, that you are the wise man of the north. Have you, Sir, followed the Tao?'

'I have not yet followed it,' replied Confucius.

'Well, Sir, where have you looked?'

'I looked for it in what can be measured and regulated but even after five years I still haven't been able to find it.'

'So, Sir, what did you do then?' asked Lao Tzu.

'I looked for it in yin and yang, but ten, twelve years went by and I still couldn't find it.'

'Obviously!' said Lao Tzu. 'If the Tao could be served up, everyone would serve it up to their lords. If the Tao could be offered, there is no one who would not offer it to their parents. If the Tao could be spoken of, there is no one who would not speak of it to their brothers and sisters. If the Tao could be passed on, there is no one who would not pass it on to their heirs. However, it obviously cannot be so and the reason is as follows.

'If there is no true centre within to receive it,

it cannot remain;

if there is no true direction outside to guide it,

it cannot be received.

If the true centre is not brought out

it cannot receive on the outside.

The sage cannot draw it forth.

If what comes in from the outside is not welcomed by the true centre,

then the sage cannot let it go.

[...]

Confucius went to see Lao Tzu and talked with him about benevolence and righteousness. Lao Tzu said, 'If you get grit in your eye from winnowing chaff, then Heaven and Earth and the four directions get mixed up. A mosquito or gadfly which stings you can keep you awake all night. And benevolence and righteousness, when forced upon us, disturb your heart and produce great distress. You, Sir, if you want to stop everything below Heaven losing its original simplicity, you must travel with the wind and stand firm in Virtue. Why do you exert yourself so much, banging a big drum and hunting for a lost child? The snow goose doesn't need a daily bath to stay white, nor does the crow need to be stained every day to stay black. Black and white comes from natural simplicity, not from argument. Fame and fortune, though sought after, do not make people greater than they actually are. When the waters dry up and the fish are stranded on the dry land, they huddle together and try to keep each other moist by spitting and wetting each other. But wouldn't it be even better if they could just forget each other, safe in their lakes and rivers?'

After seeing Lao Tzu, Confucius went home and for three days he said nothing. His followers asked him, 'Master, now you have seen Lao Tzu, what do you make of him?'

'I have now seen a dragon!' said Confucius. 'A dragon coils up to show its form, it stretches out to display its power. It rides upon the breath of the clouds and is nourished by yin and yang. My mouth gaped open and I could not shut it. What can I say about Lao Tzu?'

[...]

The ancient ones talked of the Timeliness of Purpose, but they did not mean having official carriages and badges of office. They simply meant that it was happiness so complete as to need nothing more. Today what is called Timeliness of Purpose means having official carriages and badges of office. Carriages and badges are of the body, they do not touch the innate nature. From time to time such benefits may come. When this happens, you cannot help it, no more than you can stop them going again. So having carriages and badges of office is no reason for becoming proud and arrogant in our purposes, nor are distress and poverty any reason for becoming vulgar. View both conditions as one and the same, so be free from anxiety and leave it at that. So if loss of what gives happiness causes you distress when it fades, you can now understand that such happiness is worthless. It is said, those who lose themselves in their desire for things also lose their innate nature by being vulgar. They are known as people who turn things upside down.

PART 10
Reality and Happiness

The season of the autumn floods had come and the hundred rivers were pouring into the Yellow River. The waters were churning and so wide that, looking across from one bank to the other, it was impossible to distinguish an ox from a horse. At this the Lord of the Yellow River was decidedly pleased, thinking that the most beautiful thing in the whole world belonged to him. Flowing with the river, he travelled east until he came at last to the North Ocean, where he looked east and could see no end to the waters. He shook his head, the Lord of the Yellow River, and looked out to confront Jo, god of the Ocean, sighing and saying.

'The folk proverb says, "The person who has heard of the Tao a hundred times thinks he is better than anyone else." This refers to me. I have heard people mock the scholarship of the Confucians and give scant regard to the righteousness of Po Yi, but I didn't believe them. Now I have seen your endless vastness. If I had not come to your gate, I would have been in danger, and been mocked by those of the Great Method.'

Jo of the North Ocean replied, 'A frog in a well cannot discuss the ocean, because he is limited by the size of his well. A summer insect cannot discuss ice, because it knows only its own season. A narrow-minded scholar cannot discuss the Tao, because he is constrained by his teachings. Now you have come out of your banks and seen the Great Ocean. You now know your own inferiority, so it is now possible to discuss great principles with you. Under Heaven there are no greater waters than the ocean. Ten thousand rivers flow into it, and it has never been known to stop, but it never fills. At Wei Lu the water disappears but the ocean never empties. Spring and autumn bring no changes. It pays no attention to floods or droughts. It is so much more than the waters of the Yangtze and the Yellow Rivers, it is impossible to estimate. However, I have never made much of this. I just compare myself with Heaven and Earth and my life-breath I receive from yin and yang. I am just a little stone or a little tree set on a great hill, in comparison to Heaven and Earth. As I perceive my own inferiority, how could I ever be proud?

'To compare all the space filled by the four oceans, is it not like a pile of stones beside a marsh in comparison with the vastness between Heaven and Earth? To compare China with all the space between the oceans, is it not like one single piece of grain in a granary? When talking of all life, we count them in tens of thousands, and humanity is just one of them. People inhabit the Nine Provinces, but humanity is just one portion of all the life that is sustained by grain, wherever carriages or boats can go. In comparison to all the multitudinous forms of life, isn't humanity like just a single hair on a horse?

[...]

The Lord of the Yellow River said, 'The debaters of this generation say, "The tiniest thing has no body, the most enormous thing cannot be contained." Are these words true?'

Jo of the North Ocean replied, 'From the viewpoint of the tiniest, we look at what is so enormous and we cannot comprehend it. From the viewpoint of the most enormous, we look at what is tiniest and we cannot see it clearly. The tiniest is the smallest of the small, the biggest is the largest of the large; so we must distinguish between them, even though this is just a matter of circumstance. However, both the coarse and the refined have form. Without any form, there is no way to enumerate them. What can be said in words is the coarseness of things; what can be grasped through ideas is the subtlety of things. But words cannot describe nor ideas grasp, and this has nothing to do with coarseness or refinement.

'So it is that the great man through his actions will not set out to harm others, nor make much of benevolence and charity; he does not make any move for gain, nor consider the servant at the gate as lowly; he will not barter for property and riches, nor does he make much of his having turned them down; he asks for no one's help, nor does he make much of his own self-reliance, nor despise the greedy and mean; he does not follow the crowd, nor does he make much of being so different; he comes behind the crowd, but does not make much of those who get ahead through flattery. The titles and honours of this world are of no interest to him, nor is he concerned at the disgrace of punishments. He knows there is no distinction between right and wrong, nor between great and little. I have heard it said, "The Tao man earns no reputation, perfect Virtue is not followed, the great man is self-less." In perfection, this is the path he follows.'

The Lord of the Yellow River asked, 'Whether they are external or internal, how come we have these distinctions between noble and mean? Why do we distinguish between small and great?'

'Viewed from the perspective of the Tao,' said Jo of the North Ocean, 'things are neither elevated nor lowly. Viewed from the perspective of things, each one considers itself as elevated and the rest as lowly. Viewed from the perspective of the everyday opinion, neither elevation nor lowliness is to be understood from the perspective of individual things. Taking into account differing views, something which is seen as big because it is big means that, in all the multitudes of life, everything can be viewed as big. Likewise, if something is seen as small because it is small, then all forms of life can be viewed as small. If we know that Heaven and Earth are as tiny as a grain or the tip of a hair is as vast as a mountain range, then we will have grasped that our understanding of size is relative. In terms of what each does, we view something as useful because it is useful, which means that, in all the multitudes of life, everything can be viewed as useful. In the same way, if something is viewed as useless because it appears useless, then all forms of life can be viewed as useless. If we know that east and west are opposite each other, but also need each other, then we can understand how mutual exchange and interaction work. Viewed from the perspective of choice, if something is seen as good because it undoubtedly is good, then in all the multitudes of life there is nothing which is not good. Likewise, if something is viewed as wrong because it undoubtedly is wrong, then there is no form of life which cannot be viewed as wrong.'

[...]

'Be quiet, be quiet, Lord of the Yellow River! How could you know anything about the gateway to nobility or meanness or the dwelling place of greatness or pettiness?'

'All right then,' said the Lord of the Yellow River. 'What am I to do and what may I not do? How can I decide what is worth keeping or rejecting and what is worth going for or leaving?'

Jo of the North Ocean said, 'Viewed from the perspective of the Tao, what is noble and what is mean are both just ceaseless changes. Don't cling to your own ideas, for this is contrary to the greatness of the Tao. What is little and what is much, these are terms of very limited use. Do not try to be just One, this just highlights how far away you are from the Tao. Be stern and strict like a ruler of a country who favours no one. Be gentle, be gentle like the local earth god to whom offerings are made and who does not grant fortune selfishly. Be open like air, like the four compass points shed light but do not permit boundaries. If you lovingly tend all forms of life, how could you favour one? This is known as being impartial. Consider all life as unified and then how could you talk in terms of long or short? The Tao has neither beginning nor end, but all living things have both death and birth, so you cannot be sure of them. One moment they are empty, the next moment full. They are unreliable. The years cannot be reversed nor time halted. Decay, maturity, fullness and emptiness, when they end, begin over again. So we can talk of great righteousness, and discuss the fundamental principle within all forms of life. The life force is a headlong gallop, speeding along, changing with every movement and altering every minute. As to what you should and should not do? Just go with this process of change.'

'If this is the case,' said the Lord of the Yellow River, 'then what is so important about the Tao?'

Jo of the North Ocean replied, 'To understand the Tao is to understand the principle. If you understand the principle, you know how to deal with things as they arise. Knowing this, you can ensure that nothing detrimental to yourself occurs. If someone has perfect Virtue, it is not possible for fire to harm, nor for water to drown, nor for either cold or heat to affect, nor birds and beasts to injure him. Not that I say that he dismisses all these things, but that he is able to discriminate between where he is safe and where he is in danger. He is at ease with both calamity and fortune, takes care as to what he approaches or avoids, and therefore nothing harms him. There is a saying that Heaven is internal, humanity external and Virtue comes from the Heavenly. Know Heaven and humanity's actions, root yourself in Heaven and follow Virtue. Then you can bend, stretch, rush forward or hold back, because you will always return to the core and it will be said you have achieved the supreme.'

'But what do you call the Heavenly? What do you call the human?'

Jo of the North Ocean said, 'Oxen have four feet: this is what I call the Heavenly. When horses are harnessed and oxen have pierced noses, this I call the human way. There is the saying. "Don't allow the human to displace the Heavenly," don't allow your intentions to nullify what is ordained. Be careful, guard it and don't lose it, for this is what I call coming back to the True.'

The one-legged creature is envious of the millipede; the millipede is envious of the snake; the snake is envious of the wind; the wind is envious of the eye; the eye is envious of the heart.

The one-legged creature said to the millipede, 'I have one foot that I hop on and I can hardly go anywhere. But you, Sir, have a multitude of feet. How do you manage?'

The millipede said, 'Don't be so certain. Have you never seen someone spit? Out comes a big blob followed by a spray, which falls down like a shower of uncountable drops. Now I just set the Heavenly machinery in motion and as for the rest - I haven't a clue!'

The millipede said to the snake, 'I get about with all these feet, but I can't keep up with you, Sir, who have no feet. Why is this?'

The snake said, 'I am moved by the designs of Heaven, how can I control that? What could I use feet for!'

The snake said to the wind, 'By moving my backbone and ribs, I get along and at least I have some visible form. Now you, Sir, come hurtling along from the North Ocean and disappear off to the South Ocean but without any visible form. How is that?'

The wind said, 'True, I come hurtling along from the North Ocean and disappear off to the South Ocean. However, it is true that, if you point your finger at me, you are greater than me, or if you stamp on me, you also win. But it is also true that I can bring down great trees and bowl over great houses; only I can do this. Therefore, the one who can overcome all the small problems is in truth the great victor. To have a great victory, why, this is what a sage does.'

[...]

Kung Sun Lung asked Mou of Wei, 'When I was younger, I learned the Tao of the earlier kings, and, as I grew up, I saw clearly the significance of benevolence and righteousness. I brought together difference and similarity, discerned hardness and whiteness, what was certain and what was not, what was possible and what was not. I laboured at understanding the Hundred Schools of Philosophy and spoke out against their teachings. I thought I had understanding of all things. Now, however, I have heard the words of Chuang Tzu, and to my surprise I am disturbed by them. Is it that my knowledge is not as good as his, or is it that his understanding is greater? I find I can't even open my mouth, so I ask you what I can do.'

Duke Tzu Mou leaned forward, sighed heavily, looked to Heaven, smiled and said, 'Dear Sir, have you not heard of the frog in the broken-down old well? He said to the turtle of the Eastern Ocean, "I have a great time! I leap on to the well wall, or I go down in the well, stepping along the broken bricks. When I enter the water, I float with it supporting my chin, feet up; on the mud, I dig my feet deep in. I look about me at the larvae, crabs and tadpoles and there is none that is as good as I. To have complete control of the waters of the gorge and not to wish to move but to enjoy the old well, this is great! Dear Sir, why don't you come down and see me sometime?'

'The turtle of the Eastern Ocean tried, but before he had put his left foot into the well, his right knee was stuck. At this he paused, shuffled out backwards and then began to speak about the ocean. "A distance such as a thousand miles doesn't come close to describing its length, nor a depth of a thousand leagues describe its deepness. In the time of Yu, nine years in every ten there were floods, but this did not raise the ocean an inch. In the time of Tang, seven years in every eight there were droughts, but this did not lower the ocean shore an inch. Nothing changes these waters, neither in the short term nor in the long term; they neither recede nor advance, grow larger nor smaller. This is the great happiness of the Eastern Ocean." When the frog in the broken-down old well heard this, he was utterly amazed and astonished; he was utterly astonished, dumbfounded and at a loss.

'For someone whose understanding can't handle such knowledge, such debates about right and wrong, if they persist in trying to see through the words of Chuang Tzu, it is like a mosquito trying to carry a mountain on its back, or a scuttle bug rushing as fast as the Yellow River. This is plainly impossible. For someone whose understanding cannot handle such knowledge, such words of subtlety, all they are capable of is gaining some short-term reward. They are like the frog in the broken-down well, are they not? But Chuang Tzu is not planted firmly in the Yellow Springs of the Underworld, nor leaping, jumping into the stratosphere. There is neither south nor north: he scatters freely to the four points of the compass, and disappears into the depth. There is neither east nor west: starting in the darkest depth, he comes back to the great path. Then you, Sir, you in your astonishment try to sift his views to criticize them, or trawl through them in order to debate. Why, this is like trying to examine Heaven through a narrow tube or using an awl to explore the whole earth. Such tools are too small, aren't they? You, Sir, be on your way! Or possibly, Sir, you have not heard of the young students of Shou Ling and how things went for them in Han Tan? Having not yet learnt the lessons that the people of that country were trying to teach them, they forgot what they had learnt at home, so were reduced to crawling back home. So, Sir, if you don't get out now, you will forget, Sir, what you already knew and fail, Sir, in your career!'

Kung Sun Lung's mouth fell open and would not shut, his tongue stuck to the roof of his mouth and wouldn't drop down, and he shuffled off and ran away.

Chuang Tzu was one day fishing in the Pu river when the King of Chu despatched two senior officials to visit him with a message. The message said, 'I would like to trouble you to administer my lands.'

Chuang Tzu kept a firm grip on his fishing rod and said, 'I hear that in Chu there is a sacred tortoise which died three thousand years ago. The King keeps this in his ancestral temple, wrapped and enclosed. Tell me, would this tortoise have wanted to die and leave his shell to be venerated? Or would he rather have lived and continued to crawl about in the mud?'

The two senior officials said, 'It would rather have lived and continued to crawl about in the mud.'

Chuang Tzu said, 'Shove off, then! I will continue to crawl about in the mud!'

[...]

Chuang Tzu and Hui Tzu were walking beside the weir on the River Hao, when Chuang Tzu said, 'Do you see how the fish are coming to the surface and swimming around as they please? That's what fish really enjoy.'

'You're not a fish,' replied Hui Tzu, 'so how can you say you know what fish enjoy?'

Chuang Tzu said: 'You are not me, so how can you know I don't know what fish enjoy?'

Hui Tzu said: 'I am not you, so I definitely don't know what it is you know. However, you are most definitely not a fish and that proves that you don't know what fish really enjoy.'

Chuang Tzu said: 'Ah, but let's return to the original question you raised, if you don't mind. You asked me how I could know what it is that fish really enjoy. Therefore, you already knew I knew it when you asked the question. And I know it by being here on the edge of the River Hao.'

[...]

Is it possible anywhere in this whole wide world to have perfect happiness or not? Is there a way to keep yourself alive or not? Now, what can be done and what is to be trusted? What should be avoided and what adhered to? What should be pursued and what abandoned? Where is happiness and where is evil?

What the whole wide world values is riches, position, long life and fame.

What brings happiness is good times for oneself, fine foods, beautiful clothes, lovely sights and sweet music.

What is despised is poverty, meanness, untimely death and a bad reputation.

What is considered sour is a lifestyle which gives the self no rest, a mouth which never has fine foods, a body without good clothes, eyes that never rest upon lovely views, an ear that never hears sweet music.

Those who cannot get these things become greatly agitated and fearful. This is a foolish way to treat the body!

Those who are wealthy weary themselves dashing around working, getting more and more riches, beyond what they need. The body is treated therefore as just an external thing.

Those in positions of power spend day and night plotting and pondering about what to do. The body is treated in a very careless way. People live their lives, constantly surrounded by anxiety. If they live long before dying, they end up in senility, worn out by concerns: a terrible fate! The body is treated in a very harsh fashion. Courageous men are seen by everyone under Heaven as worthy, but this doesn't preserve them from death. I am not sure I know whether this is sensible or not. Possibly it is, but it does nothing towards saving them. Possibly it is not, but it does save other people. It is said, 'If a friend doesn't listen to the advice you offer him, then bow out and don't argue.' After all, Tzu Hsu argued and lost his life. If he had not argued, he would not be famous. Is it possible that there really is goodness, or not?

Now, when ordinary people attempt to find happiness, I'm not sure whether the happiness found is really happiness or not. I study what ordinary people do to find happiness, what they struggle for, rushing about apparently unable to stop. They say they are happy, but I am not happy and I am not unhappy either. Ultimately, do they have happiness or not? I regard actionless action as worthy of being called happiness, though the ordinary people regard it as a great burden. It is said: 'Perfect happiness is not happiness, perfect glory is not glory.'

The whole world is incapable of judging either right or wrong. But it is certain that actionless action can judge both right and wrong. Perfect happiness is keeping yourself alive, and only actionless action can have this effect. This is why I want to say:

Heaven does without doing through its purity,

Earth does without doing through its calmness.

Thus the two combine their actionless action and all forms of life are changed and thus come out again to live! Wonder of wonders, they have not come from anywhere! All life is mysterious and emerges from actionless action. There is a saying that Heaven and Earth take actionless action, but yet nothing remains undone. Amongst the people, who can follow such actionless action?

[...]

Uncle Legless and Uncle Cripple were touring the area of the Hill of the Dark Prince and the zone of Kun Lun where the Yellow Emperor stayed. Without warning a willow tree suddenly shot up out of Uncle Cripple's left elbow. He was certainly most surprised and somewhat put out.

'Sir, do you dislike this?' said Uncle Legless.

'No,' said Uncle Cripple. 'What should I dislike? Life exists through scrounging; if life comes through scrounging, then life is like a dump. Death and birth are like the morning and the night. You and I, Sir, observe the ways of transformation and now I am being transformed. So how could I dislike this?'

Chuang Tzu went to Chu to see an ancient desiccated skull, which he prodded with his riding crop, saying, 'Sir, did you follow some unfortunate course which meant you brought dishonour upon your father and mother and family and so end up like this? Sir, was it perhaps the cold and hunger that reduced you to this? Sir, perhaps it was just the steady succession of springs and autumns that brought you to this?'

So saying, he pulled the skull towards him and lay down to sleep, using the skull as a head-rest. At midnight he saw the skull in a dream and it said, 'Sir, you gabble on like a public speaker. Every word you say, Sir, shows that you are a man caught up with life. We dead have nothing to do with this. Would you like to hear a discourse upon death, Sir?'

'Certainly,' said Chuang Tzu.

The skull told him, 'The dead have no lord over them, no servants below them. There is none of the work associated with the four seasons, so we live as if our springs and autumns were like Heaven and Earth, unending. Make no mistake, a king facing south could not be happier.'

Chuang Tzu could not believe this and said, 'If I got the Harmonizer of Destinies to bring you back to life, Sir, with a body, flesh and blood, and companions, wouldn't you like that?'

The skull frowned, looked aggrieved and said, 'Why should I want to cast away happiness greater than that of kings and become a burdened human being again?'

[...]

Confucius said: 'Have you never heard this story before? Once upon a time, a seabird alighted in the capital city of Lu. The Earl of Lu carried it in procession to the ancestral shrine, where he played the Nine Shao music and offered the offerings of the sacrifice to it. However, the poor bird just looked confused and lost and did not eat a single piece of meat, nor did it drink even one cup of wine, and within three days it died. The problem was trying to feed a bird on what you eat rather than what a bird needs.

'To feed a bird so it survives, let it live in the midst of the forest, gambol on the shores and inlets, float on the rivers and lakes, devour mudfish and tiddlers, go with the flock, either flying or resting, and be as it wishes. Birds dislike hearing human voices, never mind all the other noises and trouble! If you try to make them happy by playing the Nine Shao music in the area around their lakes, when the birds hear it they will fly away. If the animals hear it, they will run away and hide and if the fish hear it they will dive down to escape. Only the people, if they hear it, will come together to listen.

'Fish can live in water quite contentedly, but if people try it, they die, for different beings need different contexts which are right and proper for them. This is why the ancient sages never expected just one response from the rest of the creatures nor tried to make them conform. Titles should not be over-stretched in trying to capture reality and ideas should be only applied when appropriate, for this is not only sensible, it will bring good fortune.'

[...]

The priest of the ancestors looked into the pigsty and said, 'What's so bad about dying? I fatten you up for three months, then I undergo spiritual discipline for ten days, fast for three days, lay out the white reeds, carve up your shoulders and rump and lay them on the place of sacrifice. Surely you're OK with that, aren't you?'

It is, however, true to say that from the perspective of the pig it would be better to eat oats and bran and stay there in the pigsty. It is also true that, looking at this from my perspective, I'd like to be honoured as an important official while alive and, when I die, be buried with a horse-drawn hearse, lying upon a bed of feathers. I could live with that! From the pig's point of view, I wouldn't give a penny for such a life, but from my point of view, I'd be very content, though I wonder why I perceive things so differently from a pig?

PART 11
Grasping the Purpose of Life

If you have grasped the purpose of life there is no point in trying to make life into something it is not or cannot be. If you have grasped the purpose of destiny, there is no point in trying to change it through knowledge.

If you wish to care for your body, first of all take care of material things, though even when you have all the things you want, the body can still be uncared for.

Since you have life, you must first of all take care that this does not abandon the body. However, it is possible for the body to retain its life, but still not be sustained. Birth cannot be avoided, nor death be prevented. How ridiculous! To see the people of this generation who believe that simply caring for the body will preserve life. But if caring for the body is not sufficient to sustain life, why does the world continue to do this? It may be worthless, but nevertheless it cannot be neglected, we are unable to avoid it.

If someone wishes to stop doing anything to sustain the body, they are advised to leave this world, for by leaving they can be free from any commitments, and, being free from commitments, they can be virtuous and peaceful. Being virtuous and peaceful, they can be born again like others and, being born again, they approach close to the Tao. But why is it such a good idea to leave the troubles of this existence and to forget the purpose of life? If you leave the troubles of existence, your body will not be wearied; if you forget life, your energy will not be damaged. Thus, with your body and energy harmonized, you can become one with Heaven. Heaven and Earth are the father and mother of all life. Together they create a form, apart they create a beginning. If body and energy are without fault, this is known as being able to adapt. Strengthened and again strengthened, you come back again to assist Heaven.

Master Lieh Tzu asked gatekeeper Yin, 'Only the perfect man can walk under water and not drown, can walk on fire without burning, and can pass over the multitude of forms of life without fear. I would like to ask, how does the perfect one do this?'

Gatekeeper Yin replied, 'It is because he preserves his original breath and this has nothing to do with knowledge, work, persistence or bravery. Sit down, and I will tell you all about it.

'Everything has a face, forms, sounds and colour: these are just appearances. How is it possible that this thing and that thing are separated from each other? Indeed, why should any of them be viewed as truly the first of all beings? They are just forms and colours, and nothing more. However, everything arises from what is formless and descends into that which is changeless.

'If you grasp and follow this, using it to the full, nothing can stand in your way! It means being able to reside within limits which have no limit, be secluded within boundaries which have no beginning, ramble to where both the beginning and the end of all life is; combine the essential nature, nourish the original breath, harmonize Virtue and, by following this path, commune with the origin of all life. Someone like this guards his unity with Heaven, his spirit is without fault, and thus nothing can get inside and attack him!

'If a drunk falls out of his carriage, even if the carriage is going very fast, he will not die. He is just the same as others, bone and joints, but he is not injured, for his spirit is united. Since he does not realize he was travelling, he has no idea that he has fallen out, so neither life nor death, alarm nor fear can affect him, and he just bumps into things without any anxiety or injury.

'If it is possible to stay united through being drunk on wine, just imagine how much more together one could be if united with Heaven! The sage retreats to the serenity of Heaven, as a result nothing causes him harm. Even someone who is out for revenge does not break his opponent's sword. Nor does someone get cross with a tile that just fell on him, no matter how upset he is. Instead, we should recognize that everything under Heaven is united. Thus it is possible to get rid of chaos, violence and warfare and of the rigours of punishment and execution, for this is the Tao.

'Do not hearken to the Heavenly in humanity, but listen to the Heavenly in Heaven, for paying attention to Heaven's Virtue is life-giving, while attending to humanity damages life. Do not cast aside the Heavenly, and do not ignore the human aspect: then the people will draw closer to the realization of Truth!'

[...]

Confucius was sightseeing in Lu Liang, where the waterfall is thirty fathoms high and the river races along for forty miles, so fast that neither fish nor any other creature can swim in it. He saw one person dive in and he assumed that this person wanted to embrace death, perhaps because of some anxiety, so he placed his followers along the bank and they prepared to pull him out. However, the swimmer, having gone a hundred yards, came out, and walked nonchalantly along the bank, singing a song with water dripping off him.

Confucius pursued him and said, 'I thought you were a ghost, but now I see, Sir, that you are a man. I wish to enquire, do you have a Tao for swimming under the water?'

He said, 'No, I have no Tao. I started with what I knew, matured my innate nature and allow destiny to do the rest. I go in with the currents and come out with the flow, just going with the Tao of the water and never being concerned. That is how I survive.'

Confucius said, 'What do you mean when you say you started with what you knew, matured your innate nature and allow destiny to do the rest?'

He said, 'I was born on the dry land and feel content on the land, where I know what I know. I was nurtured by the water, and felt safe there: that reflects my innate nature. I am not sure why I do this, but I am certain that this is destiny.'

Woodcarver Ching carved a piece of wood to form a bell support, and those who saw it were astonished because it looked as if ghosts or spirits had done it. The Marquis of Lu saw it, and asked, 'Where does your art come from?'

'I am just a woodcarver,' Ching replied. 'How could I have "art"? One thing is certain, though, that when I carve a bell support, I do not allow it to exhaust my original breath, so I take care to calm my heart. After I have fasted for three days, I give no thought to praise, reward, titles or income. After I have fasted for five days, I give no thought to glory or blame, to skill or stupidity. After I have fasted for seven days, I am so still that I forget whether I have four limbs and a body. By then the Duke and his court have ceased to exist as far as I am concerned. All my energy is focused and external concerns have gone. After that I depart and enter the mountain forest, and explore the Heavenly innate nature of the trees; once I find one with a perfect shape, I can see for certain the possibility of a bell support and I set my hand to the task; if I cannot see the possibility, I leave it be. By so doing, I harmonize the Heavenly with Heaven, and perhaps this is why it is thought that my carvings are done by spirits!'

[...]

Workman Chui could draw as straight as a T-square or as curved as a compass, because his fingers could follow the changes and his heart did not obstruct. Thus his mind was one and never blocked. The feet can be forgotten when you walk in comfortable shoes. The waist can be forgotten when your belt fits comfortably. Knowledge can forget yes and no, if the heart journeys contentedly. Nothing changes inside, nothing proceeds from outside, if you respond to what occurs in a contented way. By starting with what is contented, not undergoing that which is disturbing, it is possible to know the contentment of forgetting what contentment is.

[...]

Chuang Tzu was walking through the heart of the mountains when he saw a huge verdant tree. A woodcutter stopped beside the tree, but did not cut it. When asked why he didn't he said, 'It's no good.' Chuang Tzu said, 'Because this tree is not considered useful, it can follow all the years Heaven has given it.'

The Master came out of the mountains and stayed a night at a friend's house. This man was delighted and told his son to kill a goose and cook it. The son answered, saying, 'One goose can cackle, the other one can't. Tell me which one to prepare?' The father replied, 'Prepare the one that does not cackle.'

On the next day Chuang Tzu's followers asked him, 'Yesterday there was a tree in the heart of the mountains which was able to live all the years Heaven gives because it is no use. Now, at your friend's house, there is a goose who dies because it is no use. Teacher, what do you think of this?'

Chuang Tzu laughed and said, 'Personally, I'd find a position between useful and useless. This position between useful and useless might seem a good position, but I tell you it is not, for trouble will pursue you. It would certainly not be so, however, if you were to mount upon the Virtue of the Tao;

'never certain, never directed,

never praised, never condemned,

on the one hand a dragon, on the other a snake,

going as it seems appropriate.

Now up, now down,

using harmony as your guide,

floating on the source of all life.

'Let things be, but don't allow things to treat you as just an object, then you cannot be led into difficulties! This is the path taken by Shen Nung and the Yellow Emperor. Now, however, because of the multitudinous varieties of species and the ethical codes of humanity, things certainly aren't what they were!

'There is unity only in order to divide;

fulfilment only in order to collapse;

a cutting edge is blunted;

those who are elevated are overthrown;

ambition is thwarted;

the wise are conspired against;

the fools are conned.

'So what can be trusted? My followers, just the Tao and its Virtue!'

[...]

Confucius was besieged in the area between Chen and Tsai and had no hot food for seven days. The Grand Duke Jen came out to express his concern and said, 'Master, do you think you will die?'

'Certainly,' said Confucius.

'Master, are you frightened by death?'

'Certainly.'

'I would like to tell you the Tao of never dying,' said Jen. 'There is a bird that dwells in the Eastern ocean called Helpless. This bird is helpless for it flips and flops, flips and flops, as if it had no strength, flying only with the assistance of the other birds and jostling to return to the nest. None of them likes to be in front or behind, preferring to pick away at what others leave. Thus, when the bird flies, it is never alone, and no others outside the flock, such as humans, can do it any harm, so it avoids disasters.

'The straight tree is the first to be chopped down; the well of sweet water is the first to run dry. Sir, your intention is to display your knowledge in order to astonish the ignorant, and by developing your self, to cast a light upon the crudeness of others. You shine, you positively glow, as if you carried with you the sun and moon. All this is why you cannot avoid disasters.

'I have heard the great fulfilment man say, "The boastful have done nothing worthwhile, those who do something worthwhile will see it fade, fame soon disappears." There are few who can forget success and fame and just return to being ordinary citizens again! The Tao moves all, but the perfect man does not stand in its light, his Virtue moves all, but he does not seek fame. He is empty and plain, and seems crazy. Anonymous, abdicating power, he has no interest in work or fame. So he doesn't criticize others and they don't criticize him. The perfect man is never heard, so why, Sir, do you so want to be?'

Confucius said, 'Splendid!' then said farewell to his friends, left his followers and retired into a great marsh, put on animal skins and rough cloth and lived off acorns and chestnuts. He went out amongst the animals and they were not afraid, amongst the birds and they did not fly away. If the birds and animals were not alarmed, then neither should people be either!

Confucius asked Master Sang Hu, 'I have been exiled from Lu twice, a tree was toppled on top of me in Sung, all records of me have been wiped out in Wei, I was impoverished in Shang and besieged in Chen and Tsai. I have had to endure so many troubles. My friends and acquaintances have wandered off and my followers have begun deserting me. But why is this happening?'

Master Sang Hu said, 'Have you not heard of the man of Chia who ran away? Lin Hui threw aside his jade emblem worth a thousand pieces of gold, tied his son to his back and hurried away. People asked, "Was it because the boy was worth more? Surely a child isn't that valuable. Was it because of all the effort required to carry the jade? But surely a child is even more trouble. So why throw away the jade emblem worth a thousand pieces of gold and rush off with the young child on your back?" Lin Hui told them, "It was greed that brought me and the jade emblem together, but it was Heaven that linked my son and me together."

'When the ties between people are based upon profit, then when troubles come, people part easily. When people are brought together by Heaven, then when troubles come, they hold together. To hold together or to separate, these are two very different things. The relationship with a nobleman can be as bland as water, that with a mean-spirited person sickly sweet as wine. However, the blandness of the nobleman can develop into affection, but the sweetness of the mean-spirited person develops into revulsion. That which unites for no apparent reason, will fall apart for no apparent reason.'

[...]

Chuang Tzu, dressed in a worn, patched gown made of coarse cloth and with shoes held together with string, went to visit the King of Wei. The King of Wei said, 'Why are you in such a state, Master?'

Chuang Tzu replied, "This is poverty but not distress. If a scholar has the Tao and the Virtue but is unable to use them, that is distress. If his clothes are worn and shoes held together with string, that is poverty but not distress. This is known as not being around at the right time. Your Majesty, have you never seen monkeys climbing? When they are amongst plane trees, the oaks and camphor trees, they cling to branches and leaves with such ease that not even the archers Yi or Peng Meng could spot them. However, when they are amongst the prickly mulberry, thorny date trees and other spiky bushes, they move cautiously, looking from side to side, shaking with fear. This is not because their sinews and bones have gone stiff or unable to bend, but because the monkeys are not in their own environment and so cannot use their skills. Now that I find myself living with a benighted leader and with rebellious ministers above me, how can I avoid distress?

[...]

Chuang Tzu was wandering through the park at Tiao Ling, when he saw a strange jackdaw come flying from the south. Its wing-span measured seven feet and its eyes were large, about an inch across. It brushed against Chuang Tzu's forehead as it passed and then came to rest in a copse of chestnut trees. Chuang Tzu said, 'What sort of bird is this, with wings so vast but going nowhere, eyes so large but it can't see properly?' Hitching up his robe, he hurried after it with his crossbow in order to take a pot shot at it. On the way he saw a cicada which was basking in a beautiful shady spot, without a thought for its bodily safety. Suddenly, a praying mantis stretched forth its feelers and prepared to spring upon the cicada, so engrossed in the hunt that it forgot its own safety. The strange jackdaw swept down and seized them both, likewise forgetting its own safety in the excitement of the prize. Chuang Tzu sighed with compassion and said, 'Ah! So it is that one thing brings disaster upon another, and then upon itself!' He cast aside his crossbow and was on his way out, when the forester chased after him, shouting at him for being a poacher.

Chuang Tzu went home and was depressed for three months. Lin Chou, who was with him, asked him, 'Master, why are you so miserable?'

Chuang Tzu said, 'I was so concerned with my body that I forgot my self. It was like looking into cloudy water, thinking it was really clear. Furthermore, I heard my Master say once, "When associating with the locals, act like a local." So I went out walking in the park at Tiao Ling and forgot my own self. A strange jackdaw touched my forehead, then settled in a copse of chestnut trees and there forgot its own true being. The forester thought I was to blame. This is why I'm miserable.'

[...]

Confucius went to see Lao Tzu and found him washing his hair. He had spread it out over his shoulders to dry. He stood there without moving, as if no one else existed in the world. Confucius stood quietly and then, after a while, quietly came into his vision and said, 'Were my eyes dazzled, is this really you? Just now, Sir, your body was as still as an old dead tree. You seemed to have no thought in your head, as if you were in another world and standing utterly alone.'

'I let my heart ponder upon the origin of beginnings,' said Lao Tzu.

'What do you mean?' asked Confucius.

'The heart may try to reason this out but doesn't understand it, and the mouth may hang open but can't find words to say. Still, I will attempt to describe this to you. Perfect yin is harsh and cold, perfect yang is awesome and fiery. Harshness and coldness emanate from Earth, awesomeness and fieriness emanate from Heaven. The two mingle and join, and from their conjunction comes to birth everything that lives. Maybe there is one who controls and ensures all this, but if so, then no one has seen any form or shape. Decay and growth, fullness and emptiness, at one time dark, at another bright, the changes of the sun and the transformation of the moon, these go by day after day, but no one has seen what causes this. Life has its origin from which it emerges and death has its place to which it returns. Beginning and end follow each other inexorably and no one knows of any end to this. If this is not so, then who is the origin and guide?'

'I want to ask what it means to wander like this,' said Confucius.

Lao Tzu said, 'To obtain this is perfect beauty and perfect happiness, and to obtain perfect beauty and wander in perfect happiness is to be a perfect man.'

'I would like to hear how this is done,' said Confucius.

Lao Tzu replied, 'Creatures that eat grass are not put out by a change of pasture. Creatures that are born in the water are not put out by a change of water. They can live with a minor change, but not with a change to that which is the most significant. Joy, anger, sadness and happiness do not enter into their breasts. All under Heaven, all forms of life, come together in the One. Obtain the One and merge with it and all your four limbs and hundred joints will become just dust and ashes. For death and birth, ending and beginning are nothing more than the sequence of day and night. Then you will never be disturbed in your contentment by such trifles as gain and loss, for example, good fortune or bad! Those who ignore the status of authority, casting it aside like so much mud, they know that their own self is of greater significance than any title. The value of your self lies within and is not affected by what happens externally. The constant transformation of all forms of life is like a beginning without end. What is there in this to disturb your heart? Those who comprehend the Tao are freed from all this.'

'Master,' said Confucius, 'your Virtue is like that of Heaven and Earth, but even you have to resort to these perfect words to guide you. Who amongst the great men of antiquity could have lived this out?'

Lao Tzu replied, 'I certainly do not. The flowing of the stream does nothing, but it follows its nature. The perfect man does the same with regard to Virtue. He does nothing to cultivate it, but all is affected by its presence. He is like the height of Heaven: natural; or the solidity of Earth, the brightness of sun and moon: all natural. There is no need to cultivate this!'

[...]

Chuang Tzu went to see Duke Ai of Lu. Duke Ai said, 'There are many learned scholars in Lu but few of them study your works, Master.'

Chuang Tzu said, 'Lu has few learned ones.'

Duke Ai said, 'There are men wearing the dress of learned scholars throughout the state of Lu. How can you say there are few?'

Chuang Tzu said, 'I have heard that those learned ones who wear round caps on their heads, know the seasons of Heaven; those who wear square shoes know the shape of the Earth; those who tie semi-circular disks to their belts deal perfectly with all that comes before them. But a nobleman can follow the Tao without having to dress the part. Indeed, he might wear the dress but not understand the Tao at all! Should my Lord not be sure on this point, why not issue an order of state saying, "Any wearing the dress but not practising the Tao will be executed!"'

This is exactly what Duke Ai did, and five days later throughout the kingdom of Lu not a single learned one wore the dress! Only one old man wore the dress of the learned and stood at the Duke's gate. The Duke immediately called him in and discussed the affairs of the kingdom with him, and though they went through a thousand issues and tens of thousands of digressions, the old man was never at a loss.

Chuang Tzu said, 'So, in the whole kingdom of Lu there is just this one man who is among the learned ones. How can you claim there are many?'

PART 12
Do Not Ask about the Tao

Knowledge strolled north to the shores of the Dark Waters, scaled the mount of Secret Heights and came upon Words-of-Actionless-Action. Knowledge said to Words-of-Actionless-Action, 'I want to ask you something. What sort of thought and reflection does it take to know the Tao? In what sort of place and in what sorts of ways should we undertake to rest in the Tao? What sort of path and what sort of plans do we need to obtain the Tao?' These three questions he asked of Words-of-Actionless-Action, but he did not answer. Not only did he not answer, he had no idea what to answer.

Knowledge did not obtain any answers, so he travelled to the White Waters of the south, climbed up on to the top of Doubt Curtailed and there caught sight of Wild-and-Surly. Knowledge put the same question to Wild-and-Surly. Wild-and-Surly said, 'Ah ha! I know, and I will tell you.' In the middle of saying this, he forgot what he was going to say!

Knowledge did not obtain any answers, so he went back to the Emperor's palace to see the Yellow Emperor and to ask him. The Yellow Emperor said, 'Practise having no thoughts and no reflections and you will come to know the Tao. Only when you have no place and can see no way forward will you find rest in the Tao. Have no path and no plans and you will obtain the Tao.'

Knowledge said to the Yellow Emperor, 'You and I know this, but the others did not know, so which of us is actually right?'

The Yellow Emperor said, 'Words-of-Actionless-Action was truly right. Wild-and-Surly seems right. In the end, you and I are not close to it.

'Those who understand, do not say.

Those who say, do not understand.

And so the sage follows the teachings without words.

The Tao cannot be made to occur,

Virtue cannot be sought after.

However, benevolence can be undertaken,

righteousness can be striven for,

rituals can be adhered to.

It is said, "When the Tao was lost, Virtue appeared;

when Virtue was lost, benevolence appeared;

when benevolence was lost, righteousness appeared;

when righteousness was lost, ritual appeared.

Rituals are just the frills on the hem of the Tao, and are signs of impending disorder."

'It is said, "One who follows the Tao daily does less and less. As he does less and less, he eventually arrives at actionless action. Having achieved actionless action, there is nothing which is not done." Now that we have become active, if we wish to return to our original state, we will find it very difficult! Who but the great man could change this?

'Life follows death and death is the forerunner of life.

Who can know their ways?

Human life begins with the original breath;

When it comes together there is life,

When it is dispersed, there is death.'

[...]

Confucius said to Lao Tzu, 'Now, today, you seem relaxed, so I would like to ask about the perfect Tao.'

Lao Tzu said, 'You should cleanse and purify your heart through fasting and austerities, wash your spirit to make it clean and repress your knowledge. The Tao is profound and almost impossible to describe! I will attempt to offer some understanding of it:

'The brightly shining is born from the deeply dark;

that which is orderly is born from the formless;

the spiritual is born from the Tao;

the roots of the body are born from the seminal essence;

all forms of life give each other shape through birth.

Those with nine apertures are born from the womb,

while those with eight are born from eggs.

Of its coming there is no trace,

no sign of its departure,

neither entering the gate nor dwelling anywhere,

open to all the four directions.

Those who travel with the Tao will be strong in body,

sincere and profound in their thought,

clear of sight and hearing,

using their hearts without tiring,

responding to all without prejudice.

As a result of this, Heaven is high and Earth wide,

the sun and moon move and everything flourishes.

This is the Tao!

'Even the broadest knowledge does not comprehend it.

Reason does not mean wisdom, so the sage casts these aside.

There is something which is complete, no matter what you add;

is not diminished, no matter what you take away.

This is what the sage holds to.

It is as the ocean, deeply deep,

as the mountains, high and proud,

its end is its beginning,

it carries all forms of life and never fails.

The Tao of the nobleman is just external garb!

That which sustains all forms of life and never falters,

this is the true Tao!'

[...]

Great Purity asked Endless, 'Sir, do you know the Tao?'

'I do not know it,' said Endless.

Then he asked Actionless Action, who replied, 'I know the Tao.'

'Sir,' asked Great Purity, 'about your knowledge of the Tao, do you have some special hints?'

'I have.'

'What are they?'

Actionless Action said, 'I know that the Tao can elevate and bring low, bind together and separate. These are the hints I would give you to know the Tao.'

With these different answers Great Purity went to No Beginning and said, 'Between Endless's statement that he doesn't know, and Actionless Action's statement that he does know, I am left wondering which of these is right and which is wrong.'

No Beginning said, 'Not to know is profound and to know is shallow. To be without knowledge is to be inward, to know is to be outward.'

Then indeed did Great Purity cast his eyes upward and sigh, 'Not to know is to know and to know is not to know! Who knows about not knowing about knowing?'

No Beginning said:

'The Tao cannot be heard: what is heard is not the Tao.

The Tao cannot be seen: what can be seen is not the Tao.

The Tao cannot be spoken: what is spoken is not the Tao.

Do we know what form gives form to the formless?

The Tao has no name.'

No Beginning continued:

'To be questioned about the Tao and to give an answer means that you don't know the Tao.

'One who asks about the Tao has never understood anything about the Tao.

'Do not ask about the Tao, for the asking is not appropriate, nor can the question be answered, because it is like asking those in dire extremity. To answer what cannot be answered is to show no inner understanding. When someone without inner understanding waits for an answer from those in dire extremity, they illustrate that they neither grasp where they stand outwardly nor understand the great Beginning within. So they cannot cross the Kun Lun mountains nor wander in the great Void.'

[...]

Nan Jung Chu gathered his provisions and set off, and after seven days and seven nights he arrived at the home of Lao Tzu.

'Have you come from Chu?' said Lao Tzu, and Nan Jung Chu replied, 'I have.'

'So, Sir, why have you brought this great crowd of other people with you?' Nan Jung Chu spun round and looked behind him in astonishment.

'Sir, don't you understand what I am saying?' said Lao Tzu.

Nan Jung Chu hung his head in shame and then looked up, sighed and said, 'Now I can't remember what to say in response and have therefore also forgotten what I was going to ask.'

'What are you saying?' said Lao Tzu.

'Do I have any understanding?' said Nan Jung Chu. 'People will call me a fool. Do I understand? This just upsets me. If I am not benevolent, then I distress others. If I am benevolent, then I distress myself. If I am not righteous, then I harm others. If I am righteous, then I upset myself. How can I get out of all this? These three issues perplex me, so following Chu's instructions I have come to ask you about them.'

Lao Tzu replied, 'Just now I looked deep into your eyes and I could see what sort of a person you are. What you have just said convinces me I am right. You are bewildered and confused, as if you had lost your father and mother and were looking for them using a pole to reach the bottom of the sea. You are lost and frightened. You want to rediscover your self and your innate nature but you haven't a clue how to set about this. What a sorry state you are in!'

Nan Jung Chu asked to be allowed to go into his room. He sought to develop the good and rid himself of the bad. After ten days of misery he came out and went to see Lao Tzu again.

'I can see that you have been washing and purifying yourself thoroughly,' said Lao Tzu, 'but you are still impure despite the outward cleanliness. Something is stirring inside you and there is still something rotten within. Outside influences will press upon you and you will find it impossible to control them. It is wiser to shut the gate of your inner self against them. Likewise, when interior influences disturb you and you find it impossible to control them, then shut the gate of your self so as to keep them in. To struggle against both the outside and inside influences is more than even one who follows the Tao and its Virtue can control, so how much more difficult it is for one who is just starting out along the Tao.'

Nan Jung Chu said, 'A villager fell ill and his neighbour asked how he was. He was able to describe his illness, even though he had never suffered from it before. When I ask you about the great Tao, it is like drinking medicine that makes me feel worse than before. I would like to know about the normal method for protecting one's life, that is all.'

'The basic way of protecting life - can you embrace the One?' said Lao Tzu. 'Can you hold it fast? Can you tell good from bad fortune without using the divination of the tortoise shell or the yarrow sticks? Do you know when to stop? Do you know when to desist? Can you forget others and concentrate upon your inner self? Can you escape lures? Can you be sincere? Can you be a little baby? The baby cries all day long but its throat never becomes hoarse: that indeed is perfect harmony. The baby clenches its fists all day long but never gets cramp, it holds fast to Virtue. The baby stares all day long but it is not affected by what is outside it. It moves without knowing where, it sits without knowing where it is sitting, it is quietly placid and rides the flow of events. This is how to protect life.'

'So this is what it takes to be a perfect man?' said Nan Jung Chu.

'Indeed no. This is what is known as the melting of the ice, the dissolving of the cold. Are you up to it? The perfect man is as one with others in seeking his food from the Earth and his joy from Heaven. However, he remains detached from consideration of profit and gain from others, does not get embroiled in plots and schemes nor in grandiose projects. Alert and unceasing he goes, simple and unpretentious he comes. This indeed is called the way to protect life.'

'So it is this which is his perfection?'

'Not quite,' replied Lao Tzu. 'Just now I asked you, "Can you become a little baby?" The baby acts without knowing why and moves without knowing where. Its body is like a rotting branch and its heart is like cold ashes. Being like this, neither bad fortune will affect it nor good fortune draw near. Having neither bad fortune nor good, it is not affected by the misfortune that comes to most others!'

[...]

There is a saying:

'Perfect behaviour does not discriminate amongst people;

perfect righteousness takes no account of things;

perfect knowledge makes no plans;

perfect benevolence exhibits no emotion;

perfect faith makes no oath of sincerity.'

Suppress the whims of the will and untie the mistakes of the heart.

Expunge the knots of Virtue,

unblock the flow of the Tao.

Honours and wealth,

distinctions and authority,

fame and gain,

these six are formed by the illusions of the will.

Looks and style,

beauty and reason,

thrill of life and memories,

these six are the faults of the heart.

Hatred and desire,

joy and anger,

sadness and happiness,

these six are the knots of Virtue.

Rejection and acceptance,

giving and taking,

knowledge and ability,

these six are the impediments to the free flow of the Tao.

When these four sets of six no longer trouble the breast,

then you will be centred.

Being centred, you will be calm.

Being calm, you will be enlightened.

Being enlightened, you will be empty.

Being empty, you will be in actionless action,

But with actionless action nothing remains undone.

The Tao is the centrepiece of the devotions of Virtue.

Life is the brightness of Virtue.

Innate nature is what motivates life.

[...]

Chuang Tzu's family were poor so he went to borrow some rice from the Marquis of Chien Ho. The Marquis of Chien Ho said, 'Of course. I am about to receive the tax from the people and will give you three hundred pieces of gold - is that enough?'

Chuang Tzu flushed with anger and said, 'On my way here yesterday I heard a voice calling me. I looked around and saw a large fish in the carriage rut. I said, "Fish! What are you doing there?" He said, "I am Minister of the Waves in the Eastern Ocean. Sire, do you have a measure of water you could give me?" Well, I told him, "I am going south to visit the Kings of Wu and Yueh and after that I would redirect the course of the Western River so it will flow up to you. Would that do?" The large fish flushed with anger and said, "I am out of my very element, I have nowhere to go. Give me just a little water and I can survive. But giving me such an answer as that means you will only ever find me again on a dried fish stall!"'

[...]

The great One knows,

the great mystery reveals,

the great yin observes,

the great eye sees,

the great equal is the origin,

the great skill creates it,

the great trust touches it,

the great judge holds fast to it.

Heaven is in everything: follow the light, hide in the cloudiness and begin in what is. Do this and your understanding will be like not understanding and your wisdom will be like not being wise. By not being wise you will become wise later. When you ask questions, set no limits, even though they cannot be limitless. Although things seem to be sometimes going up and sometimes descending, sometimes slipping away, nevertheless there is a reality, the same today as in the past. It does not change, for nothing can affect it. Could we not say it is one great harmony? So why shouldn't we ask about it and why are you so confused? If we use that which does not confuse to understand that which does confuse, then we can come back to that which does not confuse. This will be the great unconfusing.

[...]

'The four seasons each have their own original life,

and Heaven does not discriminate,

so the cycle is fulfilled.

The five government offices have different roles,

but the ruler does not discriminate,

so the state is well run.

The great man does not discriminate

between war and peace,

so his Virtue is perfect.

All the forms of life are different,

but the Tao does not discriminate,

so it has no name.

Being nameless, it is also actionless action,

yet all life occurs.

The seasons end and begin;

the generations change and transform.

Inauspicious and auspicious fortune falls upon you,

sometimes unwelcomed,

other times welcomed.

Settle into your own views,

argue with others,

at times condemn those who are upright,

then those who are bent.

You should be like a great marsh land

with space for a hundred kinds of trees.

Or be like a great mountain

where the trees and grasses rest on the same ground.

This is what is meant by Talk of the Villages.'

PART 13
Can I Ask You about Truth?

In the past King Wen of Chao loved swords. Specialists came to his gate, over three thousand of them, all experts in swordsmanship. They were his guests. Day and night they fought before him until the dead or wounded each year were more than a hundred. But the King never ceased to be delighted at watching them. This went on for three years, then the country began to fall apart and the other princes began to plot its overthrow.

Crown Prince Kuei was distressed by this, and he presented the situation to his followers:

'If there is anyone here who can persuade the King to put away these swordsmen, I will give him a thousand pieces of gold,' he said. His followers replied,

'Chuang Tzu can do this.'

The Crown Prince sent an ambassador with a thousand pieces of gold to Chuang Tzu. Chuang Tzu refused the gold but returned with the ambassador. He came in to see the Crown Prince and said, 'Oh Prince, what is it you wish to tell me that you send me a thousand pieces of gold?'

'I have heard, Sir, that you are an illustrious sage,' said the Crown Prince. 'The gift of a thousand pieces of gold was a gift for your attendants. However, you have refused to accept this, so what more dare I say?'

Chuang Tzu said, 'I have heard that the Crown Prince wants to use me to help the King give up his abiding passion. If in trying to do so I upset the King and fail to achieve what you hope for, then I might be executed. So what use would the gold be to me then? Or, if I could get the King to give up, and fulfil your hopes, what is there in this whole kingdom of Chao that I could not ask for and be given?'

'You're right,' said the Crown Prince. 'However the King will only see swordsmen.'

'That's all right. I'm quite good with a sword,' replied Chuang Tzu.

'Fair enough,' said the Crown Prince, 'but the swordsmen the King sees are all tousle-headed with spiky beards, wearing loose caps held on with simple, rough straps and robes that are cut short behind. They look about them fiercely and talk only of their sport. The King loves all this. Now, if you go in wearing your scholar's garb you will start off on completely the wrong foot.'

'With your permission I will get a full swordsman's outfit,' said Chuang Tzu.

Within three days he had got this and returned to see the Crown Prince. The Crown Prince took him to see the King, who drew his sword and sat waiting for him. Chuang Tzu walked slowly into the hall through the main door. When he saw the King, he did not bow.

'What instruction have you for me, that you have persuaded the Crown Prince about beforehand?' demanded the King.

'I have heard that the King likes swords and so I have brought my sword for the King to see.'

'What use is your sword in combat?'

'My sword can kill one person every ten paces, and after a thousand miles it is not faltering.'

The King was pleased and said, 'There can be no one else like you under Heaven!'

'A fine swordsman opens with a feint then gives ground, following up with a cut, stalling his opponent before he can react,' replied Chuang Tzu. 'I would like to show you my skills.'

'Rest awhile in your rooms, Master, and await my commands,' said the King. 'I shall make arrangements for the contest and I will call you.'

The King spent the next seven days testing his swordsmen. More than sixty died or were severely wounded, leaving five or six who were selected and commanded to present themselves in the hall. Then he called in Chuang Tzu and said, 'Now, this very day I shall pit you against these men to show your skills.'

'I have longed for such an opportunity,' said Chuang Tzu.

'Sir, what sort of sword will you choose, long or short?' asked the King.

'Any kind will do,' said Chuang Tzu, 'but I have three swords, any of which I could use if the King agrees. But first I would like to say something about them and then use them.'

'I would like to hear about these three swords,' said the King.

'I have the sword of the Son of Heaven, the sword of the noble Prince and the sword of the commoner,' said Chuang Tzu.

'What is this sword of the Son of Heaven?'

'The Son of Heaven's sword has as its point the Valley of Yen, and the Great Wall and Chi and Tai mountains as its blade edge. Chin and Wey are its ridge, Chou and Sung are its hilt and Han and Wei its sheath. On all four sides it is surrounded by barbarians and it is wrapped in the four seasons. The Sea of Po encompasses it and the eternal mountains of Chang are its belt. The five elements control it and it enacts what punishment and compassion dictate. It comes out in obedience to yin and yang, stands alert in spring and summer and goes into action in autumn and winter. Thrust forward, there is nothing in front of it; lift it high, and there is nothing above it; swing it low, and there is nothing below it; spin it around, there is nothing encompassing it. Raised high, it cleaves the firmaments; swung low, it severs the very veins of the Earth. Use this sword but once and all the rulers revert to obedience; all below Heaven submit. This is the sword of the Son of Heaven.'

King Wen was astonished and seemed to have forgotten everything else.

'What of the sword of the noble Prince?' he asked.

Chuang Tzu said, 'The sword of the noble Prince, its point is sagacious and courageous people; its blade is those of integrity and sincerity; its ridge is those of worth and goodness; its hilt is those who are trustworthy and wise; its sheath is of the brave and outstanding. When this sword is thrust forward, it encounters nothing; when wielded high, it has nothing above it; when swung low, it has nothing below it; when swirled about, it finds nothing near it. Above, its guidance comes from Heaven and it proceeds with the three great lights. Below, it is inspired by the square, stable nature of the earth, proceeding with the flow of the four seasons. In the middle lands it restores harmony to the people and is in balance with the four directions. Use this sword but once and it is like hearing the crash of thunder. Within the four borders everyone obeys the laws and everyone attends to the orders of the ruler. This is the sword of the noble Prince.'

'What of the sword of the commoner?'

'The sword of the commoner is used by those who are tousle-haired with spiky beards, wearing loose caps held on by ordinary coarse cords, with their robes cut short behind. They stare about them fiercely and will only talk about their swordsmanship while fighting before the King. Raised high, it cuts through the neck; swung low, it slices into the liver and lungs. The people who use the sword of the commoner are no better than fighting cocks who at any time can have their lives curtailed. They are useless to the state. Now you, O King, have the position of the Son of Heaven but you make yourself unworthy by associating with the sword of the commoner. This is what I dare to say.'

The King brought him up into his hall where the butler presented a tray of food, while the King strode three times round the room.

'Sire, sit down and calm yourself,' said Chuang Tzu. 'Whatever there was to say about swords has been said.'

Following this, King Wen did not go out for three months and all his swordsmen killed themselves in their own rooms.

[...]

Confucius wandered through the Black Curtain Forest and sat down beside the Apricot Tree Altar. His followers started reading their books while Confucius played his lute and sang. He was not even halfway through the song when a fisherman stepped out of his boat and came towards him. His beard and eyebrows were white and his hair was wild, while his sleeves hung down beside him. He walked up the slopes until he reached the drier ground and then stopped, resting his left hand on his knee and his chin in his right hand, and listened until the song was over. Then he called over Tzu Kung and Tzu Lu and the two of them went to him.

'Who is that?' he said, pointing at Confucius.

'He is a nobleman from Lu,' replied Tzu Lu.

The fisherman then enquired as to Confucius' family. Tzu Lu replied, 'The family of Kung.'

'What does this man of Kung do for a living?'

Tzu Lu was working out what to say when Tzu Kung replied, saying, 'This man of the Kung family in his innate nature holds fast to loyalty and faithfulness; in his behaviour he shows benevolence and righteousness; he makes the rituals and music beautiful, and balances human relationships. He pays respect above him to the ruler of his generation and in his dealings with those below him he tries to transform the ordinary people, as he wants to bless the whole world. This is what this man of the Kung family does.'

The fisherman enquired further, 'Does he have any land over which he rules?'

'No,' said Tzu Kung.

'Is he an adviser to a king?'

'No.'

The stranger laughed and backed away, saying, 'So benevolence is benevolence, yet he won't escape without harm to himself. Exhausting the heart and wearing out the body puts his true nature in jeopardy. Sadly, I believe he is far removed from the Tao.'

Tzu Kung went up and told Confucius about this. Confucius laid aside his flute and stood up, saying, 'Maybe he is a sage!' and he went down the slope to find him. He reached the water's edge as the fisherman was about to pole away. Seeing Confucius, he poled back again and confronted him. Confucius stepped back somewhat hastily, bowed twice and went forward.

'What do you want, Sir?' said the stranger.

'Just now, Master, you said a few words but didn't finish,' said Confucius. 'Being unworthy, I do not understand them. So I would like to be with you and to hear even just the sounds of your words in the hope that they might enlighten me!'

'Oh-ho, you have a good love of study, Sir!'

Confucius bowed twice and stood up. 'Ever since I was little I have pursued study, and now here I am sixty-nine years old, yet I have never heard the perfect teaching, so what can I do but keep my heart open?'

The stranger said, 'Like seeks like and each note responds to its own. This is the boundary established by Heaven. I will not discuss that which concerns me, but will concentrate on what you need to know about. You, Sir, are wrapped up in the affairs of the people. The Son of Heaven, the noble princes, the great ministers and the common folk, when these four groups do what is right, there is the beauty of unity. If these four groups break apart, then there is terrible great disorder. If ministers do what they should and the ordinary people are concerned with what they do, then no one infringes upon another.

'Fields in ruin, leaking roofs, lack of food and clothing, unjust taxes, disputes between wives and concubines, disorder between the young and the old, these are what trouble the common folk.

'Inability to do the job, being bored by their work, bad behaviour, carelessness and laziness in those below, failure to succeed, insecurity in employment, these are what trouble the great ministers.

'Lack of loyal ministers, civil war in the kingdom, workmen with no skills, tributes that are worthless, poor positioning at the spring and autumn gatherings, the disquiet of the ruler, these are what trouble the noble princes.

'Yin and yang out of harmony, fluctuations in heat and cold which damage all, oppression and rebellion by nobles, all leading to uprisings, ravage and abuse of the people, the rituals badly performed, the treasury empty, social relationships in turmoil and the people debauched, these are what trouble the Son of Heaven and his people.

'Now, Sir, at the higher end of the scale, you are not a ruler, nor a noble nor even a minister in a court, while at the other end you are not in the office of a great minister with all his portfolios. Nevertheless, you have decided to bring beauty to the rituals and the music and to balance human relationships and thus to reform the ordinary people. Isn't this rather overdoing it?

'Furthermore, there are eight defects that people are liable to, as well as four evils that affect their affairs, which must not be ignored:

'To be involved with affairs that are not yours is to be overbearing.

'To draw attention to yourself when no one wants you is to be intrusive.

'To suck up to someone with speeches designed to please is to be sycophantic.

'Not to distinguish between good and evil in what others say is to be a flatterer.

'To gossip about other's failings is to be slanderous.

'To separate friends and families is to be malevolent.

'To give false praise in order to hurt others is to be wicked.

'Having no concern for right or wrong, but to be two-faced in order to find out what others know, is to be treacherous.

'These eight defects cause disorder to others and harm to the perpetrator. A nobleman will not befriend one who has them, nor will an enlightened ruler appoint such a person to be a minister.

'With regard to the four evils of which I spoke, they are:

'Ambition - To be fond of taking on vast enterprises, altering and changing the old traditions, thus hoping that you can increase your fame and standing.

'Greediness - To be a know-all and to try and get everything done your way, seizing what others do and claiming it as your own.

'Obstinacy - To see your errors without doing anything to change them and to persist in doing things the wrong way.

'Bigotry - To smile upon someone who agrees with you but when that person disagrees, to disown and despise them.

'These are the four evils. If you can cast aside the eight defects and avoid the four evils, then you are at a point where it is possible to be taught.'

Confucius looked sad and sighed, bowed twice, stood up and said, 'Lu has exiled me twice, I have fled from Wei, they have felled a tree on me in Sung and laid siege to me between Chen and Tsai. I have no idea what I did to be so misunderstood. Why was I subject to these four forms of trouble?'

The stranger looked distressed, then his expression changed and he said, 'It is very difficult, Sir, to make you understand! There was once a man who was frightened by his own shadow and scared of his own footprints, so he tried to escape them by running away. But every time he lifted his foot and brought it down, he made more footprints, and no matter how fast he ran, his shadow never left him. Thinking he was running too slowly, he ran faster, never ceasing until finally he exhausted himself and collapsed and died. He had no idea that by simply sitting in the shade he would have lost his shadow, nor that by resting quietly he would cease making footprints. He really was a great fool!

'You, Sir, try to distinguish the spheres of benevolence and righteousness, to explore the boundaries between agreement and disagreement, to study changes between rest and movement, to pontificate on giving and receiving, to order what is to be approved of and what disapproved of, to unify the limits of joy and anger, and yet you have barely escaped calamity. If you were to be serious in your cultivation of your own self, careful to guard the truth and willing to allow others to be as they are, then you could have avoided such problems. However, here you are, unable to cultivate yourself yet determined to improve others. Are you not obsessed with external things?'

Confucius, really cast down, said, 'Can I ask you about truth?'

'True truth is simple purity at its most perfect,' replied the stranger. 'To be without purity, to be without sincerity means you cannot move other people. So if you fake mourning and weeping, then no matter how thoroughly you do this, it's not real grief. If you make yourself act angry, even if you sound very fierce, this won't inspire awe. If you force yourself to be affectionate, no matter how much you smile, you cannot create harmony. True grief may make no sound but is really sorrowful; true anger, even if there is no manifestation of it, creates awe; true affection doesn't even need to smile but creates harmony. When someone has truth within, it affects his external spirit, which is why truth is so important.

PART 14
Epilogue

Chuang Tzu said, 'To know the Tao is easy, not to speak about it is hard. Knowing and not saying, this is to aspire to the Heavenly. Knowing and saying, this is to be subject to the human element. In the past people paid attention to the Heavenly, not to the human.'

[...]

A man from Sung, called Tsao Shang, was sent by the King of Sung as an ambassador to the state of Chin. When he left Sung he was given only a few carriages. However, the King of Chin was so delighted with him that he gave him a hundred more. On returning to Sung he met Chuang Tzu and said, 'Living in poor streets of an impoverished village, making sandals and starving, with a shrivelled neck and a sickly face, this I cannot stand! But being in the confidence of a ruler of ten thousand chariots and being given a hundred of them, this I enjoy and am good at.'

Chuang Tzu said, 'Well now. When the King of Chin falls ill, he summons his doctor who lances the ulcer or squeezes the boil and as a reward receives one carriage. The doctor who applies a suppository gets five carriages. The lower down the service, the more carriages given. So, Sir, I assume you must at least have been licking his piles to have been given so many carriages? Be gone, Sir!'

[...]

Someone offered Chuang Tzu a court post. Chuang Tzu answered the messenger, 'Sir, have you ever seen a sacrificial ox? It is decked in fine garments and fed on fresh grass and beans. However, when it is led into the Great Temple, even though it most earnestly might wish to be a simple calf again, it's now impossible!'

Chuang Tzu was dying and his followers wanted to provide a glorious funeral. Chuang Tzu said, 'I will have Heaven and Earth as my shroud and coffin; the sun and moon as my symbols of jade; the stars for my pearls and jewels; all the forms of life as my mourners. I have everything for my funeral, what is there missing? What more could I need?'

His followers said, 'We are worried, Master, that the crows and kites will eat you.'

'Above ground I shall be eaten by crows and kites,' said Chuang Tzu, 'and below ground by worms and ants. Aren't you just being rather partisan in wanting to feed only one of these groups, so depriving the others?

'Trying to use what isn't equal to produce equality is to be equally unequal. Trying to prove something by something uncertain is only certain to make things uncertain. The person whose eyesight is clear and thinks he understands is victim to these sights, whereas the one who is guided by the spirit perceives the reality. That there is a difference between what we see with our eyes and what we know through our spirit is a wisdom from long ago. But the fool relies upon his eyes and loses himself in what is merely human, and everything he does is just a façade - how sad!'

[...]

'The blank and the motionless have no form;

change and transformation are never at rest;

what is death?

what is life?

what is the companionship of Heaven and Earth?

where does the spirit of clarity go?

when forgotten, what becomes of it?

All forms of life are gathered around us, yet none of them is our destination. In the past people thought this was the way of the Tao. Chuang Tzu heard of these ideas and was pleased. He taught them using strange and mysterious expressions, wild and extraordinary phrases, and terms which had no precise meaning. He taught what he believed, yet was never partisan, nor did he view things from just one perspective. He saw the whole world as lost in foolishness and thus incapable of understanding anything sensible.

译者导读

约翰·洛克（John Locke，1632—1704），英国著名思想家、哲学家和著述家，经验主义代表人物，是全面系统地阐述宪政民主基本思想的第一位作家，在社会契约理论上作出重要贡献。洛克1632年生于萨默塞特郡（Somerset）威灵顿村，曾就读牛津大学基督教堂学院，后转攻医学，学成后成为沙夫茨伯里伯爵（辉格党创立人之一）私人医师，为辉格党重要思想领袖。1683年被怀疑涉嫌刺杀查理二世国王，逃至荷兰，1688年返回英格兰，整理书稿，并出版《人类理解论》《政府论》《论宽容》等著作，1704年病逝于艾塞克斯郡。

洛克最著名的作品《人类理解论》于1671年开始撰写，1690年得以出版，自首次出版到1700年已出版二十个版本。在书中，洛克批评了宣称人生下来便带有内在思想的哲学理论，他主张人所经历过的感觉和经验才是形塑思想的主要来源。从哲学的继承性上看，洛克走的是弗兰西斯·培根和托马斯·霍布斯的路线，即知识起源于感觉和经验。书中涉及的思想对于伏尔泰等众多西方哲学家也产生了极大影响，在西方哲学史上起到承前启后的作用。由于他在这方面的理论，洛克可以被归类为经验主义者。

本书截取《人类理解论》中精华而成，全书分为两大部分。第一部分介绍人类的观念。洛克认为观念来源为二，即感觉和反思。感觉来源于感官感受外部世界，而反思则来自于心灵观察本身。与理性主义者不同的是，洛克强调这两种观念是知识的唯一来源，并将观念划分为简单观念和复杂观念。简单观念可以被直接感知，而复杂观念只能融合许多简单观念提炼而出。此外，洛克还对人类常见的心理状态作出描述，并谈到观念的整零与正误。第二部分介绍语言的使用。洛克认为语言是观念的载体，因此语言的作用主要为记载和传播。语言是人类所造，用以表达观念，因此其中的缺陷不可避免。然而在语言的使用过程中，人们也会有意无意地滥用语言，使世界上出现很多无谓的争吵和对抗。但洛克认为，如果人们加以注意，正确使用语言，便可大大地减少交流中的误会和理解中的困难。在现如今这个网络语言满天飞的时代，本书可谓是校正自我用语、减少沟通障碍的助力。

论观念

观念通论及观念的起源

1.观念是思考的产物

每个人在思考时都能有所意识，思考便会产生观念。无疑，这些观念存在于人们的脑海中，一些可以用字词来表达，如“白、硬、甜、思、动、人、象、军、醉”，另一些则不能。那么我们首先要问，这些观念是如何产生的？我知道，人们普遍认为，人自落地那刻起，就带有观念和天性，这是与生俱来的。对于这个说法，我进行过仔细的研究，也解释了观念从何而来，以及这些观念通过何种方式以何种程度进入人的脑海。因此，对于观念和天性与生俱来的说法，我不敢苟同。我也希望每个人通过自身的观察和体验去验证我的这种说法。

2.观念由感觉和反思而来

我们假设人的头脑如同一张白纸，没有任何个性和观念，那么如何才能拥有个性和观念呢？人们无限的幻想所充斥的琳琅宝库从何而来？理性与知识的原料又从何而来？对此我一句话便可作答——从经验而来。我们的知识基于经验也源于经验。我们观察到的，要么是外部的可感物，要么是我们自身察觉和反思得来的内在心理活动。观察带给我们思考的原料，加强我们的理解。这便是知识的来源，我们固有的及习得的观念都源于此。

3.感觉的对象是观念的来源之一

第一，我们的感官在熟知一些特定的感知物之后，会通过多种方式，将几种对于事物不同的感知传递到我们的脑海中，因此我们就有了“黄、白、热、冷、软、硬、苦、甜”及其他一些观念，称为可感知性。我所说的传递到脑海的感觉，是指感官对于外部物体的感受。我们的观念大多源于感官，通过感官让我们理解。我把这称为“感觉”。

4.心理活动是观念的另一来源

第二，观念的第二个来源是我们的心理活动。心理活动也为我们提供观念，加强我们的理解。心理活动之所以是内在的，是因为它是我们的灵魂对已有观念的反思，而反思得来的观念是不能从外部事物上获得的。这些观念包括“知觉、思考、怀疑、相信、推理、认知、意愿”，以及我们头脑里的各种活动。对于这些活动，我们有所意识，并加以注意，从而形成自己的观念，进一步加强我们的理解。这和我们对外物的感知同理。这一来源是个性化的，虽然不是感官（因为无关于外物感知），但是形成却十分相似，因此可以称为内部感官。对于前一种，我称之为“感觉”，那么对于后一种，我就称之为“反思”，因为只有人们在反思时，才能形成以上观念。在本书以下的部分，我在提到“反思”时都是在指人们对内心活动的注意，因为只有对内心活动加以注意，才能形成有助于理解的观念。这两种来源，一则为外部原料，帮助人们形成感觉；一则为内心活动，促使人们进行反思。在我看来，观念只有这两种来源。我这里所提到的“活动”一词是广义上的，不仅可以理解为观念在头脑中的反应，也可以理解为由观念而引发的情感，如某想法带来的满足感或不安感。

5.所有观念均源于二者之一

在我看来，对任何观念的理解，哪怕只有一瞬，都是源于以上两种途径之一的。外部事物在我们的头脑中形成不同的感觉；我们的头脑又通过心理活动的加工促进理解。

全面研究一下两种途径及其模式、组合和关系就能发现，它们涵盖了我们的所有观念，我们头脑中的所有观念无一不是源于二者之一。你可以联系自身，仔细审视自己的理解，告诉我在你自身的观念中，有没有源于感官及反思以外的。不管你脑中有多么丰富的知识，仔细分析下来，就会发现所有观念都源于二者之一，只不过人们的理解把它们无限组合并放大了。这点我们之后也会谈到。

6.对儿童的观察

凡是仔细研究过初生儿的人都会认为，婴儿在坠地时是没有任何观念来帮助他们在今后形成知识的。儿童的观念是逐渐形成的。尽管很多观念显而易见，为人熟知，在他们记得时间和次序前就已经深植脑海，但是直到他们年龄稍长，开始拥有特定观念时，他们才记得幼时拥有过寻常观念，几乎每个人都是如此。如果想试验一下，可以强迫一个儿童保有很少的观念（即便是寻常观念）直至成年。然而儿童所处的世界有很多实体，这些实体以一种永恒且多变的方式影响着他们，不管他们愿不愿意，各种观念都印在了他们的脑海中。只要睁着眼睛，光和颜色就随处可见；声音以及形状一直刺激着他们对应的感官，进入他们的头脑。但是，如果一个儿童被置于一个只有黑白的地方，就算他长至成年，也肯定不辨红绿。同样，如果他小时候没尝过牡蛎和菠萝，长大了也就不能区分这两种食物。

7.人们接触的事物不同，观念便不同

人们在外界接触到的事物种类越多，获得的观念就越多，反之亦然。同理，人们内心反思越多，获得的观念也越多。有时，尽管你十分关注自己的头脑活动，但得出的也只是简单清晰的观念。只有在你专注研究某一领域时，才能只关注这一领域的相关内容，而非对所有内容都加以留意。这样你就能形成关于风景画的特定看法，或者更加了解钟表的零件和运作。而那些对什么都感兴趣的人，则很难做到这点。他也许每天都会看见这幅画或这个钟表，但是如果不加以思考，不考察各个部分，就只能对它们有一个模糊的概念。

8.反思得来的观念往往需要人们的注意，因此出现较晚

为什么儿童迟迟不能具有心理活动产生的观念呢？为什么有些人一生都没有清晰、完整的观念呢？因为，尽管他们不断形成一些观念，但是如果没有对之加以理解，进一步探究，形成思考的产物，那么这些观念只能是表面上的，就不能产生深刻的印象或在脑海中留下清晰、明了、经久的观念。新生的婴儿周围充满了新鲜的事物，不断刺激着他们的感官，吸引着他们的注意力。他们不断留意新事物，更喜欢变幻的花样。因此，儿童初生之年注意力都消耗在了外部事物上。可见人们在年幼时会努力熟悉外部事物，在成长的过程中更多留意的是外部感觉，很少审视自身的观念，直到成熟一些才进行反思。但是，有些人终其一生也未曾反思。

9.灵魂开始领悟时，才会产生观念

要问人的观念什么时候产生，就要问他什么时候开始领悟，因为观念无异于领悟。有人说灵魂总是在思考，只要灵魂存在，就会不断地领悟观念；还说灵魂必会思考，如同物体必有外延。如果这一说法是正确的，那么人们观念的起源就是灵魂的起源。这样说来，灵魂与其观念，物体与其外延就是同时存在的。

10.没有证据证明灵魂一直在思考

灵魂同生命的雏形究竟是一前一后还是同时出现，这个问题留给专业人士解答吧。我认为自己的灵魂是迟钝的，因为我并不经常思考，我还认为思考的频率应该与物体运动的频率一致。在我看来，思考之于灵魂就如同运动之于物体，前者不是后者的本质，而是作用之一。因此，我们可以认为灵魂能够思考，但不能认为灵魂必须一直思考。不眠不休的造物者也许一直在思考，但这对于正常人来说，是不可能的。我们的经验告诉我们一个不争的事实：我们身体的某个部分有思考的能力。但是经验没有告诉我们，这个部分能不能不停思考。所以，说思考对灵魂来说必不可少、密不可分，正如不进行推理（必要的步骤）就要得出一个问题（并非不言自明）的答案一样。乍一听上去，每个人都认为“灵魂一直在思考”不言自明，但究竟是否如此，还需要大家去验证。比如我昨晚是不是彻夜思考，就是未知的。因此，我们如果把所争论的事情作为假设的论据，来证明这个问题，就犯了窃取论点之过。正如假设所有在走的表都在思考，认为这已经得到了充分的验证，就认为我的表走了一夜，也思考了一夜一样。但是不愿自欺的人应该将自己的假设建立在事实之上，并通过合理的经验验证，而不应将自己的假设当作事实。回到我彻夜思考的问题上，就等于不管我自己是否感觉到自己在思考，只因为有人假设我在思考，就得出我是彻夜思考的这样一个结论。

固执己见的人不仅会把不确定的事说成真的，甚至会把错的也说成对的。是不是有人会通过我的话推出，只要我们在睡梦中感觉不到某物，就证明它不存在？我不是因为在睡梦中感觉不到灵魂，就否认它的存在，而是认为，不管是睡着还是醒着，只要在思考，就会有感觉。这并不针对所有事物，但对于我们的思维，只要我们在思考，就一定会有感觉，除非哪天我们能在意识不到的情况下思考。

11.灵魂不能随时意识到自身

我承认，醒着的人每时每刻都在思考，因为醒着就是指能思考。至于无梦的睡眠是否是身心合一的整个人的一种状况，则值得醒者思考。很难想象，一个事物可以思考，却意识不到。如果一个熟睡的人，他的灵魂是在思考的，自己却没有意识，那我就要问，这个思考过程中有没有愉悦或痛苦，能否感受幸福与不幸？我相信，他和他身下的床或那块土地一样，肯定感受不到。因为，既要感到幸福或不幸，又意识不到，在我看来是完全矛盾的，也是不可能的。如果一个人的灵魂可以在身体熟睡时去思考、享受，或是关注愉悦或痛苦，而他却意识不到，也不参与其中，那么醒着的苏格拉底和熟睡的苏格拉底必然不同。因此，他就成了两重的：一重是他熟睡时的灵魂，另一重是醒时身心合一的苏格拉底其人。因为醒着的苏格拉底并不知道也不关心熟睡时灵魂独自享受的幸福与承担的不幸，正如他不关心一个不认识的印度人的死活。如果我们完全意识不到自己的行动和感觉，特别是各种快乐和痛苦，以及由此产生的顾虑，就很难定位自我。

12.如果熟睡的人能在不自知的情况下思考，那么熟睡的他与醒着的他便是两个人

有些人说，灵魂在熟睡时也能思考。因此，在它思考与感悟时自然可以感受高兴、苦恼和其他情绪，而且灵魂自身肯定也能意识到这些感受。但是这种说法并不全面，显然，熟睡的人是意识不到这些感受的。假设卡斯特睡着后灵魂出窍（这在这些人看来不无可能，因为他们认为其他动物虽无思考的灵魂，但也有生命。因此，他们也必须承认，身体离了灵魂照样可以生活，正如灵魂离了身体依然可以存在、思考，并感受幸福与不幸）、独立思考；又假设，他的灵魂可以自行选择思考的地点——另一个人的身体，比如波利克斯，他也在沉睡中，同样没有灵魂。这个地点是可行的，因为卡斯特的灵魂既然可以在他睡觉时思考，卡斯特又意识不到，那么思考在任何地点都能进行。这样我们就有一个灵魂在两个人的身体间来回移动。我们假设这两个身体一睡一醒，互相交替。这样灵魂就在醒着的人身体中思考，而睡者对它所想的，全无意识、全无知觉。那么，卡斯特和波利克斯，既然共用一个灵魂，而一个的所知所感另一个浑然不觉，那么他们是两个独立的人吗？就像卡斯特和赫尔克里士，苏格拉底和柏拉图？会不会一人很幸福，另一人很不幸呢？如果二者独立，那么既然灵魂离开身体独自思考，而身体却没有意识，那么灵魂和身体也被分成两个个体了。这是不可能的，因为没有人会认为，人的同一性是由于灵魂与不变分子结合所致。如果分子不变是同一性的必要条件，那么由于我们身体中的分子每时每刻都在变化，每个人在前后两日或前后两时都不可能同一了。

13.很难让那些睡觉不做梦的人相信，他们是在思考的

因此，我想，每一次打盹儿都能动摇他们的理论，即灵魂每时每刻都在思考。至少很难让那些睡觉不做梦的人相信，他们在睡着的几个小时里是在思考的，只是没有意识到。就算我们把睡梦中的他们叫醒，他们也说不出自己在想什么。

14.要说人在梦中是在思考的，只是不能记得，也是站不住脚的

也许有的人会说，就算人在熟睡，灵魂也是在思考的，只不过没有在记忆里存留。人在睡着的时候可能在不停地思考，醒了之后却可能一丁点儿都不记得。这种说法也很难让人相信，需要证据证明，不能空口无凭。谁能干脆地说，大部分人的一生当中，在睡梦中被人叫醒，会不记得自己在想什么。我认为，大部分人在睡觉时都不会做梦。我曾经遇到一位记忆力颇好的学者，他一向不曾做梦，只有在他高烧刚退才开始做梦，可是那时候，他已经二十五六岁了。我相信世界上还有很多这样的例子，至少每个人都认识几个睡觉不做梦的人。

15.基于这一假设，睡者的思想一定是很合理的

如果我们经常思考，却没有一刻记得，就是无效思考。这样的思考如同镜子，很多图画和想法出现其中，却无一保留。它们消失不见，不曾留下任何印记。所以镜子就算有了这些观念也好不了多少，正如灵魂有了这种观念也好不了多少一样。也许有人会说，醒着的时候，思考涉及人身，这样对观念的记忆就留在脑海中，留下了思考过的痕迹；但是，人在熟睡时，灵魂是独立于人身进行思考的，并没有涉及身体的各个器官，所以就不会记得思考过。不过要如此假设，就不得不荒谬地承认有二重人格；这一层我已经说过了，就不再提。就算假设二重性是存在的，假如灵魂可以在没有人身的帮助下进行思考，那么也能不靠人身保留住这些观念，不然灵魂或任何独立的精神进行思考就毫无用处了。如果灵魂不记得思考过什么，不能存留以备后用，不能在需要时回想起来，回忆不出之前的观念，不去利用之前的经验、推理和深思，那么思考的意义又是什么呢？这样说来，这些认为灵魂可以独立思考的人并没有提高灵魂的地位，同那些他们所谴责的、认为灵魂只是物质中一个微小部分的人没什么两样。随风而去的尘上字迹，在一堆原子上或动物的元气上印的印记，都是有用的，都可以使其主体高贵起来，正如转瞬即逝的灵魂之思，一旦离开视线，就永远消失了，不留一丝记忆。自然不造无用的精良之物。很难想象，我们全知的造物者赋予我们思考的能力，如此绝妙，几乎同她自身一般不可思议，竟是徒然与无用的，使我们一生中至少四分之一的思考毫无意义。审视一下就会发现，就连宇宙中随处可见的无知觉的物质运动，也不至于那样无用，甚至完全白费。

16.基于这一假设，灵魂必有观念源于感觉和反思之外，只不过不得而见

无疑，也有例子证明，在睡觉时所得的观念是可以存留的。不过，对于那些熟悉梦境的人来说，不用我们告知，他们就自然知道这些观念是多么狂放、松散，多么残缺不全、条理紊乱。我很想知道，灵魂独立思考时是否没有在身体中思考合理。如果独立思考更不合理，这些人会说灵魂只有在身体中思考才能得出完整的、理性的观念。如果独立思考是合理的，为什么我们的梦境大多是破碎的、不合理的呢？为什么我们的灵魂没有存留下那些更合理的独语与冥思呢？

17.如果我只思考，却不知道思考的内容，则他人更不可能知道

我希望那些有把握说“灵魂每时每刻都在思考”的人告诉我们，儿童在没有依赖感官获得任何观念时，在其灵魂与身体结合之前，或正在结合那一刻，他们的观念是什么。我想，梦境均是白天所思，只不过大部分都是胡乱拼凑而来的。奇怪的是，如果灵魂有自己的观念，而非从感官和反思而来（观念必然源于这两个途径，除非此前身体就有一定印记），那么为什么私下思考（私下程度之大，以至于当事人都没有察觉）过后一点都不能记起，之后也没有因新发现而欣喜。如果观念不止源于感觉或反思，那么人在睡眠时，灵魂退出肉体思考长达数小时，而在如此长的时间里，观念却没有一点来自感觉或反思以外的途径，这是不合常理的。奇怪的是，在人的一生当中，灵魂从未记起自身形成的观念，也就是并非来自于人身的观念；而在人们醒着的时候，所有观念也都是由灵魂和肉体结合而生的。如果灵魂每时每刻都在思考，在与肉体结合之前或在从肉体处获得一些观念之前已形成自己的观念，就必须说，只有在睡着时，它才能记起自身的观点，只有当灵魂退出肉体独自思考时，形成的观念才是自然的、同质的，而非源于肉体的。既然人在醒了之后不再记得熟睡时的所思所想，那么从上面的假设中我们只能得出，要么灵魂能记得肉体所不能的，要么记忆只能保留源于肉体的观念，或是有关这些观念的心理活动。

18.人们如何知道灵魂在不停地思考呢？既然这不是一个自明命题，就需要证据来证明

我很想知道，那些自信地宣称“灵魂在不停地思考”的人是怎么知道的。在他们自己都感受不到的情况下，他们怎么知道自己在思考？恐怕他们的言论是在没有证据的情况下发表的，并没有真正去感知。只是用一个混淆的概念去支持这个假设，而真正的真理，不是不言自明，就是可以用常识证明。在这方面，他们顶多可以说“灵魂是在不停地思考的，只是记忆没有保留罢了”。但我认为，更可能的情况是，灵魂并不是每时每刻都在思考的；它思考的时间还没有不思考的时间长，甚至思考后的很长时间都意识不到曾经有所思考。

19.一个人不可能此刻还在思考，下一刻就忘了思考内容

要说灵魂可以思考，而人本身不能，就等于说一个人拥有两个人格，这点我们已经讨论过。如果仔细考究一下这个说法，就会怀疑其正确性。因为，就我所知，这些声称灵魂每时每刻都在思考的人并没有说，人的肉体也一直在思考。灵魂在思考，而人的肉体却没有；抑或是人一直在思考却没有意识，这可能吗？也许这在别人看来简直是在胡说八道。要说人的肉体一直在思考，只是没有意识，就等于说人的肉体在缺少四肢的情况下可以延伸一样。顺着这个逻辑，可以推出一个人一直很饿，却感觉不到饥饿感。饥饿只在饥饿感中有所体现，正如只有在意识到时才能称之为思考。如果他们说，有人能一直意识到自己在思考，那么我要问，他们是怎么知道的呢？意识只有当事人自身才能察觉。如果我觉得自己意识不到某物，那谁又能说我能意识得到呢？任何人的知识都没有经验多。比如叫醒一个熟睡中的人，问问他醒前那刻在想什么，如果他不记得自己刚才在想什么，那么告诉他答案的人一定是先知。那为什么不干脆告诉他，他刚才并没有在睡觉呢？这着实超越了哲学范畴，既然我并未觉察到自己的观念，那么定是神祇将我的观念告诉别人的。如果我本身都觉不到自己在思考，并且断言自己不曾思考，可是他们却能分明得知我的观念，那么他们一定洞见力极强。可是在狗或象表示出一切能思考的象征以后，那些人却仍然说它们是不能思考的。也许有人认为这超越了玫瑰十字会[1]（Rosecrucians），因为将自己的观念隐藏起来不为人所知似乎更为容易，而洞察他人自身尚不可知的观念则更难。但也不能仅仅把灵魂定义为一个能思考的实体。如果这个定义是正确的（虽然我不这么认为），那么很多人都会怀疑自己是不是真的有灵魂，因为他们生命中的大半都是在没有思考中度过的。就我所知，任何定义或假设都不够有力到足以驳倒恒常的经验。也许是因为人们喜欢知道意识不到的事，所以世界上才有了这么多无用的争端和谣传吧。

20.从对儿童的观察得知，所有的观念都源于感官或反思

我不相信，在感官给灵魂提供观念之前，灵魂就能思考。随着这些观念的积累与保留，人们才能在实际运用中提高思考能力，此后才能将观念整合，反思自己的心理活动，进一步积累观念，锻炼记忆、想象、推理与其他思考能力。

21.人如果愿意通过观察和经验得到知识，而不是把自己的假设当作自然规律，会发现新生儿并不曾有多少思考，更别说推理了。但理性的灵魂通常不会思考过多而不去推理。初生的婴儿大部分时间都在睡梦中度过，饿了、疼了或是有其他强烈的感觉时，才会有所知觉，加以关注。如果看到这一层，就会认为母亲腹中的婴儿同植物无异，大部分时间都没有知觉，除了睡觉别无他做，也不需要寻找事物，因为他们周围满是轻柔的恒温的液体。他们可目不见光，耳不听声，其余的感官也不用感知其他纷杂。

22.自儿童诞生那日起，便开始观察记录时间在他身上留下的痕迹。你会发现，由于感官的作用，他脑海中的观念越来越多，他也越来越清醒，思考得也越多。一段时间以后，他开始熟悉周围的事物，会对那些最熟悉的留下深刻的印象。这样，他逐渐认识同他交流的人，把这些人同陌生人区别开来。这也证明了他慢慢将通过感官得来的观念加以保留和区别。头脑就这样通过推理与反思，逐渐扩展、组合这些观念并将这些观念抽象化，从而增加自身的观点。我稍后还会提到这一点。

23.如果有人问，人是从什么时候开始有观念的呢？我想，答案是，当他最初有感觉时，他就有了观念。既然在感官传输观念之前，头脑中都是没有观念的，那么当人有了感觉时，也就有了观念。因为感觉就是身体的某个部分有一定的印象或动作，从而产生一定的知觉。当我们的感官对外部事物有印象时，头脑才开始感知、记忆、考虑及推理。

24.一切知识的来源

有时我们会反思自己的心理活动，反思那些由感官得来的观念，并对之加以保存，形成新的观念，我们将这称为“反思”。这些观念并不是我们的感官对外部事物的印象，并不是头脑所固有的。这些心理活动，由人自身产生，当人们开始反思的时候，它们也就成了反思的对象，也就是所有知识的起源。对于人类来说，最大的能力就是头脑可以接收观念，包括感官对外部事物产生的观念以及自身在反思这些观念时形成的新观念。这是人类探索世界的第一步，他后来自然而然所形成的一切观念，也是建立在这个基础上的。那些高入云霄，直达天际的深奥的思想也是基于此的。人的思考虽然玄妙，但头脑所想莫不是源于基本的观念，源于感官和反思。

25.在接受简单观念时，理解大部分是被动的

在简单观念阶段，理解都是被动的，是否需要这些简单观念作为知识的原料不是我们能决定的。因为，不管我们愿不愿意，我们感官感受的对象中大部分都会将与之有关的观念印在我们的脑海中。而我们的心理活动也一定会让我们多少留下一丝关于它们的概念。当一个人在思考时，不可能完全没有意识。当头脑在接受这些简单观念时，理解是不能拒绝的，也不能改变或重造，就像镜子不能拒绝、改变或抹去它所成的像。因为我们周围的物体以各种方式刺激着我们的感官，所以头脑就要被迫接受一些印象，与之相关的观念也就不能避免了。

简单观念

1.单纯的现象

要了解我们知识的本质、方式和限度，必须仔细研究我们的观念，既包括简单观念也包括复杂观念。

刺激我们感官的各种性质本身是混合的，没有分割、没有距离。但我们分明看到，这些通过感官得来的性质在脑海中形成的观念确实是简单而单纯的。尽管视觉和触觉同时来自同一个物体，但是却可以产生不同的观念。比如一根蜡烛，视觉上可以看到它在跳动，能看到它的颜色，而触觉上能感到它的柔软和温暖。这些简单观念都系于同一物体，却又彼此不同，就如不同感官产生的观念般分明。冰块给人又凉又硬的感觉，正如百合纯白带香，如糖之甘甜、玫瑰之芬芳。人对这些简单观念的认知是最清晰的。因为每一个观念本身都单纯而不复杂，现象和脑海中形成的概念始终如一，不会同其他观念混淆。

2.头脑不能制造或销毁简单观念

这些简单观念是我们知识的原料，通过我们之前提到的感官和反思传输到我们的大脑中。一旦大脑对这些简单观念有了理解，就可以近乎无限地重复、对比和组合，也会产生很多复杂的观念。就连智慧非凡或理解力极强的人，就算思维敏捷多样，也不可能避开上面两种方式创造或形成新的简单观念。此外，理解力也不能销毁已有的简单观念。人类的统治，不管是在自己的小世界里摆弄自己的思想，还是在大千世界里处理有形的事物，都大同小异。不论他有什么奇招妙法，力之所及亦只是对手中那些现成材料加加减减，不能创造一丝一毫，也无法销毁一点一滴。同样，每个人也不能从感官（源于外物）和反思（源于心理活动）以外的来源获取任何简单观念。我想没有人能品尝到味觉不能分辨的味道，也没有人能闻到鼻子不能嗅出的气味。如果有人能做到，我想这无异于证明了盲人可以识别颜色，聋子可以分辨声响。

3.因此，尽管我们都觉得除了上帝赋予我们的五种感官（人们常认为五种），不可能造出其他的感官了。我也认为，除了声音、味道、气味和其他可见可触的性质外，无论构成如何，物体中也不会再有其他性质了。如果人生而只有四种感官，那么我们应该不会想象或注意到第五种，就像我们现在有五种感官，就注意不到第六种，甚至第七种、第八种。在这无垠的宇宙当中，或许其他地方的生物有着其他的感官，这点猜测是我们不能否认的。人类不能妄自尊大，应该考虑世界的无限，并发现在自己所在之处也有无限精彩，这样也许就会认为，在宇宙的他处，也许会有未知的他类智能。我们无从了解，正如抽屉或者柜子里的小虫不能像人一样去感觉和理解。这正凸显了造物者的智慧。这里我遵从惯例，认为人有五种感官，也许不止五种，但这两种说法都能证明我的观点。

复杂观念

1.复杂观念是头脑对简单观念的加工

上面我们也谈到了，头脑在接收由感官和反思得来的简单观念时是被动的，头脑也不能创造这些观念，它所形成的所有观念全部由这些简单观念构成。然而，虽然头脑在接收简单观念时是被动的，但也会发挥自己的能动性，将简单观念作为基础和原料，形成其他观念。能动性主要分为三类：（1）将几个简单观念合并为一个复杂观念；（2）将两个观念（简单或复杂）并列起来，同时观察，而不把它们合并为一；（3）将某些观念同其他关联观念分别开来，也叫作“抽象”。这样就得到了概括性的观念。这些过程都显示了人的能力及作用，在物质世界与思想世界都并无二致。因为在这两个世界当中，人只能将原料合并、并列或完全分开，不能进行创造或将其摧毁。在我们讲复杂观念时，我们先来看第一种作用，在适当的时机再引入后两种。观察发现，简单观念是会组合的，所以头脑也可以将几个简单观念合并起来作为一个观念去思考。简单观念的合并不仅是因为外部物体将他们连在一起，还有头脑的作用。由简单观念组成的观念称为复杂观念，比如“美丽、感激、人、军队和宇宙”。这些观念都是由简单观念结合而成的，或是说由简单观念构成的复杂观念。而头脑更倾向于把这些组合起来的简单观念作为整体，赋予它们一个名称，再进行思考。

2.复杂观念自动形成

头脑可以通过重复和联合的能力，变更或增加观念，远比感官和反思得来的观念多得多。但说到底，这些观念还都是源于两种途径的简单观念。因为简单观念都由事物本身而来，头脑所获得的简单观念也仅限于此，不过也无异。同感觉性质有关的观念都源于感官，思考的对象也都源于本身。但是，在获得这些简单观念之后，不会仅仅去观察，而会将这些观念整合起来，形成新的复杂观念。这些联合而成的复杂观念，比头脑之前直接获得的任何观念都更紧密统一。

3.复杂观念不外乎情状、实体及关系

不管怎样组合或拆分，复杂观念的数量和种类总是无穷无尽的，充斥着人们的思想。但是我认为，它们总不外乎三大类：情状、实体及关系。

4.情状

首先，情状这种复杂观念不管再怎样组合都不可能自我生成，都依赖于一定的物体，比如“三角形、感激和谋杀”就是这样的例子。如果我这里用的“情状”一词同他处之意不同，请原谅。因为这个问题不可避免，这种情况下只能选用新词，或运用旧词的其他含义。我更倾向于选择第二种。

5.简单及复杂情状

情状有两种，应该区别对待。一类是单纯的变量，只是同样简单观念的叠加，没有混入其他简单观念，比如“十二、二十”。因为只涉及一种简单观念，我把这一类称为简单情状。另一类由不同种类的简单观念组合起来，形成一个复杂观念，比如“美丽”，涉及颜色、形态及是否能给观看者带来愉悦；“盗窃”，是否隐瞒了对某物的占有，是否征得了所有者的同意。这一类涉及很多种观念，我称之为复杂情状。

6.单一或集合实体

其次，一些实体观念是简单观念的组合，仅代表一些独立存在的特定事物。在这些事物中，那个假设的、含混的实体观念总是占据首要位置。就一个实体而言，我们有“灰白色的”这样一个简单观念，如果再附上几个条件，包括重量、硬度、延展性和熔性，就得到了“铅”。可以动的，有思想、会推理的形象就是“人”。另一些实体需要两类观念来定义，就单独存在的个体来说，我们有人和羊；就组合来看，便有了一群人和一群羊这样的集体概念。

7.关系

最后一种复杂观念是关系，由观念的对比得来。关系包括几种，这里不做展开。

8.最深奥的观念也源于这两种途径

如果我们追寻头脑思考的轨迹，仔细观察它是如何重复、增加及组合由感官和反思得来的简单观念的，我们将能获得更深层的结论。我相信，如果我们仔细留心观念的起源，就会发现就连那些最深奥的观念，不管它们看起来多么遥不可及，都是对源于感官和反思的观念的重复和组合。就连那些大而抽象的观念，如“空间、时间和无限”等都是如此。虽然看起来不好理解，但其起源都是感官或反思，都是我们的头脑运用最基本的功能，对简单观念的加工而来的。

关乎快乐和痛苦的情状

1.快乐与痛苦都是简单观念

在我们通过感官和反思得来的简单观念中，痛苦和快乐是十分重要的两个。因为，就我们自身来说，感觉有时单纯，有时伴随着苦乐。所以思想或头脑的知觉也是或单纯，或伴有苦乐喜忧。这些观念同其他简单观念一样，是不可名状、不可定义的。与通过感官获得简单观念一样，要获知这些观念，只能通过经验。因为，用善恶来定义它们，只是让我们了解它们，让我们反思自身的观念，反思善恶的多样给我们带来的影响，而我们对它们的应用和理解也是千差万别的。

2.善恶为何

要判断事物的善恶，只消看它给我们带来的是快乐还是痛苦。善，能给我们带来快乐或增加我们的快乐，消减我们的痛苦，也使我们获得善，保留善，去除恶。相反，恶，会产生痛苦，增加痛苦，消减我们的快乐，催生更多的恶，剥夺我们的善。要说苦乐，先要区分身体与心灵。但实际上，它们都是心灵的感触，或由身体的不适引起，或源于心中的想法。

3.善恶影响我们的情感

善恶，同它引起的苦乐，都是带动我们情感的铰链。如果我们对自身加以反思，观察苦乐善恶在我们心中的活动，看它们带来了什么心理变化和内在感觉，就能形成我们的情感。

4.喜爱

存在或不存在的事物给人带来的想法，使他在想起后感到愉悦，这种观念就是喜爱。一个人在秋天吃到葡萄，或春天吃不到葡萄时都称自己喜爱葡萄，是因为葡萄的味道使他愉悦。如果因为健康或身体的改变使他品尝不到葡萄的味道，他便不会再喜爱葡萄了。

5.憎恶

相反，存在或不存在的事物给人带来的想法，使他在想起后感到苦痛，这种观念就是憎恶。在这里我们不妨来思考一下各种情感观念是如何由苦乐的各种变化生成的。可以说，我们之所以对无生命无感知的个体产生爱和恨，是因为我们在使用它们时产生了愉悦和痛苦。而我们之所以对能够感知到幸福与不幸的个体产生爱和恨，通常是因为我们在考虑它们的状态或幸福时会感到不安或愉悦。因此，如果一个人的孩子或朋友的状态和幸福能让他感到愉悦，那么他就是爱他们的。这足以证明，我们的爱恨只是普通的快乐和苦痛（无论如何产生）引起的心中之感。

6.欲望

如果一个人在享受一件东西时感到喜悦，在它不见时感到不安，那么这种不安感就是欲望。欲望的大小要看这种不安感的强弱。这里，我们可以说，就算这种不安感不是人们勤奋与行动的唯一刺激，也称得上主要刺激。因为，不管一件东西有多么好，若人们没有在它不见时感到不悦或痛苦，就算没有它也很自得，就不会对它有欲望，不会想要得到它。如果只是单纯地想想，得不到也不会觉得不安，那么人们就不会采取有效大胆的行动去获得它，而只会想一想。如果获得的可能性不大，我们的不安感也会降低，那么欲望也会消失或减少。限于篇幅，这一点我们就讲这么多。

7.欢乐

拥有或即将拥有一件东西给我们带来的喜悦，因为我们可以掌控它，随心所欲地使用它，这种喜悦之感就是欢乐。一个快饿死的人，在快领到救济金时，就算还没用上，已经很欢乐了。一位父亲在儿女幸福时会感到高兴，只要儿女幸福，他就拥有可以使他高兴的事，所以只要想一想，他就会感到愉悦。

8.忧伤

如果一件东西丢了，使我们不能多拥有它一刻，那么在想到它时，便会感到一种不安，这就是忧伤。除此以外，当我们感到一种不幸，也会忧伤。

9.希望

一个人在想到未来可能会拥有某件东西时产生的愉悦之感就是希望。

10.恐惧

一个人在想到未来可能会降临在自己头上的厄运时产生的不安之感就是恐惧。

11.失望

一个人在想得到而不能时，可能会觉得不安或痛苦，有时又感到平静或懒散，这种感觉就是失望。

12.愤怒

一个人在被伤害想报复时产生的不安情绪就是愤怒。

13.嫉妒

一个人在想到别人先于自己获得了一件自己想要的东西时产生的不安之感就是嫉妒。

14.什么情感是所有人都拥有的

最后两种情感——嫉妒和愤怒，并不是所有人都拥有的，因为这两种情感并不是由我们自身的痛苦和愉悦产生的，而是涉及我们本身和他人，有些人并不会鉴赏自己的价值，也不会报复，因此也不会嫉妒和愤怒。但我认为，其他那些由痛苦和愉悦产生的情绪是所有人都拥有的。比如在“喜爱、欲望、欢乐和希望”中我们可以品味愉悦；在“憎恶、恐惧和悲伤”中会体验痛苦。虽然看起来情感总是源于苦乐，或者说苦乐总是同这些情感如影随形，但归根结底所有的情感都由事物引起。因此，我们会恨那些给我们造成痛苦的东西（至少是有感觉、有意志的主体），因为它给我们造成的恐惧是持久的痛苦。但是我们不会喜爱每一件带给我们愉悦之感的东西，因为愉悦并没有痛苦那么刻骨铭心，而且这种愉悦之感，将来也不一定会再有。不过这一点我们以后再讨论。

15.苦乐为何

我所谈到的苦与乐、愉悦与不安，不仅仅是身体上的，还有精神上的，不管它们源于称心的还是不称心的感觉或反思。

16.此外，在情感方面，痛苦的减少就等于愉悦的增多，同样，愉悦的消失或减少也是种痛苦。

17.羞耻

人们的情感也表现在身体上，并引起身体的变化。但是这些变化并不明显，所以也不是各类情感必需的部分。如果做了不体面的事，或降低别人对我们敬仰的事，我们就会产生一种不安感，这就是所谓的羞耻。人在羞耻时，通常会脸红。

18.举例说明情感源于感官和反思

不要误以为我在这章里描述了所有情感。情感的种类比我这里列出的多许多。而我上面列出的几类情感也应该进行更广泛、更准确的描述。我这里举的例子只是为了证明善恶会带来苦乐。或许我应该列举一些简单的例子来说明苦乐，比如饥渴引起的痛苦，以及吃喝可以去除痛苦，带来快乐；眼睛的干涩，悦耳的音乐；挑剔无理的强辩之苦，通情达理的交谈之乐以及有条不紊地研究发现真理之乐。但是上述的情感对我们来说更为重要，所以我列举它们，证明我们对于它们的观念由感官和反思而来。

充分观念和不充分观念

1.充分观念指能完全表现其原型的观念

我们的观念有些是充分的，有些是不充分的。充分观念完全表现了它所代表的原型；不充分观念仅表现了它所代表的原型的一部分。在这方面，我们看到：

2.简单观念全部为充分观念

首先，简单观念全部为充分观念。因为简单观念是物体的某些能力给我们造成的影响，是外力让它们给我们造成这样的感觉，所以这些观念必然和这些能力相对应、相契合，而且也符合外物的现实。比如，糖让我们觉得又白又甜，那么我们就相信糖有能力给我们带来这些观念，否则我们就体会不到这些观念。每一种感觉都对应我们的感官，这样产生的观念是真实的（不是头脑臆想的，因为头脑本身没有产生简单观念的能力），只能是充分的，因为观念和产生它们的能力相对应。因此，所有简单观念都是充分的。其实，事物的名称通常并不源于它们使我们产生的观念，而是源于它们本身带有的观念。比如，我们在触碰到火时会感到疼痛，因此火就有这种能力让我们产生疼痛的观念。可是我们却常说火光、火热，因为我们认为光和热真是在火中存在的，并不以为它们是火的能力，我们把这种观念称为火的“性质”。但事实上，这些性质也是一些能力，能使我们产生观念，因此，当我说外物中的次等性质，或是说外物使我们产生的观念时，你们应该知道我所说的只是一种能力。我这么说完全是为顺应通俗概念，方便他人理解。不过这些说法所指的都只是外物使我们产生某种感觉或观念的一些能力。如果我们没有合适的器官来接收火在视觉和触觉上给我们带来的印象，头脑不能产生火和太阳带来的光和热的观念，就算太阳持续照耀，埃特纳火山（Mount Aetna）一直高喷，世界上也不会有光和热的概念，就像如果人没有触觉就不会有疼痛的概念一样。我们对凝固、延伸和其终止以及形体的动与静都有观念，不论世上有无物体来感觉它们，它们都是实实在在存在的。因此，我们应当研究的是物质真正的变体，正是这些变体产生了我们身体的各种感觉。不过这种研究不属于我们讨论的范围，因此，我就不详细展开了。下面我讲一讲，哪些复杂的观念是充分的，哪些是不充分的。

3.所有情状都是充分的

其次，我们关于情状的复杂观念，是我们头脑对简单观念的自觉组合，并未参照原型或现有样本，它们也都是充分的。因为它们不是实际存在的事物的样本，而是头脑形成的模型，使人们可以根据这些模型去将事物分类并命名，因此，它们不缺乏任何东西。每一个模型都有自身的观念集合，头脑将它们规划整理，并不会感到任何缺陷。如果我有一个观念，是一个图形，有三条边，相交于三个点，这两个条件就能让我有一个完整的观念，不再需要其他条件。头脑会认为这个观念是完整的，可以用“三角形”来表示。但是，我们对实体的观念却并非如此。因为，在模拟事物的真实情形，并且表示出它们的特性构成的结构时，并不能让自己形成的观念达到心理预期的那种完美程度，总觉得它们缺少一些应该具有的东西。所以，实体观念都是不充分的。不过，混杂的情状和关系是无迹可寻的模型，它们所代表的只是本身，因此也是充分的。比如，你预见到自己面临危险，毫无恐惧，泰然自若，而且能沉着地考虑应付的步骤，镇定地采取行动，不为危险所慑。如果你能想到这些情形，并且把这些观念合拢起来，你的心中一定会由此产生一个复杂观念。你设想的一系列步骤就是这个复杂观念本身，而且这个复杂观念包含的一切简单观念，也都是你心中所想，再无其他，因此这个复杂观念也是充分的。随后，你把这个观念藏在记忆中，命名“勇敢”，并向人表示这个观念。如果某种行动与这个观念相符，就称它是勇敢的。这样就有了一种标准，来衡量各种行动，并且冠以这种名称。这个观念既然本身就是模型，就必然是充分的，因为它并不与别的东西相参照，也不是由别的元素所形成的，只是依原创者的喜好和愿望而定的。

4.若参照固定名称，情状就可能变得不充分

他人同你谈话之后学到“勇敢”一词，可能他对“勇敢”的定义与你不同，在使用这个词的时候，你们头脑里的观念也不同。此时，如果他自认为与你的观念相符，发音也一致，那么他的观念就很可能是错误的、不充分的。因为，在这种情况下，将别人的思考方式作为自己的思考方式，就如同将别人的说话方式作为自己文字和声音的模型一样，有所参照就会有所偏离，会导致观念的欠缺与不充分。在以某名称标记原观念（该名称原本代表的观念）及自己的观念（自以为与原观念相吻合）时，若自己的观念与原观念不完全一致，那么自己的观念就是错误的、不充分的。

5.因此，复杂情状观念在与他人的同名观念作比对时，可能出现偏差、错误、不充分。因为此时，它们的参照对象并非头脑设定的原型或模型。也只有此时，情状观念会出现错误、残缺或不充分。因此，在一切情状观念中，混杂情状观念最容易出现错误。不过这主要关乎表达得当与否，而非知识的正误。

6.若参照实质，则实体观念也是不充分的

最后，要谈一谈实体观念，我在上面也提到过，实体观念有两个参照对象：（1）一类事物的实质；（2）头脑对实际存在的外物的再现。这种再现要借助于外物的性质在人们心中所形成的观念来实现。不管是哪种，这些对原型的复制都是残缺的、不充分的。

第一，人们通常会给实体命名，让这些名称代表一类实质相同的事物。这些名称只代表人们脑中的观念，而观念往往参照事物的本质与原型。人们通常认为各种实体都有其本质，每种实体的个体本质都相同（如果接受了欧洲的教育，更容易这样认为）。这是无须证实的，如果有人不这样认为，反而会被认为是异类。这样，人们通常根据不同的本质，给不同的类别安上不同的名字。如果一个人自称为“人”，就是说自己有“人”的本质，如果你怀疑这一点，人们往往会见怪于你。但是如果你问起这本质究竟是什么，人们却又不知道。由此我们得出结论，他们脑中的观念，虽然参照本质，可是那些原型却不为人知，因此，那些观念必然不是充分的，毕竟观念并未反映原型。我上面也谈到了，复杂观念就是时常共存的简单观念的集合。但是这种复杂观念并不是任何实体的实质，否则物体的各种性质都会依靠于这个复杂观念，都可以由这个观念推出，我们也会知道观念与本质的联系。比如，从三条边围成的面积推出三角形的其他性质。但事实上，在我们的复杂实体观念中，并没有任何观念，可以为它们体现出的其他性质提供依托。人们认为“铁”有一定的颜色、重量和硬度，此外，“铁”还有一个性质，就是延展性。但是，这个性质同“铁”这个复杂观念并无必然联系。我们不能说“铁”的延展性依赖于它的颜色、重量与硬度，也不能说它的颜色、重量与硬度取决于它的延展性。但是，虽然我们不知道事物的本质是什么，却总把某些性质划为本质。比如，许多人断定，我手上戒指的原材料必须具备特定本质才是“黄金”。这一本质包括特定的颜色、重量、硬度、易熔性、形定性、接触水银后颜色变化等性质。我试着去探寻这一本质，却发现根本找不到。我力所能及的顶多是假设它仅是一种物体，而该物体的各种性质取决于它的本质或内部构成，这些性质包括形状、大小和组成。而我对于这些性质并没有清晰的认识，因此，我对本质也没有任何概念，而正是这本质决定了黄灿灿的、比同体积的物体重的、遇水银变色的物体为“黄金”。如果有人要说，决定事物性质的本质及内部构成并不是上面提到的形状、大小和组成，而是别的“特殊形式”，那我就更不能理解了。因为，对于前一种说法，就算我不知道事物的形状、大小和组成，不理解为什么上面描述的事物不是我用来削铅笔的东西，而非得是我手指上戴的东西，但至少我还能有所参照。但是，如果有人告诉我本质并非形状、大小和组成，而是所谓的“实体的形式”（我必须声明，对于“形式”这个词，除了它的读音，我一点概念都没有），那么这将对我了解事物的实质或构成毫无帮助。我不仅对这种特殊物质的实质一无所知，对其他自然物质的实质也一无所知。不仅我是如此，我相信，其他人也是如此，只要仔细审视一下他们的知识就能发现这点。

7.既然如此，当人们给我手指上的这块东西命名“黄金”时，他们难道不知道这是对拥有同样实质的一类东西进行命名吗？如果知道（看起来也确实如此），那么这一名称所指的必然是这类事物共有的实质，因此，人们所形成的观念也应该关于名称所代表的实质。不过，既然使用这个名称的人本身都不知道实质究竟是什么，那么他们的实体观念肯定是不充分的，因为我们原以为观念中包含事物的本质，实则不然。

8.如果把实体观念看作性质的集合，那么它们也是不充分的

第二，有的人认为，设定一些不可知的本质来区别各种实体是没用的，因此便忽略了这点，而试图把各种实体中共存的可感性质观念组合起来，以模拟各种实体。尽管这些人比上述那些人（他们认为实质是存在的，只是他们不知道）更接近于实体的真相，但就算他们想把实体的观念复制在心中，他们的观念也不是完全充分的；而且那些副本也不能精确地、充分地把它们原型中所有的观念都包括进去。因为我们复杂观念的来源（即这些物体的性质和能力）是复杂多样的，而我们的复杂观念却不能如此包罗万象。显然，我们抽象的实体观念并不能包括事物本身共存的一切简单观念，因为人们很少把他们所知道的一切简单观念都放入复杂的实体观念中。他们想让事物名称意义尽量简明，所以在形成实体观念时，常常只采用其中的少数简单观念。然而，所采用的简单观念和那些未被采用的简单观念相比并无优越性，两种情况之下，我们的实体观念都是不足的、不充分的。形成复杂实体观念的那些简单观念，除了某些物体的形状和体积之外，通通都只是一些能力。这些能力是与其他实体相关联的，因此，我们永远不能保证自己知道某物体的所有能力。因为要想知道它的所有能力，必须以各种方式，让它和别的实体接触，看能发生什么变化。就某一实体而言，这都不能实现，更别说所有实体了。因此，我们不可能通过探究一个实体的所有性质来获得充分的观念。

9.任何人初次见到“黄金”时，都不能合理地从这块东西的体积和形状推断出它的本质和内部构成。因此，他对“黄金”观念的理解中，也不包括这些性质。他会率先把这种物体的特殊颜色和重量抽象出来，形成关于这种物体的复杂观念。不过这两种性质只是两种能力，一种能力以某种形式刺激我们的视觉，让我们产生黄色这一观念；另一种能力即可以抬高天平另一端的同体积物体。此外，还有易熔性及形定性，这是被动的能力，当火在黄金上施动时，黄金就会展现这两种特性。黄金在王水中还具有延展性和可溶性。这两种能力也是同其他实体的作用相关的，它改变了外形并且分解成不易察觉的部分。这些性质加起来通常使人们形成一个复杂观念，让我们推断出这种物质就是“黄金”。

10.只要你大致或具体思考过这个物体的性质，就不会怀疑，我们所谓的“黄金”，有无限种性质尚未包含在上述复杂观念之内。我想，更精准地研究过黄金的人所提出的性质能达到上述的十倍之多，而且这些性质都和黄金的颜色和重量一样，与内部构成密不可分。如果有人对于金属的知识更加丰富，也许能提出百倍之多的性质。但是，这些性质也许仅仅是黄金所有性质的千分之一。因为，实验过就知道，金属与不同物体发生反应产生的变化超乎我们的认知，甚至超乎我们的想象。只要想一下，就会发现我所说的是正确的。不说复杂的，只要看一下再简单不过的三角形，就能发现虽然数学家已经探索出了它的很多性质，但是还有更多有待发现。

11.综上所述，我们的复杂实体观念都是不完整、不充分的。对于不同的数学图形来说，我们可以把它们同其他图形对照，得出具体性质，但结论同样如此。比如，如果我们只了解椭圆形的几个性质，那么我们对椭圆形的观念将是十分不确定、不完整的。但反过来说，我们如果了解这个图形的本质，就会发现它的各种性质，并见证它是如何体现这些性质，如何与这些性质密不可分的。

12.简单观念是模本，而且是充分的

因此，头脑中有三种抽象观念，或者说名义上的本质。

第一，简单观念，即模本，是完全充分的。简单观念意在表达一种能力，即某种事物给我们带来某种感觉的能力，因此，某种感觉的出现，一定是某种能力的结果。我写字用的纸张，在日光下（普通意义上的日光）给我带来的感觉就是“白色的”，这就是头脑以外事物能力的结果，因为头脑本身并没有形成观念的能力，所以这一感觉仅仅是上述能力的结果。因此，简单观念都是真实的、充分的。我脑中形成的“白色的”感觉，是纸张能力的结果，这种感觉同纸张的能力相符，不然纸张的能力会让我形成其他观念。

13.实体观念虽然也是模本，却是不充分的

第二，复杂实体观念，虽然也是模本，却是不完全、不充分的。显然，即使头脑把任意物体中的简单观念都集合起来，也不能确保这些观念就是这一物体的全部。因为这些观念不涉及与其他物体的作用，不涉及其他物体给该物体带来的改变，或该物体给其他物体造成的改变，所以我们不能获取与该物完全相符的主动及被动的性质。因此，对于任何物体，我们都没有充分的复杂观念。退一步说，即便我们能在复杂观念中精确地把任何实体的所有第二性质（或能力）集合起来（或者已经精确地集合起来），也不能获知该物的本质。因为，我们所观察到的能力或性质并不是该物的本质，而是本质的体现，所以不管这些性质是什么，它们的集合都不是事物的本质。由此可见，我们的实体观念是不充分的。此外，人们既没有全面的实体观念，也不知道实体的本质究竟是什么。

14.情状观念和关系观念都是原型，都是充分的

第三，关于情状和关系的复杂观念都是原型，并不是副本，也不是追寻实体之迹而来，人们并没有期望它们和一个模型相吻合或精确地对应。它们是简单观念的集合，头脑将它们组合在一起，各集合中的内容正是头脑所想，因此，它们本身就是原型和本质。它们为这些情状而设，又存于这些情状，因此，只要这些情状存在，就会和这些复杂观念精准相合。因此，情状观念或关系观念都是充分的。

观念的正误

1.只有命题才分真假

按照用语搭配，真假只能形容命题，但是有时也用来定义观念。因为我们看到，人们在用字时，都很随便，都容易偏离它们严谨的、原本的意义。不过我仍觉得，我们在定义各种观念的正误时，常以不言而喻的命题为基础。只要我们考察一下它们被定义为正误的具体场合，就能发现这点。在这些场合中，我们都能发现一些支持或否决它们的理由。因为我们的观念只是我们头脑中的现象或知觉，所以我们不能说它们本身是正是误，就像我们也不能就一件东西的名字判断正误一样。

2.哲学中的“正”通常内含默认命题

如果“正”是哲学范畴上的，那么观念和文字都可以为正，正如其他事物，存在即为正。不过即使在哲学意义下，也许我们谓之“正”的事物也不自觉地参照了我们的观念，并且以观念为“正”的标准。这种参照正是一个心理命题，只是我们不常注意它罢了。

3.如果我们只把观念当作头脑中的一种现象，则观念没有正误之分

但是我们这里探讨的“正”，并不是哲学意义上的，而是普通意义上的。那么，我们头脑中的观念，都是一些知觉或现象，都不是错误的。我们头脑中关于人马兽的观念并没错，正如我们口里说的、纸上写的人马兽都没错一样。因为，正误源于心里或口头上的证实或证伪，所以除非我们的头脑证明或否定我们的观念，否则它们是不能被定义为“误”的。

4.观念若比对别物，则可分正误

当头脑中的观念同外物作对比后，便可判断正误。因为对比过后，头脑会默默判断观念同外物是否一致。判断得出的一致与否也决定了观念的正误。判断通常有如下几种：

5.人们通常会参照别人的观念、实体或判断的本质

第一，当头脑判断观念是否与他人的观念一致，有相同的命名时，观念就有了正误。比如，当头脑中关于正义、节制、宗教的观念，与他人关于这些词的观念相同，便会认为他们的观念是正确的。

第二，当头脑判断观念是否与实体一致时，观念就有了正误。因此，人和人马兽这两个观念是关于实体的，前者同实体相一致，后者不一致，则前者是真实存在的，后者是虚构的。

第三，当头脑将观念同物体的实质相对比时，因为物体的大部分性质都存于本质，如果观念和本质不一致，就是错误的。

6.人们为何要进行参照

头脑经常会不自觉地对观念作出判断。但是，如果我们仔细观察便会发现，这些判断多涉及抽象的复杂观念。因为，头脑的自然趋势是获取知识，如果只关注具体事物，则进程过慢，工作过多。所以，为了走捷径并且使各种观念更加全面，就要扩充知识的基础，第一步就是通过自己思考或同别人交谈，把知识打包分类，并合理地把从某一事物上获取的知识推广至同类事物，这样就在重要任务（获取知识）上有了长足的进步。这也就是我们总是把具体事项归在概括性的观念之下分门别类的原因。

7.如果我们仔细考察一下头脑的思考方式，再看一下它获取知识的方式，就能发现头脑获得观念后，不管是用于思考或是交谈，首先会把观念抽象化，给它命名，然后储存在记忆中，并认为观念包含着这类事物的本质，并且永远用这一名称标记它。因此，我们就会发现，当人们看到一个不认识的事物时，首先会问那是什么，问的也只是事物的名称，似乎知道了名称就认识了这类事物或了解了它们的本质。这是因为，人们在命名时就是依据本质来命名的，并且常假设这名称同本质相关。

8.头脑中的抽象观念介乎实体与其名称之间。我们的观念既包含了正确的知识又包含了妥善明了的表达。因此人们便想当然地认为，这些抽象的观念同它们所指称的实体是一致的，同它们常规语言命名也是一致的。因为，如果没有这两个一致，人们在自行思考时就会出现错误，在同别人交谈时也会毫无意义。

9.虽然简单观念与其他同名观念相对照可能为误，但它们为误的可能性最小

第一，如果用别人的同名观念来衡量我们自己观念的正误，那么两者均可为误。但是简单观念为误的可能性最小。因为，一个人通过自己的感官和每天的观察，很容易便可了解通用的各种名称所代表的那些简单观念。而且因为简单观念数量少，所以即使遇到疑问和错误，也能借助观念所寓托的事物进行更正。因此很少人把简单观念的名称弄错，把绿色说成红色，把苦说成甜。更少有人混淆不同的感官名词，把颜色说成味道。因此人们对于简单观念的命名往往相同。

10.由此来看，复杂情状观念最易出错

复杂情状观念最易出错，比复杂实体观念出错的可能性更大。因为实体（尤其是语言中的自成词而非外来词所指的实体）中有一些可感性质，把它们和其他实体区分开来，而且只要人们在说话时稍加留意，就不至于把相应的名称应用在不相干的实体上。但是复杂情状却不好界定，比如正义或残忍、自由或挥霍。所以，当我们把自己的观念同他人的同名观念作对比时，可能会发现自己的观念是错误的，而被我们命名为“正义”的观念，可能应该有其他的名称。

11.就算不是最易出错的，至少也更容易出错

与其他观念相比，不管我们的复杂情状观念是不是更容易与别人心中的同名观念不一致，至少可以确定，相较于其他观念，复杂情状观念更容易出错。比如，如果一个人对正义、感激或光荣的理解是错误的，只能因为他对这几个词的理解与别人不同，而别无他因。

12.复杂情状观念容易出错的原因

因为复杂情状的抽象观念是人们对简单观念的整合，所以每种物质的本质也是由人定下的，除了人们对它们的命名外没有其他标准。因此我们没有其他方式来界定和比照复杂情状观念，那些能正确应用这些名称的人心中的观念就是我们仅有的标准。所以我们观念的正误就要看能否同他们的观念相一致。观念名称的正误问题，我们就讨论到这里。

13.如果把实体作为参照，那么除了实体观念以外，我们的观念都是正确的

第二，如果参照实体，把实体作为观念正误的标准，那么除了复杂实体观念，其他观念都是正确的。

14.首先，在以下情况中，简单观念是正确的及其原因

第一，简单观念是我们凭借着与生俱来的能力所接受的一些知觉，而且这些知觉也是外界事物依照自身的能力，依“道”而生的（虽然我们不谙此道，但这道却合乎上帝的仁慈和智慧）。因此，这些观念的正确度就源于它们给我们带来的印象，又因这些印象必然符合外物的能力（否则我们也不会有相应的印象），所以这些简单观念即由这些能力产生，因此是正确的。此外，很多人认为简单观念就是事物本身，所以也不太可能出错。因为造物者凭借智慧，已经给它们做上标记加以区分，好让我们能把它们区分开来，选取自己需要的。所以，不论我们认为蓝色存在于紫罗兰中，还是我们心中虚构的，都不能变更这一简单观念的本质，即蓝色的产生是由于紫罗兰本身的组织质地对阳光的反射。正是由于这种不变的本质，使我们能够凭视觉把这种事物同其他事物区分开来，不论帮助我们区分的标记是紫罗兰中各部分的特殊组织，还是颜色本身。因此，不论是这种颜色，还是能让我们产生这一观念的特殊组织，我们都称为“蓝”。因为“蓝”只是一种区分标记，表示我们的双眼在紫罗兰中所见的颜色，至于“蓝”由何组成，我们就不得而知了。就算知道，对我们也没有用处。

15.每个人对蓝色的观念不尽相同也无妨

即使我们器官结构不同，导致不同人对同一事物的观念不同，比如一个人看紫罗兰得出的观念与另一人看金盏花得出的观念相同，我们的简单观念也不太容易出错。因为一个人不能透过另一个人的身体去看这些器官产生的印象是什么，所以也就不能将两者产生的观念进行比较，得出对错。只要含有紫罗兰的特质，就能使人产生“蓝色”的观念，只要含有金盏花的特质，就能使人产生“黄色”的观念。不管这两种表象究竟给他们带来什么印象，他们都结合现象，加以区别，取己所用。他们总可以同别人一样区别两种花产生的“蓝”“黄”的表象和这两种颜色在脑中形成的观念。我猜想，任何事物给不同人带来的观念总是相近的。我有很多理由支持这一想法，但这不是我们现在谈论的问题，我就不赘述了。就算反对观点得以证实，也无益于我们知识的增加或生活的便捷，所以也就不用费力考察了。

16.首先，在以下情况中，简单观念是正确的及其原因

据前所述，若参照我们身边的外物，则简单观念均为正确的。因为我们所见的现象和脑中的知觉都由外物而来，通过我们的感官，让我们形成一定的印象。因此，我们对它们的印象同它们产生这些现象的能力是一一对应的。所以，这些观念不可能出错。“蓝”或“黄”，“甜”或“苦”，这些观念永远不会出错，因为这些观念都是对事物最真实的反映。也许名称的应用会出错，但是观念本身是不会出错的，比如一个不懂英文的人，把“紫”这个单词误说成“红”。

17.其次，情状也是正确的

第二，若复杂情状观念参照实体本质而形成，则不会出错。关于情状的复杂观念，并未参照自然之物，所以复杂观念所包括的，仅仅是关于这一情状的观念，别无其他。比如，某人有财产有权位，可以衣食无忧、生活安逸，但他却从不恣意吃穿挥霍。如果我看到他，那么我对他的行为所产生的观念，一定不会是错误的。因为我的观念只是对他行为的反映，无所谓正误。但是当我用“节俭”或“美德”来形容这一行为时，也许就是一个错误的观念。除非这一行为与“节俭”在言语适当的情况下所属的观念一致，且符合定善恶的法则。

18.最后，实体观念何时是错误的

第三，我们的复杂实体观念，虽然参照实体本身，但也可能出现错误。无疑，如果实体观念所代表的是不可知的本质，则观念必然是错误的。但是我们如果认为这些实体观念是人心中一些简单观念的集合，认为它们由事物中常存的简单观念集合而来，并且假设它们就是这些模型的副本，它们便成了错误的观念。（1）当人们将现实生活中没有联系的简单观念加以组合时就成了错误观念。比如，马的形象和大小加上犬吠，三者无论怎么组合都没有联系，硬组合在一起就是关于马的错误观念。（2）如果将原本结合的简单观念之一剔除，掺入另一个简单观念，形成的整体实体观念也是错误的。比如，黄金的性质有延展性、硬度、易熔性、一定重量和黄色，如果加上铅或铜的固定性就会形成错误的复杂观念。加上其他简单观念，比如绝对固定性，也是错误的。因为在这两种情况下，黄金这一复杂观念虽由简单观念组成，但这些简单观念却不能统一，所以这一复杂观念就是错误的。但是，如果去掉固定性这个条件，或者把这个条件与其他条件分开，那么这个复杂观念就是一个不充分、不完全的观念，而不是错误观念。因为，虽然这个观念包含的因素并不全面，但其他观念可以统一共存。

19.正误常伴随着确认与否决

尽管我已经从普通意义上讲了观念在何种情况下、基于何种基础上为正或误，但是如果我们仔细研究一下各个情况，就会发现我们所认为的正误都源于头脑对各个情况作出的判断。因为正误一定伴随确认或否决，这种确认或否决可能是明白表示出来的，也可能是隐含起来的，当标记同它们所代表的事物相吻合时则为正，否则，则为误。我们常用的标记就是观念或语言，形成心理命题或语言命题。若标记的分合同它们所代表事物的分合相一致，则为正，反之，则为误，这一点我们将在之后讨论。

20.观念本身无所谓正误

我们不能仅仅依据观念是否同实体或他人的观念一致就判断一个观念的正误。因为，如果这些标记中的一切都在事物中存在，切切实实代表了这一事物，则观念不可能为误。但是，就算标记同现实中的事物不同，我们也不能断定它们就是错误的，因为它们可能原本就没有代表这些事物。不过，以下几种情况的确是错误的：

21.首先，当我们认为心中观念同他人相一致，但其实却不一致时，观念为误

第一，如果头脑形成一个观念，认为此观念与他人的同名观念相一致，或认为此观念与这名称所指的定义一致，但实际上却并非如此时，观念为误。这种情况在复杂情状观念中最为常见，但其他类别的观念也有此情况。

22.其次，当我们认为心中观念同实体一致，但其实却不一致时，观念为误

第二，如果一个复杂观念由一系列简单观念组成，并认为它与一类真实存在的事物一致，而自然中却并不存在这种事物，这种情况下，观念为误。比如，把黄金的颜色、熔性与固定性和锡的重量混合。

23.再次，当我们认为心中的观念充分，但其实却并不充分时，观念为误

第三，有时一个复杂观念包含很多简单观念，这些简单观念确实存在于很多类事物中，但是这一复杂观念的概括并不完全，所代表的事物中还有其他不可分割的元素，这时，这一复杂观念便不充分。比如，若将黄色、延展性、重量及熔性这几个元素组合，便推断出这是黄金这一复杂观念，却忽略了黄金必有的特定固定性及溶于王水的性质，那么得出的黄金这一复杂观念即不充分。

24.最后，若认为观念能代表本质，则观念为误

第四，如果一个复杂观念仅包含事物本质表现出的部分性质，而我们却认为这一复杂观念包含了它本质的全部，那么我们就犯了更大的错误。这些部分性质是该事物主动或被动与他物接触时表现出的性质，多为人们熟知，所以人们便形成了对该事物的复杂观念。与人们在尝试和检查后得到的性质相比，这些性质仍是少数；就算该事物方面的专家，了解的性质和事物真正的本质相比也是冰山一角。三角形的本质虽然较简单，仅包含少数观念，即三条边围成一个空间，但是这一本质所表现出的性质却数不胜数。所以，就算事物本质较简单，体现出的特征也是无穷无尽的。

25.观念何时为误

如果人们对身外的事物并无概念，但是通过自己设想，可能会形成一些观念（人们可以对这些观念随便命名），这些观念可能既不与事物的本质一致，也不与他人的观念一致，这时观念可能是错误的。但是，如果人们的观念仅仅是关于内心的事物，那么观念不可能出错。比如，如果我在人的身体和四肢上安上马的头和脖子，我所形成的这个观念因为只代表我内心的事物，所以不可能是错的。但是，如果我把它叫作“人”或“鞑靼”（Tartar），并且认为它代表外界的一种真实的存在，或认为它与他人的同名观念是相同的，那么我就错了。这种情况下的观念就是错误的，并不是说观念本身是错误的，错的是隐含的心理判断，即这一观念所指的就是与它一致的某事物。但是，如果我只是在心里设定这个观念，而不把它与某个实体或名称（即“人”或“鞑靼”）对应，而是自己给它命名，那么我就只是给它假设了一个名字，并不是我的判断或观念出错。

26.把这类观念称为正误更为合适

总体来说，当我们在思考自己的观念时，不管是参照它们名称的所指，还是参照实体，在看它们能否契合时，还是用正误来表示更为合适。如果有人非要用真假来表示，也无妨，毕竟这是个人自由。只不过我认为当观念中包含心理命题时这样表达更为合适。一个人心中的所有观念，就其本身来看并无错误，只有把不一致的部分堆到一起，形成的复杂观念才是错误的。其他一切观念本身都是正确的，而且我们关于它们的知识也都是正确的、真实的知识。但是如果我们把它们同某事物（它们的模型和原型）相对比，结果却不相符，那么它们就成了错误的。

论文字

文字或语言通论

1.人类生而能发清晰可辨之音

上帝造人为好交际之物，使其需要并倾向于与同类为伴；此外还赋其语言，用于交流，连接社会。人生而能发清晰可辨之音，谓之“文字”（words）。然而，这并不足以形成语言。因为鹦鹉等其他一些鸟类，在调教下也能发出清楚的声音，但是它们却不能使用语言。

2.文字是观念的符号

除了要有清晰可辨的声音之外，还要把这些声音作为内部观念的符号，代表头脑中的观念。只有这样，观念才能明于他人，得以传达。

3.文字须具概括性

然而上述两点性质并不能保证文字尽其功用。把声音作为观念的符号还不够，只有当这些符号能概括一类特定事物时，才能使语言尽其功用。因为，如果每种事物都需要特定文字表示自己的名称，那么文字的使用就会过于繁杂，失其功用。要去其繁杂，语言就要增加概括性词语，使特定文字可以代表一类特定事物。文字可以代表一类观念，这也是文字的优越之处。概括性的名称表达的观念也是概括性的，而某单一观念也有具体名称来对应。

4.除了用文字来代表观念，人们还用文字来表示简单或复杂观念存不存在。比如拉丁语中的无（Nihil），在英语中就是无知（ignorance）和无益（barrenness）。我们不能说否定词无关观念，这样它们就成了毫无意义的。实际上，它们关乎肯定词，只是肯定词的否定形式。

5.文字终归源自可感观念

只消看一下我们对于一般性可感观念的依赖，就能认识到我们各种概念和知识的起源。我们还应该看到，很多文字表达的观念及行为虽然并非感官，但也是源于感官的，也通过显而易见的可感观念转换为更加深奥的含义，用以代表那些感官所不能认知的观念，比如想象（imagine）、领会（apprehend）、理解（comprehend）、坚持（adhere）、猜想（conceive）、灌输（instil）、厌恶（disgust）、扰乱（disturbance）、宁静（tranquility），等等。这些词都源于可感事物，并适用于特定的思考形式。灵魂（spirit），最基本的意思是呼吸，天使（angel），原本的意思是使者。我确信，如果我们追本溯源便会发现，在所有语言当中，即便事物的名称并非代表可感物，它们也定是源于可感观念的。因此，我们可以猜想，最初创造语言的那些人心中所有的概念都是什么样的，它们源于何处。也可以猜想，自然在命名事物时，也在无意中暗示了人们，他们知识的来源和法则。因为，人们在命名他人所能感知的自身行为时，或在命名不为感官所察知的观念时，爱借用普通熟知的感觉观念，来使别人能感其所感，而表面无敏感变化。待这些行为的名称为人共知后，就能表示他们的心理活动，也能通过文字很好地描述他们的其他观念。因为这些观念仅包括外在可感观念及内在心理活动。我们上一章也谈到了，我们的观念仅源于外部可感物及内部可意识的心理活动。

6.分配

为了更好地理解语言在教育和知识方面的效用及力量，我们还要考虑以下几点：

一、在使用语言时，各种名称之应用。

二、既然所有的名称（除了固有名词）都是概括性的，并不代表单一特定事物，而是某种事物，那么随后我们应该考虑，这些种类中究竟包括什么？只有考察过后，我们才能正确使用文字，得出语言的天然优势及劣势，并在文字发生指称模糊不清时进行补救，避免不便。否则，我们就不能对知识进行清晰有序的讨论。因为知识关乎命题，通常为最普遍的命题，所以知识与文字的关联远远超乎人们的想象。

我们将在下一节进一步考察。

文字的缺陷

1.文字用以记载思想和交流思想

通过前节所述，我们很容易便可得出语言的缺陷，而且也由于文字含混不清的本质，导致这一缺陷不可避免。要看文字是否有缺陷，首先要看它们的功用和目的。因为文字的完善程度取决于是否能利用文字达到目的。文字有两大功用：

一、记载思想；

二、交流思想。

2.所有文字均可用于记载

第一，任何文字均可记载思想，帮助我们记忆，正如自说自话。如果说声音这种符号与观念本身没有任何必然联系，那么以此类推，我们也可以使用任意文字表达自己的观念。如果一直使用同一词语表达相同的观念，那么此时文字就没有缺陷。因为我们用这些文字表达了自己的意思，此时文字的使用就是正确的、无缺陷的。

3.用通俗的和专业的文字交流思想

第二，文字交流思想之功用，也分两层。

一是通俗用法，二是专业用法。

一、通俗用法涉及普通谈话和商业中所用的文字，通常关于日常事务和人们的生活琐事。

二、专业用法包括准确传达概念，用普遍的命题表达确信无疑的真理，使人们在寻求真理时有所依附，感到满意。

这两种用法区别甚大，后者比前者精准得多。下面我们将进行介绍。

4.文字的缺陷在于指称不定

在交流中，理解是语言的最终目标。不管是在通俗层面还是在专业层面，如果文字不能使听者心中激起与说者心中相同的观念，那么文字就没有达到这一目标。既然声音与我们的观念没有必然联系，而且它们的指称都是我们任意强加的，那么它们的含混不清和缺陷，多半是源于它们所代表的观念自身，而不是由于此声音比彼声音更能表示那些观念，因为所有声音同样完善。

所以，一些文字比另一些文字更含混不清，通常是它们所代表的观念的缘故。

5.文字存在缺陷的原因

文字本身没有意义，但是，如果我们要想和别人交流思想、进行交谈，就必须学习并记下文字背后的观念。但有时这并不容易，如：

一、文字表示的观念十分复杂，多由很多不同观念组成。

二、文字表示的观念同自然之物并无固定联系，也没有确定的标准对之进行修订和校正。

三、文字的意义需同一个鲜为人知的标准相参照。

四、文字的所指同事物的本质并不完全相同。

这些困难发生在可了解的文字意义方面。至于那些不可了解的文字意义，我们此处将略过。比如由于机能原因不能了解代表简单观念的名称，比如盲人对颜色名称没有概念、聋子对声音名称没有概念等。

在以上几种情况中，我们都能发现文字的缺陷。随后我将主要解释文字应用于各种观念时出现的缺陷。如果仔细考察，就会发现，复杂情状名称的含混和缺陷多由于前两种原因，实体名称的缺陷多由于后两种原因。

6.复杂情状名称含混不清多由于它们代表的观念过于复杂

第一，复杂情状名称的意义多含混不清。

原因一：它们表示的观念构成复杂。文字要达到交流的目的，必须在听者心中激起与说者心中相同的观念。缺少这点，人们只能以噪声相扰，不能达成对话交流的目的，即传达思想、沟通观念。但是，如果一个词语代表的观念过于复杂，经过了整合再整合，那么精确地形成并记下这一观念就是十分困难的，毫无改变地精准使用这一观念也是十分困难的。因此，很少有两个人对于复杂观念的命名所指完全相同（比如大部分品行名词）。因为就复杂观念本身来说，两个人都会持不同看法，而且同一人在过去和未来对复杂观念的看法也不相同。

7.第二，复杂情状名称没有标准

原因二：复杂情状缺少标准，不能进行修订和校正，因此它们多变化不定。它们多由人们随性组合，满足自身对话之用，满足自身观念。它们并不是对实际存在之物的描述，而是依照观念中的各种原型进行命名分类。起初创造欺骗（sham）、哄骗（wheedle）和戏弄（banter）等这些字的人，只是凭借自己的认识，把上述词语所能代表的观念都浓缩在这些词中。正如我们如今仍在向固有的语言中加入新的情状名称一样，过去的新词也是这样形成的。介于代表集合观念的名称是人们随意创造的，自然中没有对应的联合体，人们也没有一个标准去比对，所以这些名称大多意义不清。“谋杀”“亵渎”究竟代表什么，永远不能从它们所表示的事物中得知。在“谋杀”和“亵渎”这样的复杂观念中，大部分意义都不能由动作本身、心中意图或与圣物的关系中得出，同外在可见的行动也并无联系。谋杀时唯一的可见动作就是扣动扳机，而这一动作同“谋杀”这一复杂观念的其他部分并无联系。这一动作和其他部分观念之所以能共同形成“谋杀”的意义，是由于人们硬把它们结合在一起，并没有依据特定规则和模式。正是由于没有规则对他们的观念进行核准，不同人对于这一集合的理解也不同，不同人赋予这一名称的意义也不同。

8.适当性并不足以补救文字的缺陷

确实，通俗用法或适当性原则可以提供些补救，确定语言的意义，这点不容否认。通俗用法可以在普通对话中规范文字的意思，但是谁都不能确认文字的准确含义，也不能决定它们和哪些观念对应。通俗用法并不足以适用于专业的对话，大多复杂观念名称在通俗用法中有很大改变余地，而且这些复杂观念名称即便用法适当，也可以表示不同观念。此外，我们也没有关于适当性的相关规定，所以对于字词的使用方式到底是不是得当，也经常出现争端。因此，显然，这种复杂观念名称多存在缺陷，指意多含混不清。即便双方都想要理解对方，也不能每次达成一致。比如，尽管人人都会说“荣誉”和“感恩”，但是即便在同一国家，人们说同种语言，对这两个词所代表的复杂集合观念的理解也不同。

9.获知名称的方式也会导致意义含混不清

复杂情状名称的获知方式往往会使这些名称的意义更加含糊。儿童是怎样学习语言的呢？要让他们明白简单观念的名称或物体的名称，人们往往把名称代表的东西给他们看，这样他们就对这些东西有了观念。随后，再把代表事物的名称重复地说给他们听，比如“白、甜、奶、糖、猫、狗”。但是在复杂情状名称方面，尤其是其中最重要的品行名词，他们往往先学习相应的声音。如果要明白这些名称代表的复杂观念是什么，他们就要寻求他人解释，或靠自己观察（大多数情况是这样）。虽然他们想要知道这些品行名称精确的意思，但是在人们口中，这些名称往往是毫无意义的声音，就算有些意义，也大多松散不定、含混模糊。就连那些特别注意把观念表达清楚的人，在使用复杂观念名称来区别于其他名称时，也不能避免这种含混。不管是激烈的辩论还是日常的交谈，只要涉及“荣誉、信心、优雅、宗教和教堂”等名称，人们总会有不同观点，这多是因为他们对这些名称的定义不同，在谈到这些词时他们心中的指称也不同。所以这些争论都是关于一个固定声音的意义。因此，我们看到，不管是人界还是神界，法律的解释总是无穷无尽，解释说明都源源不断。因此，人们总是在不断地限制、区分、调整这些品行词的意义。但是人们对这些名称的创造仍然无穷无尽。很多人，在第一次读圣经或法典时多满足于了解文本之意，但他们一味寻求解说，在看过解说后反而疑惑了，明白的地方也糊涂了。我并不是说注解是无用的，而是想要说明，复杂情状名称的意义本身就是不确定的，就连那些有意向、有能力利用语言表达思想的人也解释不清楚。

10.因此，古代作家难免表意不明

显然，这些名称指称的不确定性使得不同国家历代作家也难免表意不清。因此，如果要了解这些名家运用自身思想完成的等身之作究竟原意为何，就需要我们特别留心，加以研习，运用智慧和判断力。不过我们在各种著作方面，不必全都过分追求其意，我们应该把重点放在包含真理和法律的那些书籍上，因为真理是我们所信仰的，法律是我们所服从的，稍有错误，稍有触犯，就会使我们陷于不利。至于别的作家，我们不必过于费心探求，因为他们所写的只是他们一家之言，因此，我们不必知道他们的观点，正如他们不必知道我们的观点一样。我们的福祸不取决于他们的著作，所以我们即使不知道他们的观念也无妨。因此，如果他们的著作用词不清，我们完全可以把它们束之高阁，这都由我们自己决定。

11.“如果你们本身不想让人理解，被忽略也实属应当。”

如果说复杂情状名称没有确定意义，是因为自然中没有真实存在的标准，使那些观念有所参照，有所校正，那么实体名称没有确定意义，就是因为相反的原因，因为实体名称代表的观念与实际存在的事物是相符的，在自然中也有相应的标准。就实体观念来说，我们不能像对待复杂情状观念那样自由组合观念，形成特定标记，并以此对事物进行分类和命名。我们必须服从自然，使我们的复杂观念符合实体，用事物本身来规范它们名称的意义，否则，我们的名称就不能成为它们的标记，也不能代表它们。在这方面，我们可以遵循一定的模式。不过，也正是由于这些模型，使得实体名称意义不明。因为这些实体观念要参照我们身外世界的标准，而我们要么根本不知道这些标准，要么知道的不全，所以实体观念的名称意义也是多变的。

12.首先，事物的名称会参照其本质，而本质是不得而知的

如上所述，在通俗用法中，事物的命名要参照两个因素。

第一，名称要能代表对应的事物。所以，名称的指称必须符合事物的实质构成，包括所有性质。但是这一构成，或称本质，是不为我们所知的。所以，不管我们赋予它什么声音，都不能十分准确。我们永远也不可能知道，真正应该被称为“马”或“锑”的事物是什么，因为本质永远不得而知，所以名称的意义也不完全。因此，按照这个假设，由于事物名称的标准不能得知，也就不能依据标准确认或调整名称的意义。

13.其次，事物的名称会参照共存的性质，而我们不能了解所有性质

第二，事物中存在的简单观念（即名称能直接表示出的），共存于多种事物中，它们是相关名称参照的标准，也是意义得以修改的标准。但是这些原型也不能消除意义的不确定性，因为这些共存于同一事物的简单观念数量很多，且每个都适于成为具体复杂观念的一部分，得到名称的直接反映。尽管每个人考察的对象相同，但实际上各自形成的观念却不同。所以，每个人使用的名称必然各不相同。这些组成复杂观念的简单性质无穷无尽，多为各种能力，同他物产生反应时会发生改变。如果你知道，活跃性高的金属在加热之后会发生很多种变化，在同其他物体发生化学反应后变化更丰富这个道理，就不会奇怪为什么在我们的能力范围之内不能悉知每种事物的全部性质。这些性质如此之多，多到人们不能确切地知道数量有多少。每个人会凭借自己的技能发现不同的性质，因此，每个人对同一事物的观念就会不同，在听到这一事物的名称时就会有多种不同指称。事物的复杂观念是由多个简单观念构成的，共存于自然之中，所以每个人都可以把自己发现的性质纳入他的复杂观念之中。比如黄金，有人认为黄金的性质包括颜色和重量，另一个人认为溶于王水是黄金的又一性质，还有人认为应该加上可熔性，又有人根据自己的经验或道听途说，提出还应该增加延展性和固定性。那么这些人里，究竟谁对“黄金”的概念最为正确？该由谁来决定呢？每个人参照的标准都源于自然，每个人都有理由认为自己提出的性质经过研究，符合“黄金”的指称，应纳入“黄金”原本的复杂观念。而没有经过仔细调查，就会忽略相关性质。自然中性质的结合是复杂观念中各简单观念结合的基础，因此各个性质和观念地位相同，没有哪个必须留下或哪个必须去除。因此，我们可以断言，虽然人们使用同一名称命名一个事物，但是他们形成的复杂观念却各有不同，而事物名称的意义也是不确定的。

14.此外，任一简单观念对应的各种性质都会同他物发生作用，有的能同多数事物发生作用，有的能同少数事物发生作用。既然如此，谁能决定，物体的性质组合中，哪些性质能得到名称的反映？谁又有权力决定，哪些明显且常见的性质应被排除？又应该加入哪些不易察觉的、特殊的性质？对这些问题的回答导致了事物名称意义的不确定性。在我们下面讨论专业用法时，就会看到，正是这种不确定性造成了犹疑、争辩和错误。

15.带有缺陷的文字可供通俗之用，但不能用于专业范畴

在日常对话中，往往由明显性质的表象决定事物的名称（比如在以种传代的各种事物方面，我们多半以它们的形状命名，对于别的事物，我们多以它们的颜色和其他可感性质命名），人们也能完全明白这些名称所指的是哪些事物，比如，人们清楚“黄金”和“苹果”指的是什么，也能把它们区分开来。不过在专业性的探讨和辩论中，虽然也应该确定一般性的真理，从前提推出结论，但是事物名称的表意却不能确定，更不易确定。比如，如果你认为“黄金”这一复杂观念包括可锻性（某种程度的固定性），就会相应作出推断并得出结论，认为“黄金”有此特征。但是，如果有人认为可锻性不是黄金的特征，那么他就永远不会承认也不会相信你的观点。

16.以液体为例

人们如果抛弃了纷乱粗疏的意念，进行严格缜密的考察，就不难发现，在一切语言中的事物名称方面，这种缺陷是很自然且难避免的。因为，此时他们会相信，许多文字的意义，在通常用法中似乎很清楚、很确定，可是实际上却含混不清。有一次，我同一伙聪明而博学的医生们在一块聚会，他们偶然谈到一个问题：是否有液体能穿过神经纤维？讨论进行了很长时间，双方各执一词，但我却希望，他们先考察确定“液体”一词的意义，再进行争辩。因为我常觉得，人们的争执不下大多困于文字的意义，而非对事物的不同认识。他们起初对我的提议有些惊讶，好在他们都很聪明，没有认为我的提议肤浅怪异。他们之所以惊讶是因为在座所有人都认为自己完全理解“液体”的含义，甚至连我也认为这个词没什么难理解的。但他们最终还是同意了我的提议。经过考察发现，这个词的表意并不如他们所想那般确定，每个人对“液体”都有自己的看法。这使他们意识到，两方辩论的结点在于“液体”的意义，而就某种流动柔软的物质可以穿过神经纤维这点却达成了一致。究竟这种流动柔软的物质应不应该被称为“液体”，大家在思考后都认为这点不值得争论。

17.以黄金为例

人们热烈的讨论，归根结底是以上这种情况，这一点在其他方面也可以看到。现在我们只消稍微仔细考察一下我们前面提到的例子——“黄金”，就能看到它的表意是很难确定的。我想大家都同意，黄金是一种金灿灿的物质。很多儿童都认为，只要是金灿灿的东西，就是黄金。所以，他们会认为孔雀尾巴上金黄金黄的那块就是黄金。又有人认为黄金应该具有可熔性，那些浴火成灰的金黄物质不是黄金。所以，“黄金”就是这样一种物质，有着金灿灿的外表，且浴火而化而非成灰。同样，还有人把重量加入这个观念中，这个性质和可熔性一样，同颜色紧密相连，也应当用那个名称来表示。因此，前面说的只有颜色和可熔性就是不完全的，其他部分性质也是如此。谁都说不清，介于这些性质都不可分割，系于自然，为什么有些应包括于本质之中，有些应排除在本质之外。代表戒指原材料的黄金，为什么颜色、重量和可熔性的组合能表示它的本质，而颜色、重量和溶于水的组合却不能呢？溶于王水这一性质同熔于火的性质一样，同本质密不可分，两种都是黄金本身可同外物发生作用的性质，这两种性质的差别只是在于外物对黄金的作用方式不同。那么凭什么可熔性可以成为黄金本质的一部分，而可溶性只是它的一种性质呢？又凭什么颜色是本质的一部分，而可锻性仅是一种性质呢？我在这里想要表达的是，上述各种性质都是依存于本质的，都会主动或被动同他物发生反应。因此，谁都不能决定“黄金”一词（参照自然中的实体）究竟表示这一组观念还是另一组观念。所以，这一名称的表意必然是不确定的。既然每个人对同一事物的观察都各有不同，而且又没有人能穷尽所有性质，那么我们对事物的描述只能是有缺陷的，而文字的表意也是不确定的。

18.简单观念名称最少含混

如前所述，简单观念名称最少含混，即便出现含混也能轻易察觉。原因如下：第一，这些名称代表的观念只关乎一种感觉，相较于那些复杂观念更容易理解，更容易记住，因此较少出现不确定的情况。而事物和混杂情状的复杂观念通常包括多个简单观念，并且人们对这些简单观念的集合还没有统一的看法，因此这些复杂观念更不容易记住。第二，简单观念名称不参照其他本质，只参照它们直接表示的那个感觉。而实体名称永远会参照其他本质，所以它们的意义含混不清，因此引发许多争辩。只要不过于执拗或存心找碴儿，在使用自己熟悉的语言时，人们很少弄错简单观念名称。比如，“白”“甜”“黄”“苦”的意思都很明显，每个人都能理解，就算不理解，本身也能意识到自己不懂了，会寻求解答。但别人具体如何使用“谦虚”或者“节俭”这样的简单观念集合，就不得而知了。我们多认为自己知道“金”和“铁”代表什么，即使这样，究竟他人如何定义这些复杂观念，我们却不能确定。但有一点我能确信，即如果说者和听者对它们特性的定义并不相同，在谈论普遍论题，确定普遍真理，考察最终结果时，一旦使用它们，就会产生错误和争论。

19.简单情状名称也较少含混

同理，简单情状名称同简单观念名称一样，也很少含混。特别是涉及图形和数字时，人们尤为清楚。只要用心就不会搞混数字“七”和“三角形”。总的来说，在任何方面，最简单的观念一定有最明确的名称。

20.超复杂混杂情状和实体名称最含混

如果复杂情状是由少数明显的简单观念组成的，那么它们的名称意义就比较明确。而如果复杂情状包括很多简单观念，那么它们的名称意义往往含混不清。至于实体名称，如果它们的观念来源既不是事物的本质，也不是它们参照模型的精确表象，就会出现很大缺陷和不确定性。当涉及专业用法时，情况更甚。

21.为何将缺陷归咎于文字

事物名称方面的混乱多由于我们缺少知识，或是不能洞悉它们的本质。你也许会想，为什么我们把这些缺陷怪到文字头上，而不怪我们自己的理解力不够呢？这一异议很有道理，所以我有必要解释一下为什么我们总是把缺陷归咎于文字。知识和文字密切相关，只有考察过文字的力量和意义后，才能对知识进行清晰恰当的分析。知识有关真理，有关命题。知识纵然终归要落到事物上，但还要通过文字表达，因此，文字同我们的知识密不可分。文字在真理和我们的理解力之间架起一座桥梁，像是可视物体往来的媒介。而它们的含混又常常蒙住我们的双眼，误导我们的理解。只要仔细研究一下人们给自己和他人带来的谬论，看一下人们的争论和观念中出现的错误，就能发现，其中的大部分都源于文字及文字意义的不确定性。因此，我们完全可以相信，文字成为了我们获取知识道路上的绊脚石。我们必须注意到这点，因为人们还没有意识到文字给我们带来的不便，反而通过研究助长这一现象，甚至冠以研究这一学科的人博学精思的美誉。但是我认为，语言是获取知识的工具，如果能完全消除这些缺陷，世界上就会减少很多争论喧嚣，通往知识与和平的道路也会越来越宽。

22.因此我们在研究前人的作品时要保持谦虚

我确信，就所有语言来说，文字的意义都依赖于使用这种语言的人所拥有的思想和观念。因此，即使对于在同一国家使用同种语言的人们来说，文字的意义也是不确定的。这点在希腊作家中就可见一斑。只要稍作研究，就会发现他们虽然用着同样的文字，但是却自说自话，表意不同。这还仅是同一个国家在某段时间的状况，如果再跨时空呢？各家有各家的观念、脾气、习俗，形容词和修辞也各不相同，虽然我们不知道当时情况怎样，但这必然会影响当时文字的意义。因此在我们解释或误解前人之作时要互相谅解，因为，虽然我们应对这些作品加以研究，但是各语言不通造成的困难是不可避免的。如果说者不能在表达自己的意思和目的之前定义各种名词（简单观念名称和明显事物名称除外），那么听者就自然会犹疑不定。宗教、法律和品行是最为重要的话题，因此，这几方面的困难也最大。

23.各家对“新旧约”的解释和评论就是最直接的证据。尽管书中所写的内容极为真实，但是读者的理解却经常出现错误。这自不必惊讶，因为上帝的意志在披上文字的外衣后必然会含混不清。正如上帝之子在披上肉体的外衣后，也不得不经受人性的一切弱点一样（罪恶除外）。我们要赞美他的慈悲，感谢他把旨意用如此了然的方式表达出来，好让我们传播于世。他给人类带来了理智之光，使那些不曾见“上帝”这个词的人也确信上帝的存在（只要他们愿意去追寻），对上帝礼敬有加。自然宗教的箴言清楚明白，为全人类所了解，不为人所争执；而书籍和语言揭示的真理，通常会困于文字这一媒介，产生很多隐晦或困难。我认为，对于前者，我们应该仔细勤恳地研习；对于后者，我们也不应过于倨傲、绝对和专横。

文字的滥用

1.文字的滥用

语言本身固有一定的缺陷，使文字的使用出现含糊纷乱。但除此之外，人们在进行交流时，往往也会故意用错或有所忽略，导致这些符号更不明白，更不清晰。

2.第一，无观念字词，或曰无清晰观念字词

第一，在这方面，最明显的滥用就是在使用文字时没有清晰明显的观念，或根本没有观念。主要有以下两种情况：

一、你可能会发现，在所有的语言当中，有些词不管是从起源看还是从使用看，都不能表示任何清晰明显的观念。这些词大多源于哲学和宗教派系。这些词的创造者，往往爱装作与众不同，不为常人理解，或支持一些奇特的观点，又或要遮掩自己假设中的弱点，因此他们会创造这些新字词。如果我们考察一下这些新字词，就会发现它们可以被称为“无意义的词汇”。这些词在发明之初就不代表任何观念，就算仔细考察一下，也会发现它们同观念并不一致。无疑，之后同派别的人在普遍使用这些词时，也只是单纯地使用声音，而没有任何意义。同派别的那些人认为嘴里说着这些词就已足够，完全可以同其他派别相区别，因此就不必费事考察这些字词代表什么观念。我就不举例了，因为大家在读书和交谈中会发现很多这样的现象。如果你想多要些例子，可以去问那些“无意义词汇的制造者”，也就是那些烦琐的学者和形而上学者（也包括后来的自然哲学家和观念哲学家），他们可以给你满意的答案。

3.二、还有一些人，滥用字词的情况更甚。他们不但不放弃那些起初就没有清晰观念的字词，反而经常在使用那些表示重要观念的字词时也表意不清。人们常常谈及“智慧”“荣耀”“恩惠”等词，但是如果问一问他们，这些词究竟是什么意思？他们就会傻眼，不知如何作答。这就证明，虽然他们知道这些声音，也能脱口而出，但却不知道这些词究竟是什么意思，也不能向别人解释。

4.这是因为，他们在了解观念之前先学习了它们的名称

从小到大，人们都习惯先学字词，再学字词代表的复杂观念或事物。人们往往不会费心去了解这些字词具体表示什么意思，而是用这些字词表示自己心中一些含混的观念，并且认为别人在使用这些字词的时候也拥有一样的观念，就好像这些字词的读音表意永恒不变似的。在日常生活中，为求对方了解起见，人们要在字词方面作些变通。但是，在讨论到自己的原则和利益时，这些无意义的文字显然会使他们的谈论充满假大空的论调。涉及品行字词时尤为如此，因为品行字词是大量任意观念的集合，并不是永远固定存在于自然中的，所以人们大多仅对它们的读音有概念，它们所表示的观念也很含糊。人们往往会使用周围人使用的字词，而且常常装出一副很自信的样子，避免别人看出他们根本不知道词义，但同时又不愿意费事了解这些字词真正的意义是什么。这样一来，他们不但可以随意使用这些字词，还可以享受另外一个优势，那就是虽然他们很少用对，但是也很少有人能说服他们，证明他们用错了。因为说服他们就等于让没有对错观念的人不要犯错，或剥夺一个没有住处的流浪汉的住宅。这是我的猜想，但事实究竟是否如此，大家可以从自身或他处观察得出。

5.第二，字词使用前后不一

第二，文字的另一种滥用，是使用时前后不一。我们常常看到，人们在描写一个话题时（特别是辩论中），同一个词（辩论的观念词）有时表示这些观念，有时表示那些观念。这是典型的滥用文字。我用文字代表自己的观念，再把这些文字告知他人，如果我时而让它们表示这个意思，时而让它们表示那个意思，我就在滥用文字，因为文字的意义并非其本身的意义，而是我强加给它的。这种任意的做法简直愚蠢，甚至是一种欺骗。一个人在对话或推理时，用同一字词表示不同简单观念集合，就像一个人在计算时，用同一数字表示不同单位集合一样。比如，用数字3表示3、4或8。真不知道谁会同这样算账的人来往！这样做的人会根据自己的利益，在做生意时把8算成7，或算成9，这样的愚蠢和欺骗人人都会生厌。但是在争辩和知识竞赛中，这种做法多被看作聪明和博学的表现。然而，我认为，这是更大的欺骗，因为真理比金钱更重要。

6.第三，字词的误用导致混淆

第三，把旧词用于新情况或不寻常的情况，或引入一些未定义的新词，又或把文字组合起来混淆原义时，这些都会带来含混，是语言的另一种滥用。逍遥学派这点最为明显，其他学派也有此现象发生。事实上，所有学派都会遇到一些困难（这也是人类知识的缺陷），因此他们会用含混的文字和意义来掩盖自己的不足，如在眼前蒙上一层迷雾。只要想想就能知道，通俗用法中，“主体”和“外延”是两个不同的观念。因为，如果它们的意义是相同的，那么我们不但可以说“外延的主体”，也可以说“主体的外延”，两种说法一样清楚适当。但有的人非得把两者的意义弄混。而且，各学派还以这种滥用，甚至文字、逻辑和通识学科的含混为荣。而辩论这种艺术，不但没有帮助我们辩明真理和知识，反而加剧了语言本身的缺陷。仔细研究这些学术著作的人会发现，其中涉及的字词比日常会话用语更晦涩、更含混，意义更不确定。

7.逻辑和辩论多导致文字的滥用

人们的角色和学识往往由他们的辩论技能决定。如果要在这方面设奖项，评奖方面包括文字使用的精巧准确，那么人们会在反对或辩护某一观点时极尽巧舌之能。胜利的标准不是真理归于何方，而是谁能辩到最后。

8.人们把巧舌善辩称为玄思

尽管这项技能并无用处，与追求真理背道而驰，但是还是被人们冠以“玄思”和“精妙”的美名，得到各学派的称颂和有识之士的推崇。怪不得当时的哲学家（我指的是那些爱争好辩的哲学家，如希腊作家卢西恩诙谐合理的讥讪）和学者要用古怪难解的复杂文字网来遮掩自己的无知。他们所追求的只是荣誉和尊重，旨在让他人知道自己学识渊博。真才实学难求，假装冒充易得，所以他们多使用难解的词汇，让别人赞叹。他们的用语越难懂，别人就会越膜拜他们。但纵观古今，这些“学识渊博”的人也没比别人更聪明、更有用。他们对人类的生活和当时的社会贡献微乎其微。因为，创造的新词没有新事物与之对应，混淆旧词的含义，使很多问题有所争议，对于人们的生活并无意义，也不值得赞赏和奖励。

9.这种学识无助于社会

尽管世界上有很多学识渊博的雄辩家和学究，但各国的和平、防御和自由却全仰赖不做学问的政治家，而艺术的发展也依靠那些没有文化、被人轻贱的手艺人。不过，这种装模作样的愚陋和学问渊博的妄语，近来却十分流行，这都是那些学究的利益和虚荣推动的，想要维护既得的权威和权力，最容易的方法就是用艰涩的文字调侃生意人和无知者，并且使聪明而无所事事之人忙着辩论毫无意义的词汇，让他们卷入无底的迷洞。此外，要想使人相信荒诞的教条，只能用一堆晦涩、含混而不确定的文字来保障它们。而这种保障，更像是强盗的窝点、狐狸的洞穴，而不像守卫战士的堡垒。这层保障不好攻破，不是因为他们本身武力高强，而是他们周围荆棘丛生，提供遮蔽。因为人们不能接受谬论，所以他们只能借晦涩艰深以自保。

10.不过这样却破坏了获取知识和沟通的工具

这种人看似有学识，实则为无知，让有求知欲的人也学不到真正的知识。而这种现象在世界上还普遍存在，看似启发理解，实则迷惑思维。我们也看到，虽然其他善意而聪明的人在教育和学术方面没有达到那种“造诣”，但他们也能正常地运用语言，良好地沟通，开发语言的真正效用。然而，虽然不做学问的人能充分了解白与黑这两个字，也知道这两个字代表的观念，但是还是有学究巧妙地证明雪是黑的，也就是证明白即黑。这样，他们就破坏了交流和教育的工具。他们所做的无非是混淆文字的意义，使语言更无用（语言本身的缺陷已然影响其效用）。不做学问之人是没有这种“本事”的。

11.这样做就等于混淆声音和字母

上述指白为黑的做法，同改变已知文字的意义一样，不能增益人们的理解，也无益于人们的生活；就算一个人学识精微，才能超群，在著作中以A代B、以D代E、以X代Y，让读者惊叹，但也是无益的。因为，要用黑这个字来表示另一个相反的观念，并且称雪为黑，就和以A代B是一样无意义；因为大家承认“黑”代表一种可感观念，“白”代表另一种可感观念。字母A代表语言器官运动后所产生的一种声音改变，而字母B代表另一种。

12.这种艺术让宗教和正义变得更加复杂

这种危害也出现在逻辑的细枝末节和好奇空洞的猜测当中，侵害了人们的生活和社会，使法律和神谕变得含混复杂，让人生百态变得混乱、无序和不定，使宗教和正义两大法则变得无用，甚至消失。大部分对人神法则的评论和争辩，除了让其意义更模糊，更复杂之外，还有什么用呢？反反复复区分，揪住细节不放，无非只能让字词更含糊不清，让读者更糊涂。为什么仆人更容易理解君主下的命令，不管以口头还是书面形式？为什么确立成法律之后臣民反而不解了呢？我前面也提到了，很多资质一般的人原本可以读懂一篇文章，或一条法律，但是在向专家或学会咨询后，反而觉得没有帮助。

13.这称不上学问

这里我不讨论上述做法是不是有什么附带利益，但是我想让大家想一想，人们是不是应该掌握事物的本质，做好该做的事；而不应该浪费时间谈论事物，卖弄文字；是不是应该直接明了地使用文字；我们使用语言是不是为了多学知识，联系社会；而不是遮掩真理，动摇人权，生烟起雾，模糊道德和宗教。至少，如果发生这类事，应该想一想这是不是学识和知识。

14.第四，把文字当作事物本身

第四，把文字当作事物本身也是对文字的滥用。从某种程度上说，这关乎所有名称，但实体名称最受影响。如果人们把自己的思想局限于一个体系，坚信传统的假设是完美无缺的，那么就容易发生这种滥用。他们会相信，这一学派的名称同事物完全对应，完全同事物的本质一致。自幼学习逍遥学派理论的人，都认为十大范畴的名称同事物的本质完全一致，他们都相信“实体形式”（substantial forms）、“植物的灵魂”（vegetative souls）、“憎恶虚空”（abhorrence of a vacuum）、“心理成像”（intentional species）等是真实存在的。人们在初学知识时就接触了这些文字，并发现学派大师和体系都十分重视这些文字，所以他们自然而然认为，这些文字同自然相一致，代表了各真实存在的实体。柏拉图派学者主张“世界的灵魂”（soul of the world），伊壁鸠鲁派（Epicureans）主张原子在静止时也有“运动的趋向”（endeavour towards motion）。几乎哲学的每个学派都有自己的一套术语，外人是不懂的。因为人们不能事事精通，所以这些妄语，倒是能粉饰人的愚陋，遮掩人的错误。因此，久而久之，这些词被同学派的人所熟知，成为语言中最重要、最有意义的部分。如果这一学派的教义盛行，那么，“转世”“轮回”这样的词就会随处可见，无疑，人们也会对这些词有印象，使他们相信对应的事物是存在的。“逍遥派形式”和“心理成像”经历的就是这样一个过程。

15.以物质为例

只要专心研读哲学著作便会看到，很多名称都被当成事物本身，这大大误导了我们的理解。但是有些文字虽被误用，却不易察觉。举一个大家都熟悉的例子：人们对“物质”一词争论不休，好似自然中真有这种东西存在，与“物体”相区别。显然，这两个词所表示的观念是不同的。因为，如果这两个词表示的观念完全相同，那么我们就可以随意替换它们。但是，我们虽然可以说“所有物体的物质相同”，却不能说“所有物质的物体相同”。我们常说一个“物体”比另一个“物体”大，却很少说一个“物质”比另一个“物质”大。为什么会这样呢？因为，“物质”和“物体”虽然并没有实质的区别，有此就有彼；但是它们代表两个不同的观念，“物质”是不完全的，是“物体”的一部分。物体代表外在实体，而物质是物体的一部分，观念更为含糊，物质是物体的构成，只是没有形状。因此，当谈到物质的时候，我们通常指向只有一个，因为物质只是一个实体观念，到处都一样，所以，我们不说不同物质。而物体，却有各种形状，各有不同。物质总要以一定的形状存在，因此要说物质具体是什么就会造成谈论和争辩的含混，这就是哲学家心里和书中的“原料”。这其中的缺陷和滥用，以及还关系什么词汇，还是由大家考察吧。但至少我可以说，如果我们能如实地观察文字本身，只把它们看作观念的符号，而非事物本身，那么世界上的争论一定会少很多。因为，在我们争论“物质”一词，或类似的名词时，我们争论的只是那个发音所表示的观念，而不过问这个观念是否同自然之物相一致。如果人们能清楚地告知他们的用词究竟表示什么观念，那么在追寻真理时，模糊和争吵就会减半。

16.错误会持续下去

不论文字的误用会产生什么不便，都有一点可以肯定，那就是人们会对错误习以为常，观念会逐渐偏离真理。我们很难使人们相信，他们的父辈、老师、牧师或学士使用的文字，代表的都不是真实存在的自然之物。这是人们不愿改掉错误的一大原因。就连那些颇有见地的、一味追求真理的人，也很难改掉这些错误。因为文字的使用时间越长，人们的印象就越深，相应的错误观念也就更难消除。

17.第五，人们常用文字来表示它们本不能表示的东西

第五，用文字表示它们原本不能表示的事物，也是一种滥用。很多时候，透过事物的类称，我们可以看到它们的名义本质。当我们把名称设为命题，加以确认或否决时，我们通常认为它们代表的就是一类事物的实在本质。如果一个人说“黄金是有延展性的”，他所暗示的，并不只是“在我的观念中，黄金是有延展性的”（尽管这句话也只能表示这个意思），还表示了“只要具备黄金的本质就有延展性”。也就是说，延展性取决于黄金的本质，与本质密不可分。但是，如果一个人不知道黄金的本质包括什么，就不能把延展性和这种本质联系起来，而只能把延展性和“黄金”的读音联系起来。如果我们认为“人”的定义是“理性的动物”，而非“无羽、宽甲、两足动物”（源于柏拉图），且“人”这个字，在这里代表的是这类生物的本质，那么就说明，“理性的动物”更适于描述“人”的本质。否则，柏拉图怎么不用“人”来表示形状和外表与他物不同的躯体呢？亚里士多德怎么不用“人”来表示兼有身体和推理能力的事物呢？还是因为“人”这个字表示着它本不能表示的其他事物。

18.用文字表示它们原不能表示的事物，就等于用文字表示它们原不能表示的事物之本质

诚然，如果文字对应的观念是事物的本质，那么事物的名称将会比现在更有用，相关的命题也会更确定。但是，由于我们不能掌握事物的本质，我们在对话时使用的文字传递的知识就很少，很不确定。因此，为了减少这种缺陷，人们就悄悄用文字表示含有这种本质的某个事物，似乎这样就更加接近本质。尽管“人”和“黄金”代表的仅仅是事物一系列性质的复杂观念，但是人们在使用这些字词时，都认为这些名称代表的是拥有这种本质（含有以上性质）的事物。这种做法，明显是对文字的滥用，不仅没有减少文字的缺陷，反而让缺陷有所增加。这是因为，我们使用的名称代表的事物并不存在于我们的复杂观念中，所以自然也就不能用这名称来表示这种事物。

19.因此，我们对事物观念的改变，并不会改变对应的事物种类

这里我要解释，为什么在复合情状中，任一观念的消失或改变，都可能使整个复杂观念改变，变成另一种类。比如，过失杀人（chance-medly）、屠杀（manslaughter）、谋杀（murder）和弑亲（parricide）。这是因为，名称表示的复杂观念包括实在本质和名义本质，除此之外，再没有参照其他本质。但是就实体来说，却并非如此。比如黄金，尽管每个人对黄金持有的观念不同，但是大家却不认为事物有所改变，因为人们在心中悄悄把这一名称同这一事物的不变本质（包括各种性质）相参照。你认为黄金还应该包括固定性和溶于王水，这也不会对事物造成改变，只是加上另一简单观念后，让这个复杂观念更加完整。但是，如果我们对名称参照的事物没有任何概念，那么观念的增加就没什么帮助，反而会给我们带来更多困难。如果我们对黄金这一事物没有任何概念，那么就算参照其本质，“黄金”一词（表示或多或少的简单观念集合，在交谈中指向某一事物）也没有什么意义。虽然在交谈中，我们会用“黄金”这一名称表示对应的实体，但是如果仔细考察一下，便会发现“黄金”一词可能和实体本身并不统一，比如就算把金叶子放在我们面前，我们也可能辨认不出。

20.文字滥用的原因在于人们假设自然的作用是规律的

人们用名称来表示事物的实在本质，是因为他们假设（如前所述），自然在产生事物时是有规则的。自然会区分不同物种，如果事物的内部构成相同，那么我们也赋予它们通用名称。但是，只要你看到同种事物的不同特质，就会相信，种类中的个体，虽然名称相同，但内部构成却彼此不同。而且，同种事物的差异程度与不同种事物的差异程度相仿。人们总是假设，内部构成相同，则名称就相同。由于这一假设，人们往往用这些名称代表事物的本质。然而，这些名称实际代表的，只是人们在使用这些事物时头脑中产生的复杂观念。这些名称表示的事物，如果与人们真正指称的事物不同，使用起来就会造成很大的歧义。这种情况在那些深受“实体形式”影响的人身上十分常见，他们坚信不同物种都是由这种“形式”来决定和区分的。

21.文字的滥用包括两种错误的假设

用各种名称来表示我们没有的观念，或不了解的本质，是十分荒谬的，因为这样我们的文字就不代表任何事物。但只要看看人们对文字的使用，就会发现这种荒谬的现象简直随处可见。当一个人问他所见的事物（不管是黑猩猩或怪胎）是不是人，他所问的并不是这个具体的事物是否符合他对“人”形成的复杂观念，而是它是否具有“人”这种事物的本质。因此，在使用事物名称时，常会出现下列两种错误假设：

一、自然界中存在一些特定的本质，各种具体的事物依照这些本质而形成，也根据这些本质得以分类。可以确定的一点是，各种事物都有其本质，使各种可感特质有所依存。但事实证明，这些本质并不能区分物种，划分界限。

二、第一点似乎已经预先假设我们知道上述本质。因为，如果不是已经知道“人”的本质是什么，我们怎么能判断一件事物是否含有这种本质呢？不过，这种假设是完全错误的。因此，如果用这些名称来表示我们本没有的观念，就会在交谈和推理时产生很多混乱，给我们的文字交流带来很多障碍。

22.第六，人们假设文字有确定且明显的意义

第六，还有一种文字的滥用也很普遍，但是却很少有人察觉，那就是，人们把文字附着在观念之上，并习以为常，他们多认为名称与所指意义之间的联系相近且必然，进而认为每个人都能理解名称的含义。因此，他们默认，在使用文字时，特别是在使用那些通用文字时，说者与听者形成的观念完全相同。因此，在交谈中，他们总会以为双方就用词达成一致，认为别人所使用的文字表意同他们自身使用的文字相同，所以就不去费神解释自己的观念，也不去了解他人的观念。这样，人们的交谈就多了很多喧闹与争吵，反而没有获得更多信息。人们总是认为同一文字表示的意义完全相同，然而事实却并非如此，个人使用的文字只是代表个人的观念罢了。在交谈或辩论中，如果有人问一个词究竟是什么意思（这是完全必要的），人们往往会觉得奇怪。但是，日常交谈中出现的争吵却多是因为双方复杂观念的所指不同。人们对每个词的定义可能都有所不同，比如一个再熟悉不过的词——“生命”。如果你问别人“生命”是什么意思，他肯定会觉得你在侮辱他的智商。但是，如果要问一粒种子有没有生命？胚胎在孵化前有没有生命？一个完全失去知觉的醉汉有没有生命？就会发现，就连“生命”这样一个尽人皆知的词也没有明确的定义。人们通常用语言中很普遍的字词表示头脑中出现的大量混合观念，就算很不精确，也能很好的应付寻常交流和日常事务。但就专业用法来说，这是绝对不够的。知识和推理要求观念精准而确定。人们不会那么冥顽不灵，以至于必须问过他人所用词汇究竟为何意才能理解他人含义；也不会那么吹毛求疵，以至于必须去纠正他人对词汇的用法。但是，一旦涉及知识，就必须要就特定文字解释清楚，人们也不必为自己的无知感到羞愧，因为如果不了解别人的说辞用意为何，开口询问也无可厚非。这种文字的滥用在学者之间最为常见，影响也最为恶劣。这些争论如此繁复顽固，阻碍我们通往知识的道路，这都是由于文字的滥用造成的。虽然人们大多认为，让人迷惑的，是书中不同的观念和种类繁多的争论，但是我却认为，这主要是由于不同学派的学者用语不同。我更愿意相信，如果他们能撇开用词，就事论事，就会发现他们的观念原是一样的，只不过表达有所不同。

23.语言的作用首先是表达观点

下面总结一下语言的缺陷和滥用。在我们同他人交谈时，语言的作用主要有三：一、让别人了解自己的想法和观点；二、尽量简单快速做到第一点；三、传播知识。如果以上三点中有任意一点做不到，语言就必然发生了滥用，出现缺陷。

一、出现以下三种情况时，文字就做不到第一点，不能把一个人的观念传达给另一个人。（1）人们口中的名称表示不确定的观念；（2）把不能表示某观念的名称硬套在该观念之上；（3）名称的使用并不确定，时而代表此观念，时而代表彼观念。

24.其次，快速传达观念

二、对于复杂观念，如果没有确切的名称来表示，就不能简单快速地表达自己的想法。有时这是文字本身的缺陷，因为文字没有表达对应意义的发音；有时是人为的滥用，因为他想要表示这一观念，却不了解这观念的名称。

25.第三是传播知识

三、如果人们的观念同现实事物不一致，那么语言就不能传播知识。虽然这原是由于我们的观念不能准确无误地反映事物的本质（缺乏专注、研究和运用所致），但是这个缺陷也会扩散到文字的使用上，我们以为文字代表了事物的本质，但实际上这种本质却不存在。

26.人们在使用语言时何以做不到上述三点

情况一：如果人们在使用文字时，脑中没有清晰的观念，那么他们在交谈中传达出的只是没有任何意义的噪音。不管他们使用多么晦涩的词汇，显得多么博学，他们的知识也没有增加。同理，正如有些人看书，只看书名，不看内容，知识也不会增加。因为，不管他们在对话中怎么使用这些字词，是依照语法结构还是润饰措辞，它们都不能表意，只是发音罢了。

27.情况二：如果人们只有一些复杂观念，却没有命名，那么这就等于，书商库房里有很多书，但都是散页的，没有书名，要想让别人知道书里讲的是什么，只能把书页拿给他们看，或自己讲给他们听。由于不知用什么字词来表示复杂观念，人们的交谈就会出现障碍，只能罗列构成这些复杂观念的简单观念，这样，别人用一句话就能说清的问题，他可能用二十句才能表达清楚。

28.情况三：在学派和交谈中使用文字，如果用同一名称表示不同观念，有时表示此种意义，有时表示彼种意义，那么这种做法正如在集市做买卖，一个名称能代表很多物品，两者都有失公平。

29.情况四：如果人们对某种语言的使用，有异于把这种语言当作母语的国家的用法，那么纵使他们有正确又清晰的理解，如果不对文字加以界定，也不能传达自己的思想。因为，即使听者对文字的读音十分熟悉，可是同一文字表示的却是不同观念，那么这些文字也不会对听者形成任何刺激，听者也就不能了解说者的观念。

30.情况五：如果人们想象自然界中不存在的事物，在脑中形成相应的观念，并给这些想象中的事物命名，那么在他的言语中，甚至在对方的头脑中就会形成一种幻念，这于现实中的知识是无益的。

31.如果空有名称却没有相应的观念，那么文字就空有读音，没有意义；如果复杂观念没有命名，那么在表达时就不能自如，解释起来就要大费周章；如果用词不严谨、反复无常，那么就不能引人注意，不能让人理解；如果措辞与大众不同，语言没有适用性，那么就等同胡言乱语；如果所言之物不存于世，理解中缺乏真材实料，那么只是自身的幻想。

32.在实体方面，文字何以失其功效

在实体观念方面，我们也容易出现以上五种问题。比如：（1）在使用“狼蛛”一词时，如果不知道它代表什么意思，就算读音再正确，也没有任何意义。（2）人们在新大陆可能会发现前所未见的动植物，虽然也能形成像马和雄鹿那样的真实观念，但是人们只能用语言加以描述，除非用土著人使用的名称称呼它们，或自己给它们命名。（3）如果时而用“物体”表示单纯的区域，时而用它来表示区域及固体，那么就会出现谬误。（4）如果把通常说的“骡子”叫作“马”，就不合适了，而且也不会有人理解。（5）如果认为“人马兽”是实在的事物，那么就是自欺欺人，把文字当作了事物本身。

33.在情状和关系方面，文字何以失其功效

在情状和关系方面，我们常犯的错误是前四个。（1）记得一些情状的名称，比如“感恩”或“慈善”，但头脑中没有确切的观念与之相符。（2）拥有一些观念，却不知道对应的名称是什么。比如，一个人喝酒了，面色改变，脾气变差，舌头打结，眼睛发红，脚上发飘，我知道这种状态，却不知道用“醉态”这个词来表示。（3）知道善恶为何，也知道它们的名称，但是却会误用。比如，用“节俭”表示“贪婪”之意。（4）在使用名称时，意义没有保持一致。（5）但是，就情状和关系来说，不会出现观念与实物不一致的情况。因为情状是头脑随意形成的复杂观念，而关系只是对两种物体的考量和比较。这两方面都是自我形成的观念，同外物无关。它们不是外物投射在头脑中的副本，也不是物体内部构成或本质的性质，而是存在于脑中的模式，就一定的行为和关系进行命名。这方面的错误，只是给自己的观念起错了名字，导致文字的使用与他人不同，使得别人不能理解我的观念，进而使得别人认为我的观念是错误的。若我在混合情状观念或关系观念中加入不合理的观念，我就是在幻想。因为，如果仔细考察一下这些观念，就会发现，它们根本不可能存在于头脑之中，更不可能指称任何实体事物。

34.第七，比喻也是对语言的滥用

机智和想象比枯燥的真理和实在的知识更动人。因此，人们不愿承认，比喻和隐喻也是一种语言的缺陷和滥用。我也承认，在交谈时，如果是为了追求愉悦，而不是为了获取知识，那么比喻和隐喻就不能算是错误。然而，如果我们要原原本本地描述事物，使用修辞方法（次序和明细除外）或演讲中运用文字的那一套，都会转而产生错误观念，煽动情感，误导判断，因此就是完美的骗局。所以，这一套在雄辩和演讲中也许是可行的，但是如果交谈的目的是传播知识、有所教益，那么就应该加以避免。若涉及真理和知识，那么这种用法，要么是语言本身的错误，要么就是语言使用者的过错。修辞用法多种多样，这里我们不必讨论。如果读者想加以学习，可以去找相关书籍，简直多不胜数。不过，人们太不注意保护利用真理和知识了，因为修辞这种用法与生俱来，而且还得到人们的喜爱。修辞学可谓是错误和欺骗的有力工具。有人加以研习，公开教授，且这种学术受人喜爱，足可见人们大多喜欢欺骗别人，被欺骗了也不自知。因此，我这样反对修辞学，人们肯定会认为我蒙昧无知、冒失粗俗。雄辩就如美人，过于美丽，不容亵渎。既然人们甘愿被骗，那么对欺骗的艺术挑错就太费力不讨好了。

前述缺陷及滥用的补救方法

1.补救方法值得我们寻求

前面我们详述过语言本身的缺陷及人们强加给它的缺陷。语言是连接我们整个社会的纽带，也是知识传播及传承的媒介，因此，我们需要谨慎思考，找到补救上述缺陷的方法。

2.寻求补救方法并不容易

我想，任谁说自己能改变世界上的某种语言或是改变本国的语言，都会受到他人嘲讽，因此没人会这样说。要求人们用始终如一的文字表达同一含义，也就是确信统一的观念，就等于认为人们观念相同，而且人们只能谈论确信的事物。任何人都不能如此要求，因为谁都不能让别人无所不知或缄口不言。如果有人认为巧舌如簧者必学识丰富，认为所言不多者必知之甚少，那么此人就涉世太浅了。

3.对于哲学来说，这些补救方法是必需的

虽然我们要允许生意人有生意人的交谈方式，承认街谈巷议也有存在的必然，虽然学术之人可能认为我们提出的供其减少争议的方法是错误的，但是我认为，如果人们愿意寻求真理，维护真理，就应该思考如何清楚明白地表达自己的观点，因为稍不注意，人们的语言就会变得含混不清，模棱两可。

4.错用文字导致重大错误

既然文字的滥用如此普遍，造成那么多错误和误解，那么人们就有理由怀疑，文字的使用，究竟是促进了还是阻碍了知识的传播呢？很多人在进行思考时，特别是针对品行问题进行思考时，总是只关注文字。此时，沉思推理过后的结果只是文字的声音而已，相关的观念都是含混的、不定的，甚至从未产生。所以，思考和推理常以含混和错误告终，并未产生确切的判断和知识。

5.固执

人们独自思考时，若用错了文字，必然会有一定的不便。但是，在同他人对话或争辩时用错文字，就会带来很多混乱。因为语言就是纽带，人们通过语言将新发现告诉彼此，互相推理，传递知识。语言的误用虽然不会堵塞知识的泉眼（因为知识存在于事物本身、语言之外），却会堵住或破坏知识传输的管道，使知识不能得到广泛传播，惠及人类。若在使用文字时没有清晰明确的意义，只能使自己和他人陷入错误之中。而刻意误用文字的人本身就是真理和知识的大敌。但是，毋庸置疑，科学和部分知识的名称和表述都是含混不定的，使得那些最为专注和眼快之人都不能有所提高。这是因为，那些自命传授与维护真理的人认为区分细微之别是一种能力，但是这种能力却基本等同于使用含混误导的词语，使人们被无知蒙住双眼，对错误固执不放。

6.争论

不管看任何有关争论的书，都能发现，那些含混不清、模棱两可的词语只是噪声和争吵的声响，并不能加强人们的理解。因为，说者和听者并没有就文字代表的观念达成一致，他们的争吵不是针对事物，而是针对名称。因此，如果人们对文字的定义不同，那么在使用这一文字时，他们理解的对象就不是一个实体，而只是声音。他们使用的文字虽然相同，但是文字代表的对象却是不同的。

7.举例：蝙蝠和鸟类

蝙蝠到底属不属于鸟类，并不是一个问题。若要问蝙蝠这个名称是不是应该用于其他生物，蝙蝠是否还具有其他特质，简直是荒谬。但是两类人会问这些问题：一类人并不完全了解这两个词代表的概念，此时就要去调查“鸟类”和“蝙蝠”的本质，补全他们的概念。看一看，他们称作“鸟类”的事物包含的所有简单观念是否都在“蝙蝠”身上有所体现。然而，这只涉及调查，并不涉及确定和否认。另一类人是互相争执的人。他们会就究竟“蝙蝠”是不是“鸟类”产生争执。此时问题就出在这两个词的所指上。双方可能认为这两个名称包含的复杂观念不同。如果双方就两个名称的所指达成一致，就不会产生争执。因为，他们很快就会清楚地辨别，“鸟类”这个类别名词中所有的简单观念是否都能在“蝙蝠”这个复杂观念中找到，此时就不会再去怀疑“蝙蝠”究竟属不属于“鸟类”了。在这里，我想让大家思考一下，是不是世界上争执的大部分都是文字层面的，是不是都是因为人们对文字的所指理解不同，是不是只要确定了文字的意义，使它们代表应该或本来的简单观念集合，这些争执就会自然终结，立即消失呢？大家可以想一下，争执的意义为何，争执对彼此有什么好处呢？如果有人能剥去语言含混模糊的外衣（其实每个人在自己使用文字时都是如此），我会认为他是传播知识、维护真理与和平的英雄，而非虚荣、野心和学派的奴隶。

8.补救方法之一：不用无意义字词

为了从某种程度上弥补上文提到的缺陷，防止缺陷带来的不便，可以先遵从以下几条原则，等待有能力之人创造出更成熟的文字体系，来惠及世界。

第一，在使用无所指字词及无意义名称时需谨慎。这些词语包括“直觉”“同情”和“憎恶”等，在用这些词时人们心中并没有具体观念，只是发音，并未表意。只要大家想一想对话中使用这类词的频率，就会发现这条原则还是十分必要的。并不是说这些词在正确使用时不能表意，而是这些文字和观念并无自然联系。人们死记硬背、生搬硬套，并不能用它们代表任何观念。而人们若想表意，必须使文字有所指。

9.补救方法二：人们用文字表达情状时也要有意义

第二，仅仅把文字作为表达观念的符号是不够的，若表达的观念是简单的，则必须清晰而不同于其他；若表达的观念是复杂的，则必须确切。也就是说，若决定用一个词语表示简单观念的组合，则用以表示的符号只能表示这一个组合，而不表示其他。这在情状名称方面，特别是品行词语方面，十分必要。因为这些词语并不是对自然界中物体的所指，没有确定的原型，所以十分容易弄混。人们都在谈论“正义”，但对“正义”的意义却各执一词。若要避免这种情况，则人们心中要对“正义”有确切的理解，知道这个复杂观念包括什么，可以将这个复杂观念分解为一个个简单观念。否则，不管是“正义”，还是其他词语的使用都会发生错误。这并不是说，每当人们在使用“正义”这个词时都要先分析一番，但是，考察名称的意义却是必要的，然后把具体观念存在头脑中，在需要时启用。若对“正义”的定义是“按照法律处置人或物”，而“法律”这个词语的本身却没有清晰的概念，那么“正义”这个复杂观念就会是含糊残缺的。然而，要达到确切性是十分复杂的。因此，很多人会认为即使对混合情状名称没有那么精准的观念也是可以原谅的。但是，如果不做到如此精准，人们心中还是会有很多混乱和模糊，同别人交谈时也会发生很多争执。

10.文字要和实体相一致

要正确使用实体名称，只有确定的观念是不够的，这些名称还必须和具体事物相一致。关于这点，我后面会详细阐述。在探寻哲学知识和争论真理时，必须要保证准确。如果这种准确性能扩展到普通对话和日常生活中自然是好的，但是却不太可行。通俗的观念适合通俗的谈话，两者虽然都很含混，但是在市场交易和红白之事中却很适用。既然行商、谈情说爱、烹饪、裁衣都有专属的表达，那么哲学家和抗辩家若想理解他人并得到理解，也应该有自己的一套表达。

11.补救方法三：注意适用性

第三，人们仅用文字表示观念是不够的，哪怕是确定的观念，也是不够的。还必须尽可能使自己的文字所表达的观念同人们普遍认为的相一致。文字，特别是业已形成的语言，并不是某个人的私有财产，而是交易交流的公共尺度。任何人不得随意更改特定表达方式，或文字代表的观念，就算情非得已必须更改，也要事先告知他人。人们之所以表达，就是为了得到理解。如果不按寻常用法来使用，就要不断地解释、询问和打断，这会造成很多不便。语言的适用性可以使我们轻而易举地理解别人，因此，我们必须费些心思加以研究。对待品行文字方面，尤应如此。要了解文字的所指和使用最好通过学习，学习那些能在写作和交谈中清楚表达自己观念的人，他们往往在遣词造句时十分恰当。依据语言的适用性来使用文字，即使不能每次都有幸得到理解，但是就算不被理解也罪在他人，因为我们已经依据适用性来使用，所以他本该理解，如果不能理解，则只怪他自己对语言体系不熟悉了。

12.补救方法四：清晰表意

第四，人们在日常使用文字时，并没有明确它们的含义，使人们确切地知道文字究竟代表什么意义。随着知识的增长，人们的观念会慢慢异于通俗观念，为此人们通常需要创造新文字（人们很少这样做，因为怕被别人认为矫揉造作或标新立异），或赋予旧文字新含义。因此，在遵从前述规则之后，确定文字的含义，清晰示人是很必要的。因为，习惯会使文字的含义不确定、不精确（常见于复杂观念），有时在交谈中，重要词语会变得模糊，出现错误。

13.要清晰表意，有三条途径

人们可用文字表达的观念种类有所不同，所以表达观念的方式在不同场合之下也应有所区分。虽然加以界定可以使文字表意清晰，但有些文字是不能界定的，正如有些文字，必须通过界定才能表意明确一样。还有一种，兼具以上两种特点，这可见于简单观念、情状及物体名称之中。

14.首先，用同义词或实物表示简单观念

第一，人们在使用简单观念名称时，若认为名称不易理解或易被误解，那么出于语言的清晰特性，出于交流的目的，就必须明示名称的意义，告诉他人名称代表的观念是什么。如前所述，这是不能通过界定来完成的。因此，如果同义词不能加以解释，就只剩一种方式了，那就是同实物相联系。有时，名称表示的观念体现在实物中，此时，如果他人熟悉此种物体，就会理解这一名称。比如，要让一个乡下人明白什么是“黄棕色”，只要告诉他那是秋天里枯叶的颜色就好了。但是要明示简单观念名称含义，最保险的方式还是把实体展示出来，使他人有相应的概念。

15.其次，界定混合情状名词含义

第二，混合情状，特别是品行混合情状，大部分都是观念的集合，是由头脑自由组合的，没有特定模式，因此相关的名称不能像简单观念名称一样，通过用实物表示的方式明示出来，不过，混合情状名词可以得到完全准确的界定。因为这些名称都是头脑任意组合而成的观念集合，并没有参考任何原型，因此人们可以明确知道这些集合由哪些观念构成，在使用时就确信无疑，在必要时，就可以声明这些集合的意义为何。因此，人们在谈论道德相关的问题时，如果不能做到清晰明确，就应当受到责备。混合情状名称并不是自然形成的，而是人们界定的，人们悉知其确切意义，所以在谈论道德相关问题时若仍然含混不清，就过于疏忽固执。而在谈论自然之物时，这是可以原谅的，因为同人们界定的名称相反，描述本存之物时含混是难免的。这点我们在后面将会看到。

16.品行可以证实

由此，我可以推出，品行和数学一样，是可以证实的。我们可以完全知晓品行文字表示的确切本质，也可以发现事物之间到底相不相符。人们也许会反驳：在品行学中，我们不止运用实体名称，还运用品行名称，这会产生一些含混。这种反驳是站不住脚的，因为在品行范畴的交谈中，我们很少探寻实体的各种不同本质。比如，我们在说“人要受到法律的制裁”时，我们所指的“人”，只是一种有形的理性生物，至于“人”的其他性质，我们并不予以考虑。因此，自然学家争论儿童或低能儿在物理意义上是否为“人”，并不妨碍品行上涉及的“人”。在品行范畴内，“人”的意义是有形的理性生物，这是确定不改的。如果我们发现猴子或其他生物能够推理，理解普通符号，从概括观念中推出结论，那么不管它们同“人”的外形多么不同，都受制于法律，属于“人”。如果运用得当，实体名称并不会扰乱品行名称，正如它们不会扰乱数学范畴一样（数学家在谈到黄金的立方体、黄金球，或其他物体时，有一个明确的不变的观念，但有时也会把这一观念错用于不适当的物体之上）。

17.界定使品行范畴的交谈变得清晰

我提到这点，是为了指出，人们在品行范畴交谈中使用混合情状名称时，对文字加以界定是很重要的，因为品行范畴的知识可以借助定义，变得清晰确定。如果做不到这层，就有失聪颖，因为界定是明确品行范畴文字意义的唯一方式，不容争辩。因此，如果人们在品行方面的讨论与自然哲学方面的讨论相较有失清晰，那么他们的疏忽和固执则不可原谅。因为在品行方面，人们讨论的是头脑中的观念，没有外物原型得以参照和比对，所以不存在虚假和不充分一说。人们在头脑中形成一个观念，把这一观念作为“正义”一词的标准，将符合标准的行为都归于这一词下，并不困难。难的是，在看到了阿里斯蒂德斯（Aristides）以后，去形成一个贴近该人的观念，因为不管人们形成的观念如何，阿里斯蒂德斯的本质都不变。就前者来说，只消知道观念的组合便可；而就后者来说，必须要探寻外物的本质、背后的构成及不同的性质。

18.界定是唯一的方法

混合情状名称，特别是品行词语的界定十分必要，另一个原因就是我上文提到的：只有加以界定，它们的意义才能得以确定。因为它们代表的观念组成大多杂乱无章，头脑将其聚合并形成特定观念，只有用文字把这些简单观念列举出来，才能使他人知晓，观念的名称代表什么。在这种情况下，感官并不能提供可感物帮助我们，也不能指示给我们某类名称表示何种观念。但就可感简单观念及实体（某种程度上）来说，感官往往可以帮助我们了解它们的名称。

19.第三，用实物表示或界定实体观念

第三，实体名称表示的是我们对特定物种的观念，要解释它们的意义，就要用到上述两种方法：实物表示及界定。通常，每种物体都有特定主要性质，此外还有其他一些附属性质，对这些性质的观念共同构成我们的复杂观念。因此，只要具有特征性标记，区别于其他物体，那么我们就会赋予这种物体相应的名称。就动植物而言，这种主要观念或标记性观念多为形状；就无生命物体而言，多为颜色；就其他一些物体而言，二者兼有。

20.观察是获知物体主要性质观念的最佳方法

这些主要可感性质是构成我们具体观念的原材料，因此，在我们定义名称时，它们也是最容易观察到，最不易变化的部分。尽管“人”就本质上来说代表的是动物和理性的统一，但是在我们的观念中，外形和其他因素一样，也是必备的。因此，很难说柏拉图对“人”的定义（无羽、宽甲、双足）不好，因为外形是一种主要性质，比推理能力更具有决定作用，因为推理能力在人初生之时很少显露，或许有人一生都不曾具备。如果否定柏拉图的定义，仅仅因为某异形生物的外形和“人”不同，而不问它是否有理性的灵魂，就将它杀死，就和谋杀无异了。这就像区别发育良好的婴儿和畸形儿，我们也不能判断他们是否有灵魂。此外，也没有人规定理性灵魂的居所必须有前庭，外形必须有所定式。

21.观察是获知这些主要性质的最好方法，此外别无他法。比如，若用文字描述“马匹”或“鹤鸵”的形状，则人们脑中形成的图片既粗略又不完整。然而，只要看一眼实物，形成的观念就会比文字描述好一千倍。再比如“黄金”，任何描述都不足以表达这一概念，只要用眼睛看到，就会形成清晰的观念。那些经常同黄金打交道的人，一眼便可识出真假纯杂，而外行人（虽然视力很好，但是却不能辨别黄金的颜色同别的黄色有何不同）却看不出其中的区别。其他实体具有的简单观念同样如此，而这些精确的观念，往往没有具体的名称。比如黄金敲打的声响同其他物体不同，但是却没有具体的名称，正如它具有的特殊的黄色，也没有相应的名称一样。

22.界定是获知物体能力的最好方法

我们对于实体的具体观念所包含的很多简单观念都关于能力，通过我们的感官并不能轻易捕获。因此，有些物体名称的意义最好通过列举相关简单观念来告知他人，而非仅仅把实物展示出来。比如，如果一个人仅仅看到黄金，对之的观念就是一个金灿灿的物体，而我的描述包括延展性、可熔性、固定性及溶于王水，这会让他对黄金有更加完整的概念。如果这种闪亮、有一定重量及延展性的物体的本质构成像三角形一样易于感知，那么黄金这种物质也会如三角形一样易于分辨。

23.对于灵魂相关知识的反思

由此可见，我们对于有形之物的知识都是建立在感官之上的。因此，对于脱离了实体的灵魂，我们并不知道它们如何获得这些知识（它们的知识应该比我们的更加完全）。我们的知识和想象的广度不会超过我们的观念，是局限于我们认知方式之内的。比我们肉体之躯高级的灵魂也许能够了解物体的构成，就像我们对三角形的了解一样清晰，也许灵魂能看到物体的性质与内部运作。但是我们永远不可能得知它们获得这些知识的方式。

24.实体观念须同具体事物相一致

实体名称代表着我们的观念，所以可以通过界定进行解释，但是，这些名称同样代表各实体，所以界定也会留下一些缺陷。毕竟实体名称不仅代表了我们的观念，最终还是要代表具体事物，这就要求名称的意义必须同事物的真实状况以及人们的观念相符。因此，就实体而言，我们不能仅仅停留在文字表示复杂观念上，应该进一步去探究实体自身的本质和性质，这样才能进一步完善我们对这种实体的观念，又或从熟悉这种实体的旁人处获知这些本质。按常理，实体的名称不仅应该代表人们心中的复杂观念，更应该代表实体中真实存在的各简单观念，因此想要正确界定实体的名称，必须探究博物志，在仔细审查后，得出它们的具体性质。因为，在针对自然实体进行对话和辩论时，为了避免各种不便，仅仅了解语言的常规使用是不够的，因为在常规使用中，文字表示的观念往往含混而不完整，仅仅使名称符合特定场合的应用也是不够的。我们还应该熟悉实体的历史，来修正并巩固我们具体名称相应的复杂观念。在同他人交谈时，如果发现自己被误解，应该告诉对方具体名称代表的复杂观念为何。对于那些追求知识和真理的人来说，更应如此。因为在儿童时期，人们对事物的观念还不完整，却已然开始习得文字，不经太多思考便随意使用，并未形成与之确切对应的观念。人们会一直将这种习惯延续至成年，因为这种习惯并没有影响他们的日常生活和交谈。然而，这套程序自开始就是错误的，不应该先习得文字，再形成与之对应的观念。由此，我们看到，人们在使用本国语言时总是符合语法规则的，但是在谈到事物本身时却经常出错。所以，在针对真理和知识发生争辩时，人们总是很少有所进展，因为真理和知识存在于事物本身，而非我们的主观想象。因此，仅了解事物的名称实则对我们知识的增长并无助益。

25.要使实体观念和具体事物相一致并不容易

因此我们希望，精通物理性质研究、熟悉各类自然实体的人可以把各类实体共通的简单观念逐条记下，这将消除很多混乱。因为人们对各种事物的熟悉程度不同，了解的性质也多少不一，如果使用同一名称就会造成很多误解。但是，将各观念逐条记录、编辑成典，几乎是不可能的，因为这会耗费很多人力、物力、财力。在这项大工程完成之前，只要我们能做到在使用时界定清楚就够了。如果人们在必要时能做到这一点，自然是很好的，但是这点也很难做到。我们在交谈和争论时，所用的文字意义并不统一，然而我们却误以为日常使用的文字意义已然确定，以为文字所代表的观念也众所周知，此刻加以询问便显示出自己的无知，所以便错用开来。但实际上，所有复杂观念名称的意义都是不确定的，也并非从一而终代表同一观念。如果没有获得必要的解释，那么我们缺少对一些事情的特定知识并不丢人。所以，就算不知道某个声音在别人心中代表什么观念，也不丢脸，因为别人并未告知我们，而离了他们的解释，我们便无从得知。在交流中，语言是必要的，所以人们一定程度上就日常用语的意义达成一致，以便于日常对话。如果人们熟悉一种语言，就不会对文字的通俗用法一无所知。但通俗用法也不是完全确定的，代表的也是某一人群的观念，因此作为标准来说，也是可变的。现下要编纂上面提到的字典也许费时、费财、费力，但是我认为，对于那些依赖外表得以区别的实体来说，画成草图装订成册也无可厚非。如此一来，就能更容易、更便捷地教给他人词语的意义（特别是其他国家和不同时代的词语），这样，我们就不用再通过著名批评家长篇累牍的评论来了解先贤观念的本真了。自然学家将会从图册中获益良多，只需稍加询问，他们就会坦言，对罂粟和野山羊之类的动植物，看图比读定义来的清楚明白。如果不用“痒痒挠”和“铜钹”解释古时候用的“马栉”和“叉铃”，而是配以图示，那么人们就会有更清楚的观念。虽然罗马时代的“宽袍”“罩衫”和“披肩”被翻译成了“袍子”“外套”和“斗篷”，但是我们对这些服饰特点还是没有什么概念，正如我们对这些服饰的裁缝师也没什么概念一样。如此云云，若实体的形状可以靠眼睛区别，最好能用图画描绘，这样比用文字描述更加到位。

26.补救方法五：文字的意义要前后一致

第五，如果人们不愿费事表明他们文字的含义，又没有对文字界定，在传教和交谈中，他们至少应该保持文字意义的前后一致。如果大家都能做到这一点，便可省下很多书籍，也能终止很多争端，一些充满隐晦辞藻的典籍也可加以浓缩，很多哲人和诗人的作品也能得以提炼。

27.何时对意义的变化加以解释

毕竟，同人们无限的思想相比，语言文字还是略显贫乏。人们想要准确表达自己的观念，就算谨慎有加，也不可避免会用相同文字表示不同意义。在交谈和争论中，尽管人们在变更词义时，可能没有机会重新定义，但人们若不是故意混淆视听，公正聪明的读者都能大致明白其中的含义。不过如果读者因此不能领会真正的意图，则作者应该加以解释，表明自己使用的词语是何意义。

译者导读

在西方文学中，厌女症（misogyny，或译为女性贬抑）由来已久。简而言之，这是一种在文学作品中歪曲事实、诟病女性并把一切罪过都归因到女性身上的思想。例如将女性说成是劣等子宫的产物，以及认为女性是人类罪恶的根源，甚至连男性的堕落也完全是由女性造成的，等等。这种对于女性的贬低由古希腊文学发端，贯穿了西方文学和宗教史，18、19世纪的哲学大师康德、黑格尔、叔本华和尼采等，也都曾在著作中表现出对女性的厌恶。

本书正是写作于14世纪这样一个视女性为敌并肆意贬低践踏的时代。克里斯蒂娜·德·皮桑（Christine de Pizan，1365—1430），出生于早期文艺复兴时代的威尼斯，幼年随受聘于法王查理五世的父亲搬到法国，在宫廷中长大。她被公认为是欧洲历史上第一位以写作为生的职业女作家，其诗歌和散文在她所处的时代就已得到高度评价。但是不同于文艺复兴时期的人文主义文学家和艺术家，克里斯蒂娜的作品并非系统地研究或阐释反封建思想，而是通过贴近现实生活的思考，从社会实际出发，以通俗易懂的方式提出了一些具有启蒙性的观点。

在本书中，她将女性划分为淑女（ladies）和一般女性（women），并用纸墨为前者建立了一个理想王国。被选入这个文字城市的女性并非由出身门第决定，而是因为各自具有过人的美德，如智慧、勇敢、忠贞、慷慨、虔诚，等等。她通过列举一百多位从神话传说到现实生活中具有过人才智和优秀品质的女性，来逐一驳斥历来男性作者们对女性各方面能力和特质的扭曲，代替女性群体发出了自信的呼声。与此同时，她也并未放弃在能力和修养上尚有待努力的广大一般女性，在书的最后，她呼吁全体女性都按照自己的社会地位，以美德和城中淑女为榜样和目标去完善自己及自己的生活。

当时社会对女性的定位，是传统道德中的辅助作用，如协助丈夫管理庄园、财产和仆人，勤俭持家，帮助丈夫匡正品行等，因此她劝诫女性们要遵循这些准则，逃离爱情的骗局，端正谈吐、谨言慎行。同时她承认社会等级的差异，建议贵族、中产阶级和平民女性都按照各自的社会阶层来扶助甚至容忍丈夫，以达到家庭的和睦和生活的平静。在书中，由代表着女性三种美德的理性、正直和公正女神指导克里斯蒂娜用智慧的铁锹挖走诟病的腐土、以历代淑女的事迹为基石所建立起来的“淑女之城”，正是她理想中可以彰显女性光辉、并从无端指责中保护她们的完美之地。

时至今日，女性如何在事业进取心与家庭责任感、职业发展与家庭生活之间取得平衡，依旧是时常困扰她们的问题。除了制度和文化的因素之外，女性对于自身潜能的肯定、摒除对于自身定位的内心障碍，充满自信地积极进取，方是最重要的内在条件和动力。因此，回溯克里斯蒂娜这部在男性占统治地位的社会中，敢于率先展现女性优良品质、提高女性对自己性别的自信和自觉的先驱性作品，对于我们今天思考女性如何规划自己独特的人生轨迹、追求恰当的人生目标，如何与男性互相配合实现社会的两性平等与和谐，依然有着重要的启示意义。

第一部分

1.由此开始《淑女之城》的第一章，讲述本书写作的缘由与目的

一日，我如常坐在书房中被各类书籍包围着，因为追求知识已成了我长久以来的习惯。在跟研习已久的几位作者的鸿篇巨著奋战了一整日之后，我开始感到有些厌倦。我从书中抬起头，决定放下这些艰深的大作，转向诗人的作品来找点浅显有趣的读物。在寻找部头小点的书时，我刚巧看到了一本虽不属于我但正由我保管着的书。我打开书，看到作者是马太奥鲁斯[1]就笑着选了它，因为虽然没读过，但听说过这本书跟其他书不同，是赞扬女性的。这时碰巧到了晚饭时间，我几乎还没有开始看，亲爱的妈妈就已经叫我下楼吃饭了。我于是放下它，决定第二天再读。

第二天早上，我再次习惯性地坐在书房里，想起了前一日打算看看的马太奥鲁斯的那本书，于是再次拿起书读了一点。但是看到它俗不可耐的言语和内容，我觉得大概只有那些喜欢看造谣中伤的人才会对此感兴趣，而对那些希望追求美德或改进自身道德标准的人来说，应该是毫无裨益的。我快速浏览到结尾，然后决定转向那些更有价值和裨益的作品。但因为看过了这本我认为没什么权威性的书，一个离奇的想法在我脑海中开始生根，并让我想弄明白，到底为什么这么多男人，包括有学识的男人在内，长久以来都针对女人和她们的作风不断记述着如此可怕的东西。我无法解释这一点。这不只是一小批作者，也不只是马太奥鲁斯这本既不权威又不会被认真看待的书，而是不可计数的哲学家、诗人和演说家都持有的态度，他们众口一词、毫无异议地认为，女人的天性就是容易屈服于恶习。

我一遍一遍地思考着这些观念，然后开始检视自身和行为，并以此为例。为了毫无偏见地公平判断这么多著名的男人是否是错的，我也回想了一下我认识的其他女性，包括很多贵妇以及不计其数的社会各阶层的女性们，她们都曾跟我分享过个人内心的想法。不论我怎么看、如何想这个问题，我都依旧无法从生活中找到任何证据来证明这个对女性天性和习惯的负面评价。即使如此，由于我几乎找不到任何作者的任何一本道德方面的书里没有那么几个章节在攻击女性，我不得不接受了他们对女人不利的意见，因为这么多有学识、有着杰出智慧和对事物有见地的男人，不太可能在这么多地方都撒了谎。基于这个简单的论点，我不得不承认这些男人应该是对的，尽管我的理解还很粗浅，并且仍然没有看到我和其他女人身上存在的重大缺陷。比起自己的判断和经验，我就这样相信了他人得出的结论。

我长时间反复地咀嚼着这些想法，以至于陷入了深度的恍惚。当我试图回忆所有写过这类主题的作者时，脑中充满了无数的名字。我于是得出结论，当神创造女人时，他的确是创造了一件卑下的事物。我震惊于这样一位精细的造物主居然会作出这样一个骇人听闻的东西，它就如这些作者所说的那样，是一个收集和保存所有罪孽与邪恶的容器。这个想法让我极其难过和恶心，于是我因为这些天性上的偏差开始鄙视我自己以及所有女性了。

随着一声长叹，我向神呼唤道：“主啊，这怎么可能？除非承认信仰的错误，否则我不能怀疑您会在您无限的智慧和无瑕的好意之中，去创造任何不好的东西。难道不是您特地亲手创造了女人，然后给了她所有您希望她拥有的品质吗？但女人不仅仅是被指控了，而且已经被审判、定罪和判决了！我只是不能理解这个矛盾而已。主啊，如果女人真的如众多男人所指责的那样，是如此可怕的罪孽，并且如您自己所说的两个以上的证人即可定罪[2]的话，我还怎么能够去怀疑他们所说的话？主啊，为什么我没有生为男人，这样我所有的渴望就是去服侍您，把万事都做正确，以成为男人们所自称的完美生物？既然您决定了不给予我这样的慈悲，亲爱的主，那么若我没能像所应当的那样去服侍您，就请原谅我和赦免我，因为报酬低的仆人对主人负有的义务也相应更少。”

我十分难过地在对神的哀叹中说了许多类似的傻话，因为我觉得我非常不幸地被他赋予了女儿身。

2.克里斯蒂娜讲述3位淑女是如何现身以及第一位是如何开口安慰悲痛中的她的

我沉浸在痛苦的思绪中，脸颊贴着手靠在椅子扶手上，满含泪水羞愧地低下头。突然之间，我看到一道如日光般的光线照射到腿上。我像从熟睡中惊醒那样吃了一惊，因为在这个时间太阳是不可能照进我书房的。在我抬头追寻光的源头时，眼前忽然出现了3位头戴皇冠的淑女，她们穿戴举止庄重，面庞散发的光芒照亮了我和我身边的一切。你可以想象，当看到她们能如此直接进入一个门窗紧闭的屋子时，我该有多么惊诧。我害怕是幽灵要引诱我，于是迅速地在额前画了个十字。

3位淑女中最前方的一位率先笑着跟我说道：“我亲爱的孩子，别害怕。我们不是来伤害你的，正相反，我们是由于怜悯你的不幸，来安慰你的。你仅仅因为有太多的人反对，就去否定那些自己确信的真理，我们希望能够帮你摆脱这些困扰着你的误解。你就像是笑话里的傻瓜，朋友们趁他在磨坊里睡着时给他穿上了女人的衣服，醒来之后设法让他相信了自己是女人，尽管一切的证据都指向了相反的那面！我亲爱的孩子，你的判断力到哪里去了？你忘记百炼才能成金的道理了吗？你忘记只有最美好的事物才最惹人争议了吗？现在把你的思路转到最高层次的领域，也就是抽象领域上，回想一下你所叙述的那些抨击女人的哲人们是否曾被证伪。事实上，他们都一直在互相攻击对方的观点，就像你读的亚里士多德的《形而上学》中，他是如何讨论和反对他人，包括柏拉图在内的观点的。也不要忘记‘教会圣师’们[3]，特别是被誉为最伟大的道德和自然哲学作者的圣奥古斯丁[4]，他们在某些问题上是全盘否定亚里士多德的。你似乎把哲学家的所有观点都当成是真理而无条件地完全接受了。”

“至于你提到的诗作，你得明白它们有时候写得和寓言一样，需要从字面意思的反面去理解。所以你应该按照反语法来读这些书，它有时候需要从正面去理解一些看似负面的话，有时候正相反。我建议你就照这样去读那些抨击女性的段落，不论作者原本的观点是什么，都把它们转化为正面的理解。马太奥鲁斯或许也正希望他的书是被这样去读的，因为他还有一些段落若只从字面上看简直就是彻底的异端邪说。至于当那些作者们——不仅是马太奥鲁斯，还包括更有权威的《玫瑰传奇》[5]的作者——在说神赐的神圣婚姻生活之所以让人无法忍受都是因为女人的时候，你的经验就应该已经告诉你他们是完全错误的了。哪个丈夫曾经如这些作者所说的那样，给予过妻子高于自己的权力，让她们可以来侮辱和玷污自己？相信我，无论你在书中读到什么，你都从未确实地看到这种事，因为它纯粹就是一些离谱的谎言。我亲爱的朋友，我必须说，是你的天真使你相信他们的话都是真理。找回你的判断力，别再用这些愚蠢的念头困扰你自己了。让我来告诉你，那些说女人坏话的人，对自己的伤害要远远超过对于他们所诟病的女人所造成的伤害。”

……

8.克里斯蒂娜讲解理性女神是如何帮助她开始挖地建地基的

理性女神回答我道：“现在站起来吧，孩子，让我们即刻前往文字之地。那里硕果累累、清溪流淌，充满了各种美好的事物，我们将在那平坦而丰饶的土地上建起淑女之城。拿好你智慧的铁锹，按照我划好的线深挖成壑，我会帮你把土扛走。”

我遵从她的指示站了起来：感谢这3位女神，我感觉身体比以前更强壮而轻盈了。她领头走在前面，我跟随着她到了所述的地点，按照指示开始用智慧的铁锹挖土。我劳动的第一个果实如下：“我的女神，我记得你之前用熔炉炼金来比喻那些男作者们对女人的全力攻击。我把这个比喻理解为，女人越被批判，她们的光彩就越被磨砺。但是请告诉我，为什么会有这么多作者在作品中攻击女人呢，因为如果我理解正确的话，这样做明明是错误的。这是天性女神让他们这么做的吗？如果说是因为憎恨，那又该怎么解释？”

理性女神回答我的问题道：“我亲爱的孩子，为了帮你把事情看得更清楚，让我把这第一筐土送走。我可以告诉你，天性女神绝没有让他们诟病女人，而是恰恰相反。世上没有什么会比天性女神遵照神的愿望赋予男女之间的联系更为牢固和紧密的了。实际上，有很多其他的原因可以解释为什么男人，包括那些你提到的作者们，一直以来都在攻击女人。有些人从好的意愿出发去批判女性：他们希望拯救那些被堕落的女人控制了的男人们，或者是防止其他人落入相同的命运，同时推而广之地鼓励男人们不要过贪婪和不道德的生活。他们因而攻击所有的女人，以试图说服男人们去反感女性这个性别。”

“我的女神，”我说道，“请原谅我打断你。他们因为有好的出发点，这么做就是对的了吗？人们行为的正误是由出发点所决定的吗？”

“你错了，好孩子，”她回答说，“因为单纯的无知是没有借口的。如果我出于好意和愚蠢而杀了你，我就是正确的了吗？无论是什么人，这么做都是在滥用他们的权力。为了第三方获利而去攻击另一方是不公平的。批判所有女人的天性也是一样完全没有道理的，我用类比来给你解释这一点。为了帮助一些误入歧途的男人放弃愚蠢的行为而去谴责所有的女人，就像火明明是维持生命所必需的好元素，只是因为有些人被烧伤了就去控告它一样，或者像因为有些人淹死了就去诅咒水一样。你可以把同样的道理推广到所有有着正反两面效果的事物上。在这种情况下，如果有蠢人错误地使用了它们，受到责备的都不应该是这些东西本身。你在自己的其他作品里已经指出过这一点了。那些坚持全盘否定看法的人，无论是出于好意还是恶意，都是为表达自己的观点而做过头了。这就像是有人拿整匹的布来给自己做一件巨大的外衣，仅仅因为它是免费的，也没有其他人出来反对。但这就阻止了其他人再来使用这匹布料。你自己其实也作过正确的评价：如果相反地，这些作者只是试图通过攻击那些确实有道德和习惯问题的人来拯救耽溺色欲的男人，我相信他们就能创作出非常有意义的作品来了。确实没有比一个放荡而堕落的女人更可怕的事物了：她就像是一个怪物，一个违背了她羞怯、温顺而纯洁的本性的生物。我可以向你保证，那些无视这么多高尚的妇女而去谴责女性有罪的作者们，绝对没有经过我的准许。他们自己铸成了大错，而那些相信了他们观点的人亦然。就让我们从你的著作中剔除这些可怕、丑陋又畸形的石头吧，因为它们在你美丽的城市里是不该有立足之地的。”

“其他男人则出于不同的理由批评女人：有些是因为他们自己沉浸在了罪恶中，有些是因为有生理障碍，有些纯粹是因为嫉妒，有些仅仅是喜欢从诽谤他人中获得乐趣。还有一些人这么做是想炫耀自己的博学：他们在书中看到了这些观点，就想引用这些作者的话。”

“那些批判女人生来即为邪恶的人，正是一些把青春浪费在了放浪形骸上、跟不同的女人有过风流韵事的男人。这些男人从各种经历中学会了狡诈，而且从不去忏悔自己的行为。他们其实对年轻时的荒唐行为还相当留恋，现在终于上了年纪，依然有心却已无力，只能悔恨地感到自己的‘好日子’一去不复返，眼睁睁地看着那些年轻的男人们夺走他们得不到手的东西。他们唯一能缓解自己挫折感的方式，就是攻击女人和试图阻止其他人去享受他们曾享受过的东西。你经常看到老头儿们走来走去说着粗俗可鄙的话，比如你说的马太奥鲁斯就很直率地承认自己只是个仍然想满足自身欲望的虚弱老人。他是个能解释我观点的非常好的例子，因为他正是这类情况里的一个典型。”

“但是感谢神明，并非所有的老年男人都是堕落的和像麻风病人一样病入膏肓的。还是有一些上等体面的人，他们的智慧和美德是由我养育的，他们用高尚而冷静的方式说话，其话语就可以反映自身的优秀品性。这样的男人是痛恨一切错误和诽谤的。因此他们并不会去攻击和诋毁某一个罪人，无论是男是女，而是会一视同仁地谴责所有的罪恶。他们给人的建议是避开恶习、追求美德并坚持坦率。”

“那些因为自身身体缺陷而攻击女人的男人，比如有阳痿或畸形的，他们的想法都很扭曲而且愤愤不平。他们唯一可以补偿机体无能的乐趣就是攻击女性，因为她们可以给其他男人带来快乐。这样他们就能确保别人也不去享受他们从未享受过的快乐。”

“那些因为嫉妒而攻击女人的男人，其实通常都明白女性比他们更具有智慧和美德。这种嫉妒的男人出于愤怒和怨恨而去攻击所有女人，觉得这样他们就可以破坏她们的名声和品性了，正如那个写了《关于哲学》的我忘记名字的作者一样。在那本书里，他花了大量的篇幅来争辩男人根本不该赞美女性，而那些去赞美的男人都违背了他那本书的标题：这些人把追求智慧的‘哲学’变成了追求愚蠢的‘愚学’。但是我可以向你保证，因为那些错误推理和荒谬结论，他自己其实才正是‘愚学’的典范。”

“至于那些本性就喜欢造谣中伤的男人去攻击女性则一点也不奇怪，因为他们会一样地攻击所有人。你可以相信我，任何蓄意攻击女性的男人都是出于他自己的邪念，因为这种行为是跟理性和天性背道而驰的。说他与理性作对，是因为他绝不会感激和承认女人们从过去到现在都在为他付出，那些美好而不可或缺的事物远远多于他可以回馈的；说他与天性作对，是因为连鸟和兽都会自然地爱它们的伴侣，也就是雌性的动物。所以当一个理性的男人不去爱女人时，他就是在严重地违反自己的天性。”

“最后，还有那些对著作浅尝辄止的人，他们满足于从比自己强得多的作者的顶尖作品里拾人牙慧。他们觉得这样做自己就不会被人批评，因为他们只是在重述别人说过的观点。相信我，这就是他们为什么会去造谣中伤的原因。有些人写下拙劣的胡言乱语，或是既不押韵又没思想的诗作，去评论女人、贵妇或其他人，而实际上品行不端的正是他们自己，他们才是最需要去提升道德水平的人。然后，那些跟他们一样无知的普通人，就会以为这些是他们所读过的最好的作品。”

9.克里斯蒂娜是如何挖土的：换句话说，她是如何向理性女神发问和得到回答的

“现在我已经把给你的任务准备好了，你可以按照我划好的线开始挖地基了。”

遵循理性女神寄予的希望，我用全力开始阐述：“我的女神，为什么最伟大的诗人奥维德[6]（尽管包括我自己在内的其他人会认为维吉尔[7]更适合那个荣誉，如果你不介意我直说的话），在他的如《爱的艺术》《爱情三论》等作品中，作过这么多贬低女人的评价？”

理性女神回答说：“奥维德对作诗的理论和实践都非常熟悉，他细腻的思想使他擅长写自己所写的任何领域。但是，他的身体却沾染了各种庸俗和肉欲的恶习：他和很多女人有过绯闻，因为他完全没有节制的概念，也不会对任何人献出忠心。他整个青年时期都是这样度过的，于是自食其果：不仅丧失了名誉和财产，甚至还丧失了一部分肢体！他不仅自己极其淫乱，还鼓励别人做同样的事，因而最终被流放。他的追随者中有一些是在罗马有影响力的年轻人，他虽然被他们从流放中救了回来，但依旧无法避免再次陷入同样的境地。所以他最后因不道德的行为而被阉割了。他是另一个证明我刚刚叙述的观点的好例子：当他发现自己再也无法沉溺于以前的快乐中时，就开始用狡诈的评论来攻击女性，希望其他人也能鄙视她们。”

“我的女神，你的话确实是真理。但我也看到一个意大利作家叫作阿斯科里[8]，如果我记得没错的话，来自于马尔谢[9]或托斯卡纳[10]。他在作品里说了一些比我读过的任何东西都要糟糕的，让人非常不悦的话，我觉得任何人在任何情况下，都不该去复述这些话。”

理性女神的回答是：“我亲爱的孩子，不必意外阿斯科里会因为仇恨和鄙视而去诽谤所有女性。出于无法形容的邪念，他希望所有男人对于女人都能有跟他一样的肮脏看法。他也同样落得了他应有的下场：由于他传播的异端邪说，他在柱刑上耻辱地死去了。”

“我的女神，我还看到了另一本拉丁文的小书，叫作《关于女人的秘密》，里面说女人的身体生来就在各个方面都是有缺陷的次品。”

理性女神回答道：“你只需要看看自己的身体就足以明白，这本书完全是充满了谎言的捏造。虽然有人把它溯源到亚里士多德，但说一个像他那样伟大的哲学家能有如此骇人听闻的谬论，还是欠考虑的。任何读过这本书的女人都能看到，它的很多叙述都和她们的自身经历完全相反，因此可以相应地推论出其他部分也是一样不可信的。不知道你还记不记得开头的地方，他说了某个主教把所有将这本书念给女人听或者给她们看的男人都驱逐出教的事？”

“是的，我的女神，我记得那个段落。”

“你知道是什么样的邪恶动机促使他把这么卑鄙的一段放在书的开头，让那些易受骗的愚蠢男人去读？”

“不知道，我的女神，请你赐教。”

“这是因为他不希望女人们能读到这本书，或者是听到别人读给她们，以免沦为她们的笑柄，或者指出它是多么一钱不值。他以为用了这个诡计，就可以骗过那些想读他的书的男人了。”

“我的女神，我似乎记得，他在长篇累牍地阐述女孩是虚弱或有瑕疵的子宫的产物之后，宣称天性女神也为自己创造出了这样的残次品而感到羞愧。”

“我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，得出这些结论的人，很明显是完全不理智地被误导了吧？首先，作为上帝仆从的天性女神，怎么可能比她力量的来源、自己的主人还要强大？全能的上帝全心全意地创造了男人和女人。当他将神意付诸实施，用大马士革的泥土创造了亚当之后，就让他住进了这卑贱地上最高贵的伊甸园。他让亚当在这里安睡，用他的一条肋骨创造了女性的躯体。这预示了女人天生是陪伴在男人身边的人，男人则应该把她作为一体同心的自身去爱，而绝非是匍匐于他脚前的奴隶。如果连神圣的创造者本身都不认为创造了女性形态是件羞耻的事情，那天性女神为什么会如此认为呢？想不到这一层的人可真是愚蠢到一定程度了。此外，女人又是怎样被创造出来的呢？我不知道你是否意识到了，但她其实也同样复制了神的形象。谁竟敢如此无礼，去说拥有这样神圣原型的事物的坏话？当然也有足够愚蠢的人坚持说，神按照自己的形象造人，指的是他的躯体本身。这也一样并非事实，因为那个时候神还没有变化成人形，所以必须得澄清，这个复制指的是他的灵魂，是那无形的才智使得人从生到死都可与神相似。他把他的灵魂同时赋予了男性和女性，并且使两性都同等的高尚和纯洁。回到我们正在讨论的人的躯体是怎样形成的这个话题，女性是被最优秀的造物者一手创造的。那么她究竟是在哪里被创造的呢？毫无疑问是在伊甸园。那么又是用什么造出的，是粗糙的材料吗？不，她是从神作出的最好的材料——男性自己的身体——中被创造出来的。”

“我的女神，从你的话中我可以看出，女性是一种非常高贵的生物。但尽管如此，西塞罗[11]不是说过‘男人不应该被女人管制’吗？让女人管了的男人是在贬低自己，因为被比自己低下的人所辖制是错误的。”

理性女神回答道：“无论男女，有德行的人才更高等：人的贵贱不是由性别来区分的，而是由此人能让自己的本性和道德完美到何种程度来决定的。因此服侍圣母的男人是幸福的，因为她的地位比天使还要高。”

“我的女神，老加图[12]，也就是那位伟大的演说家，声称如果女人没有被创造出来的话，男人就可以直接跟众神对话了。”

理性女神的回答是：“现在你看到了一个本是智慧的人却说了蠢话的例子了。是因为有了女人，男人才能跟神并肩而坐。至于那些说男人是因为叫夏娃的女人才被从伊甸园赶出去的，我的回答是，男人从圣母玛利亚那里所得到的，要远远比他因夏娃而失去的多得多。现在人类已经跟神合为一体，若夏娃没有犯错，这就是不可能的。男人和女人都应该去赞美夏娃的这个错误，正是因为她，这个荣耀才能降临在他们头上。如果人性曾因为上帝创造的一个生物的行为而崩坏，那它就已经被这个生物本身赎还了。至于像老加图说的，如果男性没有女性就能跟神对话了，他的话比他自己预想的还要正确。作为一个异教徒，他和跟他信仰相同的人们认为天堂和地狱都是由神来统治的，只是我们把地狱里的称为恶魔。所以说，如果没有圣母，男人就可以直接跟地狱里的神明对话，这是完全正确的！”

……

11.克里斯蒂娜问理性女神为什么女人不能出现在法庭上以及理性女神的回答

“我最正直可敬的女神啊，你出色的论点满足了我在众多领域里的好奇心。若不介意的话，你能否再解释一下为什么女人在审讯中既不被允许去起诉，也不可以作证，甚至都不能传递信息？有些男人宣称这都是源于一些女人在法庭中曾经的举止不端。”

“我亲爱的孩子，这个荒谬的故事是彻头彻尾的蓄意捏造。但如果你希望知道万事背后的原因和理由的话，你是永远也不可能追溯到头的。就算是亚里士多德，即便他在《论问题》和《范畴论》里解释了那么多，也依旧无法做到这一点。但是亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，回到你的问题上，你或许同样会问上帝为什么没有让男人去做女人的工作，以及让女人做男人的事情。这个问题可以这样回答，就像一个聪慧精明的主人把他的家产分为不同的部分，并把他的工人们也严格分工那样，上帝与此类似地创造了男人和女人，以便从不同的角度服侍他，并且让他们相互帮助和安慰。最后，他给了不同的性别以实现各自目的所必需的品质和特点，即使有时候人类并不尊重这种区别。神给了男人健壮有力的身躯来阔步探寻和大胆发言，这就解释了为什么是男人们在学习法律和进行执法。在那些拒绝遵守法律的情况中，男人们会通过武装和体力来强制执行，而女人们是无法做到这点的。即使上帝也经常赋予很多女性以杰出的智慧，但她们依旧不可以抛弃一贯的谦逊跑到法庭去上诉，因为已经有足够多的男人在做这件事了。为什么要让三个人去做两个人就已经游刃有余的事呢？”

“但是，如果有人说这是因为女人的聪明才智不够去学习法律，我就要引用从古到今无数优秀女性的例子来反驳他们了，她们是杰出的哲学家，或在很多远远难于单纯学习一下法律条文的领域里出人头地。我接下来会给你讲述这些例子。同时为了回答那些觉得女人缺乏明智管理或建立良好习惯的能力的人，我会举一些历史上可敬的淑女们的例子，她们完全有驾驭这些的能力。为了让你能更清楚我在说些什么，我也会给你列举一些你同时代的寡妇，她们在丈夫过世后对家产的组织和管理完全证明了智慧的女人能够在任何领域成功。”

2.关于示巴女王[13]

“如果可以的话请告诉我，你是否曾经读到过一个国王，他有比示巴女王更优秀的治理手段、政治才能和公正人品，并且还掌管着一个更为宏大的法庭？在她统治之下的广袤无垠的土地，是从她的祖先，那些被称为法老的著名国王那里继承下来的。但是，是这位女性第一次在她的疆土上创建了法律和道德规范，也就此终结了这个国家的原始形态，甚至包括埃塞俄比亚的野蛮习俗。那些描写过示巴女王的作者都特别称赞了她把文明带入治下的举措。她是法老的后代，继承了包括阿拉伯、埃塞俄比亚、埃及和位于尼罗河中游的肥沃的麦罗埃岛[14]在内的广袤疆土。她以典范性的才能管理着自己的疆域。关于这位女性我还有什么可说的吗？示巴女王非常聪颖和强大，甚至连圣经都提到了她出众的能力。她自己建立了用来治理民众的法律。她的高贵和富有，超越了尘世间的所有男人。她对于艺术和科学都十分精通，并且以自己从未去屈尊嫁人，或未曾希望任何男人陪伴在她身边为荣。”

……

14.克里斯蒂娜和理性女神之间更多的讨论和辩论

“我的女神，你说得非常好，你的话语有如音乐般悦耳。但是，如果不管我们刚刚谈到的才智，那么无法否认，女性从本质上来说还是懦弱的生物，她们有着柔软脆弱的躯体，并且缺乏强健的体魄。男人们就因为这些说女人是低等和低价值的。在他们看来，如果一个人的身体在某种意义上残缺的话，这就破坏并降低了他或她的道德水准，那么也就因此而不值得去赞赏了。”

理性女神的回答是：“我亲爱的孩子，这是一个完全站不住脚的错误结论。如果天性女神没能让一个躯体跟她所创造的其他人一样完美，无论是在形体上还是外貌上、体力上或者肢体上，她通常都会用更多的优秀来补偿他的缺失。比如说，伟大的哲学家亚里士多德常被说成是长相丑陋的，因为他的脸是扭曲的，而且一只眼睛比另一只低。但他若确实是畸形的话，那么从他的作品可以看出来，显然天性女神用非凡的才智补偿了他。对他而言，拥有这样超凡的智慧是比拥有像押沙龙[15]一样完美的躯体更有意义的。”

“亚历山大大帝也是一样，他非常矮小、丑陋又孱弱，但众所周知，他有着非凡的勇气。其他很多人也都是这样。相信我，我亲爱的朋友，一个完整强健的身体并不一定有着勇敢无畏的心。勇气是从自然的生命活力中产生的，这种力量是上帝允许天性女神赠予那些理性出众的人的天赋。这种力量存在于精神和心中，而不是存在于肉体和四肢的力量中。你经常看到彪悍健壮的男人是可怜的胆小鬼，而其他娇小孱弱的男人却很勇敢和坚韧。这也同样适用于其他的道德品质。关于勇气和体质，上帝或天性女神都没有打算通过剥夺女性的这些价值来歧视她们。与此相反，女人们在这方面的不足其实是很幸运的，因为她们至少不会有骇人听闻的残酷行径，比如从古到今的男人都有足够力气去进行谋杀和使用暴行，更不会因此而受到责罚。如果那些男人们的灵魂能在柔弱的女性身体里过一辈子，或许倒是一件好事。回到我正在说的事上，我确信天性女神若决定了不去赋予女性以强健的体魄，那她就会补偿给她们最善良的品性：对上帝的敬爱和对违背神谕的恐惧。没有这样去做的女人是违背了自己本性的。”

“但是，亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，你应该注意到了，神也明确地想向男人证明，虽然女人普遍来说没有他们身强力壮和富有勇气，但这并不意味着女性整体都缺乏这种素质。实际上有一些女性展示了足够的魄力、体力和勇气来完成了惊人的壮举，完全可以跟史书中提到的伟大征服者和武士们匹敌。之后我就给你举一个这样的例子。”

“我可爱的孩子和亲爱的朋友，我已经给你准备好了一条宽阔的沟渠，并亲自肩挑手提把土都运走了。现在该你往沟中填上沉重坚固的石块，来构成淑女之城的地基了。以你的笔为铲，抖擞精神开始建筑吧。下面就是一块很不错的结实的石头，我希望你能把它作为筑城的第一块基石。你知道连天性女神都用占星预言了这块石头应该被放在这里了吗？稍稍往后退一步，我来帮你把它放入位。”

……

16.关于亚马逊人

“在欧洲大陆附近的广阔海洋中有一个叫作塞西亚[16]的国家。有一次，男人们都在战争中阵亡了，当女人们看到自己失去了丈夫、兄弟和男性亲属，只有幼小男孩和老年男子还幸存之后，就鼓起勇气召集了一个妇女议会，决定从今往后由自己来领导自己的国家，不再受男人的管束。她们公布法令禁止任何男人出入她们的领地，但为了能维持种族延续，她们自己可以在每年的特定时间出入邻国。如果生了男婴就把他送回父亲那里，女婴则自己抚养。为了维护这个法律，她们选了出身最高贵的两位淑女为女王，一位叫作蓝佩朵，另一位叫作马佩西娅。她们很快把国内剩下的男人都驱逐出境，接着从长到幼都武装起来投入战斗，在她们的国土上奋勇杀敌，把所有的敌人都赶尽杀绝了。简单来说，她们为丈夫们的死报了仇。”

“就这样，塞西亚的女人们开始武装自己。她们后来被称为亚马逊人，意思是‘去掉了一个乳房的民族’。她们的传统是使用只有本族女性知道的秘术，贵族女孩在儿时去掉左乳房来携带盾牌，非贵族的女孩们则去掉右乳房以便操控弓箭。她们非常崇尚武力，所以通过战争极大地扩张了领土，并且名声远播。回到之前的话题，这两位女王每人带领了一支出色的军队在许多国家作战，并且成功占领了欧洲和亚洲的很大一部分地区，征服了很多王国。她们建立了很多城镇，包括亚洲颇有名望的以弗所[17]。两位女王中的马佩西娅最先战死，并由她一个年轻的女儿接替，也就是美丽的贵族未婚少女锡诺普。这位女孩为自己从未跟男人发生过关系而感到骄傲，并且选择到死都维持贞洁。她生命中唯一的真爱和快乐就是追寻武力：她对于战争和扩张从未感到过厌倦。她接连征服敌国，把他们的国土完全踏平、国民杀戮殆尽，以此来痛快淋漓地为母亲报了仇。”

……

27.克里斯蒂娜问理性女神上帝是否赋予了女性最高级的知识以及理性女神的回答

听完理性女神所说的，我回答道：“我的女神，上帝确实令人吃惊地赋予了你所提到的这些女性以超凡的力量。但是你如果不介意的话，请告诉我，在上帝赐予女性的众多品格之中，他是否曾赋予哪位出众的智力和学识。她们是否有学习的天资？我非常想知道，为什么男人们断言妇女是愚钝的。”

理性女神的回答是：“克里斯蒂娜，从我告诉你的可以很明显地看出，事实与他们所说的正相反。为了解释得更清楚一点，我来给你一些总结性的例子。我再重复一下——不要怀疑我的话——如果社会传统就是像对男孩一样地送女孩去上学，并教给她们各种知识，那么她们也会跟男孩一样轻松学会那些困难的艺术和科学知识的。实际上，这也常常是事实，就像我之前提到的，尽管女人的躯体比男人柔弱也没那么灵活，但她们的思想实际上更敏锐，并且更善于接纳新鲜事物。”

“我的女神，你在说什么呀？如果可以的话，我希望你再详细阐述一下。如果我们不能证明这个观点，那就没有一个男人会接受它，因为他们会说男人普遍来说要比女人知道得更多。”

她回答道：“你知道为什么女人比男人要无知一些吗？”

“不知道，我的女神，你得启发我一下。”

“这是因为她们必须得整天待在屋子里来照管家庭，所以较少接触到各种社会经验。没有什么比各式各样的经历和活动更能让理性的人拓宽眼界和智慧了。”

“那么我的女神，如果她们有跟男人一样的学习能力，为什么她们没有因此而更博学呢？”

“我亲爱的孩子，回答是，就像我之前告诉你的一样，让女人抛头露面去做男人该做的事情并不一定能带来什么公众利益。她们去做适合自己的事情则是非常明智的。至于说经验告诉我们女性的智力低于男性，因为身边的女人都比男人知道得少，那就让我们以穷乡僻壤的男性佃农为例吧。你可以列举出相当多的地方，那里的男人们非常落后，所以跟野兽没什么区别。但是毋庸置疑，天性女神也赋予了他们跟城镇里最聪明且有学识的男人们同样完美的头脑和身体，所以这些都是缺乏教育造成的。当然也别忘记我之前说过的，有些男人或女人天生就比其他人更聪颖。我现在就来给你列举一些具有优秀头脑的博学多才的女人，来证明女性跟男性一样聪明。”

28.理性女神从罗马的科尼菲西娅[18]开始谈论博学广识的淑女们

“科尼菲西娅的父母在她小的时候稍稍用了点手段，把她跟她的兄弟科尼菲修斯一起送去上学。这个小姑娘把她超人的智力用在了学习上，并从此开始以学习为乐。让她放弃这种天赋是非常困难的，因为她拒绝了所有通常女性要做的事情，而全身心地投入到书本中去。在刻苦学习之后，她很快就成为了一位出色而博学的诗人，在她如饥似渴地求学的哲学领域也是如此。她非常积极主动地在各个方面出人头地，所以很快超越了她的兄弟，不光是在诗歌上，更是在所有的知识领域里。”

“除此之外，她不只满足于学习理论知识，更希望能把她的知识付诸实践。她执笔创作了几部出色的著作，在圣格列高利一世[19]的时代被广为尊重，正如这位教宗在自己的著作中所指出的那样。伟大的意大利作家薄伽丘[20]在他的书中对科尼菲西娅作了这样的评价：‘作为一个女性却放下女人的事情并且投入到学习最伟大的学者的著作中，是多么光荣的一件事。’他接下来的话印证了我所说的，他说那些对自己的智商没有自信的女人们，做起事来就像是出生于荒山野岭一样，没有正确和错误以及道德的观念，放任自己被蒙蔽，还说自己除了照顾男人和生养孩子之外什么也做不了。上帝给了每个女人一副好头脑，如果她愿意的话，能用在所有博学的男人们活跃着的领域里。如果女人愿意去学，这些领域对于她们不会比对于男人来说更难，她们也能够投入足够多的精力来赢得美名，就像最出色的男人们那样。我亲爱的孩子，看看薄伽丘是怎样与我所说的相互呼应的，并注意一下他是多么赞同和欣赏妇女去学习的。”

……

30.关于一位出色的诗人和哲学家莎孚[21]

“跟普罗芭[22]一样博学的莎孚，是一位来自米蒂利尼[23]的未婚女子。这位莎孚非常美丽，言谈举止也很有魅力。但她最出众的特质是出色的智力，她也因此在科学艺术的诸多领域成为了专家。而且她不仅攻读别人的著作，自己也撰写了很多新著。诗人薄伽丘用这样美妙的词语来称颂她：‘莎孚，被她自身的好头脑和求知欲所鞭策，投身到学习中并且超越了广大的无知群众，与帕纳塞斯山[24]比肩；换句话说，她攀登到了知识的顶峰。由于她的魄力和勇敢，她获取了缪斯女神的恩惠；也就是说她沉浸在了科学艺术之中。她跋涉过长满月桂、山楂、各色鲜花香草的茂密丛林，这是语法、逻辑、几何、算术和修辞学的栖息地。她通过这条小径直到知识之神阿波罗的洞穴前，并找到了汩汩流淌的诗之神泉。在那里，她拿起琴拨用竖琴弹奏美妙的歌曲，引来仙女领舞；也就是说，她学到了和弦的美妙与和声学的规则。’”

“薄伽丘对莎孚的这些描述，应该被理解为她学习的深度和她著作的博学程度。她的著作极其艰深，就像先哲们指出的那样，即使对最聪明和受过最好教育的男人来说也不那么容易读懂。她的书写得非常精致，至今仍在流传，因而给之后立志诗歌的人们树立了出色的榜样。她发明了很多种新的诗歌形式，包括叙事诗、怨情诗、奇怪爱的挽歌等由不同情绪所激发的诗歌，它们非常洗练，因而今天被叫作莎孚诗来纪念她。至于她的作品，贺拉斯[25]回忆说在亚里士多德的老师柏拉图去世时，他的枕下就有一本莎孚的诗集。”

“长话短说，因为莎孚的学问非常有名，所以她的故里决定在显眼的地方建一尊她的铜像来表彰她在诗歌上的成就。她为自己在最伟大的诗人行列中赢得了一席之地，按薄伽丘的话说，这些诗人的光辉要远比主教的法冠、国王的王冠甚至战争胜利者的棕榈和月桂花环还要耀眼。我可以给你更多这样聪颖女性的例子，比如希腊女性雷翁提乌姆，一位杰出的哲学家，她敢于清晰明了地与当时备受尊重的思想家泰奥弗拉斯托斯辩论。”

……

33.克里斯蒂娜问理性女神是否有女性曾创造过新的知识形态

在听过理性女神的话之后，我，克里斯蒂娜，提起了如下话题：“我的女神，我清楚地看到你可以列举出无数的妇女曾在科学艺术中达到了很高的水平。但是我想问你，是否知道曾有天才的，或具有创造力的，或足够聪颖的女性，能够创造出以前并不存在的、崭新的、重要而有用的知识学派。很显然，去学习一个已有的领域，要比发现新的无人知晓的领域容易得多。”

理性女神回答道：“相信我，很多重要或值得尊崇的科学艺术都是由智慧聪颖的女性所发现的，在经由文字叙述的理论科学和需要动手的精巧技艺上都是如此。我现在给你一些例子。”

“首先，我来给你讲讲贵族尼科斯特拉塔，意大利人称她为喀尔曼塔。这位淑女是希腊的阿卡迪亚[26]国王帕拉斯的女儿。她非常聪颖，被上帝赐予了智慧的天赋，对希腊文学有着广博的知识，作品聪慧简洁，又非常有口才，所以同时代的诗人们在作品中宣称她是被神使墨丘利所垂青的。他们甚至认为她那早慧的儿子是这位神使的后代，而非她丈夫的孩子。由于家乡的一系列巨变，尼科斯特拉塔跟儿子和一群追随他们的人一起，乘坐大型船队由台伯河[27]溯流而上开往意大利。她在那里登陆，并爬上她后来为纪念她父亲而命名为帕拉蒂尼的山丘[28]。在后来建成了罗马的这座山丘上，她和儿子以及追随者们建起了自己的城堡。她发现当地土著人非常原始，就帮他们建立了一些规则，并且鼓励他们过公正理性的生活。所以她是第一位在这个后来以法理系统著称的国家里建立起法律的人，而后来的法律也几乎都源于这套系统。”

“在尼科斯特拉塔的特质中，还有神圣的预言能力。她因而可以预见到她所继承的国家有朝一日会成为世界上最伟大和最繁荣的疆土。所以在她看来，这个以后必将征服世界的最优秀的国家，不该使用外来的低劣粗糙的文字。此外，尼科斯特拉塔也希望能把她的智慧和知识，以合适的方式传授给未来的世代。因此她开始着手创造一套与其他国家都不一样的崭新的字母体系。被她创造出来的就是ABC，即拉丁字母，以及造词规则、元音与辅音的区别和语法的基础。她把这些知识和文字传授给了人们，希望它们能广为流传。这位淑女的发明已经不能再伟大了，我们对她的感谢更不能被一笔带过。这一设计精巧的科学被证明极为有用，并给世界带来了极其多的好处，所以我们可以很诚实地说，没有比这更为高贵的发明了。”

“意大利人并不缺乏对这美好礼物的感激之情，这一点做得非常正确。他们认为这是不可思议的发明，因而对她比对任何男人都要尊崇，在尼科斯特拉塔/喀尔曼塔的有生之年都把她当作女神一样崇拜着。在她去世时，他们建造了一个寺庙来纪念她，就坐落于她建城的山丘脚下。为了让她能流芳百世，他们借用了她创造的科学中的一些词汇，甚至还用她的名字来命名事物。比如为了纪念她发明的拉丁语，全国人都自称为拉丁人。此外，因为ita在拉丁语中是最重要的肯定词，就像法语里的oui一样，所以他们不仅把自己的疆土叫作拉丁，还更进一步用‘意大利（Italy）’来指代超越了国境的广袤土地，包括许多不同的区域和王国。从这位淑女的名字Carmentis，他们演化出了拉丁词carmen，意思是‘歌’。即使是在她之后很久登陆的罗马人，也把一个城门命名为‘卡曼塔里斯门（Porta Carmentalis）’。这些名字流传至今，不论罗马如何繁荣昌盛或是由哪位强大的皇帝当政，这些都未曾改变过。”

“我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，你还能有更多的要求吗？还有人认为有任何男人可以与她比肩吗？不过别以为她是唯一一位曾经创造过很多知识领域的女性……”

34.关于一位创造了无数新技术包括用钢铁制造武器的女性弥涅耳瓦[29]

“就像你看到的那样，弥涅耳瓦是一位希腊女性，也被叫作帕拉斯。这位姑娘极为聪颖，所以她那个时代的人傻傻地把她奉为了天上来的女神：因为他们不知道她的父母是谁，而她的所作所为又都是前无古人的创举。就像薄伽丘指出的一样，他们对于她的出身越是一无所知，就越对她比任何同时代女人都优秀的智慧感到惊诧。她把她超凡的技巧和独创性运用在了诸多领域。首先，她天才地创造了希腊字母速记法，可以用最简短的篇幅记下最多的内容。这个绝妙的发明至今还被希腊人使用着。她还创造了数字以及用它们去数数和快速计算的方法。简单来说，她天才地发明了很多前所未有的艺术和技能，包括制作羊毛和布料的技术。是她最早产生了剪羊毛的想法，并发明了用各种不同的工具来给羊毛松解、开松和梳理等整套流程以及除去杂毛、在金属尖端上粉碎纤维并捻到拉线棒上的方法，还有把羊毛织成布料所需的工具。”

“同样，她发现了如何从橄榄里榨油以及从其他果实里榨取果汁的方法。”

“同样，她发明了手推车和战车，以便运送东西。”

“同样，这位淑女的一项发明更不像是女性会想到的，即锻造武士们在战场上用以杀敌的钢铁武器和护身盔甲的技术。她把这项技术教给了雅典的人民，同时也教会他们组织成军队以及以部队形式的作战。”

“同样，她发明了长笛、竖笛、小号和其他管乐器。”

“这位淑女不仅非常智慧，也极其纯洁，保持了一生的贞洁。正因为她的极端纯洁，诗人们在诗作中说她与火神伏尔甘长期对抗，并最终战胜了他。这个故事可以被解释成她战胜了肉欲的激情和渴望对年轻身体的困扰。雅典人极其尊重这位女子，把她当作神一样崇拜，并把她称为女战神和女武神，因为她是这些技术的创造者。她也因为她卓越的智慧而被称为智慧女神。”

“在她死后，雅典人民建造了一座神庙进献给她，在里面供奉了一尊代表智慧和战争的女子雕像。这座雕像目光锐利，代表武士维护公正的职责以及智者无比聪慧的头脑。这座雕像戴着头盔，以喻示武士必须在战争中经受锻炼以获得无尽的勇气以及智者的计划应该是不能被人看破的。她穿着盔甲，来表明武士的地位和权力以及智者应当是作好准备面对命运起伏的远见。这座雕像拿着长矛或长枪，标志着一个武士必须是正义的化身，而智者会选择从安全的距离发起攻击。一个水晶的小圆盾挂在雕像的脖子上，代表武士必须时刻警惕并随时准备保卫国家和人民以及智者对万事的透彻理解。在这个盾牌的中心是蛇发女妖戈耳工，代表武士必须足够狡黠并要像蛇一样潜近敌人，而智者则必须警惕他人可能带来的危险。为了保卫这尊雕像，他们在旁边树了一只夜行鸟类——猫头鹰——来表示武士必须准备好在需要时不分昼夜地保护国家以及智者必须时刻警醒自己何为正途。这位弥涅耳瓦被尊崇了很长一段时间，名声远播他国，而那些国家也给她建立了寺庙。即使数个世纪之后罗马人达到了势力顶峰时，她的名望依旧存在，于是他们就把她的形象纳入了众神之中。”

35.关于发明了农业和许多其他技术的克瑞斯女王

“克瑞斯是远古时期西西里的女王。她心灵手巧地发明了农业科学和技术以及必要的工具。她教会了她的臣民们如何聚拢和驯服牛，并给牛上轭。克瑞斯也发明了犁，展示给她的人民如何用犁刀来挖开和破碎土壤以及其他所需的技能。下一步，她教给他们如何播种并覆以土壤。当种子生根发芽之后，她教给他们如何收割成捆的麦子，并通过抽打脱粒把麦粒从谷壳中取出。然后克瑞斯演示了如何用厚重的石头研磨谷物以及建造磨坊，接下去如何准备面粉并做成面包。就这样，这位淑女引导了那些如野兽般吃着橡果、野草、苹果和浆果的人们，去开始一种高贵的饮食习惯。”

“克瑞斯没有就此止步：那时候她的人民还像野兽一样四处游走，居住在树林和荒野的临时住所里。她把他们聚集起来，并教会他们如何建立城镇、组成社区。她就这样把人们带出了原始状态，引入更为文明和理性的生活方式。诗人们创作出了克瑞斯的传说，讲述她的女儿是如何被冥界之王普路托诱拐的。因为她出色的知识和给世界带来的益处，那时的人崇敬地称她为谷物女神。”

36.关于发明了园艺和种植技术的伊西斯

“伊西斯不仅仅是一位埃及女王，更由于她广博的园艺知识而被尊崇为埃及的女神。传说中描述了她是如何被朱庇特所爱，并把她变成了母牛再变回来，这都是她丰富知识的象征，就像你在自己写的《阿西亚给赫克特的信》中所指出的那样。为了造福埃及人民，她还发明了一些文字来表述他们的语言，以便把想法言简意赅地记录下来。”

“伊西斯是希腊国王依那储斯之女，智者福罗奴斯的姐妹。这位淑女和她的兄弟因故离开希腊前往埃及，在那里她教给了人民很多东西，包括如何建立庭院、种植和嫁接植物。她也建立起了一些完善的法律并鼓励希腊人民去遵循，因为直到那时他们都还处于没有司法系统的原始状态。简单来说，伊西斯为他们做了很多，所以他们在她生前和死后都为她举办过盛大的典礼。她的名声传遍世界，奉献给她的神殿和礼拜堂如雨后春笋般出现在各地。即使在罗马的巅峰时期，罗马人也为她建起了一座神殿，并在其中沿用埃及人当年的习俗为她敬献祭品，举行庄严的仪式。”

“这位尊贵淑女的丈夫叫作阿比斯，异教徒们把他错认为是朱庇特与福罗奴斯之女尼奥比的儿子。古代历史学家和诗人们也经常提到此人。”

……

43.克里斯蒂娜问理性女神是否女人天生拥有良好的判断力以及理性女神的回答

我，克里斯蒂娜，回到理性女神身边说：“我的女神，现在我看到了上帝确实使女性聪明的头脑足以学习、理解和记忆任何知识。我为此由衷地赞美上帝！但是，我也总是很惊诧地看到，有那么多头脑机敏的人，能迅速学到自己的所见所闻、在感兴趣的领域通过投入学习而掌握大量知识，但似乎在个人道德和公众行为上却缺乏判断能力，即使一些最有名的渊博学者也是如此。毫无疑问，科学知识是应该可以帮助灌输道德价值的。所以如果可以的话，我的女神，我非常希望能知道，你我的经验都已证明，女性的头脑足以理解那些科学和其他领域里最复杂的事物，那它是否也一样能够借由判断力学到东西。换句话说，女性能够区别善行和恶行吗？她们能够汲取过去的经验来修正现在的行为吗？她们能用现在的例子来预见将来应该如何行动吗？在我看来，这些就是良好判断力的体现。”

理性女神回答道：“你提得很对，我的孩子。但是不要忘记，无论男女都是有这种能力的，而且都会有一些人天生比其他人拥有更多。并且良好的判断力并不是学来的，虽然学习能够帮助那些本来就有这种倾向的人更加完美，就像你知道的，两种同向的力量加在一起比单股力量要更强有力。因此在我看来，任何有着天生判断力的人和那些善于学习知识的人都是值得嘉奖的。但是就像你自己指出的，有些人只具备一方面却缺乏另一方面：前者是神恩惠的内在品质，而后者是通过学习获得的。当然，两者都是好的。”

“有些人认为，有良好判断力却没有知识，是要好过有学识却没有善恶观的。这是一个备受争议的主张，也引发了各种质疑。你可以说，最好的人是那些对公共利益贡献最多的人。这样的话就无法否认，那些有学识的人通过传授知识对人起到的帮助是最大的，无论他们自己的判断力如何。这是因为个人的判断力只贯穿在人的有生之年，会随着人的逝去而消散。但另一方面，知识是永存的，因为那些博学者的名声是永垂青史的，他们也通过把知识教给他人或者写成书本而流传百世。因此他们的知识不会随他们而消散，就像我用亚里士多德和其他学科创始人的例子给你证明的那样。这种可以习得的知识对人类而言，比无知的人所展示的良好判断力更为有用，尽管他们曾用这些判断力非常好地统治和管理过自己的国家。说句实话，这些良好行为是暂时性的，会随着时间而消失，而知识却是不可磨灭的。”

“但我要把这些放在一旁，因为它跟我们现在要进行建城的任务并不直接相关。相对的，让我们回到你最开始问我的那个问题上来，即女性是否天生具有更好的判断力。在这个问题上，我可以肯定地给你一个‘是’的答案。这一点你应该能够从我已经讲给你的事例，以及观察妇女们是如何履行她们传统的职责上看出来。如果你看得足够仔细，你会看到妇女们在照管家庭上大都是尽其所能地做到周到、勤奋和严谨的。有时候，那些有着懒惰丈夫的妇女会给人留下喜欢找碴儿、对他们指手画脚和想树立权威的印象，但他们其实只是在把大部分妻子们的好意给故意抹黑。我下面要说的大部分都是从《所罗门智训》推导出的，它就谈到了像这样的好妻子。”

44.《圣经·箴言》里的《所罗门智训》

“如果一个丈夫能找到勇敢坚定又有着明智判断力的妻子，那他就一无所缺了。她将名声远播而她的丈夫也会为此骄傲，因为她所带来的永远都只有幸福和兴旺。她会去寻觅和购买羊毛，也就是说她给女仆们找到了一件使她们可以被雇佣的有收益的工作去做，同时保持了家用的储备，而她自己也会搭把手。她就像一艘商船，带来好的物品并提供面包。她回馈那些应得的人，他们也将成为她的密友。在她的家中，包括仆人在内都不愁吃穿。运用良好的判断力，她会斟酌地买下一片地皮用来种植葡萄，以保证家中葡萄酒的供应。她充满了勇气和决心，她的手臂因辛勤的劳作而变得肌肉坚实。即使在黑夜里，她劳作的光辉也照耀着全家。她在做着重体力劳动的同时也没有忘记女性的职责，还做着她的分内之事。她帮助和救济穷人，给痛苦的他们雪中送炭。由于她的努力，家族在风雪中免遭饥寒，连仆人们都衣装整齐。她自己穿着寓意正直和显赫的紫色丝绸，她的丈夫同样有着高贵的形象，在本地知名人士中也是第一等的。她制作上好的亚麻布料，用以出售以及自己穿着来彰显力量和光辉。她乐此不倦。她谈吐间闪耀的都是智慧的语句，而又措辞温婉。她会保证家庭富足并且无人游手好闲。她子女们的举止完全折射出她的影子，而他们的行为也能体现出她无微不至的关照。她丈夫上等的衣着举止也给她加了分。即使在女儿们成人之后她也会严格地管教着她们。她鄙视荣耀的诱惑和短暂的美貌。这样的女人会敬畏上帝也会被赞赏，神会回馈她的辛劳，因为这些劳苦全面地证明了她的美德。”

……

48.关于国王拉丁努斯之女拉维尼亚

“拉维尼亚是劳伦蒂尼的女王，同样因为她良好的判断力而闻名。她也是我们刚刚提到的克里特王萨顿[30]的后代。她是国王拉丁努斯之女，后来嫁给了特洛伊英雄埃涅阿斯[31]，尽管那之前她已经被许配给了卢杜里之王图努斯。她的父亲被一位先知告知，女儿应该嫁给特洛伊的贵族，因而一直推迟他们的婚期，尽管她的母后很希望能尽快举行婚礼。埃涅阿斯抵达意大利时，向拉丁努斯王请求进入他的领地。他不仅被批准入境，还立刻获准了跟拉维尼亚结婚。图努斯因此而跟埃涅阿斯宣战。这场战争夺去了很多人的生命，包括图努斯自己在内。埃涅阿斯巩固胜利之后跟拉维尼亚成了婚，她在埃涅阿斯去世后给他生了一个遗腹子。当她快临盆时，开始非常担心埃涅阿斯跟另一位女性所生的长子阿斯卡尼俄斯会来杀她的儿子篡夺王位。她于是去森林里生产，并给新生儿取名儒略·西尔维斯。此后拉维尼亚发誓不再改嫁，并在孀居期间显示了卓越的判断力，用她的机敏保持了王国的完好无损。她也终于赢得了继子的喜爱，从而缓和了他对自己及儿子的憎恨。当阿斯卡尼俄斯建成了阿尔巴朗格城[32]之后，就搬到那里去居住了。同时拉维尼亚也用高超的技巧统治着国家，直到她的儿子长大成人。这个孩子的后代就是罗马的建立者，罗慕路斯和雷穆斯。”

“我还有什么更多能告诉你的呢，我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜？在我看来，我已经给你引述了足够多的证据来支持我的观点，给出了充足的例子来说服你：上帝从来没有比批判男性更多地去批判女性。就像你看到的那样，我的论证是确凿的，而我的两个姐妹会继续用事实来巩固这一点。我想我已完成我建造这个城市外墙的使命，它们看上去已大功告成。请允许我让位给我的两个姐妹，你遵循她们的帮助和建议就可以很快建完剩下的部分了。”

《淑女之城》第一部分结束。

第二部分

1.第一章讲述10位女预言家的故事

在第一位淑女理性女神结束了谈话之后，第二位淑女正直女神转向我说道：“我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，我该开始履行我的职责了：在我的姐妹理性女神建完的城墙内，我们必须一起建起淑女之城的房屋来。拿起工具跟我来。不要犹豫，在你的墨水瓶里把砂浆混合均匀，并用你的笔砌起砖石的建筑吧。我会给你提供足够的材料。借上帝的恩惠，我们很快就能建起皇宫和豪院，接纳那些辉煌杰出的淑女们来永久定居。”

听到这位可敬女神的话，我，克里斯蒂娜，回答她道：“最出色的女神啊，我已经准备好了。我将服从你所有的命令，因为我唯一的愿望就是遵从你的召唤。”

她回答我说：“我亲爱的朋友，看看这些我采来切好供你建筑用的石块吧，它们美丽闪亮，比世界上任何其他的石头都要珍贵。当你和理性女神在长途跋涉的时候，我可没有偷懒吧？你现在需要把它们按照我给你的顺序整理好，排放在我为你划好的线上。”

“在知名的女性中排名最高的，是那些有着渊博学识的聪颖的女预言家们。根据最权威的记载，曾经有10位‘女预言家’，虽然有些人说只有9位。我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，把这个好好记下来：上帝曾经给予任何一位，包括那些最被他青睐的预言者们在内，比我下面要提到的淑女们更多的神启吗？他难道不是授予了她们预言的神性，使得她们可以如此直接而清晰地去叙述和记录未来吗？清晰得就像是在总结和记录过去已经发生，而不是在预见将来尚未发生的事情一样。她们甚至比任何预言家更清楚详细地描述了基督的诞生，而那是在她们的时代很久之后。这些淑女们保持了终生的贞洁和无垢。她们都被称为女预言家，但不要把这当成是她们自己的名字。这个词的意思实际上是‘获知神意的人’。她们都得到了这个名字是因为她们的预言非常准确而至关重要，恐怕只能是直接从上帝那里得知的了。因此这更像是一个职务名而非人名。尽管她们出生在世界上不同的地方、生活在不同的时代，但都清晰地预见到了未来的重要事件，包括我刚才所说的基督诞生。更值得一提的是，她们10位全都是异教徒，甚至连犹太教徒都不是。”

“第一位女预言家来自波斯，并因此被称为波斯卡。第二位来自利比亚，因而被称为利比卡。第三位生于德尔菲[33]的阿波罗神殿，因此被称为德尔菲卡。正是她在很早之前就预言了特洛伊城的毁灭，奥维德也曾在一本书中用了一些诗句来赞美她。第四位来自意大利，叫作辛梅里亚。第五位出生在巴比伦，叫作西罗菲利：当希腊人向她求教时，她预言了他们将毁灭特洛伊和它的要塞伊洛姆，不过荷马在他的史诗里把这些史实给歪曲了。她也被称为欧律斯拉俄亚，因为那是她定居的岛屿，也是她的著作被发现的地方。第六位来自萨摩斯岛，叫作萨米亚。第七位被称为酷迈，因为她出生在意大利坎帕尼亚区的酷迈城。第八位叫作赫勒斯滂蒂娜，因为她来自特洛伊平原上的赫勒斯滂[34]：她活跃在居鲁士大帝时期，和著名作者梭伦同时代。第九位叫作弗里吉卡，来自弗里吉亚，她不仅预言了很多王国的沦陷，也生动地描述了敌基督的出现。第十位叫作蒂泊蒂娜，也被称作阿布妮亚，她的著作因最清晰地记述了基督降临而被广为尊崇。尽管这些女预言家们都是异教徒出身，但她们最终都摒弃了多神的信仰，认为只有上帝是唯一存在，所有的偶像也都是假的。”

……

5.关于卡桑德拉和巴西娜王后以及更多关于尼科斯特拉塔的故事

“我们之前讨论的尼科斯特拉塔也是一位女先知，她的儿子伊凡德亦经常在历史书中出现。在与儿子一起跨过台伯河爬上帕拉蒂尼山时，她就预言了这座山会被建成有史以来最著名的城市，一座统治所有其他王国的城市。正如我们之前所提到的，她为了给这座城市奠基而筑起了一个要塞，之后罗马正是在此基础之上建立的。”

“与此类似的，高贵的特洛伊少女卡珊德拉是特洛伊王普里阿摩斯的女儿、著名的赫克特的妹妹，也是一位女预言家。她不也是因非常博学而精通所有领域吗？这位姑娘选择了侍奉神而终身不嫁，无论是面对多么高贵的王子她都矢志不渝。她因而看到了特洛伊的未来，并为此痛心不已。越是看到特洛伊在与希腊人冲突前的繁荣昌盛，她就越是哀叹痛哭。看着富丽堂皇的城市和光辉显赫的兄弟们，尤其是骁勇善战的赫克特，可怕的未来让卡珊德拉再也无法保持沉默。开战之后，她的痛楚进一步加深，从未停止过哭叫着恳求她的父兄们与希腊求和，警告他们若不如此所有人都会被这场战争所摧毁。但是没有人相信她的话，而且因为她拒绝沉默并毫不掩饰自己对于毁灭和杀戮的痛苦，她的父兄甚至还经常殴打她，说她疯了。但她依然抓住每一个机会告诉他们即将发生的一切。终于，为了从她不停的叫唤恳求声中得到一点安静，他们只好把她关在一间远离人烟的房子里。他们如果相信她就好了，因为每一件事都如她所预言的那样发生了。他们终于对自己的所作所为开始感到后悔，但是一切都为时已晚。”

“同样，巴西娜王后的预言不也是一样神奇吗？根据记载，她先嫁给了图林根[35]之王，后来又跟法国第四任国王希尔德里克一世结婚。传说在婚礼当天晚上，她说服希尔德里克一世如果当晚能不动情欲，他就能看到不可思议的景象。她让他起身去卧室的窗前，说说看到外面有什么。国王照做了，发现他似乎看到了诸如独角兽、猎豹和狮子那样的大型野兽，在王宫里跑来跑去。国王恐惧地转向王后，问她这些代表什么意思。王后承诺早晨会给他一个解释，让他安心，没有什么可害怕的，并让他回到窗前。国王照做了，这次他觉得自己看到了凶猛的熊和巨大的狼在对打。在王后让他第三次往窗外看时，他似乎看到了狗和其他小型生物相互厮打。国王对这些景象感到非常恐慌和吃惊，王后因而给他解释说，他看到的这些动物代表了他们的后裔，那些终有一日会加冕称王的未来法国王子们。不同的动物代表了这些王子们将来的性格和行为。”

“所以你可以很清楚地看到，我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，上帝是多么经常地通过女性给世界透露他的秘密。”

……

7.克里斯蒂娜对正直女神的发问

“我的女神，这些证据能证明妇女在所有被谴责的事上都是无辜的，我越听越清楚这些指控者是极其错误的。但我还是没法不提起一个在男人们甚至是在一些女人们中都相当普遍的风俗，那就是当妇女怀孕产下女儿时，丈夫们通常都很不高兴她们没能生个儿子。他们愚蠢的妻子们本应当庆幸上帝保佑她们安全分娩，并全心地感谢他，却因为丈夫的烦闷而同样悲痛不已。但是我的女神，他们为什么会如此生气，是因为女孩会比男孩带来更多的麻烦，还是说不如男孩爱戴和孝敬他们的父母？”

正直女神回答道：“我亲爱的朋友，既然你问到为什么会这样，那么我可以向你保证，那些人难过是因为无知和愚蠢。但实际上，他们不高兴的主要原因还是在忧虑把女儿嫁出去得花掉多少钱，那可都是他们的血汗钱。其他人不开心是因为他们担心一个年轻单纯的女孩会被坏人引上歪路。但是细看，这两个理由都是站不住脚的。对于那些担心女儿会误入歧途的父母们，他们所要做的就只是把她们从小好好教养大，用她们母亲自身可敬的举止和有益的忠告来作例子；但如果母亲的道德水平不够高，那她就很难成为女儿效仿的榜样了。他们应该严格地把女儿跟不良伙伴隔离开，并教会她们敬畏父母，因为严格地抚养婴幼儿有助于她们日后建立良好的行为举止。同样，对于花销问题，我想说无论社会地位如何，如果这些父母们去看看把儿子养育大以及送他们去学习知识或经商的花费，他们就会立刻意识到抚养儿子并不比女儿更省钱，这还忽略不计儿子们花在那些不体面的朋友和无谓的奢侈品上的钱。更不用提男孩们因经常卷入打斗或堕入不良嗜好而给他们的父母带来痛苦和担忧了。所有这些都给他们的父母和用在他们身上的花销抹了黑。在我看来，这些远远比女孩们可能给父母带来的麻烦要大得多。”

“你能举出有多少儿子是真正在无微不至地赡养年迈的父母吗？而这本是他们理所应当要做的。尽管你能从过去和现在的人中举出几个例子，但那只是极少数，并且也只是在最后的时刻而已。通常发生的情况是，当儿子们像小皇帝般地被宠大了，又托他们父亲出钱的福读了书学了艺或忽然暴富之后，如果父亲经济拮据、生活困顿了，他们不仅会置之不理，见面的时候更会以此为耻。若是相反的，父亲们手头宽裕，他们就巴不得他早点过世，这样自己就可以拿到遗产了。只有上帝才知道有多少庄园主和有钱人的儿子们在期盼着父母过世，以便继承他们的土地和财产。彼特拉克[36]的这些话触及了事实：‘啊，愚蠢的人，你希望能有孩子，但其实没有比他们更为致命的敌人了。若你穷困，他们会鄙视你，并祈祷你能快点死去以便早日摆脱你。若你富有，他们会祈祷你能更有钱以便攫取你的财产。’我并不是说所有的儿子均会如此，但相当多的都是这样。另外，如果他们结婚了，上帝才知道他们会多么贪得无厌地去榨干父母，哪怕老人们饿死也满不在乎，只要能够继承到他们的土地。这是多么可怕的后代！如果他们的母亲寡居，他们并不会去安慰和扶助年迈的母亲，而是会对母亲给他们的爱和投入以怨报德。差劲的孩子们认为一切都是属于他们的，所以如果母亲没有满足他们的所有要求，他们就会毫不犹豫地谩骂和诅咒她们。天知道这是在怎样地尊重他们的母亲！比这更糟糕的是，有些孩子还满不在乎地把母亲告上法庭。这就是很多父母终其一生把钱奉献给孩子们以后得到的回报。很多儿子都是这样，当然有些女儿可能也如此。但是如果你仔细观察，我想你能看到卑劣的儿子比女儿要多得多。”

“即使所有的男孩都是孝敬父母的，你也还是会看到更多的女儿，而不是儿子，在陪伴她们的父母。她们不仅更频繁地去看望父母，而且更多地在父母年老体衰之后照顾他们。原因是男孩们更倾向于去闯荡世界，而女孩们则更倾向于退守家庭，就像你自身可以验证的那样。尽管你的兄弟们是很有爱心的儿子们，但他们也早已走出家门，只有你还孤身留在母亲身边，成为她晚年最大的慰藉。总结起来，我想说那些对生了女儿感到不满的人完全是被蒙蔽了。既然现在我们在讨论这个话题，那就让我从历史上挑几位对父母非常体贴关爱的妇女讲给你听。”

8.这里开始讲一系列孝敬父母的女儿的故事，第一位是德莉佩提娜

“德莉佩提娜是老底嘉[37]的女王，非常爱她的父亲。她是伟大的国王米特利达特[38]的女儿，因为敬仰她的父亲而跟随他上了所有的战场。这位女孩非常难看，她的乳牙从未脱落因而有两排牙齿，这是种很严重的畸形。但是她非常热爱她的父亲，以至于从未离开过他的左右，无论顺境还是逆境都是如此。她是一片广袤疆土的女主人，完全可以在本国过上安全舒适的生活，但她还是希望能够分担父亲每次征战时的痛苦。即使是在他被强大的庞培[39]击败时，她也还是不离不弃地全心照顾自己的父亲。”

……

12.正直女神宣布城市的建设已经结束，可以开始请居民入住了

“我亲爱的朋友，我看我们的建筑已经大功告成，淑女之城有了足够多的房子和宽阔的街道。皇宫也已建好，防御塔高高耸立，从数英里外就能看到。现在是时候让居民们入住了。这城不该被空置，而是应该住满卓越的淑女们，并且只有她们才会被欢迎进城。我们城的居民们会有多么的幸福！她们不必担心被游牧民族赶出家门，因为这座城市有个特性，使得任何入住的居民都永远不会被驱逐。一个新的女性国度就要诞生了，而且比之前的更加完美，因为淑女们不必再离开领地来生育继承王国的下一代女性。我们将要邀请来的淑女们已经足够永世流芳了。”

“一旦我们让城里住满了当之无愧的居民，我的姐妹公正女神就会带着女王一同过来，她是一位超越了所有其他淑女的出色女性，由最尊贵的贵族们陪同着。正是她们将要占据高耸的塔中最精美的住所。所以我们现在最紧要的任务就是，当女王驾临时，她应该看到满城优秀的女性，毕恭毕敬地迎接她们至高无上的女主人、君临整个女性性别的统治者。我们应该请来怎样的市民？会包括声名狼藉的荡妇吗？当然不会！她们将全是名声远播的坚定勇敢的女性，这些品性高尚值得尊敬的妇女们，是能装点我们城市的最有意义的人群了。来吧，克里斯蒂娜，让我们起程去寻访我们的淑女们吧。”

13.克里斯蒂娜询问正直女神，婚姻变得无法忍受是不是像男人和书中所说的那样，因为无法与女人共同生活。正直女神从女性对她们丈夫的爱是多么伟大开始回答这个问题

当我们依照正直女神所述走在寻访淑女的路上时，我边走边问她：“我的女神，你和理性女神都令人信服地回答了我自己无法解答的问题，我觉得我现在对这些问题的看法更深入了。谢谢你们两位，我发现了女性完全能胜任任何需要体力或学习能力的事情。但是我现在想问你一个一直萦绕着我的重要问题。有很多男人及书中都说，是因为妇女和她们的泼皮抱怨，使得婚姻成为了男人们的永恒坟墓。这是真的吗？很多人都支持这种观点，认为女人很少关心丈夫和他们的朋友，这让他们非常恼怒。为了躲避这种痛苦和问题，很多作者建议男人们都学聪明点不要结婚，因为没有或者很少有女人会对她们的伴侣忠诚。这个观点甚至体现在了《瓦列利乌斯给鲁非诺的信》[40]中，里面引用了泰奥弗拉斯托斯[41]书中所说的，聪明的男人不该结婚，因为女人是麻烦，她们缺乏感情还成天闲言碎语。他还说如果一个男人为了生病时能有人好好照顾而结婚，那还不如去找一个忠心的仆人，而且花费还能少些。另一方面，如果妻子生病了，他就会焦急起来，并觉得不离左右是自己的义务。泰奥弗拉斯托斯还有诸多此类的叙述，但我不想再继续说下去了。我亲爱的女神，如果这些事是真的，那这问题看来非常严重，足以完全抵消掉一位妇女所能拥有的美德和优秀品质了。”

正直女神回答道：“我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，正如你自己之前说过的，没人反驳的案子容易赢。但是请相信我，持有这些观点的书全都不是女性所写的。实际上我一点也不怀疑，如果有人愿意基于事实重新写一本关于婚姻问题的书的话，肯定会形成一套完全不同的观点。我亲爱的朋友，就像你自己所知道的，有那么多妻子生活在悲惨的婚姻中，粗暴的丈夫让她们的生活凄惨到还不如被野蛮人奴役。上帝啊，有多少优雅正派的妇女无缘无故地被殴打，被辱骂、猥亵和诅咒，被沉重的负担和侮辱压迫得毫无反抗力。更不必提那些要喂很多张小嘴的妻子们了，她们在赤贫中濒临饿死，而丈夫们却要么在寻欢作乐，要么在城里或酒馆中对此置若罔闻。这些妇女们在丈夫回家后所能得到的晚餐就只是他们的逃避而已。我来问你，我有一点点是在撒谎吗？你应该不会没见过你的某个邻居被如此对待过吧？”

我回答道：“是的，我的女神。我看到过很多妇女有这样的经历，我也很同情她们。”

“我完全相信这一点。至于说丈夫们会对妻子生病感到焦虑，我问你，我亲爱的朋友，你认识这样的丈夫吗？不必再追究更多细节我就可以告诉你，所有这些流传的关于妻子的废话都是连篇的谎话。丈夫们是妻子的主人，而不是相反的。一个男人永远也不会允许自己被一个女人所驾驭。但是我向你保证，并非所有的婚姻都是如此。也有一些夫妻互相敬爱，对对方忠诚，在一起平静地生活：在这些例子里双方都是明智、体贴和高尚的。尽管有很多不好的丈夫，但也有很多正派、可敬和智慧的丈夫。那些有幸跟这些男人结婚的妻子们应当感谢上帝赐予了她们这样的幸福。你自己也能证明这一点，因为你再也不会找到比你先夫更好的丈夫了。在你看来，他比所有男人都仁慈、温柔、忠诚和深情，你心里也永远无法停止对他早逝的哀思。同时我们无法否认，还有很多温柔的女性被与此相反的丈夫们虐待着，当然我们得承认也有一些妻子确实是固执又无理取闹的。实际上，如果我说所有的妻子都是道德的典范，那我也快要被指责为骗子了。但这种女人毕竟是少数。不管怎样，我宁可不去谈论这些女人，因为她就像是完全违背了自己天性的生物。”

“说到好的妻子，让我们回到你之前提到的泰奥弗拉斯托斯，他说仆人可以像妻子那样去照顾一个病弱的男人。你可以看到无数优秀而忠诚的妻子，服侍她们无论健康的或是病中的丈夫，都像对神明那样的尽心尽力！我可不觉得你会找到像那样的仆人。既然我们开始讨论这个话题了，我就给你一些妻子的例子，她们深爱着自己丈夫并把自己全部奉献给了他们。现在，感谢主，我们可以请一位体面又可敬的淑女来到我们的城市了。这就是尊贵的绪丝克拉提亚王后，米特利达特六世的妻子。因为她所处的时代非常古老，又有着无法衡量的价值，理所应当是第一位入住为她精心准备好的宫殿的淑女。”

14.关于绪丝克拉提亚王后

“怎么可能有人比绪丝克拉提亚王后爱她丈夫还要更爱一个人呢？她是如此体贴和忠诚。这位淑女是伟大的米特利达特六世的妻子，他的治下有着24种不同的语言。尽管他是有史以来最强大的国王，罗马人仍然对他发动了可怕的战争。在长期艰苦卓绝的战斗中，无论到了何处，他的妻子都从未离开过他。这位国王遵循野蛮人的习俗娶了数位妃子，但这位尊贵的淑女非常爱她的丈夫，因而不让他单独去任何地方，她经常陪伴着他征战。尽管王国岌岌可危，性命也时时堪忧，她依旧跟随他跋涉到偏远陌生之地，远渡重洋、深入沙漠，从未离开左右。她的爱是如此强烈，她认为没有人能像她一样忠诚地侍奉主人。”

“所以跟哲学家泰奥弗拉斯托斯所说的完全相反，这位淑女非常清楚，国王和贵族们的仆从经常不怎么忠诚又对他们照顾不周。因此这位忠诚的淑女把自己完全投入在了满足主人任何可能的需要上。尽管不得不克服各种艰难困苦，她依然跟随他出生入死。因为条件不允许她穿女性服装，而且这样一位伟大国王和勇士的妻子在战争中出现在他身边也不合适，所以她剪掉了女人最好的特质，即她长长的金发，以便装扮成男人。她也从未考虑过保护自己的肌肤，她的脸庞因为绑着头盔而很快由于汗水和尘土变得肮脏。她曼妙的躯体被甲胄所包裹。她摘下了所有贵重的戒指和珠宝，手被沉重的斧子、长矛和弓箭磨砺得粗糙坚硬。她腰上佩戴的是剑而非高贵的腰带。出于对丈夫忠贞的爱情，这位淑女完全适应了新的环境，她那年轻迷人的躯体本应过着更为柔软舒适的生活，却变成了强壮有力的战士的身体。听听薄伽丘在他的诗里是怎么说的：‘有什么爱情做不到的事吗？我们看到这位淑女，曾习惯了包括柔软床铺在内的各种舒适而精致的生活，却自愿把自己变得和男人一样坚韧而粗犷，四处征战、昼夜行军，经常在沙漠和丛林的硬地上安营扎寨，永远被敌袭所威胁，被野兽和蟒蛇所环绕。’但这些她全都可以接受，只要她能留在丈夫身边来安慰和劝告他，无微不至地照顾他。”

“后来，他们共同经历了很多苦难之后，她的丈夫被罗马军事家庞培残酷地击溃了，他们不得不踏上逃亡的道路。尽管他被所有部下抛弃了，他的妻子还是独自追随着他逃过高山、峡谷和很多漆黑危险的地方。在被所有朋友抛弃了的绝望时期，国王从他忠诚的妻子对未来憧憬的鼓励中得到了安慰。尽管他们跌落到了人生的低谷，她还是用尽全力让他打起精神，寻找合适的话语来驱走他的悲伤，创造出有趣的游戏来与他同乐。她通过这些努力加上自己的温柔，给丈夫带来了巨大的慰藉，以至于无论他有多么低迷沮丧或要承受多少痛苦，她都能够让他忘却不幸。他经常感动地说他觉得自己不像是在流亡中，倒像是在宫殿里跟所爱的妻子共度美好时光一般。”

……

21.关于哲学家苏格拉底之妻赞西佩

“可敬的淑女赞西佩是一位非常智慧并具有美德的妇女，她嫁给了伟大的哲学家苏格拉底。尽管他已经年迈并且用远远多于给妻子买礼物的时间来写书，这位淑女也从没有停止过对他的爱。实际上，她崇敬他超凡的智慧以及他的善良和坚定，因而深深地爱着他，并为他感到无比骄傲。当这位勇敢可敬的赞西佩得知，她丈夫因为攻击雅典人偶像崇拜的习俗并宣扬只有一位值得尊重和侍奉的神，而被他们宣判了死刑时，她就无法控制自己的情绪了。她痛苦地哭泣着，披头散发地冲上街道。她拼尽全力来到丈夫被关押的宫殿，发现他正被奸诈的法官们包围着，而且他们给了他毒汁让他饮下来结束自己的生命。她进入房间时苏格拉底正把杯子举到唇边打算饮下，于是她冲上去抢下杯子并把毒药洒在了地上。苏格拉底为此斥责了她，并试图安慰她，告诉她要有耐心。看到无法阻止丈夫的死亡，她完全沉浸在了悲痛中，哭道：‘杀死一个好人是怎样的罪孽和损失啊！是怎样的错误和不公啊！’苏格拉底一直试着去劝解她，解释说被不公正地处死比起被罪有应得地处死要好得多。于是他就这么死去了，但在深爱着他的妻子的余生中，她没有一刻停止对他的哀思。”

……

25.克里斯蒂娜对正直女神说有些人声称女人无法保守秘密；正直女神在回应中谈到了小加图[42]的女儿珀提娅

“我的女神，我完全确信我经常亲眼看到的：无论过去还是现在，很多女人都明确地表现出了她们有多爱自己的丈夫以及有多么投入地付出。这就是我为什么觉得这一点很奇怪：男人们普遍认为不应该告诉女人任何他们需要保守的秘密，因为女人嘴太大，包括大师让·克洛皮内尔在他的《玫瑰传奇》中，以及其他的作者都这么说过。”

正直女神回答道：“我亲爱的朋友，就像你明白的那样，不是所有的女人都很聪明，男人也是一样。因此如果一个男人有那么点判断力，那他自己在告诉妻子秘密之前就应该明白她是否可信和善良，因为这有可能会带来危险的后果。任何知道自己妻子是可靠而细心谨慎的人，都是可以完全对她放心的，因为这世界上再没有比她更值得完全信任的人了。”

“至于女人是否像有些人说的那样轻率，我们还是回到爱着丈夫的那些女人身上。罗马尊敬的布鲁图[43]，珀提娅的丈夫，当然不会这么认为。这位淑女是老加图的侄子[44]小加图的女儿。他知道妻子有多聪颖和贤惠，于是告诉了她自己和另一位罗马元老卡西乌斯[45]打算在元老院刺杀恺撒。但是，这位敏感的淑女意识到了后果的可怕，因而极力劝解丈夫放弃这个计划。她被丈夫的密谋困扰得一夜无法入眠。第二天一早当布鲁图离开寝室去执行计划时，珀提娅绝望地试图阻止他，于是拿着理发的剃刀装作要修剪指甲，然后掉在了地上。她俯身去捡时，故意把刀片深深切进了手里。女仆被主人的伤情吓得大声尖叫，布鲁图听到就转身回了家。他看到她伤到自己之后就责备她，说使用剃刀是理发匠的事，不是她的事。她回答说自己没有他想得那么傻：她是故意这么做的，想试试看如果他事成之后受到伤害，自己该怎样自杀。布鲁图还是没有改变主意地离开了家。很快，他和卡西乌斯刺杀了恺撒，他们因此被判流放。即使布鲁图已经被驱逐出了罗马，他最终还是被暗杀了。珀提娅得知他的死讯之后，心神错乱，丧失了活下去的意愿。因为她想做的事太明显了，家人藏起了所有尖锐的器皿和刀具，她就在火边取了正在燃烧的煤块吞了下去。就这样，高贵的珀提娅通过灼烧内脏自杀了，这是人类曾经历过的最奇特的死法。”

……

28.对于那些说只有傻瓜才会听从妻子的建议或相信她的人的反证；克里斯蒂娜问了一些问题以及正直女神的回答

“我的女神，听到你的论述并且亲眼见到女性是多么的明智和可靠之后，我很吃惊有些人说只有傻瓜才会听取和相信妻子的建议。”

正直女神回答道：“我之前也告诉你了，并非所有的女性都是聪颖的。但是如果那些有着既有责任感又可靠的妻子的男人们也不肯信任她们的话，那他们就太傻了。从我之前讲的你可以看到：如果布鲁图听从了珀提娅的建议不要去刺杀恺撒，他就不会被暗杀，之后的种种悲剧也就可以避免了。既然我们正在讨论这个主题，我就再告诉你一些男人们因为没有听从妻子的劝解而遭难的故事吧。这之后，我会给你一些丈夫们好好听从了妻子建议的例子。”

“如果我们刚刚提到的儒略·恺撒，当初信任了他明智又聪慧的妻子，他那天就不会去元老院，也就不会死了。她看到了诸多丈夫会被暗杀的预兆，并且头天晚上正做了这样的噩梦，因此尽她所能地做了一切努力来阻止丈夫那天去元老院。”

“同样的事情在庞培身上也发生了，他最早跟茱莉亚，也就是儒略·恺撒的女儿结婚，之后我告诉过你，他的第二任妻子是一位叫作科涅莉亚的高贵淑女。就像我们之前说的一样，这位淑女非常爱她的丈夫，以至于无论怎样的逆境降临都拒绝离开他。即便是在他战败给恺撒被迫从海上逃亡时，这位科涅莉亚也跟随着他，与他共同面对所有的危险。当庞培抵达了埃及王国的时候，背信弃义的国王托勒密装作很高兴地欢迎他的到来并派人去迎接庞培，而实际是去刺杀他的。这些人让庞培把所有人都留在岸上，仅他只身一人回到船上，以便减轻船重顺利入港。庞培很乐意打算照做，但他忠诚的妻子试图阻止他就这么跟自己人分开。看到他不想改变主意，她就尝试跳回船上陪他，因为她感觉事情好像不大对劲。但是他不允许她这么做，并且让人强行留下了她。这位淑女的悲痛就此开始了，并且萦绕了她一生。她丈夫刚刚起航，视线一刻没有离开他的科涅莉亚就亲眼看到他被船上的叛徒杀死了。她极为心慌意乱，以至于如果不是被人制止住，就会当场跳入海中了。”

“与此类似，同样的厄运也降临在了特洛伊的赫克特头上。在他被杀的前一天晚上，他的妻子安德洛玛刻做了一个奇怪的梦，这个梦告诉她如果赫克特参加第二天的战斗就会丧命。她很震惊，认为这并不仅仅是个噩梦而是一个真实的预言，这位淑女双手合在胸前跪下来恳求丈夫别去参加今天的战斗，甚至还把他们两个可爱的孩子抱到他的面前。但是他完全没有在意她的话，因为他觉得如果听从一个女人的建议而离开战场，将会给他带来无法挽回的耻辱。安德洛玛刻请他的父母去替她恳求，他也同样没有听从。一切就像她所说的那样发生了。所以，如果赫克特听了她的话，就不会被阿喀琉斯杀死了。”

“我可以给你举出无数这样的例子，男人们因为不肯屈尊去听妻子有道理的建议，而遭受到了不同程度的损失。但是那些因不听信妻子而以悲剧收场的男人，可以责备的就只有他们自己了。”

……

31.关于高尚的寡妇友第德

“高尚的寡妇友第德从赫罗弗尼斯手中拯救了以色列人民。赫罗弗尼斯被尼布甲尼撒二世[46]派来统治犹太人，并占领了埃及。犹太人被赫罗弗尼斯强大的军队围困在城中，已经遭受重创坚持不了多久了。水源供应被他切断，存粮也快告罄了。感觉坚持不下去了的犹太人已经惊惶到了战败的边缘。他们开始祈祷，恳求上帝怜悯他的子民，不要让他们落到敌人手中。上帝听到了他们的祈祷，就如同他后来派的是一位女性去拯救人类那样，这次也选择了一位妇女去营救他们。”

“城中住着一位高贵勇敢的淑女叫友第德，年轻可爱，又有典范性的美德和纯真。她怜悯危难中的人们，日夜向神祈祷拯救他们。她从自己信仰的上帝那里得到了启示，密谋出了一个计划。一个夜晚，她把自己托付给上帝，在一个女仆的陪同下离开了城池，前往赫罗弗尼斯的营地。当负责警卫的哨兵在月光下看到她的美貌时，就直接把她带到了赫罗弗尼斯面前。他很高兴得到这么一个美得炫目的女人，让她在身边坐下，并很快被她的智慧、高贵举止和美貌所倾倒。他越盯着她，就越是想要得到她。有着自己打算的友第德在心中默默向上帝祈祷，希望他能在她尝试时守护她，让赫罗弗尼斯一点一点地上钩，直到时机成熟。3个夜晚之后，赫罗弗尼斯给他的贵族们举办了酒宴，喝得酩酊大醉。酒足饭饱之时，他迫不及待想与这位希伯来女人同床共枕，就派人叫了她来。友第德听了他的愿望之后，表示同意这样做，但为了得体起见，需要他把人都摈出帐外，他自己先上床，而友第德在半夜夜深人静的时候再造访他。赫罗弗尼斯接受了这些条件。这位淑女开始祈祷，希望神能在她颤抖的女性心灵中赐予足够的力量和勇气，使她的人民能从这暴君的手中解脱。”

“当友第德觉得赫罗弗尼斯已经睡着时，就和女仆蹑手蹑脚地走到他的帐篷口倾听。听到他熟睡的声音，她边呼喊着‘让我们动手吧，上帝与我们同在！’边冲入帐内，无畏地抽出了他挂在床边的宝剑，用尽全身的力气提起剑，悄然无声地砍下了赫罗弗尼斯的头。她用裙子包好头颅，迅速往回跑。友第德没有遇到一点阻碍，回到了城门，大喊道：‘来开城门吧，上帝与我们同在！’她进入城中之后，你无法想象市民们看到她的所作所为时有多么欣喜若狂。到了早晨，他们把头颅钉在尖木桩上挑出城墙去，然后披挂上阵，勇猛敏捷地袭击了还在睡梦中毫无准备的敌人。他们迅速冲进主将的帐篷，想让他尽快起来，却惊骇地发现他已经身首异处了。于是犹太人把他们全部俘虏，杀得一个不剩。以色列人就这样被友第德从赫罗弗尼斯的手中救了出来。这位英勇女性的颂歌应当在《圣经》中被永远传唱。”

……

33.关于萨宾妇女[47]

“我可以举出很多保护了自己国家或城市的古代女性异教徒的例子。但我只准备讲两个比较重要的来证明我的观点。”

“在罗慕卢斯和雷穆斯建立了罗马城之后，罗穆卢斯把他在战争中所能召集到的骑士和士兵都聚集在了城中。他非常急于为这些男人们寻找配偶，因为只有这样他们的后代将来才能继续统治这个城市。但是周边国家从国王、贵族到人民都觉得他们是个鲁莽野蛮而无法信任的民族，因此不愿意把女儿嫁给他们，甚至不愿意跟他们建立任何联系。罗穆卢斯无法给自己和士兵们找到妻子，因而想出了一个狡猾的计策。他向全境宣布，将举办一个骑士长矛比武的赛事，并且邀请所有国王、贵族以及民众带着他们的妻女出席。在庆典当天，大批的人群从四面八方聚集而来，因为太太小姐们都想要看这场比试。在这中间也有萨宾国王的女儿，一位美丽迷人的女孩，由她从国内带来的女伴们陪同。比赛是在城墙外山脚下的一块平原上举行的，所有的女性都排坐在高地上。骑士们在可爱淑女们的注视下勇气大增，武艺一个比一个出众。长话短说，当他们打斗了一阵之后，罗穆卢斯觉得执行自己计划的时机到了，于是拿出一个巨大的象牙号角吹了起来。听到这声作为行动信号的巨响，骑士们停止了互相搏击，转而冲向了妇女们。罗穆卢斯抢下了自己心仪的国王女儿，其他骑士也带走了自己看中的女人。罗马人把淑女们强行带上马匹，飞奔回城之后立刻放下城门。在城外，她们的父亲和亲属们跟这些被劫持的妇女们一样失声痛哭，但也都无济于事了。罗穆卢斯用盛大的仪式迎娶了他的妻子，其他骑士也照做了。”

“这次事件引发了一场可怕的战争。萨宾王很快就集结了大军攻打罗马人，但要打败这些战斗老手是很难的。战争持续了五年之后的某一天，双方全副武装准备在战场上兵戎相见，很明显一场伤亡惨重的战斗迫在眉睫。等到大批罗马人出了城门，王后就召集罗马妇女在一个寺庙中集会。这位聪明美丽的少妇对她们说道：‘可敬的萨宾女性们、姐妹们和伙伴们，你们都非常清楚我们是怎样被我们的丈夫们诱拐来，这又如何引起了我们父兄和丈夫之间的战争的。这场战争无论是继续下去，还是以哪一方的胜利告终，都无法避免对我们造成伤害。如果是我们丈夫输了，我们已经爱上了他们还有了孩子，我们会心碎而孩子们也将失去父亲。如果反之，我们的丈夫赢了而父兄们被杀了，我们也会深深为这场由我们引起的冲突而痛心的。已然发生的事早就无法挽回，在我看来，我们应该找到一个能和平解决这场战争的方法。如果你们决定听从我的建议，那就跟随我，我相信我们可以终止这件事。’听了她的话，其他妇女同声回应，说她们同意这样做，并愿意遵从她的指示。”

“王后于是散开头发脱下鞋，其他妇女也照做了。有孩子的就把孩子抱在怀中，还有一群孩子和孕妇也加入了行列。王后带领着这感人的队列径直走向双方列队的战场。她们站在了双方阵营中间，这样骑士们就不可能越过她们而直接攻击到对方了。女王和其他女性都跪下喊道：‘亲爱的父亲们和兄弟们，敬爱的丈夫们：看在上帝的分上和解吧！不然的话，我们就做好被你们的马蹄践踏而死的准备了。’看到自己的妻子和孩子们失声痛哭，罗马的骑士们都震惊地打退堂鼓了：他们是不可能攻击她们的。这些妇女的父亲们也被女儿们的惨状打动了。双方看着对方，出于对这些哀求他们停手的妇女们的同情，他们的恨变成了对子女的爱。萨宾人和罗马人都扔下手中的武器冲上去拥抱对方，就此和解了。罗穆卢斯带着他的岳父萨宾之王进了城，用最高的礼仪接待了他和他的军队。就这样，多亏了女王和妇女们的勇气和判断力，罗马人和萨宾人避免了互相残杀。”

……

36.反驳那些声称妇女受教育是没有好处的人

听到这些话，我，克里斯蒂娜，说道：“我的女神，我可以清楚地看到女性给世界带来了很多美好的事物。即使一些邪恶的女人做过一些坏事，在我看来这也还是远远比不上女性一直以来做过并继续在做的好事。我们之前提到的那些聪颖的、在科学艺术上接受过良好教育的妇女们尤其如此。这就是为什么我很奇怪有些男人完全反对女儿、妻子或其他女性亲属去上学，说是因为担心她们的道德会因此而崩坏。”

正直女神回答说：“这件事就足以说明，并非所有男人的看法都是有道理的，尤其这些男人更加是大错特错了。道德方面的知识应该是促进美德的，说它会产生破坏的效果是完全没有道理的。正相反，这种知识毫无疑问能够纠正人的恶习，端正人的品行。怎么会有人觉得学习好的东西会让人变坏呢？这个观点完全无法理喻，也是站不住脚的。我并不是说男人或女人可以去学习巫术或其他禁术，因为教会可不是随便就禁止了这些东西的。但是，说女人会因学习了何为正确何为合理而变坏，这是错误的。”

“罗马伟大的雄辩家和演说家昆图斯·霍腾修斯[48]，并不同意这个观点。他有一位叫作霍腾西娅的女儿，他非常喜爱她的机敏。他亲自教育她，教给了她雄辩术。薄伽丘认为她出色到不仅仅是跟她父亲的智慧、敏捷和措辞相似，而且在口才和演讲术上的优秀甚至超越了他。我们之前谈到了妇女带来的益处，而这位淑女的作为尤其值得注目。当时罗马正被后三头[49]统治着，因为罗马面临的严重财政危机，有人建议对妇女特别征税，尤其是对她们的财宝收税。这位霍腾西娅决定为妇女辩护，而这是没有男人敢做的事情。她的演说是如此具有说服力，大家都凝神听她说话，就像是在听她父亲演讲一样。她最终打赢了这场官司。”

“让我们从古代回到近代。差不多60年前在博洛尼亚[50]教书的著名法学家乔瓦尼·安德里亚，也同样反对妇女不该接受教育的观点。他给了爱女诺薇拉非常优秀的教育，包括教给她详尽的法律知识。这样当他在忙碌其他事而不能去教课的时候，就会让他的女儿去替他给学生们授业。诺薇拉讲课时在前面垂了一个帘子，免得学生们为她的美貌分心。她就这样减轻了父亲的负担，把他从部分职责中解放了出来。为了表达对女儿的爱，他把一个重要的法律说明文献命名为La Novella，使她的名字可以流传万代。”

“因此并非所有男人，尤其是那些最有智慧的男人，都会同意女性不该受教育的这个观点。但确实那些不怎么聪明的男人会产生这个想法，因为他们不希望妇女比自己知道得多。你自己的父亲，一位伟大的占星家和哲学家，就不相信科学知识会降低女性的价值。你是知道的，看着你学习给他带来了多大的快乐。相反的，正是因为你的母亲作为女性反而认为你应该像其他女孩那样忙碌度日，你才没有能够学习到更高等或更深入的科学。但就像我们之前说的，‘本性难移’。尽管你母亲反对，你还是因为自身的好学而学到了不少知识。在我看来，很明显你并未因为拥有这些知识而贬低自己：你实际上很珍惜它，而这样做是对的。”

我，克里斯蒂娜，于是回答道：“毫无疑问，我的女神，你所说的就像主祷文[51]一样完全正确。”

37.克里斯蒂娜对正直女神的发问，后者从苏珊娜[52]开始举例来反对那些说少有女性是贞洁的看法

“就我所看到的，我的女神，所有的优点和美德都能在女性身上体现，那么为什么这些男人会说没几个女人是贞洁的？如果这是真的话，那她们所有其他的品质就都毫无价值了，因为贞洁是女人最重要的美德。不过，像你之前所述，事实应该和他们所说的相去甚远。”

正直女神回答道：“正如我之前告诉你、你自己也已经明白了的那样，事实是完全相反的。对于这个问题我可以一直讲到时间的尽头。圣经提到了这么多出色又忠贞的淑女，她们宁死也不愿丧失身体贞操和道德良心。其中一位坚贞可爱的淑女就是苏珊娜，约阿希姆的妻子，他是位富有又有影响力的犹太人。有一天，这位诚实的淑女漫步在自家花园，两个年老男子接近了她。他们是假神父，想把她引向罪孽。看到她断然拒绝了他们的接近，连恳求也完全无效，他们就威胁要向法庭告发她跟年轻男人通奸。听到这样的威胁，也清楚通奸的女人是要被判以石块砸死的，她喊道：‘我现在真是进退维谷，因为如果我拒绝这些男人，我的肉身就会被处以死刑；但是如果我屈从了他们的要求，我就会在创世者眼中犯下罪孽。那么我宁可清白地去死，也不愿用罪行来激怒上帝。’苏珊娜因此高声喊叫起来，家里的其他人立刻冲了出来。长话短说，后来假神父们想方设法让法庭确信了他们的伪证，苏珊娜因此被判处了死刑。但一直在看着的上帝让预言者丹尼尔开口了，那时候他还是个母亲怀中的小孩：当这孩子看到苏珊娜被带向刑场，后面跟着一大群抽泣着的人时，就为这位无辜受刑的妇女哭了出来。她于是被带回了法庭，假神父在那里被仔细盘问并自己供认了罪行。就这样，无罪的苏珊娜被拯救了，而他们则被处罚了。”

……

44.为反驳那些说妇女希望被强暴的人，这里举了一系列例子，第一个是卢克雷蒂娅

我，克里斯蒂娜，于是说道：“我的女神，我完全相信你所说的，我确信很多美丽的女人是正派诚实的，也足以在面对引诱者的陷阱时保护自己。因此当男人们说女人希望被强暴时，我就觉得十分愤慨和难过。他们说女人即使嘴上拒绝，也不会介意被暴力推倒。我无法相信女性会从被这样粗暴的对待中获得乐趣。”

正直女神回答说：“我亲爱的朋友，你可以确信那些贞洁而有道德操守的女性不会从被强暴中获得快乐。正相反，她们觉得这是可能发生在自己身上的最糟糕的事情。有很多例子，比如卢克雷蒂娅，可以证明这一点。卢克雷蒂娅是罗马一位出身高贵的淑女，并且是罗马最贞洁的女性，她嫁给了贵族塔昆努斯·克拉迪努斯。很不幸，罗马君主卢修斯·塔克文·苏佩布[53]也为她深深倾倒了。他很清楚卢克雷蒂娅是多么的贞洁，因此不敢直接去接近她。因为知道诱惑和祈求都是没有用的，他于是开始打算用诡计得到她。他装成是她丈夫的好朋友，这样就可以在她家中来去自如。塔克文趁她丈夫不在家的某天到访，被高贵的女主人以最尊贵的礼节接待，就像对待她丈夫最好的朋友那样。那天晚上，心怀鬼胎的塔克文潜入了卢克雷蒂娅的卧室，把她吓得魂飞魄散。简单来说，在对她做了无数金银财宝的许诺之后，他发现恳求是无用的。于是他拔出剑，威胁如果她出声拒绝就杀了她。她于是让他动手，宁死也不愿意屈从。当发现威胁也无用之后，塔克文又想出一个卑鄙的办法，他声称会对外公布他发现她跟自己的一个仆人搞在一起。长话短说，相信塔克文会这么做的想法吓坏了她，于是终于屈从了他。”

“但是卢克雷蒂娅并不能轻易承受这可怕的罪过。当早晨来临时，她就去找到她的丈夫、父亲和其他近亲，他们都是罗马显赫的市民。她一边呜咽一边向他们供认了发生在自己身上的罪行。当她的丈夫和家人试图安慰她以解除她强烈的痛苦时，她从罩袍中拔出一把小刀，说：‘尽管我能开脱我的罪行并证明我是无辜的，但我还是无法摆脱痛苦和煎熬：从今天开始以我身上发生的事为鉴，女人不需要再生活在因类似事情所带来的羞愧和耻辱中。’说完这些话，她就把刀深深扎进了自己的胸膛，在自己的丈夫和他的朋友们面前当场毙命。他们像疯了一样冲向了塔克文。整个罗马都被此事激怒了：他们废黜了国王，并且险些杀掉他的儿子，只是没能找到他。从此之后罗马就再也没有过国王了。有些人说，鉴于发生在卢克雷蒂娅身上的暴行，罗马通过了一条法律，明文规定对妇女施暴者判处死刑，这是一条符合道德的合适而公正的法令。”

……

47.驳倒认为女性反复无常的证据：克里斯蒂娜提问，正直女神用数位善变而不可靠的皇帝为例作答

“我的女神，你谈到的妇女都显然是非常坚定、刚毅和忠诚的。可不可以说她们已经能跟最强的男人相媲美了呢？但男人们，特别是那些作者们众口一词的指责就是，女性是易变、浮躁、轻率、轻浮和优柔寡断的，她们像孩子一样易受人影响并且完全没有决断力。那么男人就很坚定吗？因为他们总是在责备女人易变，却从没有听他们说过男人犹豫不决。如果他们自己实际上也是反复无常的，还要去指责别人跟自己一样的缺点，或者坚持认为其他人应该有他们自身所不具备的美德，那这种行为就是让人完全无法接受的了。”

正直女神的回答是：“我最亲爱的朋友，你没听到人们常说，傻瓜很快就能看到邻居眼中的刺，却很难看到自己眼中有梁木吗？[54]我会给你看看，男人批判女人善变和反复无常是多么的荒唐不合理。他们的理论是这样的。首先，他们假定妇女先天就是软弱的。然后，他们在指责过女性这个弱点之后就认为自己是坚定的，至少比女人要坚定。实际上他们对女性坚定性的要求，要远远高于他们自己所能做到的。尽管他们自认为是坚强而高贵的，但当他们面对人性的一些可怕的弱点时，也并不能阻止自己沦陷其中。而且这并不总是不小心走入歧途的，反而经常是蓄意为之的，因为他们知道自己当下正在犯罪。但是他们之后会给自己开脱说，是人都会犯错。但如果是一位女性做了错事，而且这通常是出于一个男人纠缠不休的诡计，那你看着吧，他们就会宣扬说这是由于女性天生的软弱和善变造成的了。既然他们认为女人是如此柔弱的，那说句实话，他们就更应该去包容女性的弱点才对，更不能当同样的罪行发生在自己身上时说成是微不足道的小错，在女性身上时就指责为滔天大罪。因为没有法律，也没有文字曾说过他们被允许犯比女性更多的错，或者说过他们的弱点更可以被原谅。虽然如此，他们还是给自己树立了道德权威，远非是放过女性，反倒是把自己所有的过错和罪行都推卸到了女性身上。可是，如果女性在这样的罪行前表现出坚定和顽强，他们也完全不会去赞赏。所以无论是什么观点，男人们从任何角度都是有话可说的，而且都会证明自己是对的。你自己也在《上帝的爱之信笺》里用很长的篇幅讨论过这点。”

“你之前问我，是否男人都是正直和可敬的，以至于他们可以去指控别人善变。我会说如果你从古代开始考察人类历史直到今日，从书中汲取例子加上你过去的所见所闻，还有现在仍旧能看到的，不仅观察下层社会或未经教化的男人，也去看看上层社会的男人，你就能自己评判他们到底展现过怎样完美的坚持和定力了！当然这只是绝大多数男人的情况，感谢上帝，还有那么一些男人是聪明和坚强不渝的。”

“如果你让我给你一些从古到今的摇摆不定的男人的例子，因为男人们一直在攻击女性的这个弱点，好像他们自己的心从未动摇过似的，那我们就来看看那些最有权势的贵族们和最显赫的男人们是怎样的吧。我举他们的例子是因为，这些人一旦犯错，所带来的影响要比一般人大得多。更不用提有多少皇帝曾有过这样的过错了！我来问你，会有女人比罗马帝国皇帝克劳狄一世更为软弱、胆小而可悲吗？他是如此善变，朝令夕改到上一分钟作的决定下一分钟就会推翻。你没法相信他说的话，因为他会同意任何人说的任何话。他在震怒中下令杀掉了自己的妻子，然后当晚却问她为什么没有回卧室来睡觉！对那些被他砍了头的朋友们，他还派人去告诉他们应该来找自己玩！他缺乏勇气，所以一直处于一种惶恐的状态中，也无法信任任何人。我还能告诉你什么呢？所有道德和精神上的弱点在这位糟糕透顶的皇帝身上都能找到。但是我为什么要特别提到他呢？他是唯一一个坐在皇位上却有着这些弱点的统治者吗？提庇留皇帝就好些吗？他难道不是比任何女人都更加摇摆善变而又淫荡吗？”

48.关于尼禄[55]

“既然我们正在讨论皇帝，那就来说说尼禄怎么样？他的善变和软弱是显而易见的。他一开始还彬彬有礼地想要取悦每一个人，但是很快，他的色欲、凶残和贪婪就都失去了控制。为了更好地放纵自己的恶习，他经常半夜全副武装地跟犯罪同伙们出去寻找堕落的场所，满城乱转以满足自己的淫欲取乐。为了给自己的肮脏行径找借口，尼禄会故意去撞街上的行人，如果他们出言不逊，他就会攻击然后杀掉他们。他闯入小酒馆和妓院强暴妇女，有一次差点被一位受害妇女的丈夫杀死。他组织过通宵达旦的淫荡洗浴聚会和宴会。他会随着自己变化无常的想法一会儿下令这样一会儿下令那样。尼禄纵容肉欲，变态而放肆，傲慢并且挥霍无度。他偏爱恶人却迫害忠良。他曾参与谋杀自己的父亲，后来下令杀了自己的母亲。她死后，他还让人剖开她的身体，要看看自己当年被孕育的地方。看到了这样的她，尼禄宣布说她曾是一位美丽的女性。他杀掉了他的第一任妻子，一位高贵的女性屋大维娅，娶了第二位妻子。但他也只是开始喜欢，后来杀了她。他还下令处死了他长辈的妻子克劳迪娅，因为后者拒绝嫁给他。尼禄还杀掉了他不满7岁的继子，仅仅因为他在玩耍时被人说举止像是皇帝的儿子。”

“尼禄的老师，著名哲学家塞内加[56]，也被皇帝下令处死，因为他无法隐藏自己对眼前发生的一切的羞耻感。尼禄假装给自己的老师治疗牙疼，用药毒死了他。同样，他也赐给最显赫的贵族们和德高望重的巨头们下过毒的饮食，尽管他们都位高权重。他不仅谋杀了他的姑母以攫取她的全部财产，还毁掉了罗马所有最尊贵的家族，在流放他们的途中杀光了他们的孩子。他训练了一个凶残的埃及人来吃人肉，以便把活人喂给他吞噬。我还能说什么？要讲述他所有的邪恶或骇人听闻的罪行是不可能的。最终，他把罗马城付之一炬，让它烧了整整六天六夜。很多人在这场可怕的灾难中丧生，而他却站在自己的塔楼里唱着歌，看着城市陷入火海地狱，还高兴地欣赏着火焰的壮丽。他在晚餐桌上下令杀掉了圣彼得和圣保罗以及很多其他的殉道者。14年以来他一直这样统治着，直到罗马人民最终忍无可忍而起义推翻了他。他最后在绝望中结束了自己的生命。”

……

53.在正直女神谈完了坚定的女性之后，克里斯蒂娜问她为什么以前这些可敬的女性并没有驳斥男人和那些诽谤女性的书，正直女神给出了答案

以上就是正直女神给我讲的故事。因为篇幅所限我没法再深入讲解她说过的其他例子，比如一位希腊女性莱俄伊娜拒绝控告她的两位朋友，宁可在法官面前咬掉自己的舌头，来表明无论他如何折磨她，也无法迫使她说出他想要的东西来。正直女神还告诉了我其他一些意志坚强的女性，宁可饮下毒药自杀也不肯背弃事实和正义的故事。我于是对她说：“我的女神，你很清楚地向我展现了女性在各种美德之外，还有着多么坚定持久的意志力。这样说来，还会有男人比女性更为出色吗？所以我很诧异，有这么多可敬的女性，尤其是那些学识渊博，可以写出优美著作的女性，会容忍男人们长久以来的污蔑而不去反驳。她们应该非常清楚这些男人的指控有多么荒谬啊。”

正直女神回答道：“我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，这个问题很好回答。从我给你讲的你应该已经意识到了，我们讨论的那些品德高尚的淑女都活跃在各自的领域里，而并非是协商好一起朝着同一个目标努力的。构建城市的工作是留给你来做的，而不是她们，因为她们的作品本身就已足够让有判断力和学识的人来欣赏佩服女性了，根本不需要她们再去写些什么来说明这点。至于说还没有人驳斥过那些攻击和批判女性的男人们，我可以告诉你，凡事都有它发生的时机和地点。你想想看，上帝让那些跟他律法相违背的异端邪说兴盛了多久，这说明它们是很难被剿灭的，而且如果没有被摧毁的话还会流传至今。有很多事物都是这样毫无阻碍地兴盛起来的，而时限一到就会被驳倒了。”

我，克里斯蒂娜，又对她说道：“我的女神，你说得很对。但我也确信这段话肯定会引来很多异议。他们会说，尽管过去或现在的一些女性也许很有品行，但这并不代表所有的，哪怕只是大多数的女性都会如此。”

正直女神回答道：“说大部分女性都没有美德肯定是不对的。我之前给你讲的已经很清楚地说明这一点了：经验告诉我们，无论是工作日还是休息日，任何人都能看到妇女是多么的虔诚、慈爱和善良，更不用说她们绝不是那数不清的犯罪和暴行的始作俑者了。说以上每条都是美德一点也不过分。当上帝派先知约拿去人口众多的大型都市尼尼微[57]，如果那里的人们不忏悔罪行就毁灭它时，那里连一个好男人都找不出来。所多玛[58]也没有一个体面的男人，当罗得离开这个被天降的硫黄与火吞没的城市时，这一点已经再明显不过了。此外，你也不该忘记耶稣基督的同伴只有12位，还有一个是恶魔。再来想想那些居然说所有女人都应该是品德高尚的，否则就该被投以石块处死的男人！我想请他们好好看看自己，然后让没有罪的那位站出来投第一块石头。[59]此外，他们自己又该追求什么样的品行？我可以告诉你，等到全体男人都达到了完美境地的那一天，妇女就可以以他们为榜样了。”

54.克里斯蒂娜问正直女神有些男人所说的“极少有女人对爱情忠贞”是否正确，以及正直女神的回答

我，克里斯蒂娜，又开口继续另一个论题：“我的女神，让我们把这些放在一边，再来看看别的话题。我想问你一些跟我们之前谈论的稍稍有点不同的问题。我希望你不会介意讨论我想说的这些，尽管这件事本身跟自然规律有关，但它多少还是逾越了理性的行为。”

正直女神说：“我的朋友，你尽可以直言不讳。若是学生出于求知而向老师提出问题，那就不应该因为触及到了什么而被谴责。”

“我的女神，这世上有一种自然的魅力，让男人被女人吸引，女人被男人吸引。这不是社会规则，而是肉体的本能：被色欲所激发，两性会以一种野性的激情相爱。没有哪方明白自己为什么会如此为对方所倾倒，但他们屈服于这种感情，并且称之为情爱。男人们通常说，尽管恋爱中的女人会作出忠诚的承诺，但她不仅轻易地更换着情人，而且还很无情、阴险和虚伪。他们坚称女人的这种轻浮是因为她们缺乏道德意识。在所有作过这样批判的作者中，奥维德在《爱的艺术》中所说的尤其恶毒。在攻击了妇女在爱情上缺乏坚定性之后，奥维德和所有其他人都接着宣称，他们写这些关于妇女的虚伪和罪孽的书是为了公众利益：他们的目的是警告男人们小心女人的欺诈，还有教育他们如何躲避她们，就好像妇女是草丛里隐藏的蛇一样。我亲爱的女神，请告诉我这件事情的真相吧。”

正直女神回答道：“我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，关于他们所说的女性的诡诈，我不知道我还有什么可以告诉你的。你自己在《爱神之书》和《玫瑰浪漫之书》中驳斥奥维德和其他人时，也曾长篇讨论过这个问题。但是回到你所说的，这些男人号称写书是为了公众利益这点上，我可以证明给你看绝对不是这么回事。原因很简单：如果一个事物不是对整个城市、国家或一群人有普遍好处的话，那它就不能被称作是公众利益。女性和男性应该是同等受益的。那些仅仅是为一部分人利益所做的事，是应该叫作私人利益或个人利益的，并不是公众利益。更何况，那些为部分人利益而损害其他人的事，就不只是私人利益或个人利益的问题了，这实际上等同于损人利己：受益方的花销是靠对方买单的。这些作者绝不会让妇女去提防男人给她们设下的陷阱，尽管谁也无法否认，男人其实经常会用他们虚伪的外表和狡猾的诡计去欺骗女性。此外，女性跟男性一样是由上帝创造的人类，这一点也是毋庸置疑的。她们并非是另一种生物或者一个独特的种群，要真是那样她们倒或许可以被排除在道德教育之外了。因此我只能总结说，如果这些作者真是为了公众利益，那他们就应该在建议男人小心女人的同时，也警告女人小心那些男人们设下的陷阱。”

“让我们先把这些放在一边，回到你之前问的问题。我前面给你讲的那些例子里，妇女们坚持忠贞直到生命的最后一刻，这还不够证明女性的心灵远非这些作者们所说的，在爱情上是善变薄情的吗？她们实际上是异常坚定的。”

……

62.克里斯蒂娜向正直女神发问，后者在回答中驳斥了那些宣称妇女用魅力吸引男人的观点

我，克里斯蒂娜，又问道：“我的女神，直到你说激情就像是凶险的海面之前都是完全正确的。从我的见闻来看，任何稍有判断力的女性都应该尽全力去避免激情，因为它只会带来巨大的伤害。但是那些穿着优雅希望借此更漂亮妩媚的女人们就招来了很多批判，因为有人说她们这样做只是为了吸引男人的注意力。”

正直女神回答道：“我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，我并不想帮那些过分讲究衣着外表的女人找借口，因为这可不是人性上的小缺点。穿不合自己身份的衣着尤其该受到谴责。但是我也不希望任何人认为自己有资格去苛责那些打扮漂亮的人，我这么说当然并不是想要宽恕这种恶行。我可以向你保证，并非所有这样做的女人都是想去勾引男人的。有些人，不光是女人，男人也一样，纯粹是喜欢漂亮的东西以及精美昂贵的服饰，就像喜欢干净整洁的衣服那样。如果天性如此，那他们就很难抗拒这点了，当然若能做到则是很应该被褒奖的。我们的主是向穷人传道的，但十二门徒之一、出身高贵的巴多罗买，不就是被记载一直穿着缀满宝石的丝质流苏长袍吗？尽管这种举动通常都是狂妄的炫耀，但巴多罗买却不该因此被说成是有罪的，因为他的天性就是喜欢穿贵重的衣服。即便如此，也还是有些人说主是因此而让他被剥皮殉道的。我说这些是想告诉你，任何人去评判他人的外表都是错误的：只有上帝才有权力来审判我们。我现在来给你举一些关于这个话题的例子。”

……

64.正直女神解释说有美德的女性比有魅力的女性更容易被深爱

“就算我们假定女人们花很大的力气把自己打扮得美丽诱惑、高贵迷人，确实是因为想去吸引男人的注意力，我也会向你证明，那些体面明智的男人并不会更快更深地为之倾倒。正相反，这些重视品格的男人会更容易被可敬、正直和谦逊的女性所吸引，并且爱得更深，哪怕她们没有那么光鲜亮丽。有些人就会反驳说，既然吸引男人不是件好事，那么那些用美德和谦逊来引人眼球的女人，也根本不要有这些优秀品质不是更好吗？这种说法是完全不足取的：人不该仅仅因为一些傻瓜把优良有用的品德用错了地方，就拒绝去培养这些品德；无论发生什么，每一个人都应该尽责地端正自己的行为。”

“我现在给你一些例子来证明，很多女性因为她们的正直和道德而被爱。特别是我要给你讲的一些天堂里的圣人，她们因其圣洁而被男人们渴求着。我之前说的被强暴的卢克雷蒂娅就是这样的。使得塔克文为她倾倒的是她典范性的美德，而不仅仅是美貌。一天晚上，她的丈夫正在跟其他骑士进晚餐，其中就有这位塔克文。他们开始谈论各自的妻子，都认为自己的妻子是最有美德的。为了找出谁最符合这一殊荣，他们就动身去突击拜访各家，褒奖那些正忙着光明正大的事情的妻子们。在她们中间，卢克雷蒂娅被认为是最值得称赞的。她正如一个端庄审慎的女性那样，穿着朴实无华的长袍，跟家中的其他女性坐在一起织着羊毛，谈论着道德上的话题。陪同她丈夫的塔克文王子，被她的正直、单纯而值得赞赏的行为以及端庄的举止所深深打动，由此产生了想要占有她的欲望，并谋划出了之后的恶行。”

……

66.克里斯蒂娜向正直女神发问，后者在回答中驳斥了那些声称女性天性刻薄的说法

“我不知道还要问你些什么，我的女神，因为你已经回答过我所有的问题了。那么多男人对女性的攻击也似乎已经被你全面反驳了。就我所能看到的，他们常说的，贪婪是妇女最常见的恶习这一点，也并非事实。”

正直女神回答说：“我亲爱的朋友，我可以向你保证，女性天生可不比男性更贪婪。实际上，贪心的女人比男人要少：就像上帝知道的、你自己也清楚的那样，由于男人的贪婪导致在世上蔓延的可怕恶魔，要比女人带来的多得多。但是就像我之前给你指出的那样，一个傻瓜能很快地指出邻居的恶习，却对自己的罪行视而不见。”

“仅仅因为女性喜欢收集衣服、针头线脑和其他对于家庭来说必不可少的小东西，她们就落下了个贪婪的名声。相信我，有无数的女性若自己富有的话，都会毫不犹豫地去赠予那些她们认为会明智地用这些钱的人。另一方面，贫穷的女性就不得不去锱铢必较了。总的来说，妇女们拿到的钱是不够花的，所以才会紧紧抓住手里的那一点，因为她们知道不可能再奢求更多了。有些人指责妇女贪婪，仅仅因为她们抱怨自己那刚愎自用又挥霍无度的丈夫，并恳求他们谨慎花钱。这些女性非常清楚，是自己丈夫愚蠢的浪费让家中缺钱，导致她们和可怜的孩子们不得不受苦的。因此这些行为并不能说明这些女人是贪婪的，而正相反，是节俭的一个表现。当然，我说的只是那些谨慎地劝诫丈夫的妇女们，否则如果丈夫不喜欢被人批评，这就可能会造成严重的争执，他最后会去攻击自己那本应得到褒奖的妻子。为了证明这个恶习在女性中远非有些人说的那么普遍，让我们来看看她们经常热心作的救济吧。上帝很清楚，从过去到现在，有多少囚犯被女性的施舍慰藉和支持过，就连在遥远的阿拉伯国家的囚犯也是一样；更不用提有多少穷人、落魄贵族还有各色人等都受到过她们的帮助了。”

我，克里斯蒂娜，于是说：“我的女神，你刚说的话确实让我想起了我所见过的，所有尽其所能乐善好施的可敬淑女们。我知道我有些朋友非常高兴能对那些会好好用钱的人说‘来，拿上这个’，这远比守财奴在敛财存钱时所获得的快乐要多得多。我不明白男人们为什么要到处去说女性是贪婪的。尽管人们说亚历山大大帝以慷慨著称，我可以说我并不这么认为！”

正直女神笑了起来，回答说：“我的朋友，罗马的妇女们肯定不希望她们的城市被战争耗空、公共储备被军队用尽。当时罗马人急需钱财来支持他们庞大的军队，于是罗马的妇女们，包括寡妇在内，都出于慷慨大度拿出了自己的珠宝和所有值钱的物品，堆成一堆捐给了城里的贵族。这些妇女因她们无私的行为而被高度赞扬，之后珠宝也被退还给了她们，这确实是感谢她们拯救了罗马财富的公正做法。”

……

68.关于法国的公主和贵妇

我再一次插话道：“我的女神，既然你提到了我同时代的这位女性，并且开始谈论法国的，以及居住在这里的淑女们，我想问问你对这些女性的印象。你觉得有必要请她们中的一些人加入我们的城市吗？她们是否不如外国的女性？”

正直女神回答道：“当然，克里斯蒂娜，我可以向你保证她们中有很多我想邀请的善良女性。”

“首先，我们不会拒绝高贵的现任法国女王、巴伐利亚的伊莎贝拉[60]，她正蒙上帝的恩惠统治着我们。她没有一丝一毫的残忍、贪婪或其他的恶习，因为她的本性完全是仁慈善良的。”

“年轻的贝里公爵夫人也同样值得赞美，她是一位聪慧美丽又温柔的淑女，嫁给了法国国王‘好人’约翰二世的儿子、已故国王‘英明’查理五世的弟弟约翰公爵。这位可敬的公爵夫人是如此节制谨慎，尽管她还非常年轻，但每个人都在颂扬她表率性的举止。”

“关于奥尔良公爵夫人我还能说些什么呢？她是已故米兰公爵的女儿、‘英明’查理五世之子路易斯公爵的夫人。还会有哪位淑女比她更稳重吗？所有人都能很明白地看到她不仅为人坚定，也非常爱她的丈夫，是她的孩子们的优秀榜样。除此之外，她在自己的事上也非常机敏，对所有人一视同仁，举止冷静并且兼具了所有美德。”

“勃艮第公爵夫人是已故法王约翰二世之子‘勇敢’菲利普二世的儿子、‘无畏的约翰’的妻子。关于她还有更多可说的吗？她不也是一位上等的淑女吗？对丈夫忠诚，仁慈而赞赏他人，道德无瑕，且没有什么缺点。”

“克莱蒙伯爵夫人是贝里公爵和他第一任妻子的女儿，嫁给了波旁公爵的继承人约翰·克莱蒙伯爵。她拥有一位高贵公主所应有的所有品质，包括对丈夫的深情和出色的教养，更不必提她的美貌、智慧和善良了。她的美德则因为高贵的举止而更为耀眼。”

“在所有这些淑女中，有一位是你非常喜欢，并从她的优秀品质、仁慈和关爱中受到过恩惠的：尊贵的荷兰女公爵及埃诺女伯爵杰奎琳，她是已故的勃艮第公爵‘好人’菲利普三世的女儿，也就是现任公爵的姐姐。这位淑女难道不该因为她在个人生活上的忠诚、节俭和谨慎以及她对神的无私而强烈的信仰而跻身最优秀的女性之列吗？简单来说，她就是善良本身。”

“波旁公爵夫人不也应该因为她是这样一位可敬的淑女，而跟其他贵妇一样被后世称颂，被全力赞美吗？”

“我还能跟你说什么？要让我列举这些淑女们的优点可就没完没了了！”

“圣波勒伯爵夫人是巴尔公爵的女儿、法王的表妹，也因为她的善良美丽、品德高尚而在这些优秀的淑女中有一席之地。”

“同样，另一位你喜欢的淑女安妮，也就是已故拉马什伯爵的女儿、现任公爵的妹妹，嫁给了法国王后的哥哥巴伐利亚公爵路易斯七世。她在这群杰出的女性之中也绝不显得逊色。上帝和整个世界都能见证她的美德。”

“我们尽可以无视那些造谣中伤者，有无数的伯爵夫人、贵族女性、未婚女性、中产阶级以及各阶层妇女都是可敬和出色的。感谢上帝让她们保持了这样的美德，也愿上帝能激励那些尚未达到完美的女人们能去修正自己的所作所为。你必须对此深信不疑，因为我可以向你保证，无论那些因为嫉妒而想造谣中伤女性的人会怎么唱反调，这都绝对是事实真相。”

我，克里斯蒂娜，于是回答道：“我的女神，听到你这样说我真的非常高兴。”

她于是对我说：“我亲爱的朋友，我觉得我现在已经完成建筑淑女之城的任务了。我不仅为你建起了美丽的王宫、豪华的宅邸，而且也请来了大量各个阶层的出色淑女来住满了这些建筑物。现在我的姐妹公正女神将要来完成给这个城市收尾的工作，我也要就此打住了。”

69.克里斯蒂娜对公主及其他淑女们讲话

“最出色、正直和可敬的法国和各国贵族们，各位淑女、少女还有各个阶层的女性们，你们这些过去，或现在，或将来会热爱美德和品行的女性们：请抬起头来，在你们的城市里欢庆吧。它在上帝的帮助下即将竣工，辉煌壮丽的房屋中几乎已经住满了居民。感谢上帝为了满足我给你们建立一个高尚的永久住所的愿望，带我走过这段艰辛的学习历程，建起了这个让你们可以永久居住的城市。我一路走来，希望能与公正女神一起最终完成这个使命。她已经答应我会不停地工作，直到我们竭尽全力建成这个城市，关上城门的那个时刻。那么，为我祈祷吧，我可敬的淑女们！”

《淑女之城》第二部分结束。

第三部分

1.第一章详细叙述公正女神是如何将圣母请入淑女之城的

公正女神非常满意地走向我，说道：“克里斯蒂娜，在我看来你已经尽全力来完成你的使命了。在我姐妹们的帮助下，你把淑女之城建得让人非常满意。就像我承诺的那样，现在轮到我来最后主持它完工了。我会给你请来最尊贵的女王，她是最神圣的女性，将率领她的仆从们居住在这里。她会统治这个城市，并带来她治下的最优秀的淑女。我看到现在宫殿和华屋已经装饰完成准备停当，街道也都铺满了鲜花，迎接女王及她出色的淑女随行们驾临的准备都已作好了。”

“那么就让公主、淑女和各个阶层的女性们都上前来，恭迎这位不仅仅是统治着她们、也是以至高无上的权威统治着地上的女王吧，她的地位仅次于她受圣灵感孕而生的圣父之子。所有的妇女都应该聚在一起来祈求这位崇高、尊贵的伟大女性能纡尊降贵，到我们的城市来成为我们的一员。她也不会因为她们的卑微与自己的反差而鄙视她们。出于过人的谦逊和胜过天使的善良，她毫无疑问会同意住在淑女之城。她会住在最高的宫殿中，那是我的姐妹正直女神为她准备的，全部用荣誉和赞美建造的殿堂。”

“现在请每一位妇女上前来，跟我一起说：‘我们恭迎您，圣母，用和天使向您传报一样的‘万福玛利亚’来向您致意，因为这比其他任何称谓都更让您欣喜。现在全体女性都恳求您能与她们为伍、做她们的保护人，将您的慈悲和怜悯恩泽到她们身上，在来自敌人和外界的攻击中保护她们。请让她们畅饮源自您的美德的泉水，望她们能就此满足并学会拒绝一切恶习和罪恶。请来到我们中间，您是天上的女王、我主的神殿、圣灵的隐修地、三位一体的居所、天使的喜乐、迷途者的光明与指引以及笃信者的希望。哦，我的女神，在看到您的崇高之后，谁还敢动念去想，更不必提敢去说女性是卑鄙的了！即使所有其他女性是有罪的，您善良的光辉也耀眼到照亮了一切的邪恶。神决定让一位女性做圣母并选择了您，最出色的淑女。因为您伟大的价值，所有的男人都不仅应该停止攻击女性，更应该对她们致以最高的尊敬。’”

这位贞女回答道：“我圣子垂青的公正女神，我很乐意与这些女性同住，她们是我的姐妹和朋友，我也会站到她们身边。这是因为理性、正直和你，公正女神，甚至还有天性女神，都劝说过我如此去做。女性对我的侍奉、尊敬和赞扬都未曾有止境，因此我从今往后都应当成为女性的领头人。上帝自身一直希望如此，这是由三位一体所注定了的。”

侧立在所有俯首跪下的女性身边，公正女神回答道：“我的女神，愿您被永世赞美和称颂。拯救我们吧，我们的女神，替我们向您的圣子说情，他是不会拒绝您的任何请求的。”

……

3.关于亚历山大的圣加大肋纳[61]

“我们请来陪伴淑女之城的女王，也就是荣福圣母的女性们，都是圣洁的处女和神圣的妇女。这样我们可以证明上帝是垂爱女性的，尽管这些女性柔弱年轻，上帝给了她们跟男性一样的力量和坚毅，以便为保护神圣的信仰而去承受可怕的殉道，这些女性其实更为纤弱和年轻。所有女性都可以从这些淑女们的经历中受益。她们头上笼罩着圣光，因为她们所能传授的要比其他任何人都有启发得多，她们也因此成为本城最受尊崇的居民。”

“其中最显赫的模范女性是圣加大肋纳，她是亚历山大[62]国王高士底的女儿。尽管这位富有的未婚少女在继承父亲国土时只有18岁，但她还是在处理个人生活和公众事务上表现出了敏锐的判断力。她是一位基督徒，拒绝结婚，希望能全身心地奉献给神。有一天，罗马帝国皇帝马克森提乌斯[63]来到亚历山大，要为异教神进行一场重要的祭祀。加大肋纳在宫中听见了正在被准备为仪式杀戮的动物的咆哮声和喧闹的音乐声。她派人去打探情形，却被告知皇帝已经抵达神殿要开始祭祀了。她一听到这个消息就来到皇帝面前，开始向他阐述他这种做法的错误性。因为加大肋纳很精通神学和科学，她运用了哲学论点来证明了只有一个神，也就是创世者，只有他应该被崇敬。当马克森提乌斯听到这位高贵美丽的处女用非凡的权威性说话时，他无言以对，只能震惊地盯着她。他于是去寻找全埃及最睿智的男人，最终从这个以拥有诸多聪慧哲学家著称的国家挑出了50名带到法庭。当他们被传唤时还非常生气，抱怨说皇帝大老远地把他们请来，居然只是为了跟一个小姑娘辩论。”

“让我们长话短说。辩论那天，蒙了圣恩的加大肋纳完全占了上风，他们被她的论述所说服，更无法回答她的问题。皇帝因此大为光火，千方百计地威胁他们，但也都是白费气力。托主的福，他们一个一个都被圣处女的话所折服，皈依了基督教。皇帝在盛怒之下把所有哲学家都处以火刑。这位圣处女在他们殉道时慰藉了他们，向他们保证他们会获得永恒的荣光，并向上帝祈祷保守他们信仰的坚强。就这样多亏了她，他们得以受福殉道。上帝通过他们展示了神迹，因为火不仅没有烧到他们的身体，就连他们的衣服都没有碰到：即使当他们在火中丧生之后，依旧没有一根头发被烧焦，面庞也像是还活着一样。暴君马克森提乌斯强烈地想要得到这位美丽圣洁的加大肋纳，于是开始追求她，希望能让她顺从自己的欲望。但是当他看到这完全是徒劳无功时，他的恳求变成了威胁，最后变成了折磨。他对她处以残酷的鞭笞，然后把她扔进监狱单独监禁了12天，希望最后看到她被饿到屈服。但是上帝的天使来到她身边救助了她。12天后，皇帝看见被带到面前的加大肋纳比之前更健康和可爱了，就确信一定有人偷偷去探访了她，于是下令拷问所有的狱卒。加大肋纳出于对他们的怜悯，向马克森提乌斯发誓说她只受到过来自于上帝的慰藉。皇帝再也想不出更加残酷的刑罚了，便听从了他执政长官的建议，制作了一个装着刀刃的磔轮，这些轮子互相碾压，任何卷入它们之间的东西都会被撕成碎片。他让加大肋纳脱光后躺在轮子中间，而她在这过程中一刻也没有停止过双手合十敬拜上帝。天使下来打碎了这些轮子，站在周围的处刑者们反而被碾死了。”

“当皇帝的妻子听到加大肋纳身上发生的神迹之后，便皈依了基督教，并且开始责备丈夫的行为。她去监狱探访了圣处女，并恳求她为她自己向上帝祈祷。皇帝因此拷问了他的妻子，并且切掉了她的乳房，这位圣处女于是对她说：‘最尊贵的皇后，别害怕这些酷刑，因为今天你会迎来无尽的喜乐。’暴君将自己的妻子与一大批皈依者一起砍了头。他请求加大肋纳做他的妻子，但意识到她对此置若罔闻之后，最终也打算将她斩首。在她的祷词中，她祈求上帝恩泽那些记得她殉道的和那些在痛苦中呼唤她名字的人们。一个声音从天上而来，宣布她的祷告被恩准了。在她殉道结束时，大量的牛奶而非鲜血从她的身体中喷涌而出。天使带走了她圣洁的躯体，并埋葬在了距离亚历山大20天路程的西奈山。上帝在她的墓上显示了很多神迹，限于篇幅我无法详述：只说墓中流出的一种油治愈了很多疾病这一点就足够了。此后上帝以最可怕的形式惩罚了马克森提乌斯皇帝。”

……

17.关于一位皈依上帝、悔改了的妓女圣阿芙拉

“阿芙拉曾经是一位妓女，后来皈依了基督教。她被带到法官面前，法官问她：‘你用自己的身体去犯罪还嫌不够，还要在信仰上也走错路去崇拜外来神！你要给我们的神作献祭，他们会原谅你的。’阿芙拉回答道：‘我会献祭给我的主，耶稣基督，他为了救赎罪人而来到地上。福音书中说一个有罪的女人用眼泪给他洗脚，然后得到宽恕。他没有鄙视妓女或罪孽的税吏，而是与他们同食共饮。’法官反驳说：‘如果你不想作献祭，你就再也接不到客人，更收不到他们的礼物了。’她回答道：‘我再也不会接受一件受污的礼物了。至于以前那些错误地收下了的，我会让穷人们拿走，并为我的灵魂祈祷。’法官因为拒绝信仰他们的神而将她判了火刑。当就要被送入火中时，她赞美上帝道：‘哦，全能的上帝，耶稣基督，你让所有的罪人忏悔。请接受我此刻的殉道，并请把我从这地狱永火中接走，它现在正要以俗世火焰为表象灼烧我的肉身。’当火苗在她身边舔舐时，她高声喊道：‘我主耶稣基督，请接受我，一个穷困而有罪的女人，以你神圣的名义殉道。你自己一人为世人牺牲，你是一位正直的人却为了世人的罪而被钉上十字架，一位善人却为恶人而受死，一位受福的人却为被诅咒的人而死，一位温柔的人却为了残酷的人而死，一位纯洁无瑕的人却为堕落的人而死。我将我的躯体敬献给你，你与圣父圣灵同在同治。’就这样，蒙福的阿芙拉结束了她的生命，之后主亦借她展现了诸多的神迹。”

18.公正女神谈起几位服侍十二使徒和其他圣人并为他们提供避难所的高贵淑女

“我亲爱的朋友克里斯蒂娜，关于这个话题我还能再说些什么？我可以继续给你详述无数这样的例子。因为你之前说过，你对于写书的人对女性如此多的批判感到震惊，我可以向你保证，无论你在异教书中读到了什么，你在圣经中都不会找到太多对于女性的负面评价，在耶稣基督还有他的十二使徒，甚至圣人们的故事中都是如此。如果你读了这些章节，就会看到无数的女性被上帝赐予了出众的美德和坚贞。妇女们是多么慷慨热忱地对待神的仆人们啊！又曾对他们展示出了多么榜样性的慈悲和忠诚！这么多的庇护和关爱，绝非可以一笔带过的。即使有愚蠢的男人想把这些当成是无足轻重的事忽略掉，根据我们的信仰也无法否认，这些都是通向天堂的阶梯上的横木。”

“我们可以引用德鲁夏妮的例子，她是一位高尚的寡妇，将福音书作者圣约翰领到了家中，侍奉他并为他准备餐饭。当约翰从流放中回来，就在全城的人民欢欣鼓舞地去迎接他的同时，德鲁夏妮的遗体正在被下葬。她是因为他的长期离开而悲痛过世的。邻居们告诉他：‘约翰，这里躺着的是德鲁夏妮，她如此仁慈地接待了你，她因为你的离去而辞世。她再也无法服侍你了。’约翰于是喊道：‘站起来，德鲁夏妮！回家去把饭给我做好！’她就从死亡中被带了回来。”

“同样，我们还可以说说可敬的苏珊娜，一位来自法国利摩日的贵妇。她是第一位给圣徒马尔蒂阿提供庇护所的人，后者奉使徒彼得之命来到法国传教。这位淑女对他无比仁慈。”

“同样，马克西米拉也是如此，她把使徒安德烈从十字架上放下并安葬，却不顾自己的性命安危。”

“同样，神圣的处女伊菲格涅亚是使徒马太的忠诚追随者，并在他死后建了一座教堂来纪念他。”

“同样，另一位对使徒保罗怀着神圣敬爱的女性，一直跟随着他并勤勉地照顾着他。”

“同样，在十二使徒时代，有一位叫海伦的高贵王后，这位海伦并非是那位康斯坦丁大帝的母亲，而是阿迪亚波纳的王后。她到了耶路撒冷，当时这个城市正因为一场饥荒而粮食极度匮乏。当海伦听说我主在耶路撒冷传教的圣徒快要饿死时，就买了足够多的食物供养他们，直到饥荒结束。”

“同样，当使徒保罗被尼禄下令即将砍头时，一位曾照顾过他的可敬女性普劳提拉流着苦涩的泪水走到他身边。保罗向她要了蒙在脸上的面纱，用来在行刑时遮住自己的眼睛。当她交给保罗面纱的时候，有些站在周围的恶人还嘲笑她就这么把如此漂亮的东西给扔了。保罗死后，天使把这块染了血的面纱还给了普劳提拉，她从此把它作为贵重的遗物珍藏了起来。之后保罗在她面前现身，说因为她在地上侍奉了自己，自己也将会在天上为她的灵魂祈祷。我可以给你讲很多这类的例子。”

“巴西利撒是一位充满怜悯之心的可敬妇女，她是圣徒朱利安的妻子。在婚礼的那天晚上，他们共同约定要守护童贞。这位处女的圣洁是无法衡量的，就像她救助过的女性数目一样无法计数，这些妇女是因她对虔诚生活的教导和鼓励而被救助的。简单来说，她典范性的慈悲为她赢得了神的青睐，以至于我主在她临终前曾与她直接对话。”

“我亲爱的克里斯蒂娜，我不知道还有什么可以再对你说的了。我可以给你讲无穷无尽的关于社会各个阶层的女性的事迹，无论是处女、妻子还是寡妇，她们出众的坚强和不屈不挠，都以自身为例展示了上帝的神迹。我的话到此为止了。在我看来，正如我承诺的那样，我已经很好地完成了这个城市的角楼，也请来了杰出的淑女入住。最后的这些例子将会成为我们的城门和吊闸。尽管我远没有一一列举那些神圣的女性，无论是过去的、现在的，还是将要来临的——因为这是不可能做到的——但她们都同样可以在淑女之城找到自己的一席之地。对此我们会说：‘Gloriosa dicta sunt de te,civitas Dei.’[64]现在它业已完工，城门也已关紧锁牢。我将如我所言，把它就此交付与你。永别了，愿神赐的和平永远陪伴你们！”

19.本书的完结：克里斯蒂娜对全体女性讲话

“最值得尊敬的淑女们，感谢上帝：我们城市的建设终于画上了句号。所有钟爱美德、荣誉和高贵名声的女性都可在城中找到华丽的栖身之所，不仅仅是过去的女性，现在和未来的女性皆如此，因为这个城市就是为了所有该受赏的女性而建立的。我最亲爱的淑女们，当看到经过努力击退敌人取得胜利时，人类的心灵会自然而然充满喜悦。从这一刻开始，我的淑女们，你们就可以看着新城竣工而尽情享受快乐了，当然要以虔诚和体面的合适方式享受快乐。这里不仅会给你们，或者说是你们中间证明了自己的价值的那部分人提供遮蔽，而且如果好好照管的话，更能替你们抵御反对者的攻击，从而保护你们。你们能看到，它是用美德制成，闪闪发亮到能看见人的倒影，特别是本书最后部分建起的高耸的角楼。而前两部分与你们相关的建筑也是一样的精致。我最爱的淑女们，我请求你们不要像那些傲慢的傻瓜一样去滥用这崭新的遗产，那些人的自傲因自己的成功和富有而膨胀了。相反的，你们应该去追随你们高贵的童贞女王的例子。当她听到自己将蒙最高的荣耀成为上帝之子的母亲时，却变得更为谦逊，将自己奉献为神的仆人。我的淑女们，一个人越是有道德，他就会越驯顺而温和，因此这个城市应该会让你们举止更有品行，并让你们变得更有价值和宽容。”

“你们当中已婚的人，不要因丈夫的欺凌而绝望，因为自由未必是世上最好的事情。上帝的天使对以斯拉所说的话就可以证明这一点：‘那些滥用自由意志的人必会犯罪，背叛神而堕落；他们因此被毁灭了。’如果妻子们温柔、善良、明智，又爱她们的丈夫，则应该感谢神。这绝不是一件小事，而是女性在世上可以获得的最大恩惠之一。这样的妻子应该专心服侍丈夫，用忠贞的心来敬爱和珍视他们，履行自己的职责跟他们平和度日，向神祈祷保守他们的安全和安宁。那些丈夫不算好也不算太坏的妻子们，也应该感谢神没有让她们过得更差。她们应当尽量去缓和丈夫们的任性行为，与他们一起努力按社会地位求得平静的生活。那些刚愎自用、有罪孽而残酷的丈夫的妻子们，则应该最大限度地容忍他们。她们应该尝试着去打消丈夫们的邪念，尽可能把他们带回到合理而可敬的道路上。即使她们的丈夫罪大恶极到了任何努力都徒劳无功的程度，这些妇女的灵魂也至少可以从对此的忍耐中获益。更何况，所有人都会赞赏她们并站在她们一边。”

“因此，我的淑女们，谦逊和忍耐会把神的恩泽在你们身上放大。你们会被荣光笼罩，并被赐予天上的国度。圣格列高利一世曾说过，忍耐是通向天堂和耶稣基督的关键。你们都应该痛下决心，从今以后摆脱愚蠢而不理性的想法、琐碎的嫉妒、顽固、轻蔑的谈话或是丢脸的行为，所有这些都会扭曲人的思想，让人变得不可靠。此外，这些做法对于一个女性来说也是非常不健康和不得体的。”

“你们当中未婚的年轻处女们，请保持纯洁、谦逊、温顺和坚贞，因为那些邪恶的人已经张网在捕捉你们了。保持你们的视线向下，少说话，并且小心谨慎地做所有事。用坚贞和美德武装你们自己，以便对抗引诱者的花招儿并拒绝与他们为伍。”

“你们当中寡居的淑女们，请端正自己的衣着、谈吐和所作所为。谨言慎行，处理自己的事物时要照顾周全，在苦难面前要有耐心、要坚强和有韧劲，因为你非常需要这些品质。性格和言谈举止要谦逊，行动要宽厚仁慈。”

“简而言之，所有的女性，无论属于社会的哪个阶层，都应该特别警觉，面对伺机攻击你的名誉和美德的人要保护自己。我的淑女们，看一看那些男人们是怎样从各个方面来指责你们的吧，他们用尽了所能想出的一切恶习来全面控诉你们。给他们看看你们多么有原则，来证明他们是错误的，并以有道德的行为来反驳他们对你们的所有批判。行为举止端正到可以像赞美诗诗人说的那样，‘恶人会自食其果’。击退那些奸诈的骗子，他们只是在用花招儿和甜言蜜语来骗取你最应保护好的东西：你的贞洁和荣誉的美名。哦，我的淑女们，逃离吧，从他们想要引诱你们的激情中逃离吧！为了上帝，从那里逃离！你不会从中得到好结果的。相反的，你可以确信，它虽然表面上有吸引力，但最后只能给你带来伤害。这结局一直以来从无例外，所以不要心存侥幸。我亲爱的淑女们，请记住这些男人们是如何指控你们是软弱、轻浮和朝三暮四，但同时却在用他们能想到的最迂回、古怪和奇特的招数来陷害你们的，就像捕捉野生动物那样。逃离，从他们那里逃离，我的淑女们！不要与这些在微笑的外表下隐藏着毒牙的人有任何瓜葛，他们会把你毒死的。与此相反，我最可敬的淑女们，希望你们能在追寻美德和规避恶习中获得乐趣，使得我们城市的人口可以继续增加。让你们的心因为做了善事而喜悦。我作为你们的仆人，将我自己托付给你们。我祈求上帝将他的恩典照耀在我身上，并允许我在这地上继续投入地侍奉他。希望他能原谅我的错误，在我死后赐予我无尽的喜乐，也愿他会如此对待你们。阿门。”

《淑女之城》的第三部分暨最终章结束。

Part Ⅰ

1. Here begins the Book of the City of Ladies, the first chapter of which explains why and for what purpose the book was written

One day, I was sitting in my study surrounded by many books of different kinds, for it has long been my habit to engage in the pursuit of knowledge. My mind had grown weary as I had spent the day struggling with the weighty tomes of various authors whom I had been studying for some time. I looked up from my book and decided that, for once, I would put aside these difficult texts and find instead something amusing and easy to read from the works of the poets. As I searched around for some little book, I happened to chance upon a work which did not belong to me but was amongst a pile of others that had been placed in my safe-keeping. I opened it up and saw from the title that it was by Matheolus. With a smile, I made my choice. Although I had never read it, I knew that, unlike many other works, this one was said to be written in praise of women. Yet I had scarcely begun to read it when my dear mother called me down to supper, for it was time to eat. I put the book to one side, resolving to go back to it the following day.

The next morning, seated once more in my study as is my usual custom, I remembered my previous desire to have a look at this book by Matheolus. I picked it up again and read on a little. But, seeing the kind of immoral language and ideas it contained, the content seemed to me likely to appeal only to those who enjoy reading works of slander and to be of no use whatsoever to anyone who wished to pursue virtue or to improve their moral standards. I therefore leafed through it, read the ending, and decided to switch to some more worthy and profitable work. Yet, having looked at this book, which I considered to be of no authority, an extraordinary thought became planted in my mind which made me wonder why on earth it was that so many men, both derks and others, have said and continue to say and write such awful, damning things about women and their ways. I was at a loss as to how to explain it. It is not just a handful of writers who do this, nor only this Matheolus whose book is neither regarded as authoritative nor intended to be taken seriously. It is all manner of philosophers, poets and orators too numerous to mention, who all seem to speak with one voice and are unanimous in their view that female nature is wholly given up to vice.

As I mulled these ideas over in my mind again and again, I began to examine myself and my own behaviour as an example of womankind. In order to judge in all fairness and without prejudice whether what so many famous men have said about us is true, I also thought about other women I know, the many princesses and countless ladies of all different social ranks who have shared their private and personal thoughts with me. No matter which way I looked at it and no matter how much I turned the question over in my mind, I could find no evidence from my own experience to bear out such a negative view of female nature and habits. Even so, given that I could scarcely find a moral work by any author which didn't devote some chapter or paragraph to attacking the female sex, I had to accept their unfavourable opinion of women since it was unlikely that so many learned men, who seemed to be endowed with such great intelligence and insight into all things, could possibly have lied on so many different occasions. It was on the basis of this one simple argument that I was forced to conclude that, although my understanding was too crude and ill-informed to recognize the great flaws in myself and other women, these men had to be in the right. Thus I preferred to give more weight to what others said than to trust my own judgement and experience.

I dwelt on these thoughts at such length that it was as If I had sunk into a deep trance. My mind became flooded with an endless stream of names as I recalled all the authors who had written on this subject. I came to the conclusion that God had surely created a vile thing when He created woman. Indeed, I was astounded that such a fine craftsman could have wished to make such an appalling object which, as these writers would have it, is like a vessel in which all the sin and evil of the world has been collected and preserved. This thought inspired such a great sense of disgust and sadness in me that I began to despise myself and the whole of my sex as an aberration in nature.

With a deep sigh, I called out to God: 'Oh Lord, how can this be? Unless I commit an error of faith, I cannot doubt that you, in your infinite wisdom and perfect goodness, could make anything that wasn't good. Didn't you yourself create woman especially and then endow her with all the qualities that you wished her to have? How could you possibly have made a mistake in anything? Yet here stand women not simply accused, but already judged, sentenced and condemned! I just cannot understand this contradiction. If it is true, dear Lord God, that women are guilty of such horrors as so many men seem to say, and as you yourself have said that the testimony of two or more witnesses is conclusive, how can I doubt their word? Oh God; why wasn't I born a male so that my every desire would be to serve you, to do right in all things, and to be as perfect a creature as man claims to be? Since you chose not to show such grace to me, please pardon and forgive me, dear Lord, if I fail to serve you as well as I should, for the servant who receives fewer rewards from his lord is less obligated to him in his service.'

Sick at heart, in my lament to God I uttered these and many other foolish words since I thought myself very unfortunate that He had given me a female form.

2. Christine tells how three ladies appeared to her, and how the first of them spoke to her and comforted her in her distress

Sunk in these unhappy thoughts, my head bowed as if in shame and my eyes full of tears, I sat slumped against the arm of my chair with my cheek resting on my hand. All of a sudden, I saw a beam of light, like the rays of the sun, shine down into my lap. Since it was too dark at that time of day for the sun to come into my study, I woke with a start as if from a deep sleep. I looked up to see where the light had come from and all at once saw before me three ladies, crowned and of majestic appearance, whose faces shone with a brightness that lit up me and everything else in the place. As you can imagine, I was full of amazement that they had managed to enter a room whose doors and windows were all closed. Terrified at the thought that it might be some kind of apparition come to tempt me, I quickly made the sign of the cross on my forehead.

With a smile on her face, the lady who stood at the front of the three addressed me first: 'My dear daughter, don't be afraid, for we have not come to do you any harm, but rather, out of pity on your distress, we are here to comfort you. Our aim is to help you get rid of those misconceptions which have clouded your mind and made you reject what you know and believe in fact to be the truth just because so many other people have come out with the opposite opinion. You're acting like that fool in the joke who falls asleep in the mill and whose friends play a trick on him by dressing him up in women's clothing. When he wakes up, they manage to convince him that he is a woman despite all evidence to the contrary! My dear gift, what has happened to your sense? Have you forgotten that it is in the furnace that gold is refined, increasing in value the more it is beaten and fashioned into different shapes? Don't you know that it's the very finest things which are the subject of the most intense discussion? Now, if you turn your mind to the very highest realm of all, the realm of abstract ideas, think for a moment whether or not those philosophers whose views against women you've been citing have ever been proven wrong. In fact, they are all constantly correcting each other's opinions, as you yourself should know from reading Aristotle's Metaphysics where he discusses and refutes both their views and those of Plato and other philosophers. Don't forget the Doctors of the Church either, and Saint Augustine in particular, who all took issue with Aristotle himself on certain matters, even though he is considered to be the greatest of all authorities on both moral and natural philosophy. You seem to have accepted the philosophers' views as articles of faith and thus as irrefutable on every point.

'As for the poets you mention, you must realize that they sometimes wrote in the manner of fables which you have to take as saying the opposite of what they appear to say. You should therefore read such texts according to the grammatical rule of antiphrasis, which consists of interpreting something that is negative in a positive light, or vice versa. My advice to you is to read those passages where they criticize women in this way and to turn them to your advantage, no matter what the author's original intention was. It could be that Matheolus is also meant to be read like this because there are some passages in his book which, if taken literally, are just out-and-out heresy. As for what these authors - not just Matheolus but also the more authoritative writer of the Romance of the Rose - say about the God-given, holy state of matrimony, experience should tell you that they are completely wrong when they say that marriage is insufferable thanks to women. What husband ever gave his wife the power over him to utter the kind of insults and obscenities which these authors claim that women do? Believe me, despite what you've read in books, you've never actually seen such a thing because it's all a pack of outrageous lies. My dear friend, I have to say that it is your naivety which has led you to take what they come out with as the truth. Return to your senses and stop worrying your head about such foolishness. Let me tell you that those who speak ill of women do more harm to themselves than they do to the women they actually slander.'

[...]

8. Christine explains how Reason instructed her and helped her to begin digging up the ground in order to lay the foundations

Lady Reason replied to my words, saying: 'Stand up now, daughter, and without further delay let us make our way to the Field of Letters. There we will build the City of Ladies on flat, fertile ground, where fruits of all kinds flourish and fresh streams flow, a place where every good thing grows in abundance. Take the spade of your intelligence and dig deep to make a great trench all around where you see the line I have traced I'll help to carry away the hods of earth on my shoulders.'

Obeying her instructions, I jumped to my feet: thanks to the three ladies, my body felt much stronger and lighter than before. She took the lead and I followed on behind. When we came to the spot she had described, I began to excavate and dig out the earth with the spade of my intelligence, just as she had directed me to do. The first fruit of my labours was this: 'My lady, I'm remembering that image of gold being refined in the furnace that you used before to symbolize the way many male writers have launched a full-scale attack on the ways of women. I take this image to mean that the more women are criticized, the more it redounds to their glory. But please tell me exactly what it is that makes so many different authors slander women in their writings because, if I understand you correctly, they are wrong to do so. Is it Nature that makes them do this? Or, if it is out of hatred, how can you explain it?'

Reason answered my questions, saying: 'My dear daughter, in order to help you see more clearly how things stand, let me carry away this first load of earth. I can tell you that, far from making them slander women, Nature does the complete opposite. There is no stronger or closer bond in the world than that which Nature, in accordance with God's wishes, creates between man and woman. Rather, there are many other different reasons which explain why men have attacked women in the past and continue to do so, including those authors whose works you have already mentioned. Some of those who criticized women did so with good intentions: they wanted to rescue men who had already fallen into the clutches of depraved and corrupt women or to prevent others from suffering the same fate, and to encourage men generally to avoid leading a lustful and sinful existence. They therefore attacked all women in order to persuade men to regard the entire sex as an abomination.'

'My lady,' I said, 'forgive me for interrupting you. Were they right to do so, since they were acting with good intentions? Isn't it true that one's actions are judged by one's intentions?'

'You're wrong, my dear girl,' she replied, 'because there is no excuse for plain ignorance. If I killed you with good intentions and out of stupidity, would I be in the right? Those who have acted in this way, whoever they may be, have abused their power. Attacking one party in the belief that you are benefiting a third party is unfair. So is criticizing the nature of all women, which is completely unjustified, as I will prove to you by analogy. Condemning all women in order to help some misguided men get over their foolish behaviour is tantamount to denouncing fire, which is a vital and beneficial element, just because some people are burnt by it, or to cursing water just because some people are drowned in it. You could apply the same reasoning to all manner of things which can be put to either good or bad use. In none of these cases should you blame the thing in itself if foolish people use it unwisely. You yourself have made these points elsewhere in your writings. Those who subscribe to these opinions, whether in good or bad faith, have overstepped the mark in order to make their point. It's like somebody cutting up the whole piece of cloth in order to make himself a huge coat simply because it's not going to cost him anything and no one is going to object. It thus stops anyone else from using the material. If instead, as you yourself have rightly remarked, these writers had tried to find ways to save men from indulging in vice and from frequenting debauched women by attacking only the morals and the habits of those who were evidently guilty of such behaviour, I freely admit that they would have produced texts which were extremely useful. It's true that there's nothing worse than a woman who is dissolute and depraved: she's like a monster, a creature going against its own nature, which is to be timid, meek and pure. I can assure you that those writers who condemn the entire female sex for being sinful, when in fact there are so many women who are extremely virtuous, are not acting with my approval. They've committed a grave error, as do all those who subscribe to their views. So let us throw out these horrible, ugly, misshapen stones from your work as they have no place in your beautiful city.

'Other men have criticized women for different reasons: some because they are themselves steeped in sin, some because of a bodily impediment, some out of sheer envy, and some quite simply because they naturally take delight in slandering others. There are also some who do so because they like to flaunt their erudition: they have come across these views in books and so like to quote the authors whom they have read.

'Those who criticize the female sex because they are inherently sinful are men who have wasted their youth on dissolute behaviour and who have had affairs with many different women. These men have therefore acquired cunning through their many experiences and have grown old without repenting of their sins. Indeed, they look back with nostalgia on the appalling way they used to carry on when they were younger. Now that old age has finally caught up with them and the spirit is still willing but the flesh has grown weak, they are full of regret when they see that, for them, the "good old days" are over and they can merely watch as younger men take over from where they have had to leave off. The only way they can release their frustration is to attack women and to try to stop others from enjoying the pleasures that they themselves used to take. You very often see old men such as these going around saying vile and disgusting things, as in the case of your Matheolus, who freely admits that he is just an impotent old man who would still like to satisfy his desires. He's an excellent example to illustrate my point as he's typical of many other similar cases.

'Yet, thank goodness, not all old men are full of depravity and rotten to the core like a leper. There are many other fine, decent ones whose wisdom and virtue have been nourished by me and whose words reflect their good character, since they speak in an honourable and sober fashion. Such men detest all kinds of wrong-doing and slander. Thus, rather than attacking and defaming individual sinners, male or female, they condemn all sins in general. Their advice to others is to avoid vice, pursue virtue and stick to the straight and narrow.

'Those men who have attacked women because of their own bodily impediments, such as impotence or a deformed limb, are all bitter and twisted in the mind. The only pleasure they have to compensate for their incapacity is to slander the female sex since it is women who bring such joy to other men. That way they are convinced that they can put others off enjoying what they themselves have never had.

'Those men who have slandered the opposite sex out of envy have usually known women who were cleverer and more virtuous than they are. Out of bitterness and spite, envious men such as these are driven to attack all women, thinking that they can thereby undermine these individuals' good reputation and excellent character, as in the case of the author of On Philosophy whose name I've forgotten. In this book, he goes to great lengths to argue that men should on no account praise women and that those who do so are betraying the title of his book: their doctrine is no longer "philosophy" but "philofolly". However, I can assure you that it is definitely he who is the arch-exponent of "philofolly" because of all the false reasoning and erroneous conclusions he comes out with in his book.

'As for those men who are slanderous by nature, it's not surprising if they criticize women, given that they attack everyone indiscriminately. You can take it from me that any man who wilfully slanders the female sex does so because he has an evil mind, since he's going against both reason and nature. Against reason, because he is lacking in gratitude and failing to acknowledge all the good and indispensable things that woman has done for him both in the past and still today, much more than he can ever repay her for. Against nature, in that even the birds and the beasts naturally love their mate, the female of the species. So man acts in a most unnatural way when he, a rational being, fails to love woman.

'Finally, there are those who dabble in literature and delight in mimicking even the very finest works written by authors who are greatly superior to them. They think themselves to be beyond reproach since they are merely repeating what others have already said. Believe me, this is how they set about making their defamatory remarks. Some of them scribble down any old nonsense, verse without rhyme or reason, in which they discuss the ways of women, or princes, or whoever it might be, when it is they themselves, whose habits leave much to be desired, who are most in need of moral self-improvement. Yet the common folk, who are as ignorant as they are, think that it's the best thing they've ever read.'

9. How Christine dug over the earth: in other words, the questions which she put to Reason and the answers she received from her

'Now that I have prepared and set out this great task for you, you should carry on the task of digging up the ground, following the line which I have laid down.'

In obedience to Reason's wishes, I set to with all my might, saying, 'My lady, why is it that Ovid, who is considered to be the greatest of poets (though others, myself included, think that Virgil is more worthy of that accolade, if you don't mind my saying so), made so many derogatory remarks about women in his writings, such as the Art of Love, the Remedies of Love and other works?'

Reason replied: 'Ovid was a man very well versed in the theory and practice of writing poetry and his fine mind allowed him to excel in everything he wrote. However, his body was given over to all kinds of worldliness and vices of the flesh: he had affairs with many women, since he had no sense of moderation and showed no loyalty to any particular one. Throughout his youth, he behaved like this only to end up with the reward he richly deserved: he lost not just his good name and his possessions, but even some parts of his body! Because he was so licentious, both in the way he carried on and in the encouragement he gave to others to do the same, he was finally sent into exile. Even when he was brought back from banishment by some of his followers, who were influential young men of Rome, he couldn't help himself from falling into exactly the same pattern as before. So finally he was castrated and deprived of his organs because of his immorality. He's another good example of what I was telling you about just now: once he realized that he could no longer indulge in the same kind of pleasures as before, he began to attack women with his sly remarks in an attempt to make others despise them too.'

'My lady, your words certainly ring true. However, I've seen another book by an Italian writer called Cecco d'Ascoli who, if I remember correctly, comes from the Marches or Tuscany. In this work, he says some extraordinarily unpleasant things which are worse than anything else I've ever read and which shouldn't be repeated by anybody with any sense.'

Reason's response was: 'My dear girl, don't be surprised if Cecco d'Ascoli slandered the whole of womankind since he hated and despised them all. Being unspeakably wicked, he tried to make all other men share his nasty opinion about women. He too got what he deserved: thanks to his heretical views, he suffered a shameful death at the stake.'

'My lady, I've also come across another little book in Latin, called On the Secrets of Women, which states that the female body is inherently flawed and defective in many of its functions.'

Reason replied, 'You shouldn't need any other evidence than that of your own body to realize that this book is a complete fabrication and stuffed with lies. Though some may attribute the book to Aristotle, it is unthinkable that a philosopher as great as he would have produced such outrageous nonsense. Any woman who reads it can see that, since certain things it says are the complete opposite of her own experience, she can safely assume that the rest of the book is equally unreliable. Incidentally, do you remember the part at the beginning where he claims that one of the popes excommunicated any man found either reading the book out loud to a woman or giving it to her to read for herself?'

'Yes, my lady, I do remember that passage.'

'Do you know what evil motive drove him to put such vile words at the front of his book for gullible, foolish men to read?'

'No, my lady, you'll have to tell me.'

'It was because he did'nt want women to get hold of his book and read it or have someone else read it to them for fear that if they did, they would pour scorn on it and would recognize it for the utter rubbish that it is. By this ruse, he thought he could trick the men who wanted to read his text.'

'My lady, amongst the other things he said, I seem to remember that, after going on at great length about female children being the result of some weakness or deficiency in the mother's womb, he claimed that Nature herself is ashamed when she sees that she has created such an imperfect being.'

'Well, my dear Christine, surely it's obvious that those who come out with this opinion are totally misguided and irrational? How can Nature, who is God's handmaiden, be more powerful than her own master from whom she derives her authority in the first place? It is God almighty who, at the very core of His being, nurtured the idea of creating man and woman. When He put His divine wish into action and made Adam from the clay of the fields of Damascus, He took him to dwell in the earthly paradise, which has always been the noblest place on this lowly earth. There He put Adam to sleep and created the body of woman from one of his ribs. This was a sign that she was meant to be his companion standing at his side, whom he would love as if they were one flesh, and not his servant lying at his feet. If the Divine Craftsman Himself wasn't ashamed to create the female form, why should Nature be? It really is the height of stupidity to claim otherwise. Moreover, how was she created? I'm not sure if you realize this, but it was in God's image. How can anybody dare to speak ill of something which bears such a noble imprint? There are, however, some who are foolish enough to maintain that when God made man in His image, this means His physical body. Yet this is not the case, for at that time God had not yet adopted a human form, so it has to be understood to mean the soul, which is immaterial intellect and which will resemble God until the end of time. He endowed both male and female with this soul, which He made equally noble and virtuous in the two sexes. Whilst we're still on the subject of how the human body was formed, woman was created by the very finest of craftsmen. And where exactly was she made? Why, in the earthly paradise. What from? Was it from coarse matter? No, it was from the finest material that had yet been invented by God: from the body of man himself.'

'My lady, from what you've told me, I can see that woman is a very noble creature. Yet, all the same, wasn't it Cicero who said that man should not be subject to woman and that he who did so abased himself because it is wrong to be subject to one who is your inferior?'

Reason answered, 'It is he or she who is the more virtuous who is the superior being: human superiority or inferiority is not determined by sexual difference but by the degree to which one has perfected one's nature and morals. Thus, happy is he who serves the Virgin Mary, for she is exalted even above the angels.'

'My lady, it was one of the Catos, the one who was a great orator, who declared that if woman hadn't been created, man would converse with the gods.'

Reason's reply was: 'Now you see an example of someone who was supposed to be very wise coming out with something very foolish. It is because of woman that man sits side by side with God. As for those who state that it is thanks to a woman, the lady Eve, that man was expelled from paradise, my answer to them would be that man has gained far more through Mary than he ever lost through Eve. Humankind has now become one with God, which never would have happened if Eve hadn't sinned. Both men and women should praise this fault of Eve's since it is because of her that such an honour has been bestowed on them. If human nature is fallen, due to the actions of one of God's creatures, it has been redeemed by the Creator Himself. As for conversing with the gods if womankind hadn't been invented, as this Cato claims; his words were truer than he knew. Being a pagan, he and those of his faith believed that both heaven and hell were ruled by the gods. But the ones in hell are what we call devils, So it's definitely true to say that men would be conversing with the gods of hell if Mary had not come into the world!'

[...]

11. Christine asks Reason why women aren't allowed in courts of law, and Reason's reply

'Most honourable and worthy lady, your excellent arguments have satisfied my curiosity in so many areas. Yet, if you don't mind, I'd like you to explain to me why women are allowed neither to present a case at a trial, nor bear witness, nor pass sentence since some men have claimed that it's all because of some woman or other who behaved badly in a court of law.'

'My dear daughter, that whole ridiculous story is a malicious fabrication. However, if you wanted to know the causes and reasons behind everything, you would never get to the end of it. Even Aristotle, though he explained many things in his Problemata and Categories, was not equal to the task. But, dear Christine, to come back to your question, you might as well ask why God didn't command men to perform women's tasks and women those of men. In answer, one could say that just as a wise and prudent lord organizes his household into different domains and operates a strict division of labour amongst his workforce, so God created man and woman to serve Him in different ways and to help and comfort one another, according to a similar division of labour. To this end, He endowed each sex with the qualities and attributes which they need to perform the tasks for which they are cut out, even though sometimes humankind fails to respect these distinctions. God gave men strong, powerful bodies to stride about and to speak boldly, which explains why it is men who learn the law and maintain the rule of justice. In those instances where someone refuses to uphold the law which has been established by fight, men must enforce it through the use of arms and physical strength, which women dearly could not do. Even though God has often endowed many women with great intelligence, it would not be right for them to abandon their customary modesty and to go about bringing cases before a court, as there are already enough men to do so. Why send three men to carry a burden which two can manage quite comfortably?

'However, if there are those who maintain that women aren't intelligent enough to learn the law, I would contradict them by citing numerous examples of women of both the past and the present who were great philosophers and who excelled in many disciplines which are much more difficult than simply learning the laws and the statutes of men. I'll tell you more about these women in a moment. Moreover, in reply to those who think that women are lacking in the ability to govern wisely or to establish good customs, I'll give you examples from history of several worthy ladies who mastered these arts. To give you a better idea of what I'm saying, I'll even cite you a few women from your own time who were widowed and whose competence in organizing and managing their households after their husbands' deaths attests to the fact that an intelligent woman can succeed in any domain.'

12. About the Empress Nicaula

'Tell me, if you can, whether you have ever read about a king who was more skilled in politics, statesmanship and justice and who maintained a more magnificent court than the great Empress Nicaula? The many different vast and extensive lands which she held under her dominion were ruled by the famous kings known as pharaohs, from whom she herself was descended. However, it was this lady who first established laws and good customs in her realm, thus putting end once and for all to the primitive ways of the people in the countries under her control, even to the savage habits of the bestial Ethiopians. Those authors who have written about Nicaula praise her in particular for the way in which she brought civilization to her subjects. She was the heir of the pharaohs, inheriting a huge territory which included the kingdoms of Arabia, Ethiopia, Egypt and the island of Meroë, a long, broad stretch of land, which was extremely fertile, located in the middle of the Nile. She governed all of her territory with exemplary skill. What more can I tell you about this lady? Nicaula was so wise and so powerful that even the Holy Scriptures speak of her great abilities. She herself established just laws by which to rule her people. In nobility and wealth, she surpassed almost any man who ever lived. She was extremely well versed in both the arts and the sciences and was so proud that she never condescended to take a husband nor wanted any man to be at her side.'

[...]

14. More discussion and debate between Christine and Reason

'My lady, you have truly spoken well, and your words are like music to my ears. Yet, despite what we've said about intelligence, it's undeniable that women are by nature fearful creatures, having weak, frail bodies and lacking in physical strength. Men have therefore argued that it is these things that make the female sex inferior and of lesser value. To their minds, if a person's body is defective in some way, this undermines and diminishes that person's moral qualities and thus it follows that he or she is less worthy of praise.'

Reason's reply was, 'My dear daughter, this is a false conclusion which is completely untenable. It is definitely the case that when Nature fails to make a body which is as perfect as others she has created, be it in shape or beauty, or in some strength or power of limb, she very often compensates for it by giving that body some greater quality than the one she has taken away. Here's an example: it's often said that the great philosopher Aristotle was very ugly, with one eye lower than the other and a deformed face. Yet, if he was physically misshapen, Nature certainly made up for it by endowing him with extraordinary intellectual powers, as is attested by his own writings. Having this extra intelligence was worth far more to him than having a body as beautiful as that of Absalom.

'The same can be said of the emperor Alexander the Great, who was extremely short, ugly and sickly, and yet, as is well known, he had tremendous courage in his soul. This is also true of many others. Believe me, my dear friend, it doesn't necessarily follow that a fine, strong body makes for a brave and courageous heart. Courage comes from a natural, vital force which is a gift from God that He allows Nature to implant in some rational beings more than in others. This force resides in the mind and the heart, not in the bodily strength of one's limbs. You very often see men who are well built and strong yet pathetic and cowardly, but others who are small and physically weak yet brave and tough. This applies equally to other moral qualities. As far as bravery and physical strength are concerned, neither God nor Nature has done the female sex a disservice by depriving it of these attributes. Rather, women are lucky to be deficient in this respect because they are at least spared from committing and being punished for the acts of appalling cruelty, the murders and terrible violent deeds which men who are equipped with the necessary strength have performed in the past and still do today. It probably would have been better for such men if their souls had spent their pilgrimage through this mortal life inside the weak body of a woman. To return to what I was saying, I am convinced that if Nature decided not to endow women with a powerful physique, she none the less made up for it by giving them a most virtuous disposition: that of loving God and being fearful of disobeying His commandments. Women who don't act like this are going against their own nature.

'However, dear Christine, you should note that God clearly wished to prove to men that, just because all women are not as physically strong and courageous as men generally are, this does not mean that the entire female sex is lacking in such qualities. There are in fact several women who have displayed the necessary courage, strength and bravery to undertake and accomplish extraordinary deeds which match those achieved by the great conquerors and knights mentioned in books. I'll shortly give you an example of such a woman.

'My dear daughter and beloved friend, I've now prepared a trench for you which is good and wide, and have emptied it of earth which I have carried away in great loads on my shoulders. It's now time for you to place inside the trench some heavy, solid stones which will form the foundations of the walls for the City of Ladies. So take the trowel of your pen and get ready to set to with vigour on the building work. Here is a good, strong stone which I want you to lay as the first of your city's foundations. Don't you know that Nature herself used astrological signs to predict that it should be placed here in this work? Step back a little now and let me put it into position for you.'

[...]

16. About the Amazons

'There is a country near the land of Europe which lies on the Ocean, that great sea that covers the whole world. This place is called Scythia, or the land of the Scythians. It once happened that, in the course of a war, all the noblest male inhabitants of this country were killed. When their womenfolk saw that they had lost all their husbands, brothers and male relatives, and that only very young boys and old men were left, they took courage and called together a great council of women, resolving that, henceforth, they would lead the country themselves, free from male control. They issued an edict which forbade any man from entering their territory, but decided that, in order to ensure the survival of their race, they would go into neighbouring countries at certain times of the year and return thereafter to their own land. If they gave birth to male children, they would send them away to be with their fathers, but the female children they would bring up themselves. In order to uphold this law, they chose two of the highest-born ladies to be queens, one of whom was called Lampheto and the other Marpasia. No sooner was this done than they expelled all the men who were left in the country. Next, they took up arms, women and gifts together, and waged war on their enemies, laying waste to their lands with fire and sword and crushing all opposition until none remained. In short, they wreaked full revenge for their husbands' deaths.

'This is how the women of Scythia began to bear arms. They were later known as the Amazons, a name which means "they who have had a breast removed". It was their custom that, by a technique known only to this race of women, the most noble of them would have the left breast burnt off at a very early age in order to free them up to carry a shield. Those young gifts who were of non-noble birth would lose the right breast so that they could more easily handle a bow. They took such pleasure in the pursuit of arms that they greatly expanded their territory by the use of force, thus spreading their fame far and wide. To get back to what I was saying, the two queens Lampheto and Marpasia each led a great army into various countries and were so successful that they conquered a large part of Europe and the region of Asia, subjugating many kingdoms to their rule. They founded many towns and cities including the Asian city of Ephesus, which has long been justly renowned. Of these two queens, it was Marpasia who died first in battle and who was replaced by a young daughter of hers, a beautiful and noble maiden called Synoppe. This girl was so proud that she chose never to sleep with a man, preferring instead to remain a virgin until her death. Her only love and sole pleasure in life was the pursuit of arms: she never tired of going into battle and seizing new lands. She also avenged her mother's death fully by putting to the sword the entire enemy population and laying waste to their whole country, adding it to the others which she went on to conquer.'

[...]

27. Christine asks Reason if God has ever blessed a woman's mind with knowledge of the highest branches of learning, and Reason's reply

Having listened to what Reason said, I answered, 'My lady, God truly performed wonders by endowing these women you've just been telling me about with such extraordinary powers. But, if you don't mind, please tell me if, amongst all the other favours He has shown to women, God ever chose to honour any of them with great intelligence and knowledge. Do they indeed have an aptitude for learning? I'd really like to know why it is that men claim women to be so slow-witted.'

Reason's reply was: 'Christine, from what I've already told you, it should be obvious that the opposite of what they say is true. To make the point more clearly for you, I'll give you some conclusive examples. I repeat - and don't doubt my word - that if it were the custom to send little girls to school and to teach them all sorts of different subjects there, as one does with little boys, they would grasp and learn the difficulties of all the arts and sciences just as easily as the boys do. Indeed, this is often the case because, as I mentioned to you before, although women may have weaker and less agile bodies than men, which prevents them from doing certain tasks, their minds are in fact sharper and more receptive when they do apply themselves.'

'My lady, what are you saying? If you please, I'd be grateful if you would expand on this point. No man would ever accept this argument flit couldn't be proved, because they would say that men generally know so much more than women.'

She replied, 'Do you know why it is that women know less than men?'

'No, my lady, you'll have to enlighten me.'

'It's because they are less exposed to a wide variety of experiences since they have to stay at home all day to look after the household. There's nothing like a whole range of different experiences and activities for expanding the mind of any rational creature.'

'So, my lady, if they have able minds which can learn and absorb as much as those of men, why don't they therefore know more?'

'The answer, my dear girl, is that it's not necessary for the public good for women to go around doing what men are supposed to do, as I informed you earlier. It's quite adequate that they perform the tasks for which they are fitted. As for this idea that experience tells us that women's intelligence is inferior to that of men simply because we see that those around us generally know less than men do, let's take the example of male peasants living in remote countryside or high mountains. You could give me plenty of names of places where the men are so backward that they seem no better than beasts. Yet, there's no doubt that Nature made them as perfect in mind and body as the cleverest and most learned men to be found in towns and cities. All this comes down to their lack of education, though don't forget what I said before about some men and women being more naturally endowed with intelligence than others. I'll now go on to prove to you that the female sex is just as clever as the male sex, by giving you some examples of women who had fine minds and were extremely erudite.'

28. Reason begins to speak about ladies who were blessed with great learning, starting with the noble maiden Cornificia

'The parents of the noble maiden Cornificia used a clever trick to send her to school along with her brother Cornificius when they were both young children. This little girl applied her extraordinary intelligence so well to her studies that she began to take a real delight in learning. It would have been extremely difficult to stifle this talent in her, for she refused all normal female occupations in order to devote herself to her books. After much dedication, she soon became an excellent and learned poet not solely in the field of poetry itself but also in philosophy, which she just drank in as if it were mother's milk. She was so motivated to excel in all the different disciplines that she soon outshone her brother himself no mean poet, in all branches of scholarship.

'Moreover, she was not content simply to study the theoretical side of learning but wished to put her own knowledge into practice. Taking up her pen, she composed several distinguished works which, at the time of Saint Gregory, were held in great esteem, as he himself indicates in his writings. The great Italian author Boccaccio says of Cornificia in his book: "What a great honour it is for a woman to put aside all feminine things and to devote her mind to studying the works of the greatest scholars." He confirms what I've been telling you when he goes on to say that those women who have no confidence in their own intellectual abilities act as if they were born in the backwoods and had no concept of what is right and moral, letting themselves be discouraged and saying that they're fit for nothing but fussing over men and bearing and bringing up children. God has given every woman a good brain which she could put to good use, if she so chose, in all the domains in which the most learned and renowned men excel. If women wished to study, they are no more excluded from doing so than men are; and could easily put in the necessary effort to acquire a good name for themselves just as the most distinguished of men delight in doing. My dear daughter, see how Boccaccio himself echoes what I've been saying and note how much he approves of learning in a woman and praises them for it.'

[...]

30. About Sappho, who was an extremely fine poet and philosopher

'No less learned than Proba was Sappho, a maiden from the city of Mytilene. This Sappho was physically very beautiful, and also charming in her speech, manner and bearing. However, the finest of her attributes was her superb intellect, for she was a great expert in many different arts and sciences. Moreover, she was not only familiar with the writings and treatises of others but was herself an author who composed many new works. The poet Boccaccio pays tribute to her, describing her in these delightful terms: "Sappho, spurred on by her fine mind and burning desire, devoted herself to her studies and rose above the common, ignorant herd, making her home on the heights of Mount Parnassus; in other words, at the summit of knowledge itself. Through her extraordinary boldness and daring, she won the good will of the Muses; that is, she immersed herself in the arts and sciences. She thus made her way through the lush forest full of laurels, may trees, delicious-scented flowers of different hues and sweet-smelling herbs which is the place where Grammar, Logic, Geometry, Arithmetic, and noble Rhetoric dwell. She travelled down this path until she eventually came to the deep cave of Apollo, god of knowledge, where she found the bubbling waters of the spring of Castalia. There she took up a plectrum and played lovely tunes on the harp with the nymphs leading the dance; that is to say, she learnt the art of musical chords as well as the rules of harmonics."

'This description of Sappho by Boccaccio should be understood to refer to the depth of her learning and to the great erudition of her works which, as the Ancients themselves pointed out, are so complex that even the most intelligent and educated men have difficulty in grasping their meaning. Her books, which are exquisitely written and still popular today, offer an excellent model for those of later generations who want to perfect the art of writing verse. She invented many new forms of song and poetry, including lays, sorrowful complaints, strange love laments and other poems inspired by different emotions which are beautifully wrought and are now called Sapphic poems in her honour. On the subject of this lady's works, Horace recalls that a book of her verse was found under the pillow of the great philosopher Plato, Aristotle's teacher, when he died.

'To cut a long story short, Sappho was so famous for her learning that her native city decided to dedicate a prominent bronze statue to her in order to honour her and record her achievements for posterity. She earned herself a place amongst the greatest poets whose glory, according to Boccaccio, far outshines the mitres of bishops, the coronets and crowns of kings and even the palm wreaths and laurel garlands of those who are victorious in battle. I could give you many more examples of brilliant women, such as the Greek woman Leontium, an excellent philosopher, who dared to put forward clearly reasoned arguments against Theophrastus, a thinker who was highly regarded in his own time.'

[...]

33. Christine asks Reason if any woman has ever invented new forms of knowledge

I, Christine, on hearing Reason's words, took up this matter and said to her, 'My lady, I can clearly see that you are able to cite an endless number of women who were highly skilled in the arts and sciences. However, I'd like to ask you if you know of any woman who was ingenious, or creative, or clever enough to invent any new useful and important branches of knowledge which did not previously exist. It's surely less difficult to learn and follow a subject which has already been invented than it is to discover something new and unknown by oneself.'

Reason replied, 'Believe me, many crucial and worthy arts and sciences have been discovered thanks to the ingenuity and cleverness of women, both in the theoretical sciences which are expressed through the written word, and in the technical crafts which take the form of manual tasks and trades. I'll now give you a whole set of examples.

'First of all, I'll tell you about the noble Nicostrata, whom the Italians called Carmentis. This lady was the daughter of the king of Arcadia whose name was Pallas. She was extraordinarily intelligent and endowed by God with special intellectual gifts, having such a vast knowledge of Greek literature and being able to write so wisely, elegantly and with such eloquence that the poets of the time claimed in their verse that she was loved by the god Mercury. They similarly thought that her son, who was in his day equally renowned for his intelligence, was the offspring of this god, rather than of her husband. Because of various upheavals that occurred in her native land, Nicostrata, accompanied by her son and a whole host of other people who wanted to go with her, set off for Italy in a large fleet of ships and sailed up the River Tiber. It was here that she went ashore and climbed up a great hill which she named Mount Palatine after her father. On this hill, where the city of Rome was subsequently founded, she, her son and her followers built themselves a castle. As she found the indigenous population to be very primitive, she laid down a set of rules for them to observe and encouraged them to live a rational and just existence. Thus it was she who first established laws in this country that was to become so famous for developing a legal system from which all known laws would be derived.

'Amongst all the other attributes that this lady possessed, Nicostrata was particularly blessed with the gift of divine inspiration and prophecy. She was thus able to predict that her adopted country would one day rise above all others to become the most magnificent and glorious realm on earth. To her mind, therefore, it would not be fitting for this country which would outshine and conquer the rest of the world to use an inferior and crude set of alphabetical letters which had originated in a foreign country. Moreover, Nicostrata wished to transmit her own wisdom and learning to future generations in a suitable form. She therefore set her mind to inventing a new set of letters which were completely different from those used in other nations. What she created was the ABC - the Latin alphabet - as well as the rules for constructing words, the distinction between vowels and consonants and the bases of the science of grammar. She gave this knowledge and this alphabet to the people, in the hope that they would become universally known. It was truly no small or insignificant branch of knowledge that this lady invented, nor should she receive only paltry thanks for it. This ingenious science proved so useful and brought so much good into the world that one can honestly say that no nobler discovery was ever made.

'The Italians were not lacking in gratitude for this great gift, and rightly so, since they heralded it as such a marvellous invention that they venerated her more highly than any man, worshipping Nicostrata/Carmentis like a goddess in her own lifetime. When she died, they built a temple dedicated to her memory, situated at the foot of the hill where she had made her home. In order to preserve her fame for posterity, they borrowed various terms from the science she had invented and even used her own name to designate certain objects. In honour of the science of Latin that she had invented, the people of the country called themselves Latins. Furthermore, because ita in Latin is the most important affirmative term in that language, being the equivalent of oui in French, they did not stop at calling their own realm the land of the Latins, but went so far as to use the name Italy to refer to the whole country beyond their immediate borders, which is a vast area comprising many different regions and kingdoms. From this lady's name, Carmentis, they also derived the Latin word carmen, meaning "song". Even the Romans, who came a long time after her, called one of the gates of the city the Porta Carmentalis. These names have not been changed since and are still the same today, no matter how the fortunes of the Romans have fared or which mighty emperor was in power.

'My dear Christine, what more could you ask for? Could any mortal man be said to have done anything so splendid? But don't think that she's the only example of a woman who invented many new branches of learning...'

34. About Minerva, who invented countless sciences, including the art of making arms from iron and steel

'Minerva, as you yourself have noted elsewhere, was a maiden from Greece who was also known as Pallas. This gift was so supremely intelligent that her contemporaries foolishly declared her to be a goddess come down from the heavens, since they had no idea who her parents were and she performed deeds that had never been done before. As Boccaccio himself points out, the fact that they knew so little about her origins meant that they were all the more astonished at her great wisdom, which surpassed that of every other woman of her time. She employed her skilfulness and her immense ingenuity not just in one domain but in many. First of all, she used her brilliance to invent various Greek letters called characters which can be used to write down a maximum number of ideas in a minimum number of words. This wonderfully clever invention is still used by the Greeks today. She also invented numbers and developed ways of using them to count and perform quick calculations. In short, she was so ingenious that she created many arts and techniques that had not previously been discovered, including the art of making wool and cloth. It was she who first had the idea of shearing sheep and developing the whole process of untangling, combing and carding the wool with various instruments, cleaning it, breaking down the fibres on metal spikes and spinning it on the distaff, whilst also inventing the tools needed for weaving it into cloth and making it into fine fabric.

'Likewise, she discovered how to make oil from pressing olives and how to extract the juice from other sorts of fruit.

'Likewise, she invented the art of building carts and chariots in order to carry things more easily from one place to another.

'Likewise, an invention of this lady's which was all the more marvellous for being such an unlikely thing for a woman to think of, was the art of forging armour for knights to protect themselves in battle and weapons of iron and steel for them to fight with. She taught this art first to the people of Athens, whom she also instructed in how to organize themselves into armies and battalions and to fight in serried ranks.

'Likewise, she invented flutes, pipes, trumpets and other wind instruments.

'This lady was not only extraordinarily intelligent but also supremely chaste, remaining a virgin all her life. It was because of her exemplary chastity that the poets claimed in their fables that she struggled long and hard with Vulcan, the god of fire, but finally overcame and defeated him. This story can be interpreted to mean that she conquered the passions and desires of the flesh which so vigorously assail the body when one is young. The Athenians held this girl in the highest esteem, worshipping her as if she were a deity and calling her the goddess of arms and warfare because she was the first to invent these arts. She was also known as the goddess of wisdom, thanks to her great intelligence.

'After her death, the people of Athens built a temple dedicated to her, in which they placed a statue representing wisdom and warfare in the likeness of a girl. This statue had terrible fierce eyes to symbolize both the duty of a knight to enforce justice and the inscrutability of the thoughts of a wise man. The statue had a helmet on its head, to suggest the idea that a knight must be hardened in battle and have unfailing courage, and that the plans of a wise man should be shrouded in secrecy. It was also dressed in chainmail, to represent the power of the estate of knighthood as well as the foresight of a wise man who arms himself against the vicissitudes of Fortune. The statue held a great spear or lance as an emblem of the fact that a knight must be the rod of justice and that a wise man launches his attacks from a safe distance. Round the statue's neck hung a shield or buckler of crystal, meaning that a knight must always be vigilant and ready to defend the country and the people and that a wise man has a clear understanding of all things. In the centre of this shield was the image of the head of a serpent known as a Gorgon, to suggest the idea that a knight must be cunning and stalk his enemies like a snake whilst a wise man must be wary of all the harm that others might do to him. To guard the statue, they placed next to it a night bird - an owl - to signify that a knight must be prepared, if needs be, to protect the country both day and night, and that a wise man must be alert at all times to do what is right. This lady Minerva was greatly revered for a long time and her fame spread to many other countries, where they also dedicated temples to her. Even centuries later, when the Romans were at the height of their powers, they incorporated her image into their pantheon of gods.'

35. About Queen Ceres, who invented agriculture and many other arts

'Ceres was queen of the Sicilians in very ancient times. Thanks to her great ingenuity, it was she who was responsible for inventing both the science and the techniques of agriculture as well as all the necessary tools. She taught her subjects how to round up and tame their cattle and train them to take the yoke. Ceres also invented the plough, showing her people how to use the blade to dig and slice through the soil, and all the other skills needed for this task. Next she taught them how to scatter the seed on the ground and to cover it over. Once the seed had taken root and grown into shoots, she revealed to them how to cut the sheaves and thresh them with a flail in order to separate the wheat from the chaff. Ceres then demonstrated to them how to grind the grain between heavy stones and to construct mills, going on to show them how to prepare flour and make it into bread. Thus this lady encouraged men who had been living like beasts off acorns, wild grasses, apples and holly berries to eat a more noble diet.

'Ceres didn't stop there: she gathered together her people, who at that time were used to wandering about like animals making their temporary homes in woods or moorlands, into large groups and taught them how to build proper towns and cities and to live in communities. She thereby brought humankind out of its primitive state and introduced it to a more civilized and rational way of life. The poets wrote a fable about Ceres which tells how her daughter was abducted by Pluto, god of the underworld. Because of her great knowledge and all the good that she had brought into the world, the people of the time venerated her, calling her the goddess of corn.'

36. About Isis, who discovered the art of making gardens and growing plants

'Thanks to her extensive knowledge of horticulture, Isis was not only queen of Egypt but also the highly revered goddess of the Egyptians. The fables tell how Isis was loved by Jupiter, who turned her into a cow and then back into her original form, all of which is an allegory of her great learning, as you yourself have pointed out in your Letter of Othea to Hector. For the benefit of the Egyptians, she also invented certain types of characters to represent their language which could be used to write down ideas in a concise way.

'Isis was the daughter of Inachos, king of the Greeks, and sister of Phoroneus, who was a very wise man. It so happened that this lady and her brother left Greece for Egypt and it was there that she showed the people many different things, including how to create gardens, grow plants and graft cuttings of one species on to another. She also set up a number of fine and decent laws which she encouraged the Egyptians to live by, since up until then they had been in a very primitive state without a properly established system of justice. In short, Isis did so much for them that they honoured her with great ceremony both in her own lifetime and after her death. Her fame spread throughout the world, with temples and oratories consecrated to her springing up all over. Even when Rome was at its peak, the Romans erected a temple in her honour where they performed great sacrifices and solemn rites observing the same customs which the Egyptians used to worship her.

'This noble lady's husband was named Apis, whom the pagans mistakenly believed to be the son of the god Jupiter and of Niobe, daughter of Phoroneus. The ancient historians and poets make great mention of this man.'

[...]

43. Christine asks Reason if women are naturally endowed with good judgement, and Reason replies to her question

I, Christine, came back to Reason, saying: 'My lady, it is now clear to me that God has truly made women's minds sharp enough to learn, understand and retain any form of knowledge. Praise be to Him for this! However, I'm always surprised at how many people you see whose minds are very quick to pick up and grasp all that they are shown and who are mentally agile and clever enough to master any discipline they please, attaining great learning through their dedication to their studies, but yet seem to lack judgement when it comes to their personal morals and public behaviour. This is true even of some of the most famous and erudite scholars. There's no doubt that knowledge of the sciences should help inculcate moral values. So, if you please, my lady, I'd be keen to know whether women's minds, which both you and my own experience have proved to me to be capable of understanding the most complex matters in sciences and other disciplines, are just as proficient at learning the lessons which good judgement teaches us. In other words, can women distinguish between what is the right and the wrong thing to do? Can they modify their current behaviour on the basis of past experience? Can they use the example of the present to anticipate how they should conduct themselves in the future? In my view, this is what good judgement consists of.'

Reason replied: 'You're quite right, my dear girl. Yet don't forget that this faculty that you're talking about is inherent in both men and women, and that some are more generously endowed with it than others. Note too that good judgement does not come from learning, though learning can help perfect it in those who are naturally that way inclined, since, as you know, two forces moving in the same direction are stronger and more powerful than a single force moving on its own. Therefore, in my opinion, anyone who has naturally good judgement or good sense and who also manages to attain learning is thoroughly deserving of praise. But, as you yourself have pointed out, some have one but not the other: one is a gift from God and is an innate quality, whereas the other is only acquired after much study. Both, however, are good.

'There are those who would maintain that it is better to have good judgement and no learning than to have great learning but bad judgement. This is a highly controversial proposition that raises all sorts of questions. You could say that the best person is the one who contributes most to the common good. In that case, it's undeniable that learned individuals help others most by sharing their knowledge with them, no matter how much good judgement they might possess. This is because individuals' faculty of judgement only lasts as long as their lifetime: when they die, it does, too. On the other hand, learning which has been acquired endures for ever, in that the good reputation of those who possess it never dies and they can teach their knowledge to others as well as pass it on in books for future generations to discover. Their learning does not therefore die with them, as I can prove to you by the example of Aristotle and all the others who first brought the sciences into the world. This type of acquired knowledge has been more beneficial to humankind than all the good judgement shown by those figures of the past who had no learning, even though many of them used their good sense to govern and administer their empires and kingdoms most wisely. The fact is, these deeds are transient and vanish with time, whereas learning is indestructible.

'However, I'm going to set these matters aside for others to resolve since they are not strictly relevant to our task of building the city. Instead, let's go back to what you originally asked me about whether women naturally have good judgement. On this question, I can give you a firm "yes". You should be able to gather this not just from what I've already told you but also from observing the way in which women generally go about doing their traditionally female duties. If you care to look closely, you'll discover that for the most part women prove themselves to be extremely attentive, diligent and meticulous in running a household and seeing to everything as best they can. Sometimes, those women who have lazy husbands annoy them by giving the impression that they are nagging them, telling them what to do and trying to be the voice of authority in the house; though husbands like this are just putting a bad slant on what most wives do with all good intentions. The next part of what I have to say will be largely derived from the "Epistle of Solomon" which talks about good wives such as these.'

44. The 'Epistle of Solomon' from the Book of Proverbs

'Whoever finds a valiant woman, one of sound judgement, will be a husband who lacks for nothing. Her fame spreads far and wide and her husband puts his faith in her for she brings him nothing but good and prosperity at all times. She looks for and acquires wool, in other words she sets her maid servants a worthy task to keep them gainfully employed and her household well stocked, and she herself lends a hand. She is like the ship of a merchant which brings all good things to shore and provides the bread. She rewards those who deserve it and they are her intimate friends. In her house, there is plenty to eat, even for the servants. She weighs up the price of a piece of land before buying it and she uses her good sense to plant the vines which will keep the household in wine. Full of courage and resolve, she girds her loins with strength and toughens up her arms with continuous hard work. Even in the dark of night, the light of her labours still shines through. She toils at the heavy tasks yet doesn't neglect women's work either, for she does her fair share. She extends a helping hand to the poor and brings them comfort in their suffering. By her efforts, the house is protected against the cold and the snow and her servants' clothing is lined. She dresses herself in silk and purple: that is, in integrity and splendour. Her husband too cuts an honourable figure when he is seated in the top ranks with the most venerable people in the land. She makes fine linen cloth, which she sells, and wraps herself in strength and glory. For this, she will have everlasting joy. Words of wisdom spring from her lips and her tongue is ruled by gentleness. She makes sure that the household is fully provided for and does not eat the bread of idleness. Her children's behaviour shows that she is their mother and their actions reveal her tender care. Her husband's fine appearance does her credit. She governs her daughters in all matters, even when they are fully grown. She despises the trappings of glory and the transience of beauty. Such a woman will fear the Lord and be praised, and He will reward her for her labours as they attest to her virtue far and wide.'

[...]

48. About Lavinia, daughter of King Latinus

'Lavinia, queen of the Laurentines, was similarly renowned for her good sense. Descended from the same Cretan king, Saturn, whom I've just mentioned, she was the daughter of King Latinus. She later wed Aeneas, although before her marriage she had been promised to Turnus, king of the Rutulians. Her father, who had been informed by an oracle that she should be given to a Trojan prince, kept putting off the wedding despite the fact that his wife, the queen, was very keen for it to take place. When Aeneas arrived in Italy, he requested King Latinus's permission to enter his territory. He was not only granted leave to do so but was immediately given Lavinia's hand in marriage. It was for this reason that Turnus declared war on Aeneas, a war which caused many deaths and in which Tumus himself was killed. Having secured the victory, Aeneas took Lavinia as his wife. She later bore him a son, even though he himself died whilst she was still pregnant. As her time grew near, she became very afraid that a man called Ascanius, Aeneas's elder son by another woman, would attempt to murder her child and usurp the throne. She therefore went off to give birth in the woods and named the newborn baby Julius Silvius. Vowing never to marry again, Lavinia conducted herself with exemplary good judgement in her widowhood and managed to keep the kingdom intact, thanks to her astuteness. She was able to win her stepson's affection and thus defuse any animosity on his part towards her or his stepbrother. Indeed, once he had finished building the city of Alba, Ascanius left to make his home there. Meanwhile, Lavinia ruled the country with supreme skill until her son came of age. This child's descendants were Romulus and Remus, who later founded the city of Rome. They in turn were the ancestors of all the noble princes who came after them.

'What more can I tell you, my dear Christine? It seems to me that I've cited sufficient evidence to make my point, having given enough examples and proofs to convince you that God has never criticized the female sex more than the male sex. My case is conclusive, as you have seen, and my two sisters here will go on to confirm this for you in their presentation of the facts. I think that I have fulfilled my task of constructing the enclosure walls of the City of Ladies, since they're all now ready and done. Let me give way to my two sisters: with their help and advice you'll soon complete the building work that remains.'

End of the First Part of the Book of the City of Ladies.

Part Ⅱ

1. The first chapter tells of the ten Sibyls

After the first lady, whose name was Reason, had finished speaking, the second lady, called Rectitude, turned to me and said, 'My dear Christine, I mustn't hang back from performing my duty: together we must construct the houses and buildings inside the walls of the City of Ladies which my sister Reason has now put up. Take your tools and come with me. Don't hesitate to mix the mortar well in your inkpot and set to on the masonry work with great strokes of your pen. I'll keep you well supplied with materials. With the grace of God, we'll soon have put up the royal palaces and noble mansions for the glorious and illustrious ladies who will come to live in this city for evermore.'

On hearing this honourable lady's words, I, Christine, replied to her, saying, 'Most excellent lady, here I stand ready before you. I will obey your every command, for my only wish is to do your bidding.'

She then answered me, 'My dear friend, look at these beautiful gleaming stones, more precious than any others in the world, that I have quarried and cut ready for you to use in the building work. Have I stood idly by whilst you were toiling away so hard with Reason? You must now arrange them in the order that I shall give you, following the line that I have traced for you.

'Amongst the highest rank of ladies of great renown are the wise sibyls who were extraordinarily knowledgeable. According to the most authoritative sources, there were ten sibyls, though some maintain there were only nine. My dear Christine, take good note of all this: what greater gift of divine revelation did God ever bestow on any prophet, even the most beloved, than that which He granted to these noble ladies I'm talking about? Didn't He confer on them the holy spirit of prophecy which allowed them to speak and write so straightforwardly and clearly that it was as if they were recounting past and completed actions in the manner of a chronicle, rather than anticipating events that would happen in the future? They even spoke more plainly and in greater detail than any prophet about the coming of Christ, which happened a long time after their day. These ladies kept their virginity intact and their bodies unsullied for the whole of their lives. All ten of them were called Sibyl, but this shouldn't be taken to be a proper name. The word "sibyl" in fact means "one who is privy to the thoughts of God". They were all given this name because their prophecies were of such momentous events that they could only have known of them if they had had access to the mind of God Himself. It's therefore a title of office rather than the name of an individual. Though they were all born in different countries of the world and lived in different eras, they all foresaw great future events including, with particular clarity, the birth of Christ, as I've already mentioned. Moreover, all ten of them were pagans, not even of the Jewish faith.

'The first sibyl came from the land of Persia, and for this reason is called Persica. The second one was from Libya, hence she was known as Libica. The third, born in the temple of Apollo at Delphi, was therefore called Delphica. It was she who predicted the destruction of Troy long before it occurred and she to whom Ovid dedicated a few lines in one of his books. The fourth one was from Italy: her name was Cimeria. The fifth, born in Babylon, was called Herophile: she was the one who prophesied to the Greeks who had come to consult her that they would destroy both Troy and its citadel, Ilium, and that Homer would give an untruthful version of these events in his writings. She was also known as Erythrea, for that was the name of the island where she made her home and where her books were subsequently discovered. The sixth one came from the island of Samos, and was called Sarnia. The seventh was known as Cumana, because she was born in the Italian city of Cumae, in the region of Campania. The eighth was named Hellespontina, for she came from Hellespont on the plains of Troy: she flourished during the time of Cyrus and the famous author Solon. The ninth one, called Phrygica, was from Phrygia, and she not only spoke at length about the fall of many different kingdoms but also described in vivid detail the coming of the false prophet Antichrist. The tenth was called Tiburtina, also known as Albunea, whose writings are held in great esteem because she wrote about Jesus Christ most clearly. Despite the fact that these sibyls were all of pagan origin, each of them eventually repudiated this faith on the grounds that it was wrong to worship a multiplicity of gods, that there was only one true God, and that all idols were false.'

[...]

5. About Cassandra and Queen Basine, as well as more about Nicostrata

'That Nicostrata whom we discussed earlier was also a prophetess. As soon as she crossed the River Tiber and had climbed up on to Mount Palatine with her son Evander, of whom the history books make great mention, she prophesied that on that hill would be built the most famous city that had ever existed, one which would rule over all other earthly kingdoms. In order to be the first person to lay down a founding stone, she constructed a fortress there, as we have said before, and it was on this spot that Rome was founded and subsequently built.

'Likewise, wasn't the noble Trojan maiden Cassandra, daughter of King Priam of Troy and sister of the illustrious Hector, also a prophetess, she who was so learned that she knew all the arts? Having chosen never to take any man for her lord, no matter how high-born a prince he might be, this girl foresaw what would happen to the Trojans and was forever sunk in sorrow. The more she saw the glory of Troy flourish and prosper in the period before the conflict between the Trojans and the Greeks began, the more she wept, wailed and lamented. The sight of the city in all its wealth and magnificence, and of her brothers in all their splendour, especially the noble Hector who was so full of valour, made it impossible for Cassandra to keep to herself all the horror that was to come. On seeing the war break out, her grief intensified and she never left off crying, shrieking and imploring her father and brothers to make peace with the Greeks for heaven's sake, warning them that otherwise the war would destroy every one of them. But her words were all in vain for no one believed her. Moreover, since she refused to be silent but understandably gave full vent to her sorrow at all this destruction and killing, she was often beaten by her father and brothers who told her that she was mad. Yet she never let up for a moment: even if her life depended on it, she would never stop telling them about what was going to happen. In the end, in order to have some peace and to block out the incessant noise she made, they had to shut her up in a distant room far away from other people. However, it would have been better for them if they had believed her, because everything came to pass just as she had said. They eventually regretted what they had done, but by then it was too late.

'Likewise, weren't the prophecies of Queen Basine equally extraordinary, she who had been married to the king of Thuringia and then became the wife of Childeric, the fourth king of France, as the chronicles recall? The story goes that, on her wedding night, she persuaded King Childeric that if he kept himself chaste that night he would receive a marvellous vision. Thereupon she told him to get up and go to the bedroom window and to describe what he could see outside. The king did as she said and it seemed to him that he could see great beasts such as unicorns, leopards and lions coming and going in the palace. Turning round to the queen in terror, he asked her what it all meant. She replied that she would reveal the answer to him in the morning and reassured him that he had nothing to fear but should go back to the window again. This he did, and the second time he thought he saw fierce bears and enormous wolves which seemed to be attacking each other. The queen sent him back to the window a third time and he thought he could see dogs and other small creatures tearing each other to pieces. The king was so horrified and amazed at these things that the queen had to explain to him that the animals he had seen in his vision represented their descendants, the successive generations of French princes who would one day sit on the throne. The different types of animal symbolized what the temperament and behaviour of these various princes would be like.

'So, you can clearly see, my dear Christine, how often God has disclosed His secrets to the world through women.'

[...]

7. Christine addresses Lady Rectitude

'My lady, the more evidence I see and hear which proves that women are innocent of everything that they have been accused of, the more obvious it is to me how in the wrong their accusers are. Yet I can't help myself from mentioning a custom which is quite common amongst men and even some women, which is that when wives are pregnant and give birth to a daughter, their husbands are very often unhappy and disgruntled that they didn't bear them a son. Their silly wives, who should be overjoyed that God has delivered them safely and should thank Him with all their hearts, are also upset because they see that their husbands are distressed. But why is it, my lady, that they are so displeased? Is it because girls are more trouble than boys or less loving and caring towards their parents than male children are?'

Rectitude replied, 'My dear friend, since you've asked me why this happens, I can assure you that those who upset themselves tend to do so out of ignorance and stupidity. However, the main reason why they are unhappy is because they worry how much it's going to cost them to marry off their daughters since they will have to pay for it out of their own pockets. Others, though, are dismayed because they're afraid of the danger that a young and innocent girl can be led astray by the wrong sort of people. Yet neither of these reasons stands up to scrutiny. As for being worried that their daughters will disgrace themselves, all the parents have to do is bring them up properly when they're little, with the mother setting them an example through her own respectable behaviour and good advice; though if the mother has lax morals, she will hardly be a fit example for the daughter to follow. Daughters should be kept on a tight rein away from bad company and taught to fear their parents because bringing infants and children up strictly helps to establish good conduct later in life. Likewise, on the question of the expense involved, I would say that if the parents, whatever social class they may be, looked carefully at what it costs them to set their sons up or to pay for them to study or learn a trade, let alone all the extra money which their sons spend on disreputable acquaintances and unnecessary luxuries, they would soon realize that sons are scarcely less of a financial burden than daughters. Not to mention all the terrible anguish and worry that many sons frequently inflict on their parents by getting into nasty fights and vicious brawls or by falling into depraved habits, all this to the shame of their parents and at their expense. To my mind, this far outweighs any distress that their daughters might cause them.

'See how many names you can cite of sons who actually looked after their aged parents with kindness and consideration, as they should do. Though one can find both past and present examples, they're rather thin on the ground and their assistance comes only at the last minute. What usually happens is that, when they're all grown up, having been treated like a god by their parents and having learnt a trade or studied thanks to their father's help, or become rich and affluent by some stroke of good fortune, if their father falls on hard times or into destitution, they'll turn their backs on him and be ashamed and embarrassed when they see him. If, on the other hand, the father is well off, they can't wait for him to die so that they can get their hands on his estate. God knows how many sons of great lords and wealthy men long for the death of their parents in order to inherit their lands and possessions. Petrarch definitely spoke the truth when he said: "O foolish man, you wish to have children but you can have no deadlier enemies than these. If you are poor, they will despise you and will pray for your death so as to be rid of you. If you are rich, they will pray for it all the more in order to grab your wealth." I don't mean to say that all sons are like this, but many of them are. Moreover, if they're married, God knows how insatiable they can be as they suck their mother and father dry to the extent that they wouldn't care if the poor old things starved to death as long as they can inherit the lot. What dreadful offspring! If their mothers are widowed, instead of comforting them and being a rod and staff to them in their old age, they pay them back terribly for all the love and devotion their mothers have spent on bringing them up. Bad children have the idea that everything should belong to them, so if their mothers don't give them all they want, they don't hesitate to pour down their curses upon them. Heaven knows what kind of respect this is to show one's mother! Worse still, some of them think nothing of taking their mothers to court and bringing a case against them. That's the reward that many parents get for having spent their whole lives putting their money to one side for the benefit of their children. Plenty of sons are like this, and it may be too that some daughters are of the same ilk. But if you look closely, I think you'll find that there are more unworthy sons than daughters.

'Even if all male children were dutiful, the fact remains that you see more daughters than sons keeping their mothers and fathers company. They not only visit them more often, but also comfort them and look after them more when they're old and infirm. The reason for this is that boys tend to go out and about in the world whereas gifts tend to be retiring and stay closer to home, as you yourself can attest. Though your brothers are very loving and devoted sons, they have gone out into the world whilst you have stayed behind alone to take care of your dear mother and are the main comfort to her in her old age. To sum up, I would say that those who are upset and unhappy at having daughters are completely deluded. Whilst we're on this subject, I'd like to tell you about several women mentioned amongst others in the history books who were very kind and caring towards their parents.'

8. Here begins a series of daughters who loved their parents, the first of whom is Drypetina

'Drypetina, Queen of Laodicea, was very loving towards her father. She was the daughter of the great King Mithradates and was so devoted to him that she followed him into all his battles. This girl was extremely ugly, for she had two sets of teeth, a very severe deformity. However, she loved her father so much that she never left his side, in good times or in bad. Despite the fact that she was the queen and lady of a vast realm, which meant that she could have lived a safe and comfortable life in her own country, she preferred to share her father's sufferings and hardships whenever he went off to war. Even when he was defeated by the mighty Pompey, she still did not abandon him but looked after him with great care and dedication.'

[...]

12. Here Rectitude explains that the houses of the city have been completed and that it is time they were filled with inhabitants

'My dearest friend, it seems to me that our building is well underway and that the City of Ladies now has plentiful housing all along its wide streets. The royal palaces are completed and the defence towers and keeps are now standing proud, tall enough to be seen from miles away. It's high time that we began to fill this city with people. It should not stand deserted or empty but should be full of illustrious ladies, as they alone are welcome here. How happy the inhabitants of our city will be! They will have no cause to fear being thrown out of their homes by enemy hordes, for this place has a special property which means that those who move into it will never be dispossessed. A new Realm of Femininia is at hand, except that this one is so much more perfect than the previous one because the ladies who live here will have no need to leave their territory in order to breed the new generations of women who will inherit their realm down the ages. The ladies we're going to invite here will be sufficient in number to last for all time.

'Once we have filled the city with worthy citizens, my sister, Lady Justice, will come bringing with her the queen, a magnificent lady who surpasses all others, accompanied by a host of the noblest princesses. It is they who will occupy the finest buildings and will make their homes in the lofty towers. So it's all the more urgent that, when the queen comes, she should find the city full of excellent ladies ready to receive her with all honours as their supreme mistress and as the empress of their sex. What type of citizens shall we bring? Will they be dissolute women of ill repute? Most certainly not! They will all be valiant ladies of great renown, for we could wish for no worthier population nor more beautiful adornment to our city than such virtuous and honourable women as these. Come now, Christine, let's set out in search of our ladies.'

13. Christine asks Lady Rectitude if it's true what men and books say about the institution of marriage being unbearable because women are so impossible to live with. In her reply, Rectitude begins by discussing the great love that women have for their husbands

Whilst we were doing as Rectitude had said and were on our way to fetch the ladies we were looking for, I said to her as we walked along, 'My lady, you and Reason have conclusively replied to all the questions and queries that I was unable to answer for myself and I think that I'm now much better informed than I was before on these matters. Thanks to you two, I have discovered that women are more than capable of undertaking any task which requires physical strength or of learning any discipline which requires discernment and intelligence. However, I would now like to ask your opinion about something which is weighing very heavily on my mind. Is it true what so many men say and so many authors in their books claim about it being the fault of women and their shrewish, vengeful nagging that the married state is such a constant hell for men? There are plenty of people who maintain that this is the case, arguing that women care so little for their husbands and their company that there is nothing which irritates them more. In order to avoid this misery and these problems, many authors have advised men to be wise and not to marry at all, on the grounds that there are no women - or hardly any - who are faithful to their spouses. This view is even echoed in the Letter of Valerius to Ruffinus which quotes Theophrastus who, in his book, stated that no wise man would take a wife because women cause trouble, lack affection, and gossip incessantly. He also says that if a man gets married thinking that he'll be well looked after and well cared for if he falls ill, he'd be much better off being attended by a loyal servant, who would also cost him a lot less too. If the wife falls ill, on the other hand, he'll be all anxious and will feel obliged not to leave her side. Theophrastus came out with much more in this vein, but I won't go into it any further. My dear lady, if such things are true, it would seem that these faults are so awful that they cancel out completely whatever good qualities or virtues a woman might have.'

Rectitude replied, 'My dear Christine, as you yourself said earlier on this subject, it's certainly easy to win your case when there's no one to argue against you. But believe me when I tell you that the books which put forward these ideas were definitely not written by women. Indeed, I have no doubt that if one wanted to write a new book on the question of marriage by gathering information based on the facts; one would come up with a very different set of views. My dear friend, as you yourself know, there are so many wives who lead a wretched existence bound in marriage to a brutish husband who makes them suffer greater penance than if they were enslaved by Saracens. Oh God, how many fine and decent women have been viciously beaten for no good reason, heaped with insults, obscenities and curses, and subjected to all manner of burdens and indignities, without uttering even a murmur of protest. Not to mention all those wives who are laden down with lots of tiny mouths to feed and lie starving to death in penury whilst their husbands are either out visiting places of depravity or living it up in town or in taverns. All that wives such as these get for supper when their husbands come home is a good hiding. I ask you, am I telling lies? Haven't you ever seen any of your neighbours being treated in this way?'

I replied, 'Yes, my lady. I've seen many women treated like this and I felt sorry for them.'

'I can well believe it. As for those husbands who are anxious when their wives fall ill, I ask you, my dear friend, do you know of any? Without going into further detail, let me tell you that all this rubbish that has ever been said and written about wives is just a string of falsehoods tied together. It is the husband who is the master of the wife, and not the other way round. A man would never allow himself to be dominated by a woman. However, let me assure you that not all marriages are like this. There are some married couples who love each other, are faithful to each other, and live together in peace: in these cases it is both spouses who are sensible, kind and gentle. Though there are bad husbands, there are also some who are decent, honourable and wise. The women who have the good fortune to marry them should thank God for giving them so much happiness here on this earth. You yourself can attest to this since you couldn't have wished for a better husband than you had. In your opinion, he surpassed all other men in kindness, gentleness, loyalty and affection, and you will never stop grieving for his death in your heart. Whilst it's undeniable that there are many fine women who are badly treated by their contrary husbands, it's also true to say that some wives are wilful and unreasonable. Indeed, if I claimed that all wives were paragons of virtue, I would quite rightly be accused of being a liar. However, these women are in the minority. Anyway, I'd rather not discuss such women because they're like creatures who go totally against their nature.

'Talking about good wives instead, let's go back to what that Theophrastus, whom you mentioned earlier, said about a sick man being as well looked after and as faithfully attended by a servant as by a wife. You see countless good and loyal wives who serve their husbands in sickness or in health with as much loving care as if they were gods! I don't think you're going to find many servants like that. Since we're on this subject, I'll now give you some examples of wives who adored their husbands and were utterly devoted to them. Now, thank the Lord, we can come back to our city with a fine host of decent and respectable ladies whom we can invite inside. Here is the noble Queen Hypsicratea, who was once wife of the mighty King Mithradates. Because she belongs to such ancient times and is of such inestimable worth, she shall be the first to take her place in the magnificent palace which has been prepared for her.'

14. About Queen Hypsicratea

'How could anyone show more love for another person than the beautiful Hypsicratea did for her husband, she who was so kind and loyal? This lady was the wife of the great King Mithradates who ruled over lands where twenty-four different languages were spoken. Despite the fact that this king was the most powerful on earth, the Romans waged a terrible war on him. In all the time that he was engaged in his lengthy and arduous battles, his good wife never left him, no matter where he went. As was the barbarian custom, this king also had several concubines. However, this noble lady bore her husband such a deep love that she refused to let him go anywhere without her and frequently went off with him into battle. Though the fate of the kingdom was at stake and the threat of death at the hands of the Romans ever present, she travelled everywhere with him to far-off places and strange lands, crossing seas and perilous deserts and never once failing to be his faithful companion at his side. Her affection for him was so strong that she deemed that no man could possibly serve her lord with such perfect loyalty as she could.

'So, contrary to what the philosopher Theophrastus says on the subject, this lady was well aware that kings and princes can often have disloyal servants who serve them badly. Therefore, like the faithful lady she was, she devoted herself to ensuring that her lord's every possible need was met. Though she had to endure many hardships, she followed him through thick and thin. Since it was impractical for her to wear women's clothing in these conditions, and it was thought improper that the wife of such a great king and warrior should be seen at his side in battle, she cut off her finest womanly attribute, her long, golden hair, in order to disguise herself as a man. Neither did she give a thought to protecting her complexion, for she strapped on a helmet and her face soon grew dirty from all the sweat and dust. Her lovely, graceful body she clad in armour and weighed down with a coat of chainmail. She took off all her precious rings and costly jewellery and instead roughened her hands from carrying heavy axes and spears, as well as a bow and arrows. Round her waist she wore no elegant girdle but a sword. Because of the great love and loyalty she bore her husband, this lady so thoroughly adapted herself to her new surroundings that her charming and delicate young body, which was made for softer and more pleasurable living, was transformed into that of a strong and powerfully built knight-in-arms. Listen to what Boccaccio says in his version of the story: "Is there anything that love cannot accomplish? Here we see this lady, who was used to the finer things in life such as a soft bed and every possible comfort, choosing of her own free will to make herself as tough and rugged as any man, journeying over hill and dale, travelling by day and night, bedding down in deserts and forests often on the hard ground, in perpetual fear of the enemy and surrounded on all sides by wild beasts and serpents." Yet all this seemed agreeable to her as long as she could be at her husband's side to comfort and advise him, seeing to his every need.

'Later on, after having suffered many great hardships together, her husband was cruelly defeated by Pompey, a prince of the Roman army, and had to take flight. Though he was abandoned by all his men, his wife alone stayed with him, following him as he fled across mountains and valleys and through many dark and dangerous places. On the point of despair at having been deserted and forsaken by all his friends, the king was comforted by his faithful wife who gently encouraged him to hope for better days to come. Even when they were at their lowest ebb, she still made every effort to bring him good cheer and to lift his spirits by finding the right words to dispel his sadness and by inventing some amusing and distracting games for them to play together. By means of these things and her great kindness, she brought him such consolation that no matter how downcast or dejected he was, or how much suffering he had to bear, she found a way to make him forget his unhappiness. He was often moved to say that he didn't feel like he was in exile but rather as if he were at home in his palace having a delightful time with his devoted wife.'

[...]

21. About Xanthippe, wife of the philosopher Socrates

'The honourable lady Xanthippe was a very wise and virtuous woman who married the great philosopher Socrates. Though he was already very old and spent more time poring over his books than buying his wife little treats and presents, the good lady never stopped loving him. Indeed, she thought so highly of his extraordinary wisdom, as well as his great goodness and steadfastness, that she loved him very deeply and took enormous pride in him. When the brave and noble Xanthippe learnt that the Athenians had sentenced her husband to death for having attacked their practice of worshipping idols and for claiming that there was only one god whom they should honour and serve, she was unable to control her emotions. Rushing out into the street with her hair all undone and racked with sobbing, she fought her way into the palace where her husband was being held and found him surrounded by the treacherous judges who were already handing him the cup of poison that would end his life. She came into the room just as Socrates had raised the cup to his lips and was about to drink the poison, whereupon she dashed it from his hands and spilt all the liquid on to the floor. Socrates chided her for this and tried to comfort her by telling her to have patience. Unable to do anything to prevent his death, she gave full vent to her sorrow, crying, "What a crime and a great loss it is to kill such a good man! What a sin and an injustice!" Socrates kept on trying to console her, explaining that it was better to be wrongfully put to death than to have deserved one's punishment. So he died, but throughout the rest of her life his loving wife never stopped grieving for him in her heart.'

[...]

25. Christine speaks to Lady Rectitude about those who claim that women cannot keep a secret. In her reply, Rectitude talks about Portia, Cato's daughter

'My lady, I am now totally convinced of what I have often seen for myself: many women of both the past and the present have clearly shown their husbands how much they love them and are devoted to them. That's why I'm so puzzled by a saying which is very common amongst men, including Master Jean de Meun in his Romance of the Rose, as well as other writers, that a man should avoid telling a woman anything which he wants kept secret because women are incapable of keeping their mouths shut.'

Rectitude replied, 'My dear friend, as you are aware, not all women are necessarily very wise and neither are all men. Therefore, if a man has any sense, he should judge for himself if his wife is trustworthy and well-meaning before he tells her anything in confidence, because it could have dangerous consequences. Any man who knows that his wife is dependable, careful and discreet can rest assured that there is no other creature in the world whom he can trust more implicitly nor on whom he can rely so completely.

'On the question of whether women are as indiscreet as some maintain, we also come back to the issue of wives who loved their husbands. The noble Brutus of Rome, who was married to Portia, certainly did not subscribe to this opinion. This fine lady, Portia, was the daughter of Cato the Younger, the nephew of Cato the Elder. Knowing how wise and virtuous she was, her husband did not hesitate to tell her that he and Cassius, another Roman nobleman, planned to kill Julius Caesar in the senate. However, foreseeing that this deed would have terrible repercussions, the sensible lady did her best to dissuade her husband from carrying out his plan. She was so disturbed by the thought of what he intended to do that she was unable to sleep at all that night. The next morning, as Brutus left the bedroom to go off and execute his plan, in a desperate attempt to stop him, Portia seized a barber's razorblade as if to clip her fingernails with it and dropped it on the floor. She then reached down to pick it up again and deliberately dug it deep into her hand. Horrified by the sight of her wound, her ladies screamed so loudly that Brutus turned back. When he saw how she had cut herself, he scolded her and told her that it was a barber's job to use the razor, not hers. She replied that she hadn't acted as stupidly as he might think: she had done it on purpose in order to find out how to kill herself, should any harm come to him after he had carried out his plan. Still refusing to change his mind, Brutus left the house. Soon after, he and Cassius together killed Julius Caesar. They were sent into exile for what they had done and Brutus was subsequently murdered, even though he had already been banished from Rome. When his wife, Portia, learnt of his death, she was so distraught that she had no further desire to live. Since all the sharp instruments and knives had been taken away from her, because it was obvious what she intended to do, she went over to the fire and swallowed some live coals instead. The noble Portia thus killed herself by burning her insides, truly the strangest death that anyone has ever suffered.'

[...]

28. Proof against those who claim that only an idiot takes his wife's advice or puts his trust in her. Christine asks some questions to which Rectitude replies

'My lady, having heard your arguments and seen for myself how sensible and dependable women are, I'm amazed that some people claim that only a stupid idiot listens to his wife and trusts her advice.'

Rectitude replied, 'I pointed out to you earlier that not all women are wise. However, those men who do have responsible, trustworthy wives are fools if they refuse to put their faith in them. You can see this from what I've just told you: if Brutus had let Portia persuade him not to assassinate Julius Caesar, he himself would not have been killed and he could have avoided causing all the harm that was subsequently done. Whilst we're on this subject, I'll tell you about certain other men who suffered the consequences of not listening to their spouses. Afterwards, I'll go on to give you some examples where the husbands did well to take their wives' advice.

'If Julius Caesar, whom we've just mentioned, had trusted his sensible and intelligent wife, who had seen various signs foretelling her husband's assassination and had a terrible dream about it the night before, which made her do everything she could to try to stop him from going to the senate that day, he would not have gone and met his death.

'The same can be said of Pompey, who first married Julia, daughter of Julius Caesar, as I told you before, and then took as his second wife another noble lady, by the name of Cornelia. Going back to what we were talking about earlier, this lady loved her husband so dearly that she refused to leave him, no matter what misfortune befell him. Even when he was forced to escape by sea after having been defeated in battle by Julius Caesar, this good lady Cornelia went with him and faced every danger at his side. When Pompey arrived at the kingdom of Egypt, the treacherous King Ptolemy pretended that he was glad to receive him, sending his people ahead to welcome Pompey although in fact their mission was to kill him. These people told Pompey to get back on board ship and leave everybody else ashore so as to lighten the vessel of its load and thus manoeuvre it more easily into port. Pompey was happy to comply with their wishes but his loyal wife tried to dissuade him from separating himself from all his men by doing so. Seeing that he wasn't going to change his mind, she tried to jump back on to the ship with him because she suspected deep down that something was amiss. However, he wouldn't allow her to do so and had to have her held back by force. That was the point at which all this lady's sorrow began, a sorrow which was to haunt her all her life. No sooner had her husband sailed only a short way out than, having never taken her eyes off him for a second, she saw him being killed by the traitors on board. She was so distraught that she would have thrown herself into the sea if she hadn't been restrained.

'Likewise, the same sort of misfortune struck the worthy Hector of Troy. The night before he was killed, his wife Andromache had a most extraordinary dream which told her that if Hector went into battle the next day he would surely lose his life. Horrified by what she took to be not simply a nightmare but a true prophecy, this lady went down on her knees and begged her husband with hands joined together in supplication not to join the fighting that day, even bringing their two lovely children before him in her arms. However, he took no notice of her words, thinking that he would bring irreparable dishonour on himself if he allowed a woman's advice to stop him from going into combat. Neither was he moved by his mother's and father's entreaties after Andromache had asked them to intercede on her behalf. It thus all happened exactly as she had said and it would have been better for Hector if he had listened to her because he was killed by Achilles in battle.

'I could give you endless other examples of men who came to harm in various ways for not deigning to take their good wives' sensible advice. However, those who met a bad end because they dismissed what their wives had to say have only themselves to blame.'

[...]

31. About Judith, the noble widow

'Judith, the noble widow, saved the people of Israel from destruction at the time when Nebuchadnezzar II sent Holofernes to rule over the Jews, having conquered the land of Egypt. This Holofernes and his great army were besieging the Jews inside the city and had already inflicted so much damage on them that they could scarcely hold out much longer. He had cut off their water supply, and their stocks of food were almost exhausted. Despairing of being able to withstand much more, the Jews were on the point of being defeated by Holofernes and were in total dismay. They began to say their prayers, beseeching God to have mercy on His people and to prevent them from falling into the clutches of the enemy. God heard their prayers and, just as He would later save the human race by a woman, so He chose on this occasion to send a woman to their rescue.

'In the city lived a noble and valiant lady called Judith, who was a young and lovely woman of exemplary virtue and chastity. She took pity on the people in their distress and prayed to God day and night to save them. Inspired by God, in whom she had placed her trust, Judith hatched a daring plan. One night, commending herself to the Lord's care, she left the city accompanied only by one of her maid servants and headed for Holofernes's camp. When the soldiers who were on sentry duty saw in the moonlight how beautiful she was, they took her straight to Holofernes, who was delighted to receive such a dazzling woman. He made her sit down beside him and was soon entranced by her intelligence, proud bearing and beauty. The more he gazed at her, the more he burned with desire for her. She, who had other ideas, offered up a silent prayer to God to beg for His help in her endeavours, and managed to string Holofernes along with little promises until she could find the right moment. Three nights later, Holofernes threw a banquet for his barons and drank very heavily. Sated with food and drink, he couldn't wait any longer to sleep with the Hebrew woman so he sent for her to come to him, which she did. When he told her what he wanted, she was ready to do as he wished on condition that, for the sake of propriety, he made all his men leave his tent. He should then get into bed first, to be joined by Judith at midnight when everyone else was asleep. Holofernes accepted her terms. The good lady then began to pray, begging God to give her the necessary strength and courage in her trembling woman's heart to rid her people of this foul tyrant.

'When Judith thought that Holofernes would have fallen asleep, she and her maid servant crept up to the opening of his tent and stood listening. Hearing him sound asleep, the lady exclaimed, "Let's do it now, for God is with us!" She went inside and fearlessly grabbed hold of his sword that was hanging by the bed and drew it out of its scabbard. Using all her strength to lift the blade, she cut off Holofernes's head without making a sound. With the head wrapped in her skirts, she ran back to the city as fast as she could. Having returned to the gates without meeting any opposition, she called out, "Come and open up, for God is with us!" Once she was back inside, you can't imagine how overjoyed they all were at what she had done. In the morning, they impaled the head on a spike and stuck it on top of the city walls. They then threw on their armour and mounted a bold and swift attack on the enemy who were still sleeping, never once suspecting that this might happen. The enemy rushed to their leader's tent to wake him up and to get him out of bed as quickly as possible, but they were horrified to find him slain. The Jews took them all prisoner and killed every last one. Thus the people of Israel were delivered out of the hands of Holofernes by Judith, that valiant woman whose praises shall be sung for ever in Holy Scripture.'

[...]

33. About the Sabine women

'I could give you many examples of pagan women of antiquity who saved their countries, towns or cities. However, I'll limit myself to two important instances with which to prove my point.

'After the foundation of Rome by Romulus and Remus, Romulus filled the city with as many knights and soldiers as he could collect together after the numerous victories he had won. He was most anxious to obtain wives for these men in order that they would have heirs who would reign over the city in the years to come. However, he was unsure how to go about finding women for himself and his companions to marry, as the kings, princes and people in the surrounding country were reluctant to give them their daughters or to establish any links with them because they considered them to be too reckless, uncivilized and unreliable a race. For this reason, Romulus had to devise a cunning plan. He had it announced throughout the land that a tournament of jousting would take place and he invited all the kings, princes and citizens to come and bring their ladies and daughters to watch the entertainment provided by the foreign knights. On the day of the festivities, a vast crowd gathered on all sides, for a large number of ladies and maidens had come to watch the sport. Amongst them was the daughter of the Sabine king, a charming and beautiful girl, accompanied by all the other ladies and girls of her country whom she had brought along. The games took place outside the city walls, on a plain at the foot of a hill, with the ladies seated high up in rows. The knights outdid each other in their feats and exploits, for the sight of these lovely ladies inspired them to great deeds of bravery and daring. To keep my story brief, after they had been fighting for a while, Romulus decided that it was time to execute his plan and so took out a great ivory horn on which he gave a loud blast. At this sound, which was a signal for them to act, the knights stopped their jousting and ran towards the ladies. Romulus snatched the king's daughter, with whom he was already smitten, whilst the other knights each took the one they wanted. Forcing the ladies to get up on to their horses, the Romans galloped off towards the city and bolted the gates firmly behind them. Outside, the women's fathers and kinsmen let out great cries of grief, as did the ladies themselves who had been abducted, but their weeping was totally in vain. Romulus married his lady with great ceremony, and all the other knights did likewise.

'This event caused a terrible war to break out. As soon as he could, the Sabine king gathered a great army together to attack the Romans. However, it was not easy to defeat them as they were such experts in battle. The war had already lasted five years when, one day, the two sides prepared to meet in full strength on the battlefield and it was obvious that there was going to be an appalling massacre with enormous loss of life. The Romans had already left the city gates in huge numbers when the queen called all the ladies of Rome to meet together in a temple. This wise and beautiful young woman addressed them, saying: "Honourable Sabine ladies; sisters and companions, you all know only too well how we were abducted by our husbands and how this has caused a war between our fathers and kinsmen on the one side and our husbands on the other. There is no way that this deadly conflict can continue or even come to an end, without it being to our detriment, no matter who has the final victory. If we lose our husbands, whom we quite rightly adore now that we have borne them children, we shall be broken-hearted and devastated to see our babies deprived of their fathers. If, on the other hand, our husbands are victorious and our fathers and kinsmen are killed, we will surely deeply regret that all this conflict happened because of us. What is done is done and cannot now be undone. In my view, we need to find some way to bring this war to a peaceful end. If you decide to take my advice and follow my lead in what I'm going to do, I think that we'll be able to bring this about.' Hearing her words, the other ladies replied with one voice that they would do as she said and would obey her instructions.

'The queen therefore undid her hair and took off her shoes, as did all the other ladies. Those who had babies picked them up in their arms and carried them with them. In addition, there was a whole host of children, as well as pregnant women. The queen walked at the head of this touching procession and they all headed straight for the battlefield just as the two armies were lining up. They took up their position in between the opposing sets of troops, making it impossible for the knights to attack each other without first running into the women. The queen and all the other ladies fell to their knees and shouted out, "Dear fathers and kinsmen, beloved husbands: for God's sake, make peace! If not, we are prepared to die trampled underfoot by your horses." Seeing their wives and children in tears, the knights were astonished and dismayed: there was certainly no way that they would run at them. The women's fathers were similarly moved to compassion at the sight of their daughters in this terrible state. The two sides looked at each other and, out of pity for the women who were humbly begging them to desist, their hatred turned to proper filial love. Sabines and Romans alike were forced to throw down their weapons as they rushed to embrace each other and make peace. Romulus led his father-in-law, the king of the Sabines, into the city and received him and his whole army with great honour. Thus, thanks to the good sense and bravery of the queen and her ladies, the Romans and the Sabines were prevented from massacring each other.'

[...]

36. Against those who claim that it is not good for women to be educated

After hearing these words I, Christine, said, 'My lady, I can clearly see that much good has been brought into the world by women. Even if some wicked women have done evil things it still seems to me that this is far outweighed by all the good that other women have done and continue to do. This is particularly true of those who are wise and well educated in either the arts or the sciences, whom we mentioned before. That's why I'm all the more amazed at the opinion of some men who state that they are completely opposed to their daughters, wives or other female relatives engaging in study, for fear that their morals will be corrupted.'

Rectitude replied, 'This should prove to you that not all men's arguments are based on reason, and that these men in particular are wrong. There are absolutely no grounds for assuming that knowledge of moral disciplines, which actually inculcate virtue, would have a morally corrupting effect. Indeed, there's no doubt whatsoever that such forms of knowledge correct one's vices and improve one's morals. How could anyone possibly think that by studying good lessons and advice one will be any the worse for it? This view is completely unthinkable and untenable. I'm not saying that it's a good idea for men or women to study sorcery or any other type of forbidden science, since the Holy Church did not ban people from practising them for nothing. However, it's just that it's not true to say that women will be corrupted by knowing what's right and proper.

'Quintus Hortensius, who was a great rhetorician and a fine orator of Rome, did not subscribe to this opinion. He had a daughter named Hortensia, whom he loved dearly for her keen wits. He educated her himself, teaching her the science of rhetoric in which, states Boccaccio, she so excelled that she not only resembled her father in her intelligence, agile memory and excellent diction, but in fact surpassed him in her marvellous eloquence and command of oratory. On the subject of what we said before about all the benefits that women have brought, the good that this lady did is especially worthy of note. It was at the time when a triumvirate ruled over Rome that this Hortensia decided to take up the cause of women, thus performing a task which no man dared to do. As Rome was in great financial straits, it was proposed to levy certain charges on women and, in particular, to put a tax on their valuables. This Hortensia spoke so persuasively that she was listened to as attentively as if it had been her father speaking, and won her case.

'If we discuss more recent times, rather than going back to ancient history, Giovanni Andrea, the famous legist who taught at Bologna nearly sixty years ago, similarly opposed the view that women should not be educated. He gave his beloved daughter Novella, a fine and lovely girl, such a good education and detailed knowledge of law that, when he was busy with other tasks which prevented him from lecturing to his students, he could send his daughter in his place to read to them from his professorial chair. In order not to distract the audience by her beauty, Novella had a little curtain put up in front of her. Thus she lightened her father's load and relieved him of some of his duties. In his devotion to her, he chose to preserve her name for posterity by writing an important commentary on a legal text which he named La Novella in her honour.

'Therefore, it is not all men, especially not the most intelligent, who agree with the view that it is a bad idea to educate women. However, it's true that those who are not very clever come out with this opinion because they don't want women to know more than they do. Your own father, who was a great astrologer and philosopher, did not believe that knowledge of the sciences reduced a woman's worth. Indeed, as you know, it gave him great pleasure to see you take so readily to studying the arts. Rather, it was because your mother, as a woman, held the view that you should spend your time spinning like the other gifts, that you did not receive a more advanced or detailed initiation into the sciences. But, as that proverb which we've already had occasion to quote says, "What is in our nature cannot be taken away." Despite your mother's opposition, you did manage to glean some grains of knowledge from your studies, thanks to your own natural inclination for learning. It's obvious to me that you do not esteem yourself any less for having this knowledge: in fact, you seem to treasure it, and quite rightly so.'

I, Christine, then replied, 'Without a doubt, what you're saying, my lady, is as true as the Lord's Prayer itself.'

37. Christine addresses Rectitude, who gives examples to contradict those who claim that few women are chaste, beginning with Susanna

As far as I can see, my lady, all forms of goodness and virtue can be found in the female sex. So why is it that these men say that so few women are chaste? If this were true, all their other qualities would be worthless, because chastity is the supreme virtue in a woman. Yet, hearing what you've just said, the truth would seem to be very different from what they claim.'

Rectitude answered, 'The complete opposite is true, as I've told you before and as you yourself already know. I could keep telling you more on this subject until the end of time itself! The Holy Scripture mentions so many excellent and chaste ladies who preferred to die rather than lose their chastity, bodily integrity and good conscience. One such lady was the virtuous and lovely Susanna, wife of Joachim, who was a very rich and influential member of the Jewish race. As this honest lady was walking in her garden one day, she was approached by two old men, corrupt priests, who tried to tempt her into sin. Seeing that she completely rejected their advances and that their pleas were getting them nowhere, they threatened to denounce her in court for having been found with a young man. On hearing their threats, and knowing that the punishment for an adulterous woman was to be stoned, she exclaimed, "I am caught for all sides, for if I refuse to do what these men want, my body shall be put to death. But, if I give in to their demands, I shall be committing a sin in the eyes of the Creator. However, I would rather be innocent and suffer death than risk rousing God's anger by sinning." Susanna therefore screamed out loud and the other members of her household came running. To cut a long story short, the corrupt priests managed to convince the court with their false testimony and Susanna was sentenced to death. Yet God, who always looks after His own, opened the mouth of the prophet Daniel, who was just a small child in his mother's arms: when the boy saw Susanna being led to her punishment, followed by a great crowd of people who were all weeping, he cried out that the innocent woman had been wrongfully accused. She was taken back to the court where the corrupt priests were properly cross-examined and found guilty by their own confessions. The blameless Susanna was saved and it was they who were punished instead.'

[...]

44. In order to contradict those who claim that women want to be raped, here begins a series of examples, the first of which is Lucretia

I, Christine, then said, 'My lady, I fully believe what you say and I'm sure that there are many beautiful women who are upright, decent and fully able to protect themselves from the traps laid by seducers. It therefore angers and upsets me when men claim that women want to be raped and that, even though a woman may verbally rebuff a man, she won't in fact mind it if he does force himself upon her. I can scarcely believe that it could give women any pleasure to be treated in such a vile way.'

Rectitude replied, 'My dear friend, you can be sure that women who are chaste and lead a moral existence would find no pleasure in being raped. On the contrary, they think that it is the worst thing that could possibly happen to them. There are several examples, such as that of Lucretia, which prove that this is definitely the case. Lucretia, a high-born lady of Rome and, indeed, the most virtuous of all Roman women, was married to a nobleman called Tarquinius Collatinus. Unfortunately, Tarquin the Proud, son of King Tarquin, was deeply smitten with the great Lucretia. Having seen with his own eyes how supremely chaste she was, he didn't dare approach her directly. Despairing of being able to persuade her with bribes and entreaties, he plotted how to win her by trickery. He therefore pretended to be a close friend of her husband's, which meant that he was able to come and go as he pleased in her house. One day, when he knew that her husband was absent, he was welcomed most honourably by his noble hostess, as befitted a guest whom she took to be her husband's great friend. That night, Tarquin, who had other ideas, scared Lucretia out of her wits when he broke into her bedroom. In short, having made her numerous promises of gifts and presents if she would do what he wanted, he saw that pleading with her was getting him nowhere. He therefore pulled out his sword and threatened to kill her if she made a sound or refused to give herself to him. She told him to go ahead and kill her because she preferred to die rather than submit to his advances. When he realized that his threats were all in vain, Tarquin came up with another despicable ruse, declaring that he would let it be known publicly that he had found her with one of her servants. To cut a long story short, the thought that he would do such a thing so appalled her that she finally gave in to him.

'Yet Lucretia was unable to bear this awful offence with resignation. When morning came, she went to find her husband, father and close relatives, who were all the most prominent citizens of Rome. With great sobs and moans, she confessed to them the deed that had been perpetrated on her. As her husband and family were trying to comfort her in her terrible distress, she drew out a knife from under her gown, saying: "Though I Can absolve myself of sin and prove myself innocent this way, I can't get rid of my suffering and pain: henceforth no woman need live in shame and dishonour because of what has been done to me." With these words, she plunged the knife deep into her breast and immediately fell down dead in front of her husband and his friends. Like madmen, they all rushed after Tarquin. The whole of Rome was incensed by what had happened: they deposed the king and would have killed his son if they had caught him. After that, Rome never had another king. Some say that because of the outrage done to Lucretia, a law was passed which sentenced to death any man who raped a woman, a law which is moral, fitting and just.'

[...]

47. Proofs to refute the view that women are lacking in constancy: Christine asks questions, to which Rectitude replies with various examples of emperors who were unreliable and inconsistent

'My lady, the women you've been talking about were certainly extremely steadfast, resolute and faithful. Could one say as much of even the strongest men who ever lived? Yet, of all the vices that men, and especially authors, accuse women of possessing, they are unanimous that the female sex is unstable and fickle, frivolous, flighty and weak-minded, as impressionable as children and completely lacking in resolution. Are men therefore so unwavering that it is utterly unheard of for them to vacillate, given that they criticize women for being so unreliable and changeable? If, in fact, they themselves are lacking in constancy, it's totally unacceptable for them to accuse others of having the same failing or to insist that others should possess a virtue which they themselves do not.'

Rectitude's reply was, 'My dear sweet friend, haven't you heard the common saying that fools are very quick to spot the mote in their neighbour's eye but slow to see the beam in their own? I'll show you just how unreasonable it is for men to criticize women for being inconstant and capricious. Their argument goes like this. First, they all assume that women are by nature weak. Then, having accused women of weakness, they presumably think themselves to be constant, or at least that women are not as constant as they are. Yet it's undeniable that they expect far greater constancy from women than they themselves can muster. Though they consider themselves to be so strong and to be made of such noble stuff, they're unable to stop themselves from falling prey to some awful vices and failings. Nor is this by any means always out of ignorance. Indeed, it's often down to deliberate bad intentions, because they're well aware that they're committing a sin. But they then excuse themselves, saying that to err is to be human. However, should a woman fall into error, usually thanks to a man's incessant scheming, lo and behold, they declare this to be due to women's innate weakness and inconstancy. Considering that they think women are so feeble, they should, rightly speaking, show greater tolerance of female frailty and not accuse women of dreadful sins that they consider to be only minor peccadilloes when they themselves are guilty of them. For there is no law, no written text, which says that they are allowed to sin more than women, or that their vices are any more excusable. None the less, they in fact give themselves such moral authority that, far from letting women get away with anything, they fall over themselves to impute to the female sex all manner of crimes and offences. Neither do they give women any credit for being strong and steadfast in the face of such awful criticisms. So, whatever the argument is, men have it both ways and always turn out to be in the tight. You yourself have discussed this at length in your Letter of the God of Love.

'You asked me earlier whether men are so upright and worthy that they are justified in accusing others of inconstancy. I would say that if you examine human history from antiquity up to the present day, taking evidence from books and from both what you have seen with your own eyes in the past and what you can still see all around you today, and looking at men not just from the lower or uneducated classes but also from the upper classes, you can judge for yourself what perfection, strength and constancy they've displayed! This is the case with the vast majority of men, though there are some, thank heavens, who are wise, strong and steadfast.

'If you want me to give you examples of male inconstancy from the recent and distant past, since men persist in attacking women for this failing as if their own hearts were never subject to instability or change, just look at the behaviour of the most powerful princes and the most eminent men, in whom these are more dangerous faults than in others. Not to mention how many emperors are guilty of these things! I ask you, was the mind of a woman ever as weak, fearful, pathetic and frivolous as that of the Emperor Claudius? He was so unstable that whatever he ordered one minute, he reversed the next. It was impossible to take him at his word and he agreed with anything anybody said. In a fit of mad cruelty, he had his wife killed, and then, that night, he asked why she wasn't coming to bed! To those of his friends whom he had beheaded, he sent word that they should come and play with him! He was so lacking in courage that he lived in a constant state of fear and was unable to trust anyone. What can I tell you? Every kind of moral and mental debility was to be found in this atrocious emperor. But why am I just talking about this particular one? Was he the only ruler to sit on the imperial throne who was prey to such weakness? Was the Emperor Tiberius any better? Wasn't he more guilty of inconstancy, changeability and immorality than any woman has ever been?'

48. About Nero

'Whilst we're on the subject of emperors, what about Nero? It was glaringly obvious just how unstable and weak he was. Initially he was very laudable and made an effort to please everyone. Soon, however, his lechery, cruelty and greed knew no bounds. The better to indulge his vices, he would often arm himself at night and go off with his partners in crime to seek out places of depravity and corruption, amusing himself by running round town gratifying his obscene desires. As a pretext for committing his foul deeds, Nero would bump into people in the street and, if they said anything, he would attack them and kill them. He broke into taverns and brothels and raped women, on one occasion narrowly escaping death at the hands of a man whose wife he had raped. He organized lewd bathing parties and feasts that lasted all night. He would order first one thing and then another, as his capricious fancies took him. Nero indulged in all sorts of carnal pleasures, excesses and perversions, and there were no limits to his arrogance and extravagance. He loved those who were wicked and persecuted those who were virtuous. He was complicit in the murder of his father and he later had his own mother killed. When she was dead, he ordered her body to be opened up so that he could see where he had been conceived. Seeing her like that, Nero declared that she had once been a truly beautiful woman. He killed Octavia, his first wife, who was a fine lady, and took a second one, whom he loved at first but then had her murdered as well. He also ordered the death of Claudia, who had been the wife of his predecessor, since she refused to marry him. Nero similarly had his stepson killed when he was not yet seven years old purely because it was said of the boy that, when he was at play, his behaviour was obviously that of the son of an emperor.

'Nero's teacher Seneca, the noble philosopher, was also put to death by the emperor's orders, for he was unable to contain his shame at what was going on before his very eyes. Nero poisoned his prefect by pretending to give him a cure for his toothache. Likewise, he gave poisoned food and drink to the noblest of his princes and to the most venerable and illustrious of his barons, who exercised a great deal of power. Not only did he murder his aunt and seize all her wealth, but he also destroyed all the most notable families of Rome and drove them into exile, killing all their children in the process. He trained a ferocious Egyptian man to eat human flesh so that he could feed him living victims to devour. What can I tell you? It would be impossible to relate all his appalling crimes or the full extent of his foul wickedness. To cap it all, he set Rome on fire and let it burn for six whole days and nights. Many people died in this terrible catastrophe, whilst he stood singing on his tower, watching the inferno rage through the city and taking enormous delight in the beauty of the flames. At his dinner table, he had Saints Peter and Paul beheaded, as well as many other martyrs. For fourteen years he continued in this fashion until the Romans could finally take no more and rebelled against him. In his despair, he took his own life.'

[...]

53. After Rectitude has finished talking about women who were steadfast, Christine asks her why it is that all these worthy ladies of the past didn't refute the men and books who slander the female sex. Rectitude gives her answer

Such were the stories that Rectitude told me on this subject. Lack of space prevents me from going into detail on all the other examples she gave me, such as that of Leaena, a Greek woman, who refused to denounce two men who were friends of hers, preferring to bite off her own tongue in front of the judge in order to show him that no matter how much he tortured her he had no hope of extracting by force the information he wanted from her. Rectitude also told me about some other women who were so strong willed that they chose to die from drinking poison rather than fail to uphold truth and decency. I then turned to her and said, 'My lady, you've clearly demonstrated to me just how consistent and steadfast women are, in addition to all their other virtues. Surely there's no man of whom it could be said that he was their equal in this respect? I'm therefore amazed that so many worthy women, especially those who were learned and educated enough to write fine books in elegant style, could have allowed men to come out with their slanders all this time without contradicting them, when they knew only too well how false these men's accusations were.'

Rectitude replied, 'My dear Christine, this is an easy problem to solve. You should realize from what I've already told you that the virtuous ladies I've discussed with you were each involved in different types of activity and didn't all work towards the same end. This task of constructing the city was reserved for you, not them. These women's works alone were enough to make people of sound judgement and keen intelligence appreciate the female sex fully without their having to write anything else. As for the fact that the men who attacked and criticized women haven't yet been challenged, let me tell you that there's a time and a place for everything in the eternal scheme of things. Just think how long God allowed heresies against His holy law to prosper, which meant that they were very hard to stamp out and would still be around today if they hadn't been disputed and crushed. There are many things which flourish without hindrance until the time comes to take issue with them and refute them.'

I, Christine, came back to her again, saying: 'My lady, you're quite right. Yet I'm convinced that there will be plenty of dissenting voices raised against this very text. They'll say that, though some women of the past or the present might be virtuous, this isn't the case with all of them, or even the vast majority.'

Rectitude answered, 'It's just not true to say that the vast majority aren't virtuous. This is clearly proven by what I've said to you before: experience tells us that anyone can see for themselves, on any day of the week, how pious and full of charity and goodness women are. Not to mention the fact that it isn't women who are responsible for all the endless crimes and atrocities that are committed in the world. It's hardly surprising if not every single one of them is virtuous. In the whole of Nineveh, which was a very large city with a huge population, there wasn't one good man to be found anywhere when Jonah the prophet was sent by God to destroy it if the people didn't repent of their sins. Nor was there a single decent man living in the city of Sodom, as became clear when Lot left the place to be consumed by fire sent down from the heavens. What's more, you shouldn't forget that, though Jesus Christ's company only comprised twelve men, there was still one who was evil. To think that men dare to say that all women should be virtuous or that those who aren't should be stoned! I would ask them to take a good look at themselves and then let he who is without sin cast the first stone. Moreover, to what kind of behaviour should they themselves aspire? I tell you, the day that all men attain perfection, women will follow their example.'

54. Christine asks Rectitude if it's true what certain men have said about how few women are faithful in love, and Rectitude gives her reply

Going on to a different subject, I, Christine, spoke up once again and said, 'My lady, let's put such topics to one side and move on to something else. Departing a little from the kind of things we've been talking about up until now, I'd like to ask you a few questions. I hope you won't mind discussing these matters that I'd like to raise with you: although the subject itself relates to the laws of nature, it does somewhat overstep the bounds of rational behaviour.'

Rectitude's answer was, 'My friend, say what you like. The pupil who puts questions to his teacher in the spirit of enquiry shouldn't be reprimanded for touching on any subject whatsoever.'

'My lady, there's a kind of natural attraction at work on earth which draws men to women and women to men. This isn't a social law but an instinct of the flesh: stimulated by carnal desire, it makes the two sexes love each other in a wild and ardent way. Neither sex has any idea what it is that causes them to fall for each other like this, but they succumb in droves to this type of emotion, which is known as passionate love. Yet men often say that, despite all the protestations of fidelity that a woman in love may make, she not only flits from one lover to another but is also extraordinarily unfeeling, devious and false. They assert that this fickleness in women comes from their lack of moral character. Of all the various authors who have made such criticisms of women, Ovid is particularly virulent in his book, the Art of Love. Having attacked women for their lack of steadfastness in love, Ovid and all the others then go on to claim that they have written their books about the deceitful ways and sinfulness of women for the common good of all: their aim is to ware men about women's wiles and to teach them how to avoid them, just as if women were snakes hidden in the grass. So, my dear lady, please tell me what the truth of the matter is.'

Rectitude replied, 'My dear Christine, as for what they say about women being underhanded, I'm not sure what more I can tell you. You yourself have tackled this issue at length, when you refuted Ovid, along with all the others, in your Letter of the God of Love and the Letters on the Romance of the Rose. However, getting back to what you said about these men's claims to be writing for the common good, I'll prove to you that this is definitely not the case. Here's why: you can't define something as being for the common good of a city, country or any other community of people, if it doesn't contribute to the universal good of all. Women as well as men must derive equal benefit from it. Something which is done with the aim of privileging only one section of the population is called a private or an individual good, not a common good. Moreover, something which is done for the good of some but to the detriment of others is not simply a private or an individual good. In fact, it constitutes a type of injury done to one party in order to benefit the other: it thus only profits the second party at the expense of the first. Such writers don't speak to women in order to teach them to beware the traps laid for them by men, even though it's undeniable that men very often deceive women by their false appearances and cunning ruses. Besides, its beyond doubt that women count as God's creatures and are human beings just as men are. They're not a different race or a strange breed, which might justify their being excluded from receiving moral teachings. I can thus only conclude that if these authors were really writing for the common good, they would warn women against the snares set by men as well as advising men to watch out for women.

'Let's leave these issues for now and go back to your earlier question. What I told you before about those examples of women whose devotion endured until the day they died obviously wasn't sufficient proof for you that, far from being as inconstant or as fickle in love as these writers maintain, the female sex is in fact extremely steadfast in matters of the heart

[...]

62. Christine addresses Rectitude who, in her reply, refutes the view of those who claim that women use their charms to attract men

I, Christine, then said, 'My lady, you were quite right before when you said that passionate love was like a perilous sea. From what I've seen, women with any sense should do everything they can to avoid it, for they only come to great harm. Yet, those women who want to look lovely by dressing elegantly come in for a lot of criticism, because it's said that they only do so in order to attract attention from men.'

Rectitude answered, 'My dear Christine, it's not my business to try and find excuses for those women who are too fussy and obsessive about their appearance, for this is no small failing in a person. Wearing clothes that aren't fitting to one's station in life is particularly reprehensible. However, whilst I've no intention of condoning such a vice, neither do I want anyone to think that they have the right to lay more blame than is strictly necessary on those who make themselves beautiful in this way. I can assure you that not all women who do this are interested in seducing men. Some people, not just women but also men, have a legitimate taste and natural bent for taking pleasure in pretty things and expensive, elaborate clothes, as well as in cleanliness and fine array. If it is in their nature to behave like this, it's very difficult for them to resist, though it would be greatly to their credit ff they did. Wasn't it written of Saint Bartholomew the Apostle, a man of high birth, that he spent his whole life draped in fringed robes of silk which were hemmed with precious stones, despite the fact that Our Lord preached poverty? Though such behaviour is usually rather pretentious and ostentatious, Saint Bartholomew can't be said to have committed any sin because it was in his nature to wear expensive clothes. Even so, some do say that it was for this reason that Our Lord was content for Bartholomew to be martyred by being flayed alive. My reason for telling you these things is to show you that it's wrong for any mortal creature to judge another's appearance; God alone has the right to judge us. I'll now give you some examples on this subject.'

[...]

64. Rectitude explains that some women are loved more for their virtue than others are for their attractiveness

'Even supposing that the reason women put such efforts into making themselves beautiful and seductive, elegant and alluring, were because they wanted to attract male attention, I'll prove to you that this does not necessarily mean that men who are decent and sensible are going to fall more quickly or more heavily for them. On the contrary, those men who value integrity are more readily attracted to women who are virtuous, honest and modest, and love them more deeply, even if they are less glamorous than flirts such as these. Now, some might retort that, since it's a bad thing to appeal to men in the first place, it would be better if those women who used their virtue and modesty to catch men's eyes didn't in fact possess such qualities at all. However, this argument is utterly worthless; one shouldn't refrain from cultivating things which are good and useful just because some idiots use them unwisely. Everybody should do their duty by acting well, no matter what happens.

'I'll now give you some examples which prove that many women have been loved for their uptight and moral behaviour. Most notably, I could tell you about various saints of paradise whom men lusted after specifically for their purity. This is also what happened to Lucretia, whose rape I recounted to you earlier. It was because of her exemplary virtue, not simply her beauty, that Tarquin fell for her. One night, her husband was at supper in the company of some other knights, one of whom was this Tarquin who subsequently raped her. Each of them started to talk about his wife, claiming that his was the most virtuous of them all. In order to find out whose wife was the worthiest of this accolade, they rode off to call on each of their houses in turn. Those wives whom they found busy at some honest task or other were held in the greatest esteem. Of all the women, Lucretia was deemed to be the one who was spending her time in the most commendable way. Like the highly respectable and sober woman she was, Lucretia wore a plain gown as she sat with the other ladies of her household busily working wool and conversing on moral subjects. The king's son, Tarquin, who had accompanied Lucretia's husband, was so impressed by her integrity, her simple and laudable conduct, as well as her modest beating, that he conceived a burning desire for her and began to hatch the wicked plan which he would later execute.'

[...]

66. Christine addresses Rectitude who, in her reply, refutes the opinion of those who claim that women are by nature mean

'I'm not sure what more to ask you, my lady, as all my questions have been answered. It seems to me that you've completely disproved the slanders which so many men have come out with against women. As far as I can see, it's even untrue what they so often say about avarice being the most prevalent of all the female vices.'

Rectitude replied, 'My dear friend, I can assure you that avarice is no more inherent in women than it is in men. Indeed, there would appear to be fewer avaricious women than men: as God knows and as you yourself can attest, the terrible evil that is so rampant in the world as a result of men's avarice is far greater than that which comes from women who possess this failing. However, as I pointed out to you before, the fool is all too ready to spot his neighbour's misdeed even though he is blind to his own great crimes.

'Just because women take pleasure in storing up cloth, thread, and all the other little items that are indispensable to a household, they earn themselves a reputation for being avaricious. Believe me, there are many, if not countless, women who, if they enjoyed great wealth, would not think twice about giving rewards and making generous gifts to those whom they thought would spend the money wisely. On the other hand, a woman who is poor is necessarily obliged to watch her pennies. In general, women are kept so short of money that they tend to hang on to the little they have because they know how hard it is to lay their hands on any more. Some people even go so far as to accuse women of being avaricious if they complain to their wayward husbands who are extravagant spendthrifts and beg them to be more careful with their money. Women like this know only too well how, thanks to the husband's foolish squandering, the whole household has to go without, and they and their poor children suffer as a result. This doesn't mean that such women are grasping or avaricious; on the contrary, it's a sign of their great prudence. Of course, I'm only referring to those wives who are discreet about admonishing their husbands. Otherwise this can cause great rows in marriage when the husband doesn't take too kindly to being criticized and ends up attacking his wife for something which is actually to her credit. As proof that this vice is not as common in women as some might say, just look at all the almsgiving that they eagerly perform. God knows how many prisoners, both in the past and still today, even those locked away in Saracen countries, have been comforted and helped out by women who were ready to give them money, not to mention how many poor people, impoverished gentle-folk and others they've also supported.'

I, Christine, then said, 'In fact, my lady, what you've just said reminds me of all the honourable ladies that I've seen making discreet displays of generosity, as far as their means allowed them. I know some of my female contemporaries take far greater delight in saying, "Here, take this" to someone who can put the money to good use than any miser ever did in grabbing some cash and hoarding it away in his coffers. I've no idea why men go around saying that women are avaricious. Although it's said that Alexander was famous for his generosity, I can tell you that I've seen little evidence for this!'

Rectitude burst out laughing and replied, 'My friend, the ladies of Rome were certainly not found wanting when the city was so heavily depleted by war that all the public funds to pay for troops were exhausted. The Romans were extremely hard pressed to find ways to raise money for the enormous army which they desperately needed. Out of their own great generosity, the ladies of Rome, including the widows, put all their jewellery and everything of value that they owned into a pile, which they then freely donated to the princes of the city. These ladies were very highly praised for their unselfish action. Their jewels were later returned to them, as was only right, for it was thanks to them that Rome's fortunes were restored.'

[...]

68. About the princesses and ladies of France

Once again I, Christine, interjected, 'My lady, now that you've reminded me of this woman of my own day and have started talking about the ladies of France, as well as those who have made their homes here, I would like you to tell me what you think of such women. Do you consider some of them to be worthy of inclusion in our city? Are they any less deserving of a place than foreign women?'

Rectitude replied, 'Certainly, Christine, I can assure you that there are many virtuous ladies among their number whom I'd be delighted to invite to become our citizens.

'First of all, we wouldn't refuse entry to the noble queen of France, Isabeau of Bavaria, who, by the grace of God, is now reigning over us. She has neither a shred of cruelty or greed in her body nor a single evil trait, for she is full of kindness and benevolence towards her subjects.

'No less worthy of praise is the young duchess of Berry, a wise, beautiful and gentle lady married to the Duke John, son of King John of France and brother of the late king, Charles the Wise. This honourable duchess conducts herself with such sobriety and discretion, even though she's still only a very young woman, that everybody commends her highly for her exemplary behaviour.

'What can I say about the duchess of Orleans, daughter of the late duke of Milan and wife of the Duke Louis, son of Charles the Wise, King of France? Could any lady be more prudent than she is? It's plain for all to see that she is not only steadfast and constant, but also very loving towards her husband and a fine example to her children. Moreover, she is astute in her affairs, fairminded with everyone, sober in her bearing and endowed with every possible virtue.

'And what of the duchess of Burgundy, wife of the Duke John, son of Philip, who was himself son of the late King John of France? Isn't she also a fine lady, loyal to her husband, kind-hearted and well-disposed towards others, morally impeccable, and with no failing whatsoever?

'The countess of Clermont, daughter of the duke of Berry by his first wife, who is married to Count John of Clermont, son and heir of the duke of Bourbon, is everything that a noble princess should be in terms of her deep affection for her husband and her excellent upbringing in every respect, not to mention her beauty, wisdom and goodness. Her virtues shine all the more brightly thanks to her noble conduct and fine bearing.

'Amongst these ladies, there is one of whom you're particularly fond and to whom you're indebted as much for her own good qualities as for the kindness and affection you have received from her: this is the noble duchess of Holland and countess of Hainault, daughter of the late Duke Philip of Burgundy and sister of the present duke. Shouldn't this lady take her place amongst the ranks of the very finest ladies for her faithfulness, prudence and circumspection in her affairs, as well as her selflessness and extreme devotion to God? In a word, she is goodness itself.

'Doesn't the duchess of Bourbon also deserve to be commemorated for posterity alongside these other illustrious princesses, given that she is such an honourable lady, worthy of praise in every respect?

'What can I tell you? It would take me for ever to list the good qualities of all these ladies!

'The countess of Saint-Poi, daughter of the duke of Bar and first cousin to the king of France, also merits a place amongst these fine ladies, for she is kind and beautiful, noble and virtuous.

'Likewise, another lady to whom you're devoted, Anne, daughter of the late count of La Marche and sister of the present duke, who is married to Louis of Bavaria, brother of the queen of France, would not disgrace this company of splendid ladies whose praises should be sung to the skies. Both God and the whole world are witness to her excellent qualities.

'Despite what the slanderers may say, there's a positively infinite number of countesses, baronesses, ladies, maidens, bourgeoises and women of every estate who are honourable and distinguished. God be praised for keeping them all in virtue, and may He inspire those who are less than perfect to mend their ways. You must have no doubts about this, for I can assure you that it's the absolute truth, no matter what those who defame women out of envy might say to the contrary.'

I, Christine, then replied, 'My lady, it certainly gives me great pleasure to hear you say this.'

She then turned to me and said, 'My dear friend, it seems to me that I've now completed my task in the construction of the City of Ladies. I've not only built all the lovely palaces and splendid houses and mansions for you, but also filled them almost to overflowing with a vast number of wonderful ladies from all different ranks of society. My sister Justice will now come forward to put the finishing touches to the city, and I will say no more.'

69. Christine addresses princesses and all other ladies

'Most excellent, upstanding and worthy princesses of France and other countries, as well as all you ladies, maidens, and women of every estate, you who have ever in the past loved, or do presently love, or who will in the future love virtuous and moral conduct: raise your heads and rejoice in your new city. With God's help, it is now nearly complete, being resplendent with buildings and almost entirely filled with inhabitants. Thanks be to God for having led me through this difficult labour of learning in my desire to build an honourable and permanent place for you to dwell inside the walls of this city which will last for all eternity. I have come this far in the hope of being able to finish this task with the help of Lady Justice, who has promised me that she won't rest until she and I have done all we can to complete the city and shut its gates. So, pray for me, my worthy ladies!'

End of the Second Part of the Book of the City of Ladies.